<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101231005</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32413</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharmacogenet Genomics</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharmacogenet. Genomics</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Pharmacogenetics and genomics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1744-6872</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1744-6880</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26313485</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4591203</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/FPC.0000000000000173</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS712825</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Escitalopram pharmacogenetics: CYP2C19 relationships with dosing and clinical outcomes in Autism Spectrum Disorder</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bishop</surname>
<given-names>Jeffrey R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Najjar</surname>
<given-names>Fedra</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rubin</surname>
<given-names>Leah H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guter</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Owley</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mosconi</surname>
<given-names>Matthew W.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jacob</surname>
<given-names>Suma</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cook</surname>
<given-names>Edwin H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>a</label>University of Minnesota College of Pharmacy, Department of Pharmacy Practice</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>b</label>University of Illinois at Chicago College of Medicine, Department of Psychiatry</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>c</label>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Departments of Psychiatry and Pediatrics</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>d</label>University of Minnesota College of Medicine, Department of Psychiatry</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: Jeffrey R. Bishop, Department of Experimental and Clinical Pharmacology, University of Minnesota College of Pharmacy, 308 Harvard St SE, 7-115 Weaver-Densford Hall, Minneapolis, MN 55455, <email>jrbishop@umn.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2">
<p>
<bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold>
</p>
<p>J.R.B is on a scientific advisory board for Physician’s Choice Laboratory Services and Ortho-McNeil Janssen, E.H.C has been a consultant for a Seaside Therapeutics multi-site clinical trial. SJ serves as a part of a Roche Pharmaceuticals multi-site clinical trial. The remaining authors report no disclosures.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>4</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>548</fpage>
<lpage>554</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1097/FPC.0000000000000173-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Purpose</title>
<p id="P1">Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors such as escitalopram are commonly used to treat patients with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD), but there are individual differences in treatment response and tolerability. <italic>CYP2C19</italic> encodes the primary enzyme responsible for escitalopram metabolism and we investigated whether polymorphisms in <italic>CYP2C19</italic> were related to symptoms and dosing in a pharmacogenetic study of ASD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P2">Participants completed the Aberrant Behavior Checklist-Community Version (ABC-CV) weekly for 6 weeks. Escitalopram was initiated at a dose of 2.5 mg qd with weekly increases to 20 mg unless intolerable side-effects occurred. Three <italic>CYP2C19</italic> metabolizer groups, including ultrarapid, extensive, and reduced metabolizers, were examined in relation to symptom improvement and tolerated dose.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">ABC-CV scores improved over the course of treatment (p&lt;0.0001). There were no differences identified in the rate of improvement across metabolizer groups for the ABC-CV-irritability subscale, which was the primary outcome for clinical symptoms. There was a trend for a metabolizer group by time interaction with respect to dose (p=0.10). This interaction was driven by the linear rate of change from week 1 to study endpoint between the reduced metabolizers and ultrarapid metabolizer groups (p=0.05). Post hoc analyses identified significant differences in the rate of dose escalation between ultrarapid metabolizers and extensive metabolizers and for ultrarapid metabolizers compared to reduced metabolizers (p’s&lt;0.04), whereby ultrarapid metabolizers exhibited a slower rate of change in dose over time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p id="P4"><italic>CYP2C19</italic> ultrarapid metabolizers were associated with reduced tolerance to a fixed titration schedule of open label escitalopram in this ASD study sample. Possible explanations may involve the altered kinetics of faster metabolizers or previously unknown activities of escitalopram metabolites.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Escitalopram</kwd>
<kwd>CYP2C19</kwd>
<kwd>Autism Spectrum Disorder</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>