<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="brief-report" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jneuro</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jneurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J. Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Journal of Neuroscience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0270-6474</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1529-2401</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Society for Neuroscience</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26511255</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4623232</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1666-15</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1666-15.2015</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Brief Communications</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Selective Dysregulation of Hippocampal Inhibition in the Mouse Lacking Autism Candidate Gene <italic>CNTNAP2</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jurgensen</surname>
<given-names>Sofia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Castillo</surname>
<given-names>Pablo E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"></xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1">Dominick P. Purpura Department of Neuroscience and Rose F. Kennedy Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities Research Center, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, New York 10461</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>Correspondence should be addressed to Dr. Pablo E. Castillo,
<addr-line>Dominick P. Purpura Department of Neuroscience, Rose F. Kennedy Center, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1410 Pelham Parkway South, Room 703, Bronx, NY 10461.</addr-line><email>pablo.castillo@einstein.yu.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p>Author contributions: S.J. and P.E.C. designed research; S.J. performed research; S.J. analyzed data; S.J. and P.E.C. wrote the paper.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="present-address">
<p>S. Jurgensen's present address: Genzyme, a Sanofi Company, 49 New York Avenue, Framingham, MA 01701.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>28</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>28</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 6 months and
						0 days and was based on the <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>43</issue>
<fpage>14681</fpage>
<lpage>14687</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>29</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>16</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>25</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 the authors 0270-6474/15/3514681-07$15.00/0</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="zns04315014681.pdf" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Mutations in the human gene encoding contactin-associated protein-like 2 (<italic>CNTNAP2</italic>) have been strongly associated with autism spectrum disorders (ASDs). <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice recapitulate major features of ASD, including social impairment, reduced vocalizations, and repetitive behavior. In addition, <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice show reduced cortical neuronal synchrony and develop spontaneous seizures throughout adulthood. As suggested for other forms of ASDs, this phenotype could reflect some form of synaptic dysregulation. However, the impact of lifelong deletion of <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> on synaptic function in the brain remains unknown. To address this issue, we have assessed excitatory and inhibitory synaptic transmission in acute hippocampal slices of <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice. We found that although excitatory transmission was mostly normal, inhibition onto CA1 pyramidal cells was altered in <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice. Specifically, putative perisomatic, but not dendritic, evoked IPSCs were significantly reduced in these mice. Whereas both inhibitory short-term plasticity and miniature IPSC frequency and amplitude were normal in <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice, we found an unexpected increase in the frequency of spontaneous, action potential-driven IPSCs. Altered hippocampal inhibition could account for the behavioral phenotype <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice present later in life. Overall, our findings that <italic>Cntnap2</italic> deletion selectively impairs perisomatic hippocampal inhibition while sparing excitation provide additional support for synaptic dysfunction as a common mechanism underlying ASDs.</p>
<p><bold>SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT</bold> The gene encoding contactin-associated protein-like 2 (<italic>CNTNAP2</italic>) stands out as one the first genes to have both rare and common mutations strongly associated with ASDs. Whereas <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice appear to recapitulate core behavioral endophenotypes (e.g., social impairment, language deficits, and repetitive behavior), the cellular and circuit bases of this phenotype remain poorly understood. Here, we report that synaptic inhibition specifically onto the perisomatic compartment of CA1 pyramidal cells is impaired, whereas dendritic inhibition and excitatory transmission remain basically unchanged in <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice. These findings provide additional support to the notion that disruption of inhibition, in particular perisomatic inhibition onto principal cells, could play a critical role in ASDs.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>CASPR2</kwd>
<kwd>cell adhesion</kwd>
<kwd>E/I balance</kwd>
<kwd>epilepsy</kwd>
<kwd>perisomatic inhibition</kwd>
<kwd>synaptopathy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>