<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26657971</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4682829</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0144624</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-26121</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Resequencing and Association Analysis of <italic>CLN8</italic> with Autism Spectrum Disorder in a Japanese Population</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Resequencing and Association Analysis of <italic>CLN8</italic> with ASD</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Emiko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>Yuichiro</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xing</surname>
<given-names>Jingrui</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kushima</surname>
<given-names>Itaru</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Egawa</surname>
<given-names>Jun</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Okuda</surname>
<given-names>Shujiro</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoya</surname>
<given-names>Satoshi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Okada</surname>
<given-names>Takashi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Uno</surname>
<given-names>Yota</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ishizuka</surname>
<given-names>Kanako</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sugimoto</surname>
<given-names>Atsunori</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Igeta</surname>
<given-names>Hirofumi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nunokawa</surname>
<given-names>Ayako</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sugiyama</surname>
<given-names>Toshiro</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ozaki</surname>
<given-names>Norio</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Someya</surname>
<given-names>Toshiyuki</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, Niigata University Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences, Niigata, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine, Nagoya, Aichi, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Division of Bioinformatics, Niigata University Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences, Niigata, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Oojima Hospital, Sanjo, Niigata, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="aff005">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, Hamamatsu University School of Medicine, Hamamatsu, Shizuoka, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Zwick</surname>
<given-names>Michael Edward</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Emory University School Of Medicine, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001">
<p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: EI YW JE T. Someya. Performed the experiments: EI YW JE JX IK SH. Analyzed the data: EI YW JE SO. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TO YU KI AS HI AN NO T. Sugiyama. Wrote the paper: EI YW JE T. Someya.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>jeg5414@med.niigata-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<elocation-id>e0144624</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>16</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2015 Inoue et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Inoue et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0144624.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Rare variations contribute substantially to autism spectrum disorder (ASD) liability. We recently performed whole-exome sequencing in two families with affected siblings and then carried out a follow-up study and identified ceroid-lipofuscinosis neuronal 8 (epilepsy, progressive with mental retardation) (<italic>CLN8</italic>) as a potential genetic risk factor for ASD. To further investigate the role of <italic>CLN8</italic> in the genetic etiology of ASD, we performed resequencing and association analysis of <italic>CLN8</italic> with ASD in a Japanese population. Resequencing the <italic>CLN8</italic> coding region in 256 ASD patients identified five rare missense variations: g.1719291G&gt;A (R24H), rs201670636 (F39L), rs116605307 (R97H), rs143701028 (T108M) and rs138581191 (N152S). These variations were genotyped in 568 patients (including the resequenced 256 patients) and 1017 controls. However, no significant association between these variations and ASD was identified. This study does not support a contribution of rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations to ASD susceptibility in the Japanese population.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by a grant from the Niigata Medical Association, by a grant from the Japan Foundation for Neuroscience, and by a “Integrated Research on Neuropsychiatric Disorders” of the Strategic Research Program for Brain Sciences from the Japan Agency for Medical Research and development, AMED. The funders had no role in the study design, data collection or analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"></fig-count>
<table-count count="3"></table-count>
<page-count count="9"></page-count>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<title>Data Availability</title>
<p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a neurodevelopmental disorder characterized by early-onset difficulties in social communication and unusually restricted, repetitive behavior and interests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref001">1</xref>]. Genetic risk of ASD has been suggested to involve the combined effects of many common variations of small effect, as well as rare variations of large effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref002">2</xref>].</p>
<p>Our recent whole-exome sequencing (WES) study in two families with affected siblings (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0144624.s001">S1 Fig</xref>) and a follow-up study identified ceroid-lipofuscinosis, neuronal 8 (epilepsy, progressive with mental retardation) (<italic>CLN8</italic>) as a potential genetic risk factor for ASD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>]. In one family, a rare heterozygous missense variation, R24H, was transmitted from an affected father to three affected sons and thus co-segregated with ASD. In the follow-up study (550 patients and 1017 controls), heterozygous <italic>CLN8</italic> R24H was identified in one patient and one control. R24H had a higher mutant allele frequency in patients (0.09%) compared with controls (0.05%), although the association was not significant.</p>
<p>Certain homozygous or compound heterozygous <italic>CLN8</italic> mutations cause two distinct variants of neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis-8 (OMIM#600143): Northern epilepsy variant (OMIM#610003), also known as progressive epilepsy with mental retardation (EPMR; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref004">4</xref>]), and a more severe form of variant late-infantile neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref005">5</xref>]. For example, R24G co-segregated with EPMR; all 22 patients were homozygous, and all 10 parents and 19 of 28 healthy siblings were heterozygous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref004">4</xref>]. To our knowledge, no studies investigating neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis-8 have described heterozygous carriers who manifest psychiatric traits compatible with ASD and/or intellectual disability. However, other rare heterozygous <italic>CLN8</italic> variations may confer increased susceptibility to ASD.</p>
<p>CLN8 is involved in cell proliferation during neuronal differentiation and in protection against neuronal cell apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref006">6</xref>]. Teratocarcinoma P19 cells expressing the deletion mutant <italic>Cln8</italic> K61del showed an increased proliferation rate throughout neuronal differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref006">6</xref>]. In P19 cells, <italic>Cln8</italic> mutations (K61del, A30P, Y158C and Q194R) and <italic>Cln8</italic> silencing by small hairpin RNA increased apoptosis rates induced by <italic>N</italic>-methyl d-aspartate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref006">6</xref>]. Of note, several lines of evidence suggest that abnormal neural cell proliferation and/or death are implicated in the pathophysiology of ASD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref007">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref009">9</xref>]. A longitudinal and cross-sectional magnetic resonance imaging study of autism cases demonstrated early brain overgrowth during infancy and the toddler years, followed by an accelerated rate of size reduction and perhaps degeneration from adolescence to late middle age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref007">7</xref>]. A postmortem study showed higher prefrontal neuron counts and brain weight in children with autism compared with controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref008">8</xref>]. Levels of anti- and pro-apoptotic proteins are reduced and increased, respectively, in the postmortem brain of ASD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref009">9</xref>].</p>
<p>To further investigate the role of <italic>CLN8</italic> in the genetic etiology of ASD, we resequenced the <italic>CLN8</italic> coding region in 256 ASD patients, and then performed an association study with 568 patients and 1017 controls.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee on Genetics of Niigata University School of Medicine, and the Ethics Committee of the Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine and associated institutes and hospitals. This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants and/or their families.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>All participants were unrelated and of Japanese descent. The Niigata sample consisted of 256 patients with ASD (202 males and 54 females; mean age, 19.0 [SD 9.2] years) and 667 control individuals (341 males and 326 females; mean age, 38.3 [SD 10.8] years). The sample included 241 patients and 667 controls involved in the study by Egawa <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>]. Patient and control groups were not sex- or age-matched. Each participant was subjected to psychiatric assessment, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>]. In brief, patients were diagnosed by experienced child psychiatrists according to Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for autistic disorder (<italic>n</italic> = 72), Asperger’s disorder (<italic>n</italic> = 116), or pervasive developmental disorder not otherwise specified (PDD-NOS; <italic>n</italic> = 68). The Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule has not been translated into Japanese. Although the Autism Diagnostic Interview-Revised has been recently translated into Japanese, no training in the use of this interview technique was available to us in Japan. Thus, we were unable to use such standardized tests. Controls were mainly recruited from hospital staff, who showed good social and occupational skills with no self-reported personal or family history (within first-degree relatives) of psychiatric disorders. However, these control individuals were not assessed using structured psychiatric interviews.</p>
<p>The Nagoya sample consisted of 312 patients with ASD (236 males and 76 females; mean age, 19.6 [SD 10.2] years) and 352 control individuals (109 males and 243 females; mean age, 45.9 [SD 10.8] years). These individuals were identical to those in the report of Egawa <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>]. Patient and control groups were not sex- or age-matched. Cases were included if they met DSM-IV Text Revision criteria for autistic disorder (<italic>n</italic> = 131), Asperger’s disorder (<italic>n</italic> = 89), or PDD-NOS (<italic>n</italic> = 92). Control subjects were selected from the general population and had no history of mental disorders based on questionnaire responses from the subjects during the sample inclusion step.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Resequencing the <italic>CLN8</italic> coding region</title>
<p>The <italic>CLN8</italic> coding region (RefSeq accession number, NM_018941.3) was resequenced in 256 ASD patients of the Niigata sample by direct sequencing of polymerase chain reaction products, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref010">10</xref>]. Primer sequences used for amplification are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0144624.s002">S1 Table</xref>. Detailed information on amplification conditions is available upon request.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Genotyping</title>
<p>Rare non-synonymous variations with mutant allele frequencies &lt; 0.01, identified by resequencing, were genotyped in the Niigata and Nagoya samples using the TaqMan 5′-exonuclease assay (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0144624.s003">S2 Table</xref>), as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref011">11</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Deviations from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium were tested using the χ<sup>2</sup> test for goodness-of-fit. Allelic associations were tested using Fisher’s exact test. A gene-based analysis was performed using the sequence kernel association test (SKAT; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/skat/">http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/skat/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref012">12</xref>]. Files for the analysis were formatted by PLINK (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/purcell/plink/">http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/purcell/plink/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref013">13</xref>].</p>
<p>A power calculation was performed using the Genetic Power Calculator (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/gpc/">http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/gpc/</ext-link>). Power was estimated using α = 0.05, and assuming a disease prevalence of 0.01 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref001">1</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Resequencing the <italic>CLN8</italic> coding region in 256 ASD patients of the Niigata sample, we identified five rare non-synonymous variations: g.1719291G&gt;A (R24H), reported in our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>], rs201670636 (g. 1719337T&gt;G; F39L), rs116605307 (g. 1719510G&gt;A; R97H), rs143701028 (g.1719543C&gt;T; T108M) and rs138581191 (g. 1719675A&gt;G; N152S; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0144624.t001">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0144624.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0144624.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0144624.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Genomic structure of the ceroid-lipofuscinosis, neuronal 8 (epilepsy, progressive with mental retardation) (<italic>CLN8</italic>) gene.</title>
<p>
<italic>CLN8</italic> spans approximately 22.9 kb and has three exons (rectangles). Black and white rectangles represent coding and untranslated regions, respectively. A horizontal arrow shows the orientation of transcription. Vertical arrows indicate locations of rare non-synonymous variations identified by resequencing.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="pone.0144624.g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0144624.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0144624.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Rare non-synonymous <italic>CLN8</italic> variations identified by resequencing.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0144624.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0144624.t001"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dbSNP ID</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Position<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allele<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exon</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Protein</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GERP</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Function prediction</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CADD</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MAF</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PolyPhen-2</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SIFT</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HGVD</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1K (JPT)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1719291</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/A</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R24H</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.09</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Probably damaging</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tolerated</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rs201670636</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1719337</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T/G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F39L</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-9.35</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Probably damaging</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tolerated</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0060</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rs116605307</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1719510</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/A</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R97H</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-7.78</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benign</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tolerated</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0013</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rs143701028</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1719543</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C/T</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T108M</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.06</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possibly damaging</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tolerated</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.6</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0060</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rs138581191</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1719675</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/G</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N152S</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possibly damaging</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tolerated</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0023</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001">
<p>CADD, Combined Annotation Dependent Depletion; GERP, Genomic Evolutionary Rate Profiling; 1K, 1000 Genomes; HGVD, the Human Genetic Variation Database; JPT, Japanese in Tokyo; MAF, mutant allele frequency.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t001fn002">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Position on chromosome 8 according to GRCh37.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t001fn003">
<p>
<sup>b</sup>Reference/mutant allele.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>These five rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations were genotyped in the Niigata sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0144624.t002">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0144624.s004">S3 Table</xref>). In all 256 patients, genotypes of these variations, determined using the TaqMan method, were identical to those obtained by direct sequencing. Genotype distributions of the variations did not deviate significantly from Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium in ASD or control groups (data not shown). All five variations had a higher mutant allele frequency in patients compared with controls (i.e., odds ratios [OR] &gt; 1), although these associations were not significant. We then genotyped the five rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations in the Nagoya sample. Genotype distributions of the variations did not deviate significantly from Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium in ASD or control groups (data not shown). Two variations (F39L and R97H) also had a higher mutant allele frequency in patients compared with controls, although these associations were not significant. When we combined the Niigata and Nagoya samples, all five rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations had a higher mutant allele frequency in patients compared with controls, but were not significantly associated with ASD. A gene-based analysis revealed that there was no significant association between a set of these rare variations and ASD (SKAT <italic>p</italic> = 0.53).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0144624.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0144624.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Association analysis of five rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations with ASD.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0144624.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0144624.t002"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variation</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="4" rowspan="1">ASD</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Control</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allelic <italic>p</italic>
</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1/1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1/2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2/2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAF</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1/1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1/2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2/2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAF</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R24H</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Niigata</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">255</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">666</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0007</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2–41.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Nagoya</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">309</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">350</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Combined</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">564</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0009</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1016</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0005</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1–28.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F39L</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T/T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T/T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Niigata</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">255</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">664</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0015</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1–14.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Nagoya</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">308</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0016</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">352</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">∞</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Combined</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">563</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0018</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1016</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0010</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3–12.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R97H</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Niigata</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">255</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">664</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">∞</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Nagoya</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">310</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0016</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">351</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">∞</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Combined</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">565</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0018</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1015</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">∞</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T108M</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C/C</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C/T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T/T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C/C</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C/T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T/T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Niigata</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">255</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">665</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">∞</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Nagoya</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">309</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">350</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0014</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Combined</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">564</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0009</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1015</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0005</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1–28.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N152S</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/A</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G/G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Niigata</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">255</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">659</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0008</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2–41.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Nagoya</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">310</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">352</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">    Combined</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">565</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0009</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1011</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0005</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1–28.6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001">
<p>ASD, autism spectrum disorder; CI, confidence interval; MAF, mutant allele frequency; OR, odds ratio.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t002fn002">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Genotypes: reference and mutant alleles are denoted by 1 and 2, respectively.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Clinical phenotypes of patients with rare missense <italic>CLN</italic>8 variations are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0144624.t003">Table 3</xref>. R24H was identified in a male patient with autistic disorder, selective mutism, and epilepsy (patient #1). This patient corresponds to patient #1 of the Niigata cohort in our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>]. F39L was identified in a male patient with PDD-NOS (patient #2) and in a female patient with autistic disorder, dissociative fugue, and mild mental retardation (patient #3). R97H was identified in two male patients with autistic disorder (patient #4 and patient #5). T108M was identified in a female patient with Asperger’s disorder (patient #6). N152S was identified in a male patient with autistic disorder and moderate mental retardation (patient #7).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0144624.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0144624.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Clinical phenotypes of the ASD patients with rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0144624.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0144624.t003"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical phenotype</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Patient</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#1</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#2</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#3</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#4</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#5</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#6</th>
<th align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#7</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variation</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R24H</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F39L</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F39L</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R97H</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R97H</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T108M</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N152S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DSM-IV Diagnosis</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autism</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PDD-NOS</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autism</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autism</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autism</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asperger’s</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comorbidity</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Selective mutism</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dissociative fugue and mental retardation</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental retardation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Full-scale IQ</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No data</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No data</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No data</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Epilepsy</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
<td align="justify" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001">
<p>ASD, autism spectrum disorder; IQ, intelligence quotient; PDD-NOS, pervasive developmental disorder not otherwise specified.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In our previous WES study, <italic>CLN8</italic> R24H was transmitted from an affected father to three affected sons and thus co-segregated with ASD in one family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>]. In the case-control study, R24H was not significantly associated with ASD, although the H allele frequency was higher in patients than in controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>]. In this study, we resequenced the <italic>CLN8</italic> coding region in 256 ASD patients, and detected five rare missense variations (R24H, F39L, R97H, T108M and N152S). In the combined sample comprising the Niigata and Nagoya samples (568 patients and 1017 controls), which mostly overlapped with the samples in our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref003">3</xref>], all five variations had a higher mutant allele frequency in patients compared with controls. In particular, R97H was identified exclusively in two male patients with autistic disorder. However, there was no significant association between rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations and ASD. The results of our previous and present studies do not provide convergent evidence for a contribution of rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations to ASD susceptibility.</p>
<p>
<italic>CLN8</italic> encodes a protein that has five transmembrane domains (residues 21–41, 62–84, 103–123, 131–151 and 226–246), a TRAM-LAG1-CLN8 (TCL) domain (residues 62–262), and a C-terminal endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-retrieval signal (residues 283–286) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref014">14</xref>]. Genomic Evolutionary Rate Profiling (GERP; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mendel.stanford.edu/SidowLab/downloads/gerp/">http://mendel.stanford.edu/SidowLab/downloads/gerp/</ext-link>) scores for R24H and T108M were 5.09 and 5.06, respectively, indicating that these variations are evolutionarily conserved (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0144624.t001">Table 1</xref>). The functional effects of R24H and F39L were predicted to be ‘probably damaging’ by PolyPhen-2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2/">http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2/</ext-link>), whereas all five rare missense variations were predicted to be ‘tolerated’ by SIFT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.bii.a-star.edu.sg/index.html">http://sift.bii.a-star.edu.sg/index.html</ext-link>). Combined Annotation Dependent Depletion (CADD; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cadd.gs.washington.edu/home">http://cadd.gs.washington.edu/home</ext-link>) scores for R24H and T108M were 25.7 and 22.6, respectively, indicating that these variations are predicted to be among the 1% most deleterious. Nevertheless, functional analyses will be required to assess the accuracy of such predictions.</p>
<p>The neurobiology of CLN8 and the pathophysiology of ceroid lipofuscinosis-8 remain poorly understood. CLN8 is an ER resident protein that recycles between the ER and the ER-Golgi intermediate compartment using the C-terminal ER-retrieval signal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref015">15</xref>]. The mRNA levels of ER and oxidative stress marker genes are elevated in cultured fibroblasts from patients with neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses, including Northern epilepsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref016">16</xref>]. These fibroblasts show significant sensitivity to brefeldin-A-induced apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref016">16</xref>]. Levels of ER stress-associated proteins are increased in the brain of the motor neuron degeneration mouse model of ceroid lipofuscinosis-8 at the presymptomatic state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref017">17</xref>]. Taken together, these findings suggest that CLN8 dysfunction results in the impairment of ER stress responses and is, therefore, likely to be involved in the pathophysiology of ceroid lipofuscinosis-8.</p>
<p>Our ASD patients with rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations are all heterozygous, while ceroid lipofuscinosis-8 is caused by autosomal recessive mutations. Several other heterozygous <italic>CLN8</italic> missense variations have been identified by WES in 1208 Japanese individuals. These have been registered at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.med.kyoto-u.ac.jp/SnpDB/">http://www.genome.med.kyoto-u.ac.jp/SnpDB/</ext-link>. However, the variations in these Japanese individuals are not registered in the neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis (NCL) Mutation and Patient Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/ncl/mutation.shtml">http://www.ucl.ac.uk/ncl/mutation.shtml</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Chien <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref018">18</xref>] reported an ASD patient with a 2.4 Mb terminal deletion at 8p23.2-pter encompassing several genes, including <italic>CLN8</italic> and discs, large (Drosophila) homolog-associated protein 2 (<italic>DLGAP2</italic>). Haploinsufficiency of these genes may be implicated in vulnerability to ASD. Subsequently, they performed <italic>DLGAP2</italic> exon resequencing in 515 ASD patients and 596 controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref019">19</xref>]. Among 16 rare missense and nine common variations detected, two common variations were associated with ASD. However, they did not identify loss-of-function (LoF; nonsense, splice site and frameshift) mutations. That was also the case for our <italic>CLN8</italic> resequencing.</p>
<p>Two large-scale WES studies identified promising risk genes for ASD that are enriched for fragile X mental retardation protein targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref020">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref021">21</xref>]. The Autism Sequencing Consortium reported that transmission and <italic>de novo</italic> association analysis of LoF and damaging missense variations reveals 22 genes with a false discovery rate &lt; 0.05 in 3871 patients and 9937 controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref020">20</xref>]. The other WES study detected 27 genes with recurrent <italic>de novo</italic> LoF mutations in 2508 families from the Simons Simplex Collection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref021">21</xref>]. Among these 22 and 27 genes, 10 overlapped: <italic>ADNP</italic>, <italic>ANK2</italic>, <italic>ARID1B</italic>, <italic>CHD8</italic>, <italic>DYRK1A</italic>, <italic>GRIN2B</italic>, <italic>KATNAL2</italic>, <italic>POGZ</italic>, <italic>SCN2A</italic>, and <italic>TBR1</italic>. WES studies of multiplex families may be fruitful for the identification of rare inherited variations with large effects on ASD risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref022">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref023">23</xref>]. Our WES study of two families with affected siblings indicated that <italic>CLN8</italic> R24H co-segregated with ASD in one family, although <italic>CLN8</italic> was not included among promising risk genes for ASD in two large-scale WES studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref020">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref021">21</xref>]. In the present study, we performed resequencing and association analysis of <italic>CLN8</italic> in case-control samples. However, we failed to find significant associations between rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations and ASD.</p>
<p>We recognize the limitations of this study. First, our sample size (568 patients and 1017 controls) may not provide adequate statistical power to detect an association between rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations and ASD because the risk allele frequencies were extremely low (0–0.0010 in controls). Assuming a risk allele frequency of 0.001 and a genotypic relative risk for heterozygous risk allele carriers of 5.0 under the dominant model of inheritance, approximately 6000 patients and 6000 controls are needed to adequately detect association with a power of 0.80. Second, the patient groups were younger and had a higher percentage of males than the control groups in the Niigata and Nagoya samples. ASD affects more male than female individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0144624.ref001">1</xref>]. Analyzing males and females separately, we found no significant associations between rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations and ASD (data not shown). Third, we were not able to evaluate participants using standardized structured interviews. Accordingly, we could not exclude the possibility that our negative results may be due to misdiagnosis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our present study does not support the contribution of rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations to ASD susceptibility in the Japanese population.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0144624.s001">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Pedigrees of two families, each with three autism spectrum disorder siblings.</title>
<p>(A) Family #1. All three siblings (II-1, II-2, and II-3) were diagnosed with Asperger’s disorder. (B) Family #2. There were four affected individuals: a proband (II-1) with Asperger’s disorder, his brother (II-2) with Asperger’s disorder, his brother (II-3) with Asperger’s disorder and borderline intellectual functioning, and their father (I-1) with pervasive developmental disorder not otherwise specified. In family #2, a rare heterozygous missense variation, <italic>CLN8</italic> R24H, was transmitted from the affected father to the three affected sons and thus co-segregated with ASD. Shaded and unshaded symbols indicate affected and unaffected individuals, respectively. Squares and circles represent males and females, respectively.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="pone.0144624.s001.tif">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0144624.s002">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Primer sequences used for resequencing the <italic>CLN8</italic> coding region.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="pone.0144624.s002.doc">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0144624.s003">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Probes used for TaqMan SNP assays.</title>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="pone.0144624.s003.doc">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0144624.s004">
<label>S3 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Genotypes of five rare missense <italic>CLN8</italic> variations for each participant.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="pone.0144624.s004.xlsx">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank the patients, their families, and the healthy volunteers for participation, and Ms. Yamazaki for excellent technical assistance.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref001">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baron-Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Autism</article-title>. <source/>Lancet
<year>2014</year>;<volume>383</volume>:<fpage>896</fpage>–<lpage>910</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61539-1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074734</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref002">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gaugler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bodea</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Most genetic risk for autism resides with common variation</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet
<year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>881</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3039</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038753</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref003">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Egawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Novel rare missense variations and risk of autism spectrum disorder: whole-exome sequencing in two families with affected siblings and a two-stage follow-up study in a Japanese population</article-title>. <source/>PLoS One
<year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0119413</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119413</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25806950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref004">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ranta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lonka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takkunen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses in human EPMR and <italic>mnd</italic> mutant mice are associated with mutations in <italic>CLN8</italic>
</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet
<year>1999</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref005">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ranta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Topcu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tegelberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ustübütün</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saatci</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Variant late infantile neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis in a subset of Turkish patients is allelic to Northern epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mutat
<year>2004</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref006">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vantaggiato</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Redaelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Falcone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perrotta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bondioni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A novel CLN8 mutation in late-infantile-onset neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis (LINCL) reveals aspects of CLN8 neurobiological function</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mutat
<year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1104</fpage>–<lpage>1116</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.21012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19431184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref007">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Courchesne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Solso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain growth across the life span in autism: age-specific changes in anatomical pathology</article-title>. <source/>Brain Res
<year>2011</year>;<volume>1380</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2010.09.101</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20920490</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref008">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Courchesne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mouton</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Semendeferi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ahrens-Barbeau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hallet</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Neuron number and size in prefrontalcortex of children with autism</article-title>. <source/>JAMA
<year>2011</year>;<volume>306</volume>:<fpage>2001</fpage>–<lpage>2010</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2011.1638</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22068992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref009">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>The apoptotic perspective of autism</article-title>. <source/>Int J Dev Neurosci
<year>2014</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2014.04.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24798024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref010">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nunokawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arinami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The <italic>dopamine D3 receptor</italic> (<italic>DRD3</italic>) gene and risk of schizophrenia: case-control studies and an updated meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/>Schizophr Res
<year>2010</year>;<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2009.10.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref011">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muratake</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nunokawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Someya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>No association between the <italic>brain-derived neurotrophic factor</italic> gene and schizophrenia in a Japanese population</article-title>. <source/>Schizophr Res
<year>2006</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16631352</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref012">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boehnke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rare Variant Association Testing for Sequencing Data Using the Sequence Kernel Association Test (SKAT)</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<year>2011</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2011.05.029</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21737059</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref013">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Todd-Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MAR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>PLINK: a toolset for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analysis</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<year>2007</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref014">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kousi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehesjoki</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mole</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Update of the mutation spectrum and clinical correlations of over 360 mutations in eight genes that underlie the neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mutat
<year>2012</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.21624</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21990111</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref015">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lonka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kyttälä</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ranta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jalanko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehesjoki</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>. <article-title>The neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis CLN8 membrane protein is a resident of the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<year>2000</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1691</fpage>–<lpage>1697</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10861296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref016">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>. <article-title>ER and oxidative stresses are common mediators of apoptosis in both neurodegenerative and non-neurodegenerative lysosomal storage disorders and are alleviated by chemical chaperones</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17989065</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref017">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Galizzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deidda</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cascio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Passantino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guarneri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Different early ER-stress responses in the CLN8<sup><italic>mnd</italic></sup> mouse model of neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis</article-title>. <source/>Neurosci Lett
<year>2011</year>;<volume>488</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2010.11.041</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21094208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref018">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gau</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Identification and molecular characterization of two novel chromosomal deletions associated with autism</article-title>. <source/>Clin Genet
<year>2010</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-0004.2010.01395.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20236125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref019">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gau</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Deep exon resequencing of <italic>DLGAP2</italic> as a candidate gene of autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source/>Mol Autism
<year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2040-2392-4-26</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23915500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref020">
<label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>De Rubeis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poultney</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samocha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cicek</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Synaptic, transcriptional and chromatin genes disrupted in autism</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<year>2014</year>;<volume>515</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13772</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25363760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref021">
<label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Iossifov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Roak</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronemus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krumm</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The contribution of <italic>de novo</italic> coding mutations to autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<year>2014</year>;<volume>515</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13908</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25363768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref022">
<label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chahrour</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiralerspong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamura-Ikeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ataman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Using whole-exome sequencing to identify inherited causes of autism</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<year>2013</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2012.11.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23352163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0144624.ref023">
<label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Toma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torrico</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hervás</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valdés-Mas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tristán-Noguero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Padillo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Exome sequencing in multiplex autism families suggests a major role for heterozygous truncating mutations</article-title>. <source/>Mol Psychiatry
<year>2014</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>784</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2013.106</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23999528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>