<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9206090</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2125</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Intellect Disabil Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Intellect Disabil Res</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of intellectual disability research : JIDR</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0964-2633</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1365-2788</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26610738</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4720543</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jir.12226</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS718676</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Emergence and Stability of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in Boys with Fragile X Syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grefer</surname>
<given-names>Marjorie</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>M.A.</degrees>
<aff id="A1">Department of Psychology, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Flory</surname>
<given-names>Kate</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
<aff id="A2">Department of Psychology, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cornish</surname>
<given-names>Kim</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
<aff id="A3">School of Psychological Sciences, Monash University, Melbourne, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hatton</surname>
<given-names>Deborah</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
<aff id="A4">Department of Special Education, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>Jane</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
<aff id="A5">Department of Psychology, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: Post-publication correspondence regarding this article should be sent to Marjorie Grefer, University of South Carolina, 1512 Pendleton St., Barnwell College, Columbia, SC 29208 (<email>grefer@emil.sc.edu</email>; Phone: 859-409-0909; Fax: 803-777-5676)</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>4</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>27</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>60</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>167</fpage>
<lpage>178</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1111/jir.12226-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Background</title>
<p id="P1">Children with fragile X syndrome (FXS) are at high risk for developing a range of behavioral disorders, including Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and autism spectrum disorders (ASD). However, very few studies have investigated the comorbid profile of FXS and ADHD and the possible dissociation from the FXS and ASD profile. The present study examined the relationship of childhood temperament characteristics of the Surgency facet (activity level, impulsivity, approach, shyness, and smiling and laughter) and the severity of ADHD and ASD features at two measurement time points in childhood, preschool (ages 3–4) and at school entry (ages 5–6).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P2">The study consisted of males with FXS measured at each time point (preschool and school entry), as well as comparison of typically developing (TD) boys at the preschool measurement time point. Parent reported measures of temperament and behavioral symptoms were collected at each time point. Multiple regression analyses were used to analyze obtained data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">Elevated activity level scores are associated with ADHD scores at preschool age and elevated shyness and decreased smiling and laughter is strongly associated with ADHD scores upon school entry. Impulsivity emerges as a strong indicator of elevated ADHD scores around school age, but even preschool impulsivity scores demonstrate some predictive value for higher ADHD scores later in school. Finally, no Surgency characteristic was significantly related to ASD scores at any age.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P4">Impulsivity serves as an indicator of elevated ADHD symptoms across development periods in boys with FXS, while activity level is just indicative of higher ADHD scores at the preschool age. The Surgency facet of temperament at either age does not predict strong relationships of comorbid pathologies of ADHD and ASD in FXS. However, Surgency characteristics may serve as informative discriminative factors when studying behavioral outcomes in boys with FXS.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>