<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Endocr Rev</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Endocr. Rev</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">edrv</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">endre</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">edrv</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">edrv</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Endocrine Reviews</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0163-769X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1945-7189</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Endocrine Society</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26595189</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4740344</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ER-15-1090</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/er.2015-1090</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Thyroglobulin From Molecular and Cellular Biology to Clinical Endocrinology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Di Jeso</surname>
<given-names>Bruno</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Arvan</surname>
<given-names>Peter</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff>Laboratorio di Patologia Generale (B.D.J.), Dipartimento di Scienze e Tecnologie Biologiche ed Ambientali, Università del Salento, 73100 Lecce, Italy; and Division of Metabolism, Endocrinology, and Diabetes (P.A.), University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, Michigan 48105</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>Address all correspondence and requests for reprints to: Dr Bruno Di Jeso, <addr-line>Laboratorio di Patologia Generale, Dipartimento di Scienze e Tecnologie Biologiche ed Ambientali, Universita‘ del Salento, Centro Ecotekne, 73100 Lecce, Italy.</addr-line> E-mail: <email>bruno.dijeso@unisalento.it</email> and Dr Peter Arvan, <addr-line>Division of Metabolism, Endocrinology and Diabetes, University of Michigan, Brehm Center, Room 5112, 1000 Wall Street, Ann Arbor, MI 48105-51714.</addr-line> E-mail: <email>parvan@umich.edu</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>23</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>23</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 12 months and
						0 days and was based on the <pub-date
						pub-type="epub"/>. -->
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>2</fpage>
<lpage>36</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>17</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 by the Endocrine Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="zef00116000002.pdf" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Thyroglobulin (Tg) is a vertebrate secretory protein synthesized in the thyrocyte endoplasmic reticulum (ER), where it acquires N-linked glycosylation and conformational maturation (including formation of many disulfide bonds), leading to homodimerization. Its primary functions include iodide storage and thyroid hormonogenesis. Tg consists largely of repeating domains, and many tyrosyl residues in these domains become iodinated to form monoiodo- and diiodotyrosine, whereas only a small portion of Tg structure is dedicated to hormone formation. Interestingly, evolutionary ancestors, dependent upon thyroid hormone for development, synthesize thyroid hormones without the complete Tg protein architecture. Nevertheless, in all vertebrates, Tg follows a strict pattern of region I, II-III, and the cholinesterase-like (ChEL) domain. In vertebrates, Tg first undergoes intracellular transport through the secretory pathway, which requires the assistance of thyrocyte ER chaperones and oxidoreductases, as well as coordination of distinct regions of Tg, to achieve a native conformation. Curiously, regions II-III and ChEL behave as fully independent folding units that could function as successful secretory proteins by themselves. However, the large Tg region I (bearing the primary T<sub>4</sub>-forming site) is incompetent by itself for intracellular transport, requiring the downstream regions II-III and ChEL to complete its folding. A combination of nonsense mutations, frameshift mutations, splice site mutations, and missense mutations in Tg occurs spontaneously to cause congenital hypothyroidism and thyroidal ER stress. These Tg mutants are unable to achieve a native conformation within the ER, interfering with the efficiency of Tg maturation and export to the thyroid follicle lumen for iodide storage and hormonogenesis.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>