<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101235742</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32212</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Med. Genet. B Neuropsychiatr. Genet.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>American journal of medical genetics. Part B, Neuropsychiatric genetics : the official publication of the International Society of Psychiatric Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4841</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-485X</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26592203</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4754782</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.32395</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS758817</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>RDoC and Translational Perspectives on the Genetics of Trauma-Related Psychiatric Disorders</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Montalvo-Ortiz</surname>
<given-names>Janitza L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gelernter</surname>
<given-names>Joel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hudziak</surname>
<given-names>James</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kaufman</surname>
<given-names>Joan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Psychiatry, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Veteran's Administration Connecticut Health Care Center, Newington, Connecticut</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Vermont Center for Children, Youth, and Families, University of Vermont, Burlington, Vermont</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Center for Child and Family Traumatic Stress, Kennedy Krieger Institute, Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Joan Kaufman, Ph.D., Center for Child and Family Traumatic Stress, Kennedy Krieger Institute, 1750 East Fairmont Street, Baltimore, MD 21231. <email>joan.kaufman@kennedykrieger.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>11</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>22</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>16</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>171</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>91</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/ajmg.b.32395-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Individuals with a history of child abuse are at high risk for depression, anxiety disorders, aggressive behavior, and substance use problems. The goal of this paper is to review studies of the genetics of these stress-related psychiatric disorders. An informative subset of studies that examined candidate gene by environment (GxE) predictors of these psychiatric problems in individuals maltreated as children is reviewed, together with extant genome wide association studies (GWAS). Emerging findings on epigenetic changes associated with adverse early experiences are also reviewed. Meta-analytic support and replicated findings are evident for several genetic risk factors; however, extant research suggests the effects are pleiotropic. Genetic factors are not associated with distinct psychiatric disorders, but rather diverse clinical phenotypes. Research also suggests adverse early life experiences are associated with changes in gene expression of multiple known candidate genes, genes involved in DNA transcription and translation, and genes necessary for brain circuitry development, with changes in gene expression reported in key brain structures implicated in the pathophysiology of psychiatric and substance use disorders. The finding of pleiotropy highlights the value of using the Research Domain Criteria (RDoC) framework in future studies of the genetics of stress-related psychiatric disorders, and not trying simply to link genes to multifaceted clinical syndromes, but to more limited phenotypes that map onto distinct neural circuits. Emerging work in the field of epigenetics also suggests that translational studies that integrate numerous unbiased genome-wide approaches will help to further unravel the genetics of stress-related psychiatric disorders.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>child abuse</kwd>
<kwd>psychiatric disorders</kwd>
<kwd>genetics</kwd>
<kwd>epigenetics</kwd>
<kwd>RDoC</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>