<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0236217</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6077</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuropharmacology</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neuropharmacology</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Neuropharmacology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0028-3908</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-7064</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26707655</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4755829</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2015.12.015</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS747742</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Transgenic Mice with Increased Astrocyte Expression of IL-6 Show Altered Effects of Acute Ethanol on Synaptic Function</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hernandez</surname>
<given-names>Ruben V.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Puro</surname>
<given-names>Alana C.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manos</surname>
<given-names>Jessica C.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huitron-Resendiz</surname>
<given-names>Salvador</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reyes</surname>
<given-names>Kenneth C.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Kevin</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vo</surname>
<given-names>Khanh</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>Amanda J.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gruol</surname>
<given-names>Donna L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience Department, The Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, CA 92037 U.S.A.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Dr. Donna L. Gruol, MCND, SP30-1522, The Scripps Research Institute, 10550 North Torrey Pines Road, La Jolla, CA 92037, Phone: (858) 784-7060, Fax: (858) 784- 7393, <email>gruol@scripps.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2">
<p id="P69">
<bold>Conflict of interest</bold>
</p>
<p id="P70">The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>30</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>17</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>43</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.neuropharm.2015.12.015-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">A growing body of evidence has revealed that resident cells of the central nervous system (CNS), and particularly the glial cells, comprise a neuroimmune system that serves a number of functions in the normal CNS and during adverse conditions. Cells of the neuroimmune system regulate CNS functions through the production of signaling factors, referred to as neuroimmune factors. Recent studies show that ethanol can activate cells of the neuroimmune system, resulting in the elevated production of neuroimmune factors, including the cytokine interleukin-6 (IL-6). Here we analyzed the consequences of this CNS action of ethanol using transgenic mice that express elevated levels of IL-6 through increased astrocyte expression (IL-6-tg) to model the increased IL-6 expression that occurs with ethanol use. Results show that increased IL-6 expression induces neuroadaptive changes that alter the effects of ethanol. In hippocampal slices from non-transgenic (non-tg) littermate control mice, synaptically evoked dendritic field excitatory postsynaptic potential (fEPSP) and somatic population spike (PS) at the Schaffer collateral to CA1 pyramidal neuron synapse were reduced by acute ethanol (20 or 60 mM). In contrast, acute ethanol enhanced the fEPSP and PS in hippocampal slices from IL-6 tg mice. Long-term synaptic plasticity of the fEPSP (i.e., LTP) showed the expected dose-dependent reduction by acute ethanol in non-tg hippocampal slices, whereas LTP in the IL-6 tg hippocampal slices was resistant to this depressive effect of acute ethanol. Consistent with altered effects of acute ethanol on synaptic function in the IL-6 tg mice, EEG recordings showed a higher level of CNS activity in the IL-6 tg mice than in the non-tg mice during the period of withdrawal from an acute high dose of ethanol. These results suggest a potential role for neuroadaptive effects of ethanol-induced astrocyte production of IL-6 as a mediator or modulator of the actions of ethanol on the CNS, including persistent changes in CNS function that contribute to cognitive dysfunction and the development of alcohol dependence.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>synaptic plasticity</kwd>
<kwd>EEG</kwd>
<kwd>gamma frequency</kwd>
<kwd>glia</kwd>
<kwd>ethanol withdrawal hyperexcitability</kwd>
<kwd>neuroimmune</kwd>
<kwd>STAT3</kwd>
<kwd>long-term potentiation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>