<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jneuro</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jneurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J. Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Journal of Neuroscience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0270-6474</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1529-2401</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Society for Neuroscience</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26911691</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4764663</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3195-15</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3195-15.2016</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Development/Plasticity/Repair</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An Allometric Analysis of Sex and Sex Chromosome Dosage Effects on Subcortical Anatomy in Humans</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Reardon</surname>
<given-names>Paul Kirkpatrick</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clasen</surname>
<given-names>Liv</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giedd</surname>
<given-names>Jay N.</given-names>
</name>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2002-8978</contrib-id>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blumenthal</surname>
<given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lerch</surname>
<given-names>Jason P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chakravarty</surname>
<given-names>M. Mallar</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Raznahan</surname>
<given-names>Armin</given-names>
</name>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5622-1190</contrib-id>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Developmental Neurogenomics Unit, Child Psychiatry Branch, National Institute of Mental Health, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 20892, </aff>
<aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Psychiatry, University of California San Diego, San Diego, California 92093, </aff>
<aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Psychiatry and Institute of Biomaterials and Biomedical Engineering, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario M5T 1R8, Canada, </aff>
<aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>Computational Brain Anatomy Laboratory, Cerebral Imaging Centre, Douglas Mental Health University Institute, Montreal, Quebec H4H 1R3, Canada, and </aff>
<aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup>Departments of Psychiatry and Biomedical Engineering, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec H3A 1A1, Canada</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>Correspondence may be addressed to Kirk Reardon,
<addr-line>Developmental Neurogenomics Unit, Child Psychiatry Branch, 10 Center Drive, Building 10, Room 3D42, Bethesda, MD 20892.</addr-line><email>kirk.reardon@nih.gov</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p>Author contributions: P.K.R., J.N.G., J.B., and A.R. designed research; P.K.R., L.C., J.B., J.P.L., M.M.C., and A.R. performed research; J.P.L. and M.M.C. contributed unpublished reagents/analytic tools; P.K.R. and A.R. analyzed data; P.K.R., L.C., and A.R. wrote the paper.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>24</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>24</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 6 months and
						0 days and was based on the <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>2438</fpage>
<lpage>2448</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>25</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>5</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>11</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 the authors 0270-6474/16/362438-11$15.00/0</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="zns00816002438.pdf" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Structural neuroimaging of humans with typical and atypical sex-chromosome complements has established the marked influence of both Yand X-/Y-chromosome dosage on total brain volume (TBV) and identified potential cortical substrates for the psychiatric phenotypes associated with sex-chromosome aneuploidy (SCA). Here, in a cohort of 354 humans with varying karyotypes (XX, XY, XXX, XXY, XYY, XXYY, XXXXY), we investigate sex and SCA effects on subcortical size and shape; focusing on the striatum, pallidum and thalamus. We find large effect-size differences in the volume and shape of all three structures as a function of sex and SCA. We correct for TBV effects with a novel allometric method harnessing normative scaling rules for subcortical size and shape in humans, which we derive here for the first time. We show that all three subcortical volumes scale sublinearly with TBV among healthy humans, mirroring known relationships between subcortical volume and TBV among species. Traditional TBV correction methods assume linear scaling and can therefore invert or exaggerate sex and SCA effects on subcortical anatomy. Allometric analysis restricts sex-differences to: (1) greater pallidal volume (PV) in males, and (2) relative caudate head expansion and ventral striatum contraction in females. Allometric analysis of SCA reveals that supernumerary X- and Y-chromosomes both cause disproportionate reductions in PV, and coordinated deformations of striatopallidal shape. Our study provides a novel understanding of sex and sex-chromosome dosage effects on subcortical organization, using an allometric approach that can be generalized to other basic and clinical structural neuroimaging settings.</p>
<p><bold>SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT</bold> Sex and sex-chromosome dosage (SCD) are known to modulate human brain size and cortical anatomy, but very little is known regarding their impact on subcortical structures that work with the cortex to subserve a range of behaviors in health and disease. Moreover, regional brain allometry (nonlinear scaling) poses largely unaddressed methodological and theoretical challenges for such research. We build the first set of allometric norms for global and regional subcortical anatomy, and use these to dissect out the complex, distributed and topologically organized patterns of areal contraction and expansion, which characterize sex and SCD effects on subcortical anatomy. Our data inform basic research into the patterning of neuroanatomical variation, and the clinical neuroscience of sex-chromosome aneuploidy.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>allometry</kwd>
<kwd>aneuploidy</kwd>
<kwd>morphometry</kwd>
<kwd>sex</kwd>
<kwd>subcortex</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>