<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8501362</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2898</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chronobiol Int</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chronobiol. Int.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Chronobiology international</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0742-0528</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1525-6073</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26512752</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4785888</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2015.1087021</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS760369</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Circadian Regulation Gene Polymorphisms are Associated with Sleep Disruption and Duration, and Circadian Phase and Rhythm in Adults with HIV</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Kathryn A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gay</surname>
<given-names>Caryl</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Byun</surname>
<given-names>Eeeseung</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN, PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lerdal</surname>
<given-names>Anners</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pullinger</surname>
<given-names>Clive R.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aouizerat</surname>
<given-names>Bradley E.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MAS, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Family Health Care Nursing, University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Lovisenberg Diakonale Hospital, Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Nursing Science, Institute of Health and Society, Faculty of Medicine, University of Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Physiological Nursing, University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Cardiovascular Research Institute, University of California at San Francisco, CA, USA</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Institute for Human Genetics, University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Corresponding Author: Kathryn A. Lee, RN, PhD, FAAN, School of Nursing, Box 0606, University of California, San Francisco, 2 Koret Way, Room N415Y, San Francisco, CA 94143-0606, (415) 476-4442 (phone) (415) 753-2161 (fax), <email>Kathryn.lee@nursing.ucsf.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2">
<p>
<bold>Declaration of Interest</bold>
</p>
<p>This research was supported by a grant from the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH, 5 R01 MH074358). Post-doctoral funding for Eeeseung Byun was provided by the National Institutes of Health/National Institute of Nursing Research (T32 NR007088). Data collection was supported by the General Clinical Research Center in the UCSF CTSA (1 UL RR024131). The authors report no conflicts of interest. The authors alone are responsible for the content and writing of the paper.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>18</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>29</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<fpage>1278</fpage>
<lpage>1293</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.3109/07420528.2015.1087021-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Genes involved in circadian regulation, such as circadian locomotor output cycles kaput [<italic>CLOCK</italic>]<italic>,</italic> cryptochrome [<italic>CRY1</italic>], and period [<italic>PER</italic>], have been associated with sleep outcomes in prior animal and human research. However, it is unclear whether polymorphisms in these genes are associated with the sleep disturbances commonly experienced by adults living with human immunodeficiency virus/acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (HIV/AIDS). Thus, the purpose of this study was to describe polymorphisms in selected circadian genes that are associated with sleep duration or disruption as well as the sleep-wake rhythm strength and phase timing among adults living with HIV/AIDS. A convenience sample of 289 adults with HIV/AIDS was recruited from HIV clinics and community sites in the San Francisco Bay Area. A wrist actigraph was worn for 72 hours on weekdays to estimate sleep duration or total sleep time (TST), sleep disruption or percentage of wake after sleep onset (WASO), and several circadian rhythm parameters: mesor, amplitude, the ratio of mesor to amplitude (circadian quotient), and 24-hour autocorrelation. Circadian phase measures included clock time for peak activity (acrophase) from actigraphy movement data, and bed time and final wake time from actigraphy and self-report. Genotyping was conducted for polymorphisms in 5 candidate genes involved in circadian regulation: <italic>CLOCK</italic>, <italic>CRY1</italic>, <italic>PER1, PER2,</italic> and <italic>PER3</italic>. Demographic and clinical variables were evaluated as potential covariates. Interactions between genotype and HIV variables (i.e., viral load, years since HIV diagnosis) were also evaluated. Controlling for potentially confounding variables (e.g., race, gender, CD4+ T-cell count, waist circumference, medication use, smoking, depressive symptoms), <italic>CLOCK</italic> was associated with WASO, 24-hour autocorrelation, and objectively-measured bed time; <italic>CRY1</italic> was associated with circadian quotient; <italic>PER1</italic> was associated with mesor and self-reported habitual wake time; <italic>PER2</italic> was associated with TST, mesor, circadian quotient, 24-hour autocorrelation, and bed and wake times; <italic>PER3</italic> was associated with amplitude, 24-hour autocorrelation, acrophase, and bed and wake times. Most of the observed associations involved a significant interaction between genotype and HIV. In this chronic illness population, polymorphisms in several circadian genes were associated with measures of sleep disruption and timing. These findings extend the evidence for an association between genetic variability in circadian regulation and sleep outcomes to include the sleep-wake patterns experienced by adults living with HIV/AIDS. These results provide direction for future intervention research related to circadian sleep-wake behavior patterns.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>circadian</kwd>
<kwd>genetic</kwd>
<kwd>HIV</kwd>
<kwd>autocorrelation</kwd>
<kwd>mesor</kwd>
<kwd>acrophase</kwd>
<kwd>actigraphy</kwd>
<kwd>chronotype</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>