<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="letter" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hum Genome Var</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hum Genome Var</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Human Genome Variation</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2054-345X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27081545</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4785581</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pii">hgv201537</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hgv.2015.37</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Data Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A novel <italic>SLC6A8</italic> mutation associated with motor dysfunction in a child exhibiting creatine transporter deficiency</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running">A novel <italic>SLC6A8</italic> mutation associated with motor dysfunction</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cervera-Acedo</surname>
<given-names>Cristina</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lopez</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aguirre-Lamban</surname>
<given-names>Jana</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Santibañez</surname>
<given-names>Paula</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Garcia-Oguiza</surname>
<given-names>Alberto</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Poch-Olive</surname>
<given-names>Maria Luisa</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dominguez-Garrido</surname>
<given-names>Elena</given-names>
</name>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2066-0511</contrib-id>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>
<institution>Molecular Diagnostics Laboratory, Center for Biomedical Research (CIBIR), Fundacion Rioja Salud</institution>, Logroño, <country>Spain</country>
</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Department of Pediatrics, San Pedro Hospital</institution>
, Logroño, <country>Spain</country>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>
(<email>edominguez@riojasalud.es</email>)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="equal" id="note1">
<label>3</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>29</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>15037</fpage>
<lpage></lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>16</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>13</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>14</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 The Japan Society of Human Genetics</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The Japan Society of Human Genetics</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--author-paid-->
<license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Creatine transporter (CT) deficiency is an X-linked disorder caused by mutations in the <italic>SLC6A8</italic> gene. We describe a clinical, biochemical and molecular examination of a child with X-linked cerebral creatine deficiency. Increased urinary creatine/creatinine ratio, abnormal brain proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy and reduced creatine transport confirmed the clinical diagnosis. <italic>SLC6A8</italic> analysis revealed a novel mutation that was hemizygous in the child and not detected in his mother. CT deficiency should be considered in children, especially males, with mental retardation.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Creatine transporter (CT) deficiency (OMIM 300036) has been reported to be the most common cerebral creatine deficiency syndrome (CCDS) and may be one of the leading causes of X-linked mental retardation (X-LMR) in males, with a prevalence of 2.1% according to a European X-LMR panel.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup> Clinical symptoms include delays in speech and language development, intellectual disabilities, autistic-like behavior and in some cases, seizures. However, clinical severity greatly varies, with some children exhibiting marked developmental delay and seizures and others having more modest clinical involvement.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup> X-LMR is caused by mutations in the <italic>SLC6A8</italic> gene, a member of the solute-carrier family 6 mapped to Xq28.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup> The transporter encoded by this gene, CT1, is a multi-pass membrane protein required for the uptake of creatinine in muscles and the brain. CT1 is widely expressed in brain tissue, predominantly in the cortical and subcortical regions involved in motor and sensory processing, learning, memory, and regulation of emotion-related behavior.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref></sup> To date, numerous mutations in the <italic>SLC6A8</italic> gene have been described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>The diagnosis of brain creatine deficiency is based on clinical presentation, an increased urinary creatine/creatinine (Cr/Crn) ratio, and abnormal brain Cr content assessed by brain magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> Nevertheless, brain MRS is not always feasible, and diagnosis is commonly based on clinical presentation and/or the presence of biochemical markers, such as an increased urinary Cr/Crn ratio and differential diagnosis for CT deficiency from other CCDS. The diagnosis is confirmed by measuring long-term Cr accumulation in fibroblasts or via DNA testing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> Here we describe a case of a boy who initially exhibited motor dysfunction and hypotonia and who presented with a new splicing mutation in the <italic>SLC6A8</italic> gene.</p>
<p>The patient was a 12-year-old Caucasian male born at term after an uneventful pregnancy, with an Apgar score of 9–10 and normal weight, length, and head circumference at birth. The parents were both unrelated and healthy. The patient was referred to the neuropediatric unit for evaluation and early intervention for mild hypotonia and motor delay at 15 months of age. He walked independently and uttered the first words at the age of 3 years. Simple focal seizures with secondary generalization were present from 2 to 6 years of age, and most seizures were of short duration, febrile, and non-febrile and well controlled with antiepileptic drugs. At 6 years old, the patient was submitted to a comprehensive neuropsychological evaluation to assess cognitive, speech, and social and personal ability. The Battelle Developmental Inventory total developmental quotient score was 60, with discrepancy between nonverbal and verbal skills; he exhibited qualitative communication difficulties on the Autism Diagnostic Interview-Revised. Video electroencephalography recording revealed multifocal spike and polispike waves at right frontal, temporal, and posterior regions. As then, changes in the frequency and complexity of seizures, abnormal visual sensation (colored lights), and abdominal pain and nausea have been observed. Currently, he exhibits moderately delayed motor development and learning, slight hyperactivity, and much better behavior. Seizures occur every 3–4 months.</p>
<p>Biochemical screening was performed with blood and urine samples. The Cr/Crn ratio was determined in two urine samples taken on different days. Cr uptake was assayed in fibroblasts after incubation for 24 h in medium containing physiological and supraphysiological Cr concentrations (25 and 500 μM, respectively) according to a previously reported procedure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref></sup> An abnormal Cr/Crn ratio was observed in the two urine samples (2.66 and 4.56: reference value &lt;1.5). Cr uptake in fibroblasts was nearly undetectable in culture when incubated at a physiological Cr concentration. Cr uptake after incubation with supraphysiological levels of Cr was &lt;25% compared with control cells, indicating impaired Cr uptake in fibroblasts.</p>
<p>Brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and proton MRS (<sup>1</sup>H-MRS) were performed to confirm the diagnosis. MRI showed hyperintense T2/FLAIR signals at the periventricular bifrontal white matter and semioval centers, and <sup>1</sup>H-MRS revealed a marked reduction of Cr peak.</p>
<p>Molecular analysis of blood samples from the proband and his parents were obtained after obtaining informed consent. Genomic DNA and RNA were obtained from peripheral blood using QIAamp DNA Mini Kit and QIAamp RNA Blood Mini Kit, respectively (QIAGEN GmgH, Hilden, Germany). Karyotype, CGH array 60 K (Agilent Technologies, California, USA) and a molecular study of <italic>SCN1A</italic> and <italic>FMR1</italic> genes were performed as part of clinical care, and all were normal. Multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA) (SALSA MLPA kit P049-B2, MRC-Holland, Amsterdam, Netherlands) PCR and reverse transcription–PCR, including direct gene sequencing of all exons and the flanking intronic sequences of the <italic>SLC6A8</italic> gene, were conducted. Regarding the molecular analysis, MLPA showed an aberrant pattern. DNA and cDNA sequence analysis of the <italic>SLC6A8</italic> gene revealed a 34-base pair (bp) deletion (c.1016+11_1017-52del, intron 6) at the DNA level that produced a 30-bp deletion in exon 7 (r.1017_1046del) in cDNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). The variant was considered pathogenic by splice-site analysis with the NetGene2 Server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetGene2/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetGene2/</ext-link>) and Human Splicing Finder (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.umd.be/HSF/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.umd.be/HSF/</ext-link>). The variant was not found in 100 control samples. The mutation was not detected in the mother, and therefore, it was considered <italic>de novo</italic>. However, somatic mosaicism cannot be excluded; family counseling and prenatal diagnosis during further pregnancies should be offered. This splicing mutation variant has not been previously described, and splicing mutations in <italic>SLC6A8</italic> are less common, as reported by van de Kamp <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Disorders of creatine synthesis and cellular transport result in brain creatine deficiency and represent a relatively novel cause of mental retardation and seizures. Patients with X-linked CT deficiency can have different clinical presentations, even within the same family, with developmental delays/mental retardation being present in all patients. This disease is suspected to be due to reduced brain creatine content, as detected by MRS. The increased Cr/Crn ratio in urine further verifies the diagnosis.</p>
<p>Treatment of patients with CT deficiency remains ineffective. In addition, cyclocreatine treatment in brain-specific SCL6A8 knockout mice, an animal model of human CT deficiency, showed promising results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup> The identification of new cases of CT deficiency is important, and the inclusion of Cr/Crn urine analysis in screening patients with these neurological symptoms should be considered.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref></sup> Rosenberg <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup> recommended that once increased Cr/Crn is detected, the diagnosis of CT deficiency should be confirmed by functional studies and/or DNA testing.</p>
<p>In conclusion, we report a case of a moderate form of CT deficiency caused by a novel <italic>SLC6A8</italic> mutation. Information about genotype–phenotype correlations is important for understanding genetic disorders such as CT deficiency.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="bib1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Clark AJ
, 
Rosenberg EH
, 
Almeida LS
, 
Wood TC
, 
Jakobs C
, 
Stevenson RE
et al. <article-title>X-linked creatine transporter (<italic>SLC6A8</italic>) mutations in about 1% of males with mental retardation of unknown etiology</article-title>. <source/>Hum Genet
<year>2006</year>; <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>604</fpage>–610.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16738945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Rosenberg EH
, 
Almeida LS
, 
Kleefstra T
, 
deGrauw RS
, 
Yntema HG
, 
Bahi N
et al. <article-title>High prevalence of <italic>SLC6A8</italic> deficiency in X-linked mental retardation</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<year>2004</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–105.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15154114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">
Stevenson RE
, 
Schwartz CE
, 
Schroer RJ
. <source/>X-linked Mental Retardation. Oxford University Press: New York, <year>2000</year>. </mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Salomons GS
, 
van Dooren SJ
, 
Verhoeven NM
, 
Cecil KM
, 
Ball WS
, 
Degrauw TJ
et al. <article-title>X-linked creatine-transporter gene (<italic>SLC6A8</italic>) defect: a new creatine-deficiency syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<year>2001</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1497</fpage>–1500.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Cecil KM
, 
Salomons GS
, 
Ball WSJ
, 
Wong B
, 
Chuck G
, 
Verhoeven NM
et al. <article-title>Irreversible brain creatine deficiency with elevated serum and urine creatine: a creatine transporter defect?</article-title>
<source/>Ann Neurol
<year>2001</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–404.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11261517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Betsalel OT
, 
Rosenberg EH
, 
Almeida LS
, 
Kleefstra T
, 
Schwartz CE
, 
Valayannopoulos V
et al. <article-title>Characterization of novel <italic>SLC6A8</italic> variants with the use of splice-site analysis tools and implementation of a newly developed LOVD database</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Hum Genet
<year>2011</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>–63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20717164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
van de Kamp JM
, 
Betsalel OT
, 
Mercimek-Mahmutoglu S
, 
Abulhoul L
, 
Grünewald S
, 
Anselm I
et al. <article-title>Phenotype and genotype in 101 males with X-linked creatine transporter deficiency</article-title>. <source/>J Med Genet
<year>2013</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>–472.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23644449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Dreha-Kulaczewski S
, 
Kalscheuer V
, 
Tzschach A
, 
Hu H
, 
Helms G
, 
Brockmann K
et al. <article-title>A novel <italic>SLC6A8</italic> mutation in a large family with X-linked intellectual disability: clinical and proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy data of both hemizygous males and heterozygous females</article-title>. <source/>JIMD Rep
<year>2014</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>–99.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24190795</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Arias A
, 
Corbella M
, 
Fons C
, 
Sempere A
, 
García-Villoria J
, 
Ormazabal A
et al. <article-title>Creatine transporter deficiency: prevalence among patients with mental retardation and pitfalls in metabolite screening</article-title>. <source/>Clin Biochem
<year>2007</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1328</fpage>–1331.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17825809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Stockler S
, 
Schutz PW
, 
Salomons GS
. <article-title>Cerebral creatine deficiency syndromes: clinical aspects, treatment and pathophysiology</article-title>. <source/>Subcell Biochem
<year>2007</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–166.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18652076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Almeida LS
, 
Verhoeven NM
, 
Roos B
. <article-title>Creatine and guanidinoacetate: diagnostic markers for inborn errors in creatine biosynthesis and transport</article-title>. <source/>Mol Genet Metab
<year>2004</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>–219.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15234334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Rosenberg EH
, 
Martinez Munoz C
, 
Betsalel OT
, 
van Dooren SJ
, 
Fernandez M
, 
Jakobs C
et al. <article-title>Functional characterization of missense variants in the creatine transporter gene (<italic>SLC6A8</italic>): improved diagnostic application</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mutat
<year>2007</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>890</fpage>–896.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17465020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<ref-list content-type="data-citations">
<title>Data Citations</title>
<ref id="d1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="data"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cristina</surname><given-names>Cervera-Acedo</given-names></name></person-group><data-title>HGV Database</data-title>. <year>2015</year>. <pub-id assigning-authority="figshare" pub-id-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.702" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.702</pub-id>. </mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="fig1">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Schematic representation of direct DNA (<bold>a</bold>) and cDNA (<bold>b</bold>) sequencing. (<bold>a</bold>) shows the DNA sequence of the patient and his mother. The blue arrow indicates the exact point of the 34-base pair (bp) deletion (c.1016+11_1017-52del, intron 6). (<bold>b</bold>) shows the cDNA sequence of the patient and his mother and the blue arrows highlight the 30-bp deletion in exon 7 (r.1017_1046del).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="hgv201537-f1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>