<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9312789</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">20742</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Harv Rev Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Harv Rev Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Harvard review of psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1067-3229</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1465-7309</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26954593</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4788103</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HRP.0000000000000102</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS711799</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A <italic>Perspective</italic> on the history of the concept of “disconnectivity” in schizophrenia</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coyle</surname>
<given-names>Joseph T.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Balu</surname>
<given-names>Derrick</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Puhl</surname>
<given-names>Mathew</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Konopaske</surname>
<given-names>Glenn</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Harvard Medical School, McLean Hospital, 115 Mill St, Belmont, MA 02478</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>31</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<season>Mar-Apr</season>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>80</fpage>
<lpage>86</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1097/HRP.0000000000000102-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Nearly sixty years ago Seymour Kety proposed that research on genetics and brain pathology but not on neurochemistry would ultimately lead to an understanding of the pathophysiology of schizophrenia. This <italic>Perspective</italic> will demonstrate how prescient Kety’s proposal was as advances in research on brain structure and on genetics have shaped our current understanding of the pathophysiology of schizophrenia. Brain imaging techniques have shown that schizophrenia is associated with cortical atrophy and ventricular enlargement, which progresses for at least a decade after the onset of psychosis. Cortical atrophy correlates with negative symptoms and cognitive impairment but not with psychosis in schizophrenia. Studies with the Golgi staining technique that illuminates the entire neuron indicate that cortical atrophy was due to reduced synaptic connectivity on the pyramidal neurons and not due to actual loss of neurons. Results of recent genetic studies indicate that several risk genes for schizophrenia are within two degrees of separation from the N-methy-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor, a subtype of glutamate receptor that is critical to synapse formation and synaptic plasticity. Inactivation of one of these risk genes encoding serine racemase, which synthesizes D-serine, a co-agonist of the NMDA receptor, reproduces the synaptic pathology of schizophrenia. Thus, widespread loss of cortical synaptic connectivity appears to be the primary pathology in schizophrenia that is driven by multiple risk genes that adversely affect synaptogenesis and maintenance as hypothesized by Kety.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>