<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">7600111</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">5310</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neurosci Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Neurosci. Res.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of neuroscience research</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0360-4012</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-4547</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26586374</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4837071</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jnr.23690</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS731812</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Basolateral Amygdala GABAergic System in Health and Disease</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Prager</surname>
<given-names>Eric M</given-names>
</name>
<email>eprager@wiley.com</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bergstrom</surname>
<given-names>Hadley C</given-names>
</name>
<email>habergstrom@vassar.edu</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wynn</surname>
<given-names>Gary H</given-names>
</name>
<email>gary.wynn@usuhs.edu</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Braga</surname>
<given-names>Maria F. M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Anatomy, Physiology and Genetics Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences 4301 Jones Bridge Road Bethesda, MD 20814, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Program in Neuroscience Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences 4301 Jones Bridge Road Bethesda, MD 20814, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Center for the Study of Traumatic Stress Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences 4301 Jones Bridge Road Bethesda, MD 20814, USA</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Psychiatry F. Edward Hébert School of Medicine Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences 4301 Jones Bridge Road Bethesda, MD 20814, USA</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Psychology Department Vassar College 124 Raymond Avenue Poughkeepsie, NY 12604, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding Author: Maria F.M. Braga, D.D.S., Ph.D., Department of Anatomy, Physiology, and Genetics, Department of Psychiatry, F. Edward Hébert School of Medicine, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, 4301 Jones Bridge Road, Bethesda, MD 20814, Phone: (301) 295-3524, Fax: (301) 295-3566, <email>maria.braga@usuhs.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2">
<p id="P112"><bold>Conflict of Interest</bold>: The authors declare that they have no competing interests</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>13</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>19</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>94</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>548</fpage>
<lpage>567</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/jnr.23690-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">The brain comprises an excitatory/inhibitory neuronal network that maintains a finely tuned balance of activity critical for normal functioning. Excitatory activity in the basolateral amygdala (BLA), a brain region that plays a central role in emotion and motivational processing, is tightly regulated by a relatively small population of gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) inhibitory neurons. Disruption in GABAergic inhibition in the BLA can occur when there is a loss of local GABAergic interneurons, alterations in GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor activation, or dysregulation of mechanisms that modulate BLA GABAergic inhibition. Disruptions in GABAergic control of the BLA emerge during development, in aging populations, or after a trauma, ultimately resulting in hyperexcitability. BLA hyperexcitability manifests behaviorally as an increase in anxiety, emotional dysregulation, or the development of seizure activity. This article reviews the anatomy, development, and physiology of the GABAergic system in the BLA, and circuits that modulate GABAergic inhibition, including the dopaminergic, serotonergic, noradrenergic, and cholinergic systems. We highlight how alterations in various neurotransmitter receptors, including the acid sensing ion channel 1a (ASIC1a), cannabinoid receptor 1 (CB1), and glutamate receptor subtypes, expressed on BLA interneurons, modulate GABAergic transmission and how defects of these systems affects inhibitory tonus within the BLA. Finally, we discuss alterations in the BLA GABAergic system in neurodevelopmental (autism/Fragile X syndrome) and neurodegenerative (Alzheimer’s disease) diseases, and after the development of epilepsy, anxiety, and traumatic brain injury. A more complete understanding of the intrinsic excitatory/inhibitory circuit balance of the amygdala and how imbalances in inhibitory control contribute to excessive BLA excitability will guide the development of novel therapeutic approaches in neuropsychiatric diseases.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Basolateral Amygdala</kwd>
<kwd>GABA</kwd>
<kwd>Autism</kwd>
<kwd>Alzheimer’s disease</kwd>
<kwd>Anxiety</kwd>
<kwd>Epilepsy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>