<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8211617</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6714</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Prog. Neuropsychopharmacol. Biol. Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Progress in neuro-psychopharmacology &amp; biological psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0278-5846</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1878-4216</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26776902</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4865459</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pnpbp.2016.01.001</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS754578</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The role of monoamine oxidase A in aggression: current translational developments and future challenges</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Godar</surname>
<given-names>Sean C</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fite</surname>
<given-names>Paula J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McFarlin</surname>
<given-names>Kenneth M</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bortolato</surname>
<given-names>Marco</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Dept. of Pharmacology and Toxicology, University of Kansas, Lawrence (KS), USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Consortium for Translational Research on Aggression and Drug Abuse (ConTRADA), University of Kansas, Lawrence (KS), USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Clinical Child Psychology Program, University of Kansas, Lawrence (KS), USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author: Marco Bortolato, MD PhD</bold>, Dept. of Pharmacology and Toxicology, School of Pharmacy, University of Kansas, 1251 Wescoe Hall Dr., Rm. 5040, Lawrence, KS 66044, Tel.:785-864-1936; Fax: 785-864-5219, <email>bortolato@ku.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2">
<p id="P55"><bold>Conflicts of Interest</bold>.</p>
<p id="P56">None</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>1</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>09</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>1</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>90</fpage>
<lpage>100</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.pnpbp.2016.01.001-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Drawing upon the recent resurgence of biological criminology, several studies have highlighted a critical role for genetic factors in the ontogeny of antisocial and violent conduct. In particular, converging lines of evidence have documented that these maladaptive manifestations of aggression are influenced by monoamine oxidase A (MAOA), the enzyme that catalyzes the degradation of brain serotonin, norepinephrine and dopamine. The interest on the link between <italic>MAOA</italic> and aggression was originally sparked by Han Brunner’s discovery of a syndrome characterized by marked antisocial behaviors in male carriers of a nonsense mutation of this gene. Subsequent studies showed that <italic>MAOA</italic> allelic variants associated with low enzyme activity moderate the impact of early-life maltreatment on aggression propensity. In spite of overwhelming evidence pointing to the relationship between <italic>MAOA</italic> and aggression, the neurobiological substrates of this link remain surprisingly elusive; very little is also known about the interventions that may reduce the severity of pathological aggression in genetically predisposed subjects. Animal models offer a unique experimental tool to investigate these issues; in particular, several lines of transgenic mice harboring total or partial loss-of-function <italic>Maoa</italic> mutations have been shown to recapitulate numerous psychological and neurofunctional endophenotypes observed in humans. This review summarizes the current knowledge on the link between <italic>MAOA</italic> and aggression; in particular, we will emphasize how an integrated translational strategy coordinating clinical and preclinical research may prove critical to elucidate important aspects of the pathophysiology of aggression, and identify potential targets for its diagnosis, prevention and treatment.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Aggression</kwd>
<kwd>Monoamine oxidase A</kwd>
<kwd>animal models</kwd>
<kwd>Antisocial behavior</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>