<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9100095</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">8509</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Cell Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Cell. Neurosci.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Molecular and cellular neurosciences</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1044-7431</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9327</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26631648</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4867250</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2015.11.009</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS742310</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Transcriptomics Analysis of iPSC-derived Neurons and Modeling of Neuropsychiatric Disorders</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Mingyan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lachman</surname>
<given-names>Herbert M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>Deyou</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Genetics, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1300 Morris Park Ave., Bronx, New York, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1300 Morris Park Ave., Bronx, New York, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Neuroscience, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1300 Morris Park Ave., Bronx, New York, USA</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Medicine, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1300 Morris Park Ave., Bronx, New York, USA</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Neurology, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1300 Morris Park Ave., Bronx, New York, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author, Deyou Zheng, Ph.D., Phone: 718-678-1217; <email>deyou.zheng@einstein.yu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>4</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>26</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>32</fpage>
<lpage>42</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.mcn.2015.11.009-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC)-derived neurons and neural progenitors are great resources for studying neural development and differentiation and their disruptions in disease conditions, and hold the promise of future cell therapy. In general, iPSC lines can be established either specifically from patients with neuropsychiatric disorders or from healthy subjects. The iPSCs can then be induced to differentiate into neural lineages and the iPSC-derived neurons are valuable for various types of cell-based assays that seek to understand disease mechanisms and identify and test novel therapies. In addition, it is an ideal system for gene expression profiling (i.e., transcriptomic analysis), an efficient and cost-effective way to explore the genetic programs regulating neurodevelopment. Moreover, transcriptomic comparison, which can be performed between patient-derived samples and controls, or in control lines in which the expression of specific genes has been disrupted, can uncover convergent gene targets and pathways that are downstream of the hundreds of candidate genes that have been associated with neuropsychiatric disorders. The results, especially after integration with spatiotemporal transcriptomic profiles of normal human brain development, have indeed helped to uncover gene networks, molecular pathways, and cellular signaling that likely play critical roles in disease development and progression. On the other hand, many challenges remain in the usage of iPSC-derived neurons for modeling neuropsychiatric disorders, for example, how to generate relatively homogenous populations of specific neuronal subtypes that are affected in a particular disorder and how to better address the genetic heterogeneity that exists in the patient population.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Neuropsychiatric Disorders</kwd>
<kwd>iPSCs</kwd>
<kwd>Transcriptome</kwd>
<kwd>RNA-seq</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>