<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9505803</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">8623</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Arteriosclerosis, thrombosis, and vascular biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1079-5642</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1524-4636</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27102963</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4882230</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/ATVBAHA.116.304790</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS776317</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A CRISPR Path to Engineering New Genetic Mouse Models for Cardiovascular Research</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miano</surname>
<given-names>Joseph M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Qiuyu Martin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lowenstein</surname>
<given-names>Charles J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Aab Cardiovascular Research Institute, University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, 601 Elmwood Avenue, Rochester, New York 14642</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Center for Human Genetic Research, Massachusetts General Hospital, 185 Cambridge Street, Boston, Massachusetts 02114</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Address correspondence to: Joseph M. Miano, PhD, Aab Cardiovascular Research Institute, University of Rochester School of Medicine &amp; Dentistry, 601 Elmwood Avenue, Box CVRI, Rochester, New York 14642, 585-276-7703 (TEL), 585-276-1530 (Fax), <email>j.m.miano@rochester.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>9</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>21</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1058</fpage>
<lpage>1075</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1161/ATVBAHA.116.304790-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Previous efforts to target the mouse genome for the addition, subtraction, or substitution of biologically informative sequences required complex vector design and a series of arduous steps only a handful of labs could master. The facile and inexpensive clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPR) method has now superseded traditional means of genome modification such that virtually any lab can quickly assemble reagents for developing new mouse models for cardiovascular research. Here we briefly review the history of CRISPR in prokaryotes, highlighting major discoveries leading to its formulation for genome modification in the animal kingdom. Core components of CRISPR technology are reviewed and updated. Practical pointers for two-component and three-component CRISPR editing are summarized with a number of applications in mice including frameshift mutations, deletion of enhancers and non-coding genes, nucleotide substitution of protein-coding and gene regulatory sequences, incorporation of <italic>loxP</italic> sites for conditional gene inactivation, and epitope tag integration. Genotyping strategies are presented and topics of genetic mosaicism and inadvertent targeting discussed. Finally, clinical applications and ethical considerations are addressed as the biomedical community eagerly embraces this astonishing innovation in genome editing to tackle previously intractable questions.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>