<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">2983306R</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">3565</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Epilepsia</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Epilepsia</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Epilepsia</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0013-9580</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1528-1167</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27263494</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4972670</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.13429</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS786448</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Microglial activation during epileptogenesis in a mouse model of tuberous sclerosis complex</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Bo</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>Jia</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>Lirong</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rensing</surname>
<given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Department of Neurology and the Hope Center for Neurological Disorders, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA 63110</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Corresponding Author: Michael Wong, MD, PhD, Department of Neurology, Box 8111, Washington University School of Medicine, 660 South Euclid Avenue, St. Louis, MO 63110, Phone: 314-362-8713, Fax: 314-362-9462, <email>wong_m@wustl.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2">
<p>
<bold>Disclosures</bold>
</p>
<p>None of the authors has any conflict of interest to disclose. We confirm that we have read the Journal’s position on issues involved in ethical publication and affirm that this report is consistent with those guidelines.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>18</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>06</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>57</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>1317</fpage>
<lpage>1325</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1111/epi.13429-->
<abstract>
<title>Summary</title>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Objective</title>
<p id="P1">Tuberous sclerosis complex (TSC) is a genetic disorder, characterized by tumor formation in multiple organs and severe neurological manifestations, including epilepsy, intellectual disability, and autism. Abnormalities of both neurons and astrocytes have been implicated in contributing to the neurological phenotype of TSC, but the role of microglia in TSC has not been investigated. The objectives of this study were to characterize microglial activation in a mouse model of TSC, involving conditional inactivation of the <italic>Tsc1</italic> gene predominantly in glial cells (<italic>Tsc1</italic><sup>GFAP</sup>CKO mice), and to test the hypothesis that microglial activation contributes to epileptogenesis in this mouse model.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P2">Microglial and astrocyte activation was examined in <italic>Tsc1</italic><sup>GFAP</sup>CKO mice by Iba1 and GFAP immunohistochemistry. Cytokine and chemokine expression was evaluated with QPCR. Seizures were monitored by video-EEG. The effect of minocycline in inhibiting microglial and astrocyte activation, cytokine expression, and seizures was tested.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">Microglial cell number and size were increased in cortex and hippocampus of 3–4 wk old <italic>Tsc1</italic><sup>GFAP</sup>CKO mice, which correlated with the onset of seizures. Minocycline treatment prevented the increase in number and cell size of microglia in 4 week old <italic>Tsc1</italic><sup>GFAP</sup>CKO mice. However, minocycline treatment had no effect on astrocyte proliferation and cytokine/chemokine expression and the progression of seizures in <italic>Tsc1</italic><sup>GFAP</sup>CKO mice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title>Significance</title>
<p id="P4">Microglia cell number and size are abnormal in <italic>Tsc1</italic><sup>GFAP</sup>CKO mice, and minocycline treatment inhibits this microglia activation, but does not suppress seizures. Microglia may play a role in the neurological manifestations of TSC, but additional studies are needed in other models and human studies to determine whether microglia are critical for epileptogenesis in TSC.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>epilepsy</kwd>
<kwd>seizure</kwd>
<kwd>microglia</kwd>
<kwd>astrocyte</kwd>
<kwd>inflammation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>