<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8806548</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">21560</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Neuropsychol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Neuropsychol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Clinical neuropsychologist</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1385-4046</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1744-4144</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27355274</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5002352</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13854046.2016.1186661</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS812194</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>FRAGILE X-ASSOCIATED TREMOR/ATAXIA SYNDROME: ANOTHER PHENOTYPE OF THE FRAGILE X GENE</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grigsby</surname>
<given-names>Jim</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hessl</surname>
<given-names>David</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Departments of Psychology and Medicine, University of Colorado Denver, Denver CO</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>MIND Institute, University of California Davis Medical Center, Sacramento CA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of California Davis, Sacramento CA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Address correspondence to: Jim Grigsby, PhD, Department of Psychology, University of Colorado Denver, 1200 Larimer Street, Campus Box 173, Denver, CO 80217-3364, Phone: (303) 724-2415, <email>jim.grigsby@ucdenver.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>23</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>29</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>810</fpage>
<lpage>814</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1080/13854046.2016.1186661-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Objective</title>
<p id="P1">Neuropsychologists have an important role in evaluating patients with fragile X-associated disorders, but most practitioners are unaware of the recently-identified neurodegenerative movement disorder known as fragile X-associated tremor ataxia syndrome (FXTAS). The objective of this editorial is to orient the reader to FXTAS and highlight the importance of clinical neuropsychology in describing the fragile X premutation phenotype and the role practitioners may have in assessing and monitoring patients with or at risk for neurodegeneration.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Method</title>
<p id="P2">We issued a call for papers for the special issue, highlighting the primary objective of familiarizing clinical neuropsychologists with FXTAS, and with the neuropsychological phenotype of both male and female asymptomatic carriers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">Eight papers are included, including an overview of the fragile X-associated disorders (Grigsby), a review of the neuroradiological and neurological aspects of FXTAS and how the disorder compares to other movement disorders (O’Keefe et al.), a perspective on the prominence of white matter disease and dementia in FXTAS (Filley), and a review of mouse models of FXTAS (Foote). There are four research papers, including one on self-reported memory problems in FXTAS (Birch et al.), and three papers focused on the neuropsychiatric aspects of the fragile X premutation, a review (Bourgeois), an examination of autism-related traits (Schneider), and a research paper on executive functioning and psychopathology (Grigsby).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P4">The issue highlights the importance of awareness of fragile X-associated disorders for neuropsychologists, an awareness that must reach beyond neurodevelopmental aspects related to fragile X syndrome into the realm of neurodegenerative disease and aging.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd><italic>FMR1</italic> gene</kwd>
<kwd>FXTAS</kwd>
<kwd>dementia</kwd>
<kwd>movement disorder</kwd>
<kwd>executive function</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>