<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101089443</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">30404</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cerebellum</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cerebellum</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Cerebellum (London, England)</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1473-4222</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1473-4230</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27089882</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5014718</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12311-016-0779-8</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS779701</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Altered bioenergetics in primary dermal fibroblasts from adult carriers of the <italic>FMR1</italic> premutation before the onset of the neurodegenerative disease Fragile X-associated tremor/ataxia syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Napoli</surname>
<given-names>Eleonora</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Gyu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>Sarah</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hagerman</surname>
<given-names>Randi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giulivi</surname>
<given-names>Cecilia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Molecular Biosciences, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of California Davis, CA 95616</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Medical Investigation of Neurodevelopmental Disorders Institute (M. I. N. D.), University of California Davis, CA 95616</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Pediatrics University of California Davis Medical Center, University of California at Davis Medical Center, Sacramento CA 95817</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, University of California at Davis Medical Center, Sacramento CA 95817</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Address correspondence to: Dr. Cecilia Giulivi, Department of Molecular Biosciences, University of California, 1089 Veterinary Medicine Dr., VetMed 3B #3009, Davis, CA 95616, <email>cgiulivi@ucdavis.edu</email>, tel: 530-752-1038, fax: 530-754-9342</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p><bold>Conflict of Interest</bold>: R.H. has received funding from Novartis, Roche/Genentech, Alcobra, and Neuren for treatment trials in fragile X syndrome, autism and Down syndrome. She has also consulted with Novartis, Zynerba and Roche/Genentech regarding treatment for fragile X syndrome. The other authors have no financial disclosures relevant to this article.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>21</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>552</fpage>
<lpage>564</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1007/s12311-016-0779-8-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Fragile X-associated tremor/ataxia syndrome (FXTAS) is a late onset neurodegenerative disorder, characterized by tremors, ataxia, impaired coordination, and cognitive decline. While all FXTAS individuals are carriers of a 55–200 CGG expansion at the 5′ UTR of the fragile X mental retardation gene (<italic>FMR1</italic>), also known as premutation, not all carriers develop FXTAS symptoms and some display other types of psychological/emotional disorders (e.g., autism, anxiety). The goal of this study was to investigate whether the mitochondrial dysfunction previously observed in fibroblasts from older premutation individuals (&gt;60 y) was already present in younger (17–48 y), non-FXTAS affected carriers and to identify the type and severity of the bioenergetci deficit. Since FXTAS affects mostly males, while females account for a small part of the FXTAS-affected population displaying less severe symptoms, only fibroblasts from males were evaluated in this study. Based on polarographic and enzymatic measurements, a generalized OXPHOS deficit was noted accompanied by increases in the matrix biomarker citrate synthase, oxidative stress (as increased mtDNA copy number and deletions), and mitochondrial network disruption/disorganization. Some of the outcomes (ATP-linked oxygen uptake, coupling, citrate synthase activity and mitochondrial network organization) strongly correlated with the extent of the CGG expansion, with more severe deficits observed in cell lines carrying higher CGG number. Furthermore, mitochondrial outcomes can identify endophenotypes among carriers and are robust predictors of the premutation diagnosis before the onset of FXTAS, with the potential to be used as markers of prognosis and/or as readouts of pharmacological interventions.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Autism</kwd>
<kwd>Fragile X</kwd>
<kwd>mitochondria</kwd>
<kwd>neurodegeneration</kwd>
<kwd>premutation</kwd>
<kwd>triplet nucleotide diseases</kwd>
<kwd>endophenotyes</kwd>
<kwd>mitochondrial network</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>