<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9208369</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">22236</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Pharmacoepidemiology and drug safety</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1053-8569</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1099-1557</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26554750</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5071383</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.3902</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS820669</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prenatal triptan exposure and parent-reported early childhood neurodevelopmental outcomes: an application of propensity score calibration to adjust for unmeasured confounding by migraine severity</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>Mollie E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frazier</surname>
<given-names>Jean A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordeng</surname>
<given-names>Hedvig M.E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lapane</surname>
<given-names>Kate L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Quantitative Health Sciences, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, MA, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Psychiatry, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, MA, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>School of Pharmacy, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Division of Mental Health, Norwegian Institute of Public Health, Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>PharmacoEpidemiology and Drug Safety Research Group, Norway</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence to: Mollie Wood, PhD, Department of Quantitative Health Sciences, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Albert Sherman Center, AS7-1065, 368 Plantation Street, Worcester, Massachusetts 01695, USA, <email>mollie.wood@umassmed.edu</email>, Phone: (857) 998-1578</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3">
<p>Conflicts of interest summary:</p>
<p>Drs Wood and Nordeng have no conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>14</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>493</fpage>
<lpage>502</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/pds.3902-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Purpose</title>
<p id="P1">Triptan medications are serotonin agonists used to treat migraine, a chronic pain condition highly prevalent in women of reproductive age. Data on the safety of triptans during pregnancy are scant. We sought to quantify the association of prenatal triptan exposure on neurodevelopment in three-year-old children.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P2">Using data from the Norwegian Mother and Child Cohort Study, we used propensity score matching to examine associations between prenatal triptan exposure and psychomotor function, communication, and temperament. We used an external validation study to perform propensity calibration to adjust effect estimates for confounders unmeasured in the main study (migraine severity, type, and maternal attitudes towards medication use).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">We identified 4,204 women who reported migraine headache at baseline, of which 375 (8.9%) reported using a triptan ≥ once during pregnancy. Children with prenatal triptan exposure had 1.37-fold greater unadjusted odds of fine motor problems (95% CI: 1.06-1.77), which decreased after propensity score matching (OR: 1.29, 95% CI 0.97-1.73) and was further attenuated after calibration (OR: 1.25, 95%CI 0.89- 1.74). We observed no increased risk for gross motor or communication problems, and no differences in temperament. Adjustment for migraine severity using propensity score calibration had a moderate impact on effect estimates, with percent changes ranging from 2.4% to 50%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P4">Prenatal triptan exposure was not associated with psychomotor function, communication problems, or temperament in three-year-old children. Adjustment for migraine severity reduced effect estimates, and should be considered in future studies of the safety of triptans during pregnancy.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>pregnancy medication</kwd>
<kwd>migraine</kwd>
<kwd>child neurodevelopment</kwd>
<kwd>propensity score calibration</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>