<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Syndromol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Syndromol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MSY</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Molecular Syndromology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1661-8769</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1661-8777</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>S. Karger AG</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Allschwilerstrasse 10, P.O. Box · Postfach · Case postale, CH–4009, Basel, Switzerland · Schweiz · Suisse, Phone: +41 61 306 11 11, Fax: +41 61 306 12 34, karger@karger.ch</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27781032</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5073505</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000448639</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">msy-0007-0220</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Genetic Basis of Brain Malformations</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parrini</surname>
<given-names>Elena</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Conti</surname>
<given-names>Valerio</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dobyns</surname>
<given-names>William B.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guerrini</surname>
<given-names>Renzo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><sup>a</sup>Pediatric Neurology, Neurogenetics and Neurobiology Unit and Laboratories, Department of Neuroscience, A. Meyer Children's Hospital, University of Florence, Florence, Italy</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><sup>b</sup>Division of Genetic Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, University of Washington, and Center for Integrative Brain Research, Seattle Children's Research Institute, Seattle, Wash., USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">*Renzo Guerrini, MD, Neurogenetics and Neurobiology Unit, A. Meyer Children's Hospital, University of Florence, Viale Pieraccini 24, IT-50139 Florence (Italy), E-Mail <email>renzo.guerrini @ meyer.it</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>27</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>1</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 6 months and
						0 days and was based on the <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>220</fpage>
<lpage>233</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 by S. Karger AG, Basel</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Malformations of cortical development (MCD) represent a major cause of developmental disabilities, severe epilepsy, and reproductive disadvantage. Genes that have been associated to MCD are mainly involved in cell proliferation and specification, neuronal migration, and late cortical organization. Lissencephaly-pachygyria-severe band heterotopia are diffuse neuronal migration disorders causing severe global neurological impairment. Abnormalities of the <italic>LIS1, DCX, ARX</italic>, <italic>RELN</italic>, <italic>VLDLR</italic>, <italic>ACTB</italic>, <italic>ACTG1</italic>, <italic>TUBG1</italic>, <italic>KIF5C</italic>, <italic>KIF2A</italic>, and <italic>CDK5</italic> genes have been associated with these malformations. More recent studies have also established a relationship between lissencephaly, with or without associated microcephaly, corpus callosum dysgenesis as well as cerebellar hypoplasia, and at times, a morphological pattern consistent with polymicrogyria with mutations of several genes <italic>(TUBA1A</italic>, <italic>TUBA8</italic>, <italic>TUBB</italic>, <italic>TUBB2B</italic>, <italic>TUBB3</italic>, and <italic>DYNC1H1)</italic>, regulating the synthesis and function of microtubule and centrosome key components and hence defined as tubulinopathies. MCD only affecting subsets of neurons, such as mild subcortical band heterotopia and periventricular heterotopia, have been associated with abnormalities of the <italic>DCX</italic>, <italic>FLN1A</italic>, and <italic>ARFGEF2</italic> genes and cause neurological and cognitive impairment that vary from severe to mild deficits. Polymicrogyria results from abnormal late cortical organization and is inconstantly associated with abnormal neuronal migration. Localized polymicrogyria has been associated with anatomo-specific deficits, including disorders of language and higher cognition. Polymicrogyria is genetically heterogeneous, and only in a small minority of patients, a definite genetic cause has been identified. Megalencephaly with normal cortex or polymicrogyria by MRI imaging, hemimegalencephaly and focal cortical dysplasia can all result from mutations in genes of the PI3K-AKT-mTOR pathway. Postzygotic mutations have been described for most MCD and can be limited to the dysplastic tissue in the less diffuse forms.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<title>Key Words</title>
<kwd>Cortical development</kwd>
<kwd>Lissencephaly</kwd>
<kwd>Malformation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"></fig-count>
<table-count count="1"></table-count>
<ref-count count="96"></ref-count>
<page-count count="14"></page-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>