<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Biol Evol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Biol. Evol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">molbev</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">molbiolevol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Molecular Biology and Evolution</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0737-4038</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1537-1719</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27795229</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5100057</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw215</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">msw215</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Discoveries</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Natural Selection in the Great Apes</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cagan</surname>
<given-names>Alexander</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="msw215-FM3">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Theunert</surname>
<given-names>Christoph</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="msw215-FM3">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Laayouni</surname>
<given-names>Hafid</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="msw215-FM3">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Santpere</surname>
<given-names>Gabriel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="msw215-FM3">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pybus</surname>
<given-names>Marc</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Casals</surname>
<given-names>Ferran</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Prüfer</surname>
<given-names>Kay</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Navarro</surname>
<given-names>Arcadi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marques-Bonet</surname>
<given-names>Tomas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bertranpetit</surname>
<given-names>Jaume</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="msw215-FM4">
<sup>‡</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Andrés</surname>
<given-names>Aida M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="msw215-FM1">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="msw215-FM4">
<sup>‡</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="msw215-aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="msw215-aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Evolutionary Genetics, Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology, Leipzig, Germany</aff>
<aff id="msw215-aff2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Integrative Biology, University of California, Berkeley, Berkeley, CA</aff>
<aff id="msw215-aff3"><sup>3</sup>Departament de Ciencies Experimentals i de la Salut, Institut de Biologia Evolutiva, Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain</aff>
<aff id="msw215-aff4"><sup>4</sup>Departament de Genètica i de Microbiologia, Universitat Autonòma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain</aff>
<aff id="msw215-aff5"><sup>5</sup>Department of Neuroscience, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT</aff>
<aff id="msw215-aff6"><sup>6</sup>Genomics Core Facility, Departament de Ciencies Experimentals i de la Salut, Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain</aff>
<aff id="msw215-aff7"><sup>7</sup>Institució Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avançats (ICREA), Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain</aff>
<aff id="msw215-aff8"><sup>8</sup>Department of Archaeology and Anthropology, Leverhulme Centre for Human Evolutionary Studies, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="msw215-FM3">
<p><sup>†</sup>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="msw215-FM4">
<p><sup>‡</sup>These authors equally co-supervised this work.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="msw215-FM1">
<p>*<bold>Corresponding author:</bold> E-mail: <email>aida_andres@eva.mpg.de</email>.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="msw215-FM2">
<p><bold>Associate editor:</bold> Ryan Hernandez</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>04</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>04</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>3268</fpage>
<lpage>3283</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Natural selection is crucial for the adaptation of populations to their environments. Here, we present the first global study of natural selection in the <italic>Hominidae</italic> (humans and great apes) based on genome-wide information from population samples representing all extant species (including most subspecies). Combining several neutrality tests we create a multi-species map of signatures of natural selection covering all major types of natural selection. We find that the estimated efficiency of both purifying and positive selection varies between species and is significantly correlated with their long-term effective population size. Thus, even the modest differences in population size among the closely related <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages have resulted in differences in their ability to remove deleterious alleles and to adapt to changing environments. Most signatures of balancing and positive selection are species-specific, with signatures of balancing selection more often being shared among species. We also identify loci with evidence of positive selection across several lineages. Notably, we detect signatures of positive selection in several genes related to brain function, anatomy, diet and immune processes. Our results contribute to a better understanding of human evolution by putting the evidence of natural selection in humans within its larger evolutionary context. The global map of natural selection in our closest living relatives is available as an interactive browser at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tinyurl.com/nf8qmzh">http://tinyurl.com/nf8qmzh</ext-link>.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>evolution</kwd>
<kwd>adaptation</kwd>
<kwd>comparative genomics</kwd>
<kwd>primates.</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<page-count count="16"></page-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Understanding the adaptive genetic changes that led to the emergence of modern humans continues to be a major focus of modern genomics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B72">Pritchard et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B21">Enard et al. 2014</xref>). However, despite much work in this field, many central questions remain unanswered. For example, it is still unclear what percentage of the human genome has been shaped by natural selection, which genetic variants are responsible for the phenotypes that make humans unique, and to what extent demographic factors have influenced the rate of adaptive evolution through human history. These questions can only be answered through a deeper understanding of the evolution both of the human genome and also of other closely related species. While laboratory studies on adaptation in organisms such as <italic>Drosophila</italic> have furthered our understanding of adaptive evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B53">Lee et al. 2014</xref>), the usefulness of these model organisms for understanding adaptation in humans is limited by the wide disparities that exist between them and humans, in both physiology and demography. Investigation of the molecular basis of adaptation is also hindered by differences in the structure and content of the genomes of more distantly related organisms. Studying our closest living relatives, the great apes, is therefore crucial for furthering our understanding of human evolution.</p>
<p>The <italic>Hominidae</italic> (humans and great apes) share several traits that make them particularly interesting. Relative to their ancestors they have evolved larger brains, more complex social systems and, arguably, the ability to create and maintain cultural traditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B59">McGrew 2004</xref>). Furthermore, the <italic>Hominidae</italic> species differ from one another in important ways (including their morphology, physiology, behavior and life history traits) that may result from their independent adaptation to particular environments. Evolutionary genomic information can help us to understand the origin and molecular bases of both shared and species-specific traits in the <italic>Hominidae</italic>.</p>
<p>The <italic>Hominidae</italic> also provide an excellent system for comparative studies. This is because although the species are very closely related (with all lineages diverging over the last 12 My) they differ substantially in relevant features such as the effective size of their populations (Ne) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. 2013</xref>). This makes them well-suited for addressing longstanding theoretical questions in evolutionary biology. A central principle of population genetics is that the effective size of a population influences the efficacy of selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B12">Charlesworth 2009</xref>). Populations with a large Ne are expected to be more efficient at both fixing beneficial alleles and removing deleterious ones, when compared with populations with small long-term Ne or that have experienced severe bottlenecks. Empirical attempts to quantify this effect have been limited, with exceptions that include work in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B20">Elyashiv et al. 2010</xref>), <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B44">Jensen and Bachtrog 2011</xref>) and eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B32">Grossman et al. 2013</xref>), as well as comparisons of very divergent lineages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B16">Corbett-Detig et al. 2015</xref>). It remains unclear to what extent differences in Ne between closely related mammalian species impact the process of natural selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B19">Ellegren and Galtier 2016</xref>). Full genome sequences of humans and great apes provide a unique opportunity to investigate this question over a relatively short evolutionary timescale.</p>
<p>The signatures of natural selection have been extensively studied in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B8">Bustamante et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B78">Sabeti et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B66">Nielsen et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B2">Andrés et al. 2010</xref>) and some of the apes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B64">Mikkelsen et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B57">Locke et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B73">Prüfer et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B79">Scally et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B4">Bataillon et al. 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B60">McManus et al. 2015</xref>). However, no study has comprehensively investigated the evidence for natural selection across the <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages. We analyzed whole-genome sequence data from multiple individuals from lineages covering all major <italic>Hominidae</italic> species and subspecies (except <italic>Gorilla beringei beringei</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. 2013</xref>) and present the first investigation of the impact of natural selection using this dataset. We focus on attributes of the data that allow us to detect the different types of selection across evolutionary timescales. We then integrate these results to investigate the influence of Ne on the efficacy of natural selection, the targeted functional elements, the genes and biological processes targeted by each type of selection, and the conservation of selective pressures across <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec>
<title>Sample Processing</title>
<p>In order to assess the influence of natural selection, we use a dataset of 54 non-human great ape and nine human genomes sequenced to an average of 25-fold coverage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Because of differences in demography and selective pressures on autosomes and sex chromosomes, we focus exclusively on the autosomes.</p>
<p>We take particular care to minimize the influence of errors and biases in genomic data and ensure that our data is of the highest possible quality<italic>—</italic>something particularly important when comparing species. All reads were mapped to the same reference genome (human hg18). We built on the extensive data filtering strategy of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. (2013)</xref> (see “Dataset” in “Methods” section). This conservative filtering strategy resulted in the exclusion of 726 Mb (∼23%) of the autosomal genome. This includes tandem repeats (∼38 Mb), segmental duplications (∼154 Mb) and structural variants annotated in at least one species (∼334 Mb) (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), all identified by unusual read-depth, so alternative methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B29">Gokcumen et al. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B85">Sudmant et al. 2015</xref>) may identify nonidentical regions. While certain genomic regions and gene families may be enriched in structural variation and be disproportionately affected by this filtering step, their removal is essential to minimize artifacts. We also excluded genomic gaps (∼226 Mb) and base pairs that were not covered by a minimum of five reads in all individuals per species. The resulting dataset includes on an average 2,099 Mb of analyzable genome sequence per species (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Although every filtering strategy has limitations and putative biases, we aim for a conservative approach that minimizes the presence of artifacts. The result is a high-quality comparative genomic dataset that allows us to investigate the signatures of natural selection and compare them across species (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> Sample Processing, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Neutrality Tests</title>
<p>We selected a set of neutrality tests that explore different aspects of the patterns of polymorphism and in combination allow us to detect the signatures of different types of natural selection across different time depths, from the emergence of the <italic>Hominidae</italic> ∼12 Ma to recent and ongoing species-specific selective sweeps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F1">fig. 1</xref>). Many neutrality tests exist; among them we chose those that utilize the type of information that we have (i.e., that do not require phased genomes), that have been shown to have high power to detect selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B91">Zhai et al. 2009</xref>), that explore relatively independent signatures and that provide information on different timescales. To keep the analyses manageable, we focus on four tests (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F2">fig. 2</xref>):
<fig id="msw215-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 1.</label><caption><p>Timescale of neutrality tests. <italic>Hominidae</italic> phylogeny with the approximate time ranges where each neutrality test has power to detect signatures of natural selection. (<italic>a</italic>) The lineages with the number of genomes used in this study are shown on the right. The <italic>X</italic>-axis shows the timescale, in units of millions of years. Split times of lineages from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>. For FWH, MK and HKA, the approximate time range where the tests are inferred to have most power to detect selection are represented by color intensity. For ELS, we label in green the branches where the test has power to detect selection. n: number of individuals in each lineage. Ne: estimates of effective population size in units of thousands of individuals according to Watterson’s estimator, taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="msw215f1p"></graphic></fig>
<fig id="msw215-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 2.</label><caption><p>Summary of the neutrality tests used. Each box presents the input (the information used), the analysis strategy (how each test was applied on the genome-wide data), the pattern (the signatures of selection explored), the criteria to select selection candidates (the top candidates for each test) and the criteria to select candidates for GO analyses (the candidate used for gene ontology analyses).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="msw215f2p"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>To detect signals of purifying and positive selection on the coding sequences of proteins, we applied the McDonald–Kreitman test (MK test; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B58">McDonald and Kreitman 1991</xref>). The MK test is run on a protein-coding gene-by-gene basis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> MK 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). By using information on sequence divergence, it has power to detect signatures of positive and purifying selection along the entire branch lengths of the <italic>Hominidae</italic>.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To detect long-term balancing selection and positive selection that could have occurred at a deep evolutionary time, we applied a statistic based on the Hudson–Kreitman–Aguadé test (HKA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B41">Hudson et al. 1987</xref>), which has been found to be a highly powerful method to detect positive selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B91">Zhai et al. 2009</xref>). The HKA statistic was calculated across the genome in 30-kb windows with a 15-kb overlap between windows (Methods and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). As it uses both divergence and diversity data, the HKA statistic has power to detect positive selection over broad timescales as well as long-term balancing selection, including persistent balancing selection that predates the emergence of the <italic>Hominidae</italic>, such as on the MHC region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B37">Hedrick 1999</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To detect lineage-specific positive selection that occurred after the divergence of an ancestral population into two species, we applied the Extended Lineage Sorting test (ELS; SOM 13 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B31">Green et al. 2010</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link> 7 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B73">Prüfer et al. 2012</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link> 19a in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B74">Prüfer et al. 2014</xref>). The test is run across the genome and identifies regions without a predefined size (Methods and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> ELS 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To detect recent selective sweeps, we applied Fay and Wu’s H statistic (FWH; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B26">Fay and Wu 2000</xref>). The FWH statistic was calculated across the genome in 30-kb windows with 15-kb overlap between windows (Methods and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> FWH 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>Together, these tests detect the signatures of purifying, balancing and positive selection, old and recent (we refer to events in the order of millions of years for old and of hundreds of thousands of years up to present day for recent selection), in each lineage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F1">fig. 1</xref>). Integrating all results provides an unprecedentedly broad picture of the targets of natural selection in the genomes of humans and great apes.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Ne and the Strength of Natural Selection in the Great Apes</title>
<p>As discussed earlier, empirical data is limited regarding the effect of long-term Ne on the efficacy of natural selection over short evolutionary timescales in vertebrates. The relationship between population size, selection and levels of neutral diversity in populations continues to be a matter of considerable debate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B19">Ellegren and Galtier 2016</xref>). A recent study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B16">Corbett-Detig et al. 2015</xref>) proposed that the effects of linked selection can explain Lewontin’s paradox (1974), namely that neutral diversity does not scale as expected with population size. Though a recent reanalysis of this data suggests that while linked selection influences diversity along genomes, fluctuations in Ne are the major driver of levels of diversity between species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B14">Coop 2016</xref>). The debate has so far been hampered by the limited availability of population-level genome sequence data across species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B19">Ellegren and Galtier 2016</xref>). Our dataset therefore provides an ideal opportunity to investigate the relationship between Ne and selection in closely related species.</p>
<p>We find that the ratio of nonsynonymous to synonymous substitutions negatively correlates with long-term Ne in this dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. 2013</xref>), as expected with more efficient purifying selection in populations with higher Ne. Here we aim to: (1) infer the distribution of fitness effects (DFE) in each species, (2) quantify the magnitude of the influence of Ne on the DFE, (3) compare the influence of long-term versus short-term Ne, and (4) investigate its influence not only on purifying, but also on positive selection.</p>
<sec>
<title>Ne and the Strength of Purifying Selection</title>
<p>We first inferred the DFE of deleterious mutations for 3,859 one-to-one orthologous protein-coding genes with DFE-alpha (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B24">Eyre-Walker and Keightley 2009</xref>), which is based on the MK test (see Methods and MK <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The method fits a demographic model to the SFS of neutral sites, and, simultaneously, estimates the gamma-distributed DFE of new nonneutral mutations and the fraction of adaptive substitutions (α) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). For all lineages, the shape parameter of the gamma distribution is &lt;1, indicative of highly leptokurtic (L shaped) DFEs and most nonsynonymous mutations being strongly deleterious. Indeed, in all lineages the proportion of nonsynonymous mutations with a NeS &gt; 10 (S being the mean homozygous effect of a deleterious variant) is &gt;65% (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S104</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">fig. S18</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), similar to estimates for humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B24">Eyre-Walker and Keightley 2009</xref>) and gorillas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B60">McManus et al. 2015</xref>). We observe that the proportion of predicted neutral or nearly neutral mutations correlates negatively with long-term Ne (correlation of −0.64, <italic>P</italic> value= 0.04 after accounting for phylogenetic nonindependence using BayesTraitsV2 random walk/maximum likelihood method; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B69">Pagel and Meade 2013</xref>). This correlation reflects stronger purifying selection in great ape species with a larger long-term Ne.</p>
<p>Efficient purifying selection reduces also the accumulation of linked genetic variation due to background selection. Within the bins in the middle range of the HKA distribution (see “Methods” section), which are particularly sensitive to purifying selection, lower HKA scores associate with stronger background selection (lower B scores, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S6</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) and a higher proportion of protein-coding exons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F3">fig. 3</xref>). This is expected if background selection reduces diversity around protein-coding and other functional regions. Across lineages, and in agreement with the DFE-alpha results, the effects of purifying selection increase with larger Ne both when considering the proportion of protein-coding exons and the B scores (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA 3 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S5</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B62">McVicker et al. 2009</xref>). Incidentally, the effect is much weaker for nonprotein coding exons (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S5</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. 1E</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). These results are virtually unchanged if we use only lineages with less than ten individuals or only lineages with more than five individuals, suggesting that sample size differences between lineages do not affect our observations (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> subsampling analysis 1.4 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S106</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S30</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).
<fig id="msw215-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 3.</label><caption><p>Percentage of windows overlapping protein coding exons. Percentage of windows overlapping protein coding exons for noncumulative bins of the HKA empirical distribution (<italic>X</italic>-axis). Each lineage is plotted as a shaded line. The Pearson’s correlation (<italic>R</italic>) between the percentage of windows overlapping protein coding exons and Ne within each HKA bin and across all lineages is shown on the right <italic>Y</italic>-axis. Pearson’s correlation coefficient was computed both with an estimate of short- and long-term Ne (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Only <italic>R</italic> values with significant <italic>P</italic> values (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="msw215f3p"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p>The correlations with Ne above are almost always stronger with long-term Ne than with recent Ne (for 21 of the 23 HKA bins; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), indicating that we detect the effects of long-term evolutionary history rather than only differences in power due to overall levels of diversity (although differences in the accuracy of the Ne estimates may affect this comparison). Therefore, despite the recent and ongoing population declines experienced by many of these species, their long-term Ne appears to be a better predictor than recent Ne of the past efficacy of purifying selection.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Ne and Adaptive Evolution</title>
<p>With the MK-based DFE-alpha, it is possible to estimate the proportion (α) of nonsynonymous substitutions driven by positive selection, as well as the ratio of adaptive to neutral divergence (ω(α)) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S103</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). With the exceptions of <italic>Pongo pygmaeus</italic> (with poor bootstrap support), and <italic>Pan t. schweinfurthii</italic> (where two inbred individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. 2013</xref>) dramatically increase the estimates) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S103</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), both the estimated proportion (α) and the estimated rate of adaptive evolution are low (0–12% and 0–2%, respectively) in agreement with previous estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B23">Eyre-Walker 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B60">McManus et al. 2015</xref>). We observe that in nonhuman great apes both the proportion and the rate of adaptive substitutions are positively correlated with long-term Ne, after phylogenetic nonindependence is accounted for using a generalized least square approach (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S17</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> MK test 2.3, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The correlation is high and significant when all nonhuman species, except the problematic <italic>Pongo pygmaeus</italic> and <italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>, are considered (Pearson’s <italic>R</italic> = 0.9, <italic>P</italic> value = 0.004) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F4">fig. 4</xref>).
<fig id="msw215-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 4.</label><caption><p>Correlation between rate of adaptive substitutions (α) and effective population size (Ne). The X-axis shows the effective population size. On the <italic>Y</italic>-axis, the rate of adaptive substitutions is plotted as α. Correlations were calculated while controlling for the phylogenetic nonindependence using a generalized least square approach and a random walk/maximum likelihood method (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Materials</ext-link> MK 2.3, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="msw215f4p"></graphic></fig>
<fig id="msw215-F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 5.</label><caption><p>Venn Diagram of shared targets of balancing and positive selection among <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> lineages. Overlap of the number of putative target genes of balancing and positive selection as inferred by the HKA test for all <italic>P. troglodytes</italic> lineages.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="msw215f5p"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p>The effect of positive selection on linked variation also increases with long-term Ne. In the bottom bins of the HKA empirical distribution, which are enriched in targets of positive selection, the percentage of protein-coding windows correlates positively with Ne (0.05–1% bins, <italic>P</italic> values = 0.0001–0.02). Only the lowest 0.01% HKA bin is not significant, potentially due to the spatial clustering of windows as a result of selective sweeps (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA 4 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S12</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
<p>Thus, our results indicate that long-term Ne of populations significantly affects the efficacy of both purifying and positive selection. These correlations are remarkable because these species are very closely related and their long-term Ne varies by a maximum difference of 3-fold.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>The Candidate Targets of Natural Selection</title>
<p>As most genomic sites evolve neutrally or nearly neutrally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B49">Kimura 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B46">Kelley et al. 2006</xref>), we expect an enrichment of targets of natural selection in the extreme tails of the genome-wide distributions of neutrality test statistics. Therefore, we can identify candidate targets of natural selection without relying on a simulated neutral expectation, which is vulnerable to parameter misspecification, an important problem given the complex evolutionary history of the <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages. Given the little we know about the strongest targets of purifying, positive and balancing selection in nonhuman apes, this catalog is highly relevant. In addition, these loci allow us to investigate the tempo, conservation, and biological function of natural selection in the great apes. The nature of each of the tests considered means that their implementation in the genome varies and the criteria to define candidate targets of selection necessarily varies too (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F2">fig. 2</xref>).</p>
<sec>
<title>Sample Size and the Candidate Targets of Natural Selection</title>
<p>Sample size, which varies among lineages, may influence the power to detect signatures of natural selection. We assess how differences in sample size might influence our results with down-sampling analyses. We randomly down-sample, 100 times, four or eight individuals from the two lineages with the largest sample size (<italic>Pan paniscus</italic> and <italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic>) and run all neutrality tests for chromosome 1 (except the ELS test for <italic>Pan paniscus</italic> because this test is not appropriate for this lineage). We then measure the overlap between the candidates from the down-samples (0.1% or 1% tail of the empirical distribution) with the equivalent candidates from the original results (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> subsampling analysis 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
<p>The impact of sample size differs between selection tests. HKA appears very robust to sample size variation for signatures of positive selection, showing a mean overlap between the original and down-sampled results of at least 86% (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> subsampling analysis 1.1 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S21–24</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). This is likely to be because the HKA is not strongly affected by the allele frequency of polymorphisms.</p>
<p>In contrast, FWH and ELS appear more sensitive to sample size (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> subsampling analysis 1.2–1.3 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S25–28</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). This may be due to the influence of sample size on the estimates of allele frequency. Therefore, we find that the HKA test is better suited for comparative analyses where sample sizes are low or unequal between populations.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>An Available Genome-Wide Map of Natural Selection in <italic>Hominidae</italic></title>
<p>The genome-wide map of signatures of natural selection includes information about different types of selection over varying time frames. As such, it provides a broad picture of the influence of natural selection in each genomic region and <italic>Hominidae</italic> species. All the information is available as an interactive browser at webpage: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tinyurl.com/nf8qmzh">http://tinyurl.com/nf8qmzh</ext-link> following the criteria and configuration of a recently published human dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B76">Pybus et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B77">2015</xref>). The UCSC-style format facilitates the integration with the rich UCSC browser tracks, a search mask allows easy access to results for specific genes or genomic regions, and the raw scores (test statistic value and rank score/empirical <italic>P</italic> value) can be conveniently downloaded using the UCSC Table function. We expect this to be a valuable resource for a wide range of analyses.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>The Functional Targets of Natural Selection</title>
<p>The relative contributions of variants in regulatory versus protein coding regions of the genome to adaptive evolution remains a matter of controversy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B33">Halligan et al. 2013</xref>). Since <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B50">King and Wilson (1975)</xref> the relative importance of coding and regulatory variation to adaptive evolution has been contentious. Protein-coding DNA constitutes ∼1.5% of the genome but 10–15% appears to be functionally constrained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B70">Ponting and Hardison 2011</xref>). The role of nonprotein-coding genes and other nongenic elements in genome function and evolution remains debated (Encode Project Consortium 2011; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B18">Doolittle 2013</xref>) with several lines of work suggesting that nongenic regions (including some gene desserts) can play an important role in phenotype and adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B5">Bejerano et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B56">Libioulle et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B61">McPherson et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B39">Hubisz and Pollard 2014</xref>). Although the stringent filtering of the data and the imperfect annotation of nonprotein-coding functional elements hampers the comparison of protein-coding versus nonprotein regions, we investigated the functional annotations of our candidates.</p>
<p>Except for MK, the neutrality tests we used are agnostic about functional annotation. Still, most of our candidate targets of positive selection contain functional annotations: mean values across species are 72% for HKA, 71% for ELS and 80% for FWH. This is significantly greater than genome-wide expectations based on random sampling of the callable genome (<italic>P</italic> values &lt; 0.05 in all lineages except <italic>Pan paniscus</italic>, <italic>P</italic> value = 0.2, and <italic>Pongo pygmaeu</italic>s, <italic>P</italic> value = 0.11) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA 7 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S7–15</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Among these annotations, the overlap with protein-coding exons (HKA = 62%, ELS = 59%, FWH = 45%) is significantly enriched in all lineages except <italic>Pan paniscus</italic> (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.15) and <italic>Pan troglodytes verus</italic> (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.06). In contrast, the mean overlap with exons from nonprotein coding genes (HKA = 18%, ELS = 2%, FWH = 20%), is not significantly elevated relative to genome-wide levels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S7–15</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, lowest <italic>P</italic> value = 0.16 in <italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic>).</p>
<p>Candidate targets of balancing selection are also highly enriched in protein-coding exons (e.g., 64% in the top 0.01% bin) and in the top HKA bins this proportion sharply increases with the HKA score (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F3">fig. 3</xref>). The increased levels of diversity in these windows cannot be explained by technical artifacts, as these regions are not unusual in terms of coverage or mapping quality (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA 1.3–1.4, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) or by current models of neutral evolution or purifying selection, and are instead best explained by long-term balancing selection acting on or near these protein-coding exons.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>The Biological Pathways Targeted by Natural Selection</title>
<p>According to our results above, protein-coding genes appear to be a key target of natural selection in the <italic>Hominidae</italic>. We thus investigated the biological functions that these genes are involved in. For each neutrality test and lineage, we identified the genes in candidate regions of positive or balancing selection (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F2">fig. 2</xref> and “Methods” section for details) and performed gene enrichment analyses using WebGestalt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B92">Zhang et al. 2005</xref>). Our necessarily strict data filtering may disproportionally affect certain Gene Ontology (GO) categories (e.g., olfactory receptors), but we discuss below the categories that retain the strongest signatures for each type of natural selection.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Pathways Targeted by Balancing Selection</title>
<p>The top genes for balancing selection include a number of well-established targets, such as the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B42">Hughes and Yeager 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B37">Hedrick 1999</xref>). Indeed, windows containing MHC genes appear among those with the strongest signals of balancing selection in all lineages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S6 and S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). In addition, in all lineages there is a significant enrichment of immunity-related categories such as the GO “Antigen processing and presentation” category (closely related to the MHC) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S16–40</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). This provides evidence that balancing selection has a strong influence on immunological pathways in all lineages.</p>
<p>To test whether there were strong signatures of balancing selection beyond the MHC complex, we re-ran the GO enrichment analysis excluding all genes in the MHC region on chromosome 6 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S57–65</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Doing so removes the enrichment for the GO category “Antigen processing and presentation” in all lineages. Interestingly, in three of the four <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> lineages (excluding <italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>) there is significant enrichment for the GO category “Cornified envelope” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S360, S62, and S63</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), driven by the three genes <italic>SCEL, SPRR2B</italic> and <italic>SPRR2G</italic>. The cornified envelope is the most exterior layer of the skin and consists of dead cells. Related to this, we note that in <italic>Pan troglodytes verus</italic> the GO category “keratinocyte differentiation”, involved in the development of the most common cell type in the epidermis is also significantly enriched (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.0026). This is interesting because keratins and proteins similarly involved in epithelial barrier formation have been proposed as targets of balancing selection (see “Discussion” section).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Pathways Targeted by Strong Purifying Selection</title>
<p>Since <italic>Hominidae</italic> are closely related, we would expect that similar regions are evolving under purifying selection. We therefore tested whether the pathways showing the strongest signatures of constraint are consistent among lineages. From the MK test, 53 of the 152 evaluated pathways showed signatures of strong purifying selection in more than one lineage. In particular, the “Integrin signaling” pathway and “Wnt signaling” pathway, which regulate basic cellular and developmental processes and the “Alzheimer’s disease-presenilin” pathway are significantly constrained across all lineages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S102</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Pathways Targeted by Positive Selection</title>
<p>For the HKA, several lineages show evidence of positive selection targets being enriched for GO categories related to immune function. For example, the GO category “Complement activation” (genes that activate the innate immune system) is significantly enriched in <italic>Pan paniscus</italic> (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.042; all <italic>P</italic> values adjusted for multiple testing), whereas the related pathway “Complement receptor activity” is enriched in <italic>Pongo abelii</italic> (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.011) and the GO category “Viral receptor activity” in <italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic> (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.0004) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S41, S46, and S54</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
<p>We find that the FWH candidate targets of positive selection show enrichment in several GO categories related to brain development and function, exclusively within the African <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages. This includes for example the GO categories “Dendrite” (<italic>Homo sapiens P</italic> value = 0.040; <italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes P</italic> value = 0.010; <italic>Gorilla</italic> g<italic>orilla P</italic> value = 0.0024) and “Neuron spine” (<italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes P</italic> value = 0.001; <italic>Gorilla gorilla</italic> g<italic>orilla P</italic> value = 0.006). Several additional neurological categories are enriched in single lineages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S75–86</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). For example, <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> is the only lineage with significant enrichment of the GO category “Glutamate receptor activity” (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.002); glutamate is the main excitatory neurotransmitter in the brain.</p>
<p>For the MK, the set of genes with an excess of divergence is small (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S96</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) but we found a significant enrichment in genes involved in, for instance, “Ion channel activity” in <italic>Pan paniscu</italic>s (<italic>P</italic> value =0.034), and in “Glycosaminoglycan biosynthesis” in <italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic> (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.020), among other pathways (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S98–101</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Overlap betweenTargets of Positive and Balancing Selection across Lineages</title>
<p>The <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages have shared, along their evolutionary history, similar physiologies and environments. As such, they have likely been subject to common selective pressures even after their lineages split. To investigate this possibility, we identified genes that show similar signals of natural selection in multiple lineages. Since we use an empirical approach to identify candidate targets of natural selection (as the demographic models for these species are not well established), we use the same 0.1% cut-off to identify outliers from both tails of the HKA empirical distribution and one tail of the FWH distribution. Therefore, we cannot make general claims about the relative frequency of positive and balancing selection in primate species. We can though explore the level of sharing across lineages of these candidate targets. To be conservative, we only consider genes to be shared targets of selection if they appear as candidates in at least three lineages.</p>
<sec>
<title>Overlap between Selection Targets</title>
<p>We find no signals of positive selection that are shared across all lineages. In fact, there is modest sharing across lineages, a possible indication of the lineage-specific nature of the adaptive process (although we note that we are highly conservative in our selection of candidate genes and the power of FWH is reduced with lower sample sizes) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S15</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). We observe that the HKA candidates show lower sharing across lineages than those from the FWH (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S14 and S73</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). For the HKA, only 27 genes (of the 200 candidates per lineage) are shared in at least three lineages compared with 67 for the FWH, which detects more recent selective events. We note that shared signals among the <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> sub-species may not reflect truly independent signatures of selection as signals may predate their divergence into separate lineages and the possibility of admixture between sub-species. However, of these 67 genes, only a minority (8) are shared exclusively among the <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> subspecies, potentially reflecting their recently shared ancestry. The majority (59) show evidence of recent positive selection across a range of lineages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S73</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) suggesting putative parallel adaptive events.</p>
<p>Turning to the biological function of these genes, we find limited enrichment among HKA targets (the only significant GO category is “Structural molecule activity”, <italic>P</italic> value = 0.009; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>AAB, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). However, the 67 shared FWH candidate genes are significantly enriched in multiple functional categories (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S87–89</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), including several neuronal pathways, suggesting that these are a common target of recent positive selection across the <italic>Hominidae</italic>.</p>
<p>Genes targeted by balancing selection show much greater sharing across lineages, with 156 genes showing signatures of balancing selection across at least three lineages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F5">fig. 5</xref> for an example across <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> lineages). Nine genes, primarily from the MHC region, are shared across all lineages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). This likely reflects the long-term and persistent nature of balancing selection on immunity-related genes, in particular in the MHC.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We present a global investigation of the signatures of purifying, positive, and balancing selection at different time scales and across the <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages. We observe strong evidence for the signatures of each of these types of natural selection on patterns of genomic variation. By carefully avoiding technical differences, we can compare, for the first time, the patterns of different types of natural selection across the great ape species. All genomic analyses of signatures of selection are complicated to some extent by demographic processes which can result in patterns of genomic variation that obscure signatures of selection or produce false-positives. We tried to mitigate this by utilizing tests that identified putatively selected regions as outliers based on the entire distribution of patterns of genomic variation, under the assumption that the majority of the genome is evolving neutrally.</p>
<p>We find that even with the relatively similar Ne of the great apes (with a maximum difference of 3-fold), Ne has a significant effect on the efficacy of natural selection. This appears to be true for both purifying and positive selection. The evidence for adaptive evolution is stronger in protein-coding than in nonprotein coding genes, and it is overrepresented not only on loci with relevance to immune function, but also on loci involved in the development and maintenance of the brain. Long-term balancing selection, which most clearly affects the evolution of immune and skin-related loci, is more often shared across lineages than positive selection. In what follows, we briefly discuss these observations, as well as some of the biological insights from the loci identified.</p>
<sec>
<title>Effective Population Size Significantly Influences the Efficacy of Natural Selection in the <italic>Hominidae</italic></title>
<p>We estimate that at least 65% of mutations are deleterious (NeS &gt; 10) in all lineages. This estimate agrees very well with results in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B24">Eyre-Walker and Keightley 2009</xref>). Our results also agree with a recent study in gorillas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B60">McManus et al. 2015</xref>) where the DFE-alpha method provided a very similar gamma shape parameter and proportion of strongly deleterious and neutral alleles (66% and 23.8%, compared with our 65% and 22%). Regarding the prevalence of positive selection, our estimates in <italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic> (3%) also overlap with previous estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B60">McManus et al. 2015</xref>). Our results thus confirm the limited information that exists for the <italic>Hominidae</italic> and greatly expand upon it.</p>
<p>Having information for many great apes enables us to start to compare the different species. The strength of purifying selection on nonsynonymous sites, and its effects on linked variation, correlate with the long-term Ne of the populations. Similar correlations have been observed among other, more distant, species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B54">Leffler et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B16">Corbett-Detig et al. 2015</xref>). However, our results indicate that even the modest Ne differences that exist among the <italic>Hominidae</italic> have also affected the efficacy of positive selection, which is likely to be less prevalent and more dependent on environmental changes than purifying selection. Therefore, the <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages with the largest long-term effective population sizes, such as <italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic> and <italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic>, are better able to both remove deleterious alleles and fix adaptive alleles than lineages such as <italic>Pan paniscus</italic> and <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>. Even the relatively recent differences in long-term Ne between <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> sub-species seem to have resulted in differences in the efficacy of natural selection. This may be extremely important because the long-term survival of these species, which live in small populations and are endangered, may depend on their ability to adapt to changes in their local environments.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="discussion">
<title>Biological Interpretation of Candidate Genes</title>
<p>Our data indicates that adaptive evolution (positive and balancing selection) often targets protein-coding regions (be that the protein-coding sequence or the surrounding regulatory elements). This suggests that in these species variants that affect proteins have been important drivers of novel adaptations. It also supports the comparison of protein-coding versus nonprotein coding regions to establish patterns of positive selection, as long as additional confounding factors are accounted for (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B15">Coop et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B47">Key et al. 2016</xref>).</p>
<p>The candidate genes targeted by positive selection show only moderate overlap between species. This is not surprising, as different populations likely adapt differently at the genetic level even to similar environmental pressures. Nevertheless, there are certain genes, and even gene categories, that show evidence of positive selection in several lineages, which could reflect recurrent evolution at the genomic level. We note that the sharing across lineages is substantially higher when we turn to balancing selection. This is expected because we target only long-term balancing selection, which may predate the divergence of the great ape lineages.</p>
<p>There are several possible interpretations of shared signals. When the signature is shared across closely related lineages these most likely reflect shared events. When the signature is shared across distant lineages, this may reflect independent adaptive evolution. In these cases, selection may be favoring independent phenotypes in each species, for example if it affects different, neighboring functional elements in each species or, due to pleiotropy, the same functional element for a different phenotype in each species. Alternatively, these regions may represent cases of convergent evolution, where the same phenotype is selected for across species. For example, many genes involved in brain development have shared evidence for positive selection across different species. We speculate that there has been ongoing positive selection for neurological phenotypes across the great apes and that although this was likely to be highly polygenic, some of the same genes may have been involved across species.</p>
<p>The detection of specific genes that have been under adaptive evolution is of great interest, especially when dealing with lineages closely related to humans. Here we discuss some of the most interesting findings. For an extended discussion of putatively selected genes, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> section 7, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Immunity</title>
<sec>
<title>Balancing Selection on the MHC</title>
<p>Host–pathogen co-evolution can result in strong selective pressures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B1">Anderson and May 1982</xref>). In agreement with this we find, in all lineages, evidence of balancing selection maintaining adaptive diversity on immunity-related genes. As expected with long-term balancing selection, where the time to the most recent common ancestor may predate the species split, many cases are shared among closely related lineages. These results provide further evidence that advantageous diversity is extremely important for the immune system, as has been shown in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B27">Ferrer-Admetlla et al. 2008</xref>; reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B48">Key et al. 2014</xref>). Not surprisingly, the MHC genes are among the top candidate targets of balancing selection in all lineages.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Balancing Selection on the Skin Barrier</title>
<p>The cornified envelope is a layer of dead keratinocytes (corneocytes) that are linked to structural proteins. They form a protective barrier in the outermost layer of the epidermis, known as the stratum corneum, which acts as an external wall that protects the body from physical injury and bacterial invasion. We find that the candidate targets of balancing selection are enriched in genes involved in keratinocyte differentiation in <italic>Pan troglodytes verus</italic>. They are also enriched in the related biological process “cornified envelope development” in <italic>Pan t. ellioti</italic>, <italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic> and <italic>Pan troglodytes verus</italic> (the genes involved are <italic>SCEL, SPRR2B</italic> and <italic>SPRR2G</italic>) and include two additional cornified envelope genes (late cornified envelope genes 3D and 3E, <italic>LCE3D</italic> and <italic>LCE3E</italic>). In <italic>LCE3D</italic> and <italic>LCE3E</italic>, the signatures are in flanking regions (the protein-coding portions of the genes are filtered out by the segmental duplication filter). We also identify <italic>CDSN</italic>, which encodes corneodesmosin, an adhesive protein involved in skin barrier integrity and has previously been shown to have signatures of balancing selection in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B3">Andrés et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B10">Cagliani et al. 2011</xref>), as a putative target of balancing selection in three lineages (<italic>Homo sapiens, Pan paniscus, Pan troglodytes verus</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
<p>A hypothesis for why genes involved in epidermal differentiation may evolve under balancing selection has been proposed in humans in relation to the filaggrin (<italic>FLG</italic>) gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B43">Irvine and McLean 2006</xref>), which is essential for the formation of the cornified envelope yet it has two common loss-of-functions alleles (5% frequency each in Europeans) that cause icthyosis vulgaris and strongly predispose to atopic dermatitis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B43">Irvine and McLean 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B82">Smith et al. 2006</xref>). It has been proposed that the loss-of-function alleles might result in a leaky skin barrier through which low levels of pathogens can penetrate, promoting innate immunity through a process of “natural vaccination” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B43">Irvine and McLean 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Humans homozygous for loss-of-function <italic>CDSN</italic> alleles frequently show skin barrier defects and are susceptible to <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> superinfections early in life, suggesting variation in the gene influences the ability of pathogens to penetrate the skin barrier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B67">Oji et al. 2010</xref>). Interestingly, heterozygote carriers of this loss-of-function allele do not present these phenotypes, suggesting that heterozygotes may obtain benefits without the deleterious costs of homozygous carriers. Therefore, a leaky skin barrier that promotes “natural vaccination” may be a hitherto under-appreciated mechanism driving balancing selection on a variety of genes involved in development of the stratum corneum across species. We hypothesize that this mechanism may underlie the strong signatures of balancing selection we detect in <italic>CDSN</italic> (corneodesmosin) and other genes involved in the development of the cornified envelope. The presence of advantageous variation on genes involved in the formation of the epithelial barrier may therefore be more widespread than previously recognized.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Positive Selection on HIV/SIV-Related Genes</title>
<p>We also find evidence for pervasive positive selection on immune-related processes, as seen in <italic>H. sapiens</italic> and other <italic>Hominidae</italic> before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B64">Mikkelsen et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B9">Cagliani et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B11">Casals et al. 2011</xref>). MK, HKA and FWH candidate targets of positive selection all are significantly enriched in genes related to immune response (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S16–55</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">S75–86 and S99</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The particular genes vary between lineages, although some are shared across lineages.</p>
<p>Immunity-related genes with signals of selection in multiple lineages may reveal convergent adaptive response to pathogens, or adaptive introgression. The gene <italic>IDO2</italic> is identified as a FWH candidate of recent positive selection in all four <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> lineages and <italic>Pan paniscus</italic>. <italic>IDO2</italic> encodes the enzyme indoleamine 2, 3-dioxygenase 2, which is involved in T-cell regulation and the Tryptophan oxidation pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B63">Metz et al. 2014</xref>). This pathway is activated after HIV infection and causes chronic inflammation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B65">Murray 2010</xref>), likely underlying HIV-1 immunopathogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B6">Boasso and Shearer 2008</xref>). Interestingly, blocking expression of the <italic>IDO</italic> genes in rhesus macaques infected with SIV/HIV improves health outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B7">Boasso et al. 2009</xref>). Therefore, selection on this functional pathway may contribute to the ability of some <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> individuals to be resistant to AIDS progression after HIV infection, which has been attributed to a lack of HIV induced T-cell dysfunction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B38">Heeney et al. 1993</xref>). The MK test also identifies <italic>HIVEP1</italic> as a target of positive selection in <italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic> and <italic>Pan paniscus</italic>. The transcription factor encoded by <italic>HIVEP1</italic> binds enhancer elements of several promoters of viruses, including HIV-1. Investigation of these selection signals may be of relevance to treating HIV infections in humans.</p>
<p>In summary, we find strong evidence of shared signals of both balancing and, less frequently, positive selection on genes involved in immunity in the <italic>Hominidae</italic>. This likely reflects the strong and continuous selective pressure that infection and disease exerts on these populations, and the close evolutionary history of the <italic>Hominidae</italic>, which results in exposure to similar pathogens and similar genetic responses.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Neurological Functions</title>
<p>All <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages are known to possess sophisticated cognitive abilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B86">Tomasello and Call 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B59">McGrew 2004</xref>) related to their increased brain size and changes in brain organization relative to other primates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B80">Semendeferi et al. 2002</xref>). We find some of the categories with the strongest evidence of purifying selection (with MK) are involved in brain function. It is intriguing that the candidate targets of recent positive selection are also enriched in neurological functional categories, with some genes involved in brain development and function showing signatures across multiple lineages.</p>
<p>The gene with signatures of positive selection across the highest number of species and timescales is <italic>NRXN3</italic>, which codes for neurexin 3. The gene is mainly expressed in the brain and encodes for a protein involved in synaptic transmission and plasticity; it belongs to a gene family associated with several cognitive diseases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B83">Südhof 2008</xref>). <italic>NRXN3</italic> shows signatures of positive selection in six lineages, with a FWH signal of recent positive selection in <italic>Pan troglodytes ellioti, Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii, Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic> and <italic>Pongo pygmaeus</italic>, an HKA signal of positive selection in <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, and an ELS signature in all lineages where it was performed (<italic>Pan troglodytes, Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic> and <italic>Pongo abelii</italic>). Therefore, this gene may have been involved in the cognitive evolution of multiple <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages, including our own.</p>
<p>Several additional prominent candidates of positive selection are involved in cognitive and neurodevelopmental phenotypes. This includes <italic>AUTS2</italic>, identified by ELS in <italic>G. g. gorilla</italic> (second highest rank) and <italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic> (fourth highest rank), and implicated in neuronal development and autism in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B68">Oksenberg and Ahituv 2013</xref>). In addition, <italic>CSMD1</italic>, the gene with FWH signatures in the most lineages (<italic>Homo sapiens, Pan paniscus, Pan troglodytes ellioti, Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii, Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic> and <italic>Pongo pygmaeus</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S73</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), whose function is unknown but that is highly expressed in the central nervous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B52">Kraus et al. 2006</xref>) and harbors variants associated with schizophrenia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B36">Håvik et al. 2011</xref>). Further, of the four genes with FWH signatures in five lineages, two are associated with neuronal phenotypes: <italic>KCNIP4</italic>, which encodes an A-type potassium channel modulatory protein, and harbors variants associated with attention deficit hyperactive disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B89">Weißflog et al. 2013</xref>) and <italic>NRG3</italic> (Neuregulin 3), which is crucial in the development of the nervous system and whose variants are associated to schizophrenia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B13">Chen et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>In addition, 12 genes detected as positively selected by MK are related to neurodevelopmental disorders in humans (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S98</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Five (<italic>MCPH1, CASC5, PHGDH, FTO</italic> and <italic>NBN</italic>) can display a phenotype of microcephaly when mutated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B25">Faheem et al. 2015</xref>), with mutations in <italic>MCPH1</italic> and <italic>CASC5</italic> being responsible for autosomal recessive primary microcephaly (MCPH) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B90">Woods et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B28">Genin et al. 2012</xref>). <italic>MCPH1</italic> (identified here in <italic>H. sapiens</italic>) has been described as a target of positive selection in primate evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B88">Wang and Su 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B81">Shi et al. 2013</xref>); <italic>CASC5</italic> (identified here in <italic>Pan troglodytes ellioti</italic> and <italic>Pan paniscus</italic>) contains, in <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, a nonsynonymous mutation that reached fixation since the split with Neandertals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B74">Prüfer et al. 2014</xref>), suggesting recent positive selection also in our lineage. <italic>MCPH1</italic>. <italic>CENPJ</italic>, another MCPH gene, shows marginally nonsignificant evidence of positive selection (<italic>P</italic> value = 0.055 in <italic>P.t. verus</italic>). Together these results show putative adaptive evolution in genes that may have contributed to changes in brain size and function during primate evolution.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="conclusion">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>We present a comparative population genomic analysis that investigates the influence of natural selection across the <italic>Hominidae</italic>. This information sheds light on the past adaptations of each of these populations. As expected, immune function was a strong selective force in all species. Given the close evolutionary relationship, similar physiology and shared pathogens of humans with the other <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages, further functional study of these immunity-related genes may be of medical relevance. In addition, the evidence of positive selection in neuronal pathways of several lineages suggests differential adaptations in phenotypes that distinguish the <italic>Hominidae</italic> species from one another. For example, genes that show strong signals of positive selection solely on the human lineage constitute the best candidates to explain human-specific neurological phenotypes. Similarly, genes with evidence of positive selection in species that differ from one another in phenotypes including size, locomotion, morphology or diet help us to understand the genetic basis of these adaptations.</p>
<p>The fact that even the modest differences in long-term Ne between <italic>Hominidae</italic> lineages has had discernible impacts on the efficacy of natural selection, both to remove deleterious alleles and to favor adaptive ones, has additional implications. The different great ape species, all of which (except for humans) are currently endangered, may thus differ significantly in their ability to adapt to environmental change. This may affect their ability to adapt not only to constantly changing pathogens, but also to the often human-induced changes to their habitats.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec>
<title>Dataset</title>
<p>The dataset we analyzed consists of whole-genome autosomal sequences from 83 individuals across all the major lineages of the <italic>Hominidae</italic> (with the exception of <italic>Gorilla beringei beringei</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw215-F1">fig. 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The dataset was originally presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. (2013</xref>; SOM), where the SNP calling pipeline and filtering criteria are described in detail. All reads are mapped to the human reference genome (hg18). This approach has three main advantages. First, we take advantage of the extensive data-quality exploration and filtering performed in the original publication. Second, mapping to the human genome ensures that all species are mapped to a high-quality genome, avoiding the (hard to account for) biases that would result from mapping to genomes of low and varying qualities. Third, the human genome has the most comprehensive annotation of gene coding regions, which is very important in this study.</p>
<p>To avoid errors introduced by miss-mapping due to paralogous variants, we also restricted all analyses to a set of sites with a unique mapping to the human genome. To address the possible influence of unknown copy number variants (which would result in collapsing several genomic regions during mapping and produce false SNP calls), we took several steps (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Using UCSC tracks we excluded from analysis all repetitive regions (∼248 Mb), segmental duplications (∼154 Mb), genomic gaps (∼226 Mb) and tandem repeats (∼38 Mb). We also excluded structural variants detected in any of the great ape lineages (∼334 Mb) based on the most comprehensive catalogue available which was itself generated using this dataset and read-depth methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B84">Sudmant et al. 2013</xref>). Furthermore, sites with depth of coverage (DP) &lt; (mean read depth/8.0) and DP &gt; (mean read depth×3), were also removed. To maximize the number of sites to be analyzed, we excluded multiple individuals with low coverage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S1 and S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Additionally, we also required positions to have at least 5× coverage in all individuals per species. Only the resulting set of sites, which we termed “callable sites”, were used in further analyses; this minimizes, as much as possible, the effects of filtering in all enrichment analyses. This resulted in a mean of 2,099 Mb of analyzable genome sequence per species (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). We caution that despite our many efforts, which include multiple stringent filtering steps and the manual curation of targets presented in the main text, we cannot discard the presence of some artifact in our data (e.g., undetected structural variants in the candidate targets of balancing selection) although we expect that them to have a weak influence in our overall results.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Tests</title>
<sec>
<title>Hudson–Kreitman–Aguadé Test (HKA)</title>
<p>To detect long-term balancing selection and positive selection that could have occurred at a deep evolutionary timescale, we used a statistic based on the HKA test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B41">Hudson et al. 1987</xref>). Here, the HKA statistic is simply the ratio of polymorphic (SNPs) to divergent (substitutions) sites in a window. We consider as a polymorphism a genomic position that was identified as a single nucleotide variant (SNV) in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. (2013)</xref>. We consider a substitution (a divergent site) a genomic position that is identified as a fixed difference between the tested and the outgroup lineage. For consistency, <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> was used as an outgroup for all lineages. When performing the test for <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, we used the combined <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> lineages as the outgroup.</p>
<p>For each lineage, the genome was divided into 30-kb genomic windows with 15-kb overlap and the HKA statistic was calculated. We consider only windows that contain at least 300 callable and 6 informative sites, where an informative site is a SNV or substitution (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Each window in the genome was ranked according to its HKA score, and the rank was considered the window’s empirical <italic>P</italic> value (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, for an example of the distribution of polymorphic sites and substitutions across the HKA empirical distribution). To ensure that our results were not influenced by variation in data quality across the genome, we tested whether extreme HKA scores are biased in terms of coverage or mapping quality. We find no evidence for such artifacts influencing our results (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S2 and S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Fay and Wu H Test (FWH)</title>
<p>To detect complete or nearly complete positive selective sweeps caused by recent or ongoing positive selection, which result in an excess of high-frequency derived alleles, we used the FWH statistic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B26">Fay and Wu 2000</xref>). We confirmed our implementation of the FWH statistic was capable of detecting recent selective sweeps using simulations (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> FWH 1 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S19</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). For each lineage, the genome was divided into 30-kb windows with 15-kb overlap using the same strategy as the HKA test (see above and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> FWH 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Windows with less than 300 callable sites were removed. Each window in the genome was ranked according to its FWH score, and the rank was considered the window’s empirical <italic>P</italic> value.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>McDonald–Kreitman Test (MK)</title>
<p>To detect positive and purifying selection on protein coding genes, we used the McDonald–Kreitman test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B58">McDonald and Kreitman 1991</xref>). The MK test was calculated for all lineages with at least five individuals, as this was considered the minimum sample size for sufficient polymorphism data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S93</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Only <italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic> did not meet these criteria. <italic>Pan t. verus</italic> met the criterion only by including Donald, an individual excluded in all other analyses because of evidence of admixture between <italic>P.t. verus</italic> and <italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. 2013</xref>). Coordinates for coding regions of all autosomal transcript unique identifiers were taken from RefSeq hg18 and intersected with the callable sites in our data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B75">Pruitt et al. 2012</xref>). This resulted in ∼15.1 Mb of coding sequence available for analysis. For each lineage, we count all polymorphisms and substitutions that are predicted to have appeared after the most recent common ancestor with an outgroup (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic> was used for all lineages, except when performing the test for <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, in which case <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> was used) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S94</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The total number of transcripts tested for each species can be seen in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S6</ext-link>C, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, and the significant transcripts for either positive or purifying selection in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S96 and S97</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online. Variants were annotated as either synonymous or nonsynonymous using ANNOVAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B87">Wang et al. 2010</xref>). Multiallelic sites were excluded (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> MK 1.4, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Extended Lineage Sorting Test (ELS)</title>
<p>To detect lineage-specific positive selection that occurred after the divergence of two closely related lineages, we scan the genome for a signal of extended lineage sorting (see SOM 13 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B31">Green et al. 2010</xref>; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Information 7</ext-link> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B73">Prüfer et al. 2012</xref>; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Information 19a</ext-link> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B74">Prüfer et al. 2014</xref>), i.e., genomic regions where the lineage of a closely related outgroup falls basal to the lineages of a test-group of individuals. The test requires a particular relationship between the test-group and the closely related outgroup individual where the outgroup individual is sufficiently close and the test-group is sufficiently diverse so that the outgroup often falls within the diversity of the test-group. To determine which population pairs are suitable for ELS, we performed neutral coalescent simulations with ms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B40">Hudson 2002</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S66</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The fraction of derived sites in the simulations was compared with the fraction in the data, which closely matched the simulations in most cases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S20</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S66 and S67</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Three lineage pairs showed a sufficiently close relationship and were used for the ELS test: <italic>Pan troglodytes—Pan paniscus, Gorilla g. gorilla—Gorilla b. graueri, Pongo abelii—Pongo pygmaeus</italic>.</p>
<p>We use an implementation of the ELS test that is based on a hidden Markov model (HMM) that analyses SNPs in individuals from one population and the genotype from a single individual from the outgroup population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B74">Prüfer et al. 2014</xref>, SOM). The HMM then infers the posterior probability for the hidden states <italic>internal</italic> (the outgroup falls within the diversity of the test group) and <italic>external</italic> (the outgroup falls basal to the lineages of the test group) at all SNP positions.</p>
<p>Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B73">Prüfer et al. (2012</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Information 7</ext-link>), external regions were defined as a run of SNPs with a probability of &gt;0.8 for being external that is not interrupted by SNPs with a probability of &gt;0.8 for being internal, and scored by their genetic length using the 1-Mb average human recombination rate from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B51">Kong et al. (2002)</xref>.</p>
<p>For each population, the HMM was run repeatedly with each “outgroup” individual. To combine these multiple outputs, we disregarded any external region that was not in the top 5% of the empirical distribution in all runs (as truly external regions are shared among all outgroup individuals) and the remaining external regions were then assigned a final rank based on their cumulative rank score from the multiple runs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> ELS 1.3 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S68–70</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Region Annotation and GO Category Enrichment</title>
<p>Regions were annotated as genic (protein-coding and nonprotein coding) if at least 1 bp of the region overlapped with a gene using GENCODE hg18 gene coordinates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B35">Harrow et al. 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>To test for evidence of functional enrichment among the genes that we detect as putative targets of natural selection, we performed biological category enrichment analysis using the software WebGestalt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B92">Zhang et al. 2005</xref>). For the HKA and FWH tests, we selected the 200 genes with the strongest signatures of selection as our test set of candidate genes. For the ELS test, we considered all genes in the 5% longest external regions. For the MK test, we selected by species all genes with at least one transcript presenting a nominal <italic>P</italic> value of ≤0.05.</p>
<p>For each test and lineage, we tested for functional enrichment using several databases of biological pathway and functional information: GO categories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B34">Harris et al. 2004</xref>) “biological processes”, “molecular functions” and “cellular components”; the Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes (KEGG) pathway database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B45">Kanehisa et al. 2004</xref>) based on mammalian and human phenotype ontology; and the PheWas database, which is based on the human PheWas ontology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B17">Denny et al. 2010</xref>). We set a significance threshold of 0.05 and used the Bonferroni correction for multiple hypothesis testing. Significant categories driven by only one gene were discarded due to the high potential for spurious signals in such cases. For HKA results, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S3N–S3AAA</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, for ELS see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S71 and S72</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, for FWH see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary tables S5C–S5N</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, for MK test see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary table S101</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online.</p>
<p>We note that all gene pathways used were annotated for humans. While this is not ideal for pathway enrichment analyses of nonhuman species, the putative biases should be minor. This is because these functional elements are evolutionarily constrained and these species are extremely closely related (all within only 12 My). For example, there have only been 96 gene-deletion events in the great apes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="msw215-B71">Prado-Martinez et al. 2013</xref>), which should have a minimal impact on an enrichment analyses that uses thousands of genes. Furthermore, any putative annotation errors between species should be random with respect to biological pathways and not systematically biasing gene enrichment results.</p>
<p>We tested the potential effect of gene length bias on the results by repeating the enrichment analyses after randomly selecting equal numbers of windows and exploring the overlap of these (random) categories with our results (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> HKA 7, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Data Access</title>
<p>An interactive browser with the signatures of natural selection for each species is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tinyurl.com/nf8qmzh">http://tinyurl.com/nf8qmzh</ext-link> (last accessed October 10, 2016).</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">Supplementary figures S1–S22</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">tables S1–S107</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/molbev/msw215/-/DC1">supplementary materials</ext-link> are available at <italic>Molecular Biology and Evolution</italic> online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbe.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.mbe.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>).</p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="PMC_1">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mime-subtype="html" mimetype="text" xlink:href="supp_33_12_3268__index.html"></media>
<media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="supp_msw215_Cagan_S7_S15.pdf" xlink:role="associated-file"></media>
<media mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" mimetype="application" xlink:href="supp_msw215_Cagan_Supplementary_Gene_Enrichment_Tables_FWH_S75_S92.xls" xlink:role="associated-file"></media>
<media mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" mimetype="application" xlink:href="supp_msw215_Cagan_Supplementary_Gene_Enrichment_Tables_HKA_S16_S65.xlsx" xlink:role="associated-file"></media>
<media mime-subtype="msword" mimetype="application" xlink:href="supp_msw215_Cagan_Supplementary_Materials.docx" xlink:role="associated-file"></media>
<media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="supp_msw215_Cagan_Supplementary_Materials.pdf" xlink:role="associated-file"></media>
<media mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" mimetype="application" xlink:href="supp_msw215_Cagan_Supplementary_Tables.xlsx" xlink:role="associated-file"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We thank Matthias Ongyerth for assistance with data preparation, Michael Lachmann and Mark Stoneking for discussions and valuable comments, and Michael Lachmann for help with the ELS test. We thank the members of the Great Ape Genome Diversity Consortium for support throughout this work. This work was supported by funding from the Max Planck Society to K.P. and A.M.A.; by grants from the <funding-source>Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad in Spain</funding-source> (grant <award-id>BFU2013-43726-P</award-id>) and the <funding-source>Secretaria d’Universitats i Recerca de la Generalitat de Catalunya</funding-source> (grant <award-id>GRC 2014 SGR 866</award-id>) to J.B.; by an <funding-source>European Research Council</funding-source> Advanced Grant (<award-id>233297</award-id>) to S.Pääbo and <funding-source>European Research Council</funding-source> Starting Grant (<award-id>260372</award-id>) to T.M.B.; and by <funding-source>European Molecular Biology Organization</funding-source> Young Investigator Award and <funding-source>Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación in Spain</funding-source> (<award-id>BFU2014-55090-P</award-id>) to T.M.B.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="msw215-B1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>RM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>
<article-title>Coevolution of hosts and parasites</article-title>. <source/>Parasitology
<volume>85</volume>(<issue>02</issue>):<fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6755367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrés</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretzschmar</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannons</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee-Lin</surname><given-names>S-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurle</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartzberg</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Balancing selection maintains a form of <italic>ERAP2</italic> that undergoes nonsense-mediated decay and affects antigen presentation</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1001157</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20976248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrés</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubisz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Indap</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyko</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutenkunst</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Targets of balancing selection in the human genome</article-title>. <source/>Mol Biol Evol. <volume>26</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2755</fpage>–<lpage>2764</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19713326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bataillon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hvilsom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Glemin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobolth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Inference of purifying and positive selection in three subspecies of chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) from exome sequencing</article-title>. <source/>Genome Biol Evol.
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1122</fpage>–<lpage>1132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25829516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bejerano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahituv</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Siepel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>A distal enhancer and an ultraconserved exon are derived from a novel retroposon</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>441</volume>(<issue>7089</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16625209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boasso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>GM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Chronic innate immune activation as a cause of HIV-1 immunopathogenesis</article-title>. <source/>Clin Immunol.
<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17916442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boasso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>W-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryniszewska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Combined effect of antiretroviral therapy and blockade of <italic>IDO</italic> in SIV-infected rhesus macaques</article-title>. <source/>J Immunol. <volume>182</volume>:<fpage>4313</fpage>–<lpage>4320</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19299731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fledel-Alon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubisz</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Glanowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanenbaum</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sninsky</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Civello</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Natural selection on protein-coding genes in the human genome</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>437</volume>(<issue>7062</issue>):<fpage>1153</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>. <bold>20</bold><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16237444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cagliani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Riva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Biasin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fumagalli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozzoli</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo Caputo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzotta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Piacentini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresolin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Clerici</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Genetic diversity at endoplasmic reticulum aminopeptidases is maintained by balancing selection and is associated with natural resistance to HIV-1 infection</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet.
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>4705</fpage>–<lpage>4714</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20843824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cagliani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Riva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozzoli</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fumagalli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Comi</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresolin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Clerici</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sironi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Balancing selection is common in the extended MHC region but most alleles with opposite risk profile for autoimmune diseases are neutrally evolving</article-title>. <source/>BMC Evol Biol. <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>171.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21682861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casals</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laayouni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Montanucci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Muntasell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Calafell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Awadalla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Netea</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertranpetit</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genetic adaptation of the antibacterial human innate immunity network</article-title>. <source/>BMC Evol Biol.
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>202.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21745391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Effective population size and patterns of molecular evolution and variation</article-title>. <source/>Nat Rev Genet.
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19204717</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramopoulos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasseter</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallin</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nestadt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutting</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolyniec</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Fine mapping on chromosome 10q22-q23 implicates Neuregulin 3 in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet.
<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19118813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Does linked selection explain the narrow range of genetic diversity across species?</article-title>
<source/>bioRxiv
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>042598</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickrell</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudaravalli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Absher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>“The role of geography in human adaptation.”</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e1000500.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19503611</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbett-Detig</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sackton</surname><given-names>TB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Natural selection constrains neutral diversity across a wide range of species</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Biol.
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e1002112.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25859758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Basford</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastarache</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown-Gentry</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Masys</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roden</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>DC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>PheWAS: demonstrating the feasibility of a phenome-wide scan to discover gene-disease associations</article-title>. <source/>Bioinformatics
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1205</fpage>–<lpage>1210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>WF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Is junk DNA bunk? A critique of ENCODE</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci.
<volume>110</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>5294</fpage>–<lpage>5300</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23479647</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellegren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Galtier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Determinants of genetic diversity</article-title>. <source/>Nat Rev Genet
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>422</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27265362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elyashiv</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullaughey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinott</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Przeworski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Shifts in the intensity of purifying selection: an analysis of genome-wide polymorphism data from two closely related yeast species</article-title>. <source/>Genome Res.
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1558</fpage>–<lpage>1573</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817943</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B21">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>DA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide signals of positive selection in human evolution</article-title>. <source/>Genome Res.
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>895</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24619126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B22">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>ENCODE Project Consortium</collab>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>A user’s guide to the encyclopedia of DNA elements (ENCODE)</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Biol. <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1001046</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21526222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B23">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The genomic rate of adaptive evolution</article-title>. <source/>Trends Ecol Evol.
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Keightley</surname><given-names>PD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Estimating the rate of adaptive molecular evolution in the presence of slightly deleterious mutations and population size change</article-title>. <source/>Mol Biol Evol.
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>2097</fpage>–<lpage>2108</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19535738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B25">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faheem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Naseer</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasool</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumosani</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilyas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pushparaj</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Algahtani</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Qahtani</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Molecular genetics of human primary microcephaly: an overview</article-title>. <source/>BMC Med Genomics
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S4</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B26">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CI.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Hitchhiking under positive Darwinian selection</article-title>. <source/>Genetics
<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>1405</fpage>–<lpage>1413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10880498</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B27">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrer-Admetlla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquès-Bonet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramírez-Soriano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Muntasell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Calafell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertranpetit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Balancing selection is the main force shaping the evolution of innate immunity genes</article-title>. <source/>J Immunol. <volume>181</volume>:<fpage>1315</fpage>–<lpage>1322</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18606686</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B28">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Desir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Biervliet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Aa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierquin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Killian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tosi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefort</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Kinetochore KMN network gene <italic>CASC5</italic> mutated in primary microcephaly</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet.
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>5306</fpage>–<lpage>5317</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22983954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B29">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gokcumen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tischler</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tica</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Iskow</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Langdon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stütz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Benes</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Primate genome architecture influences structural variation mechanisms and functional consequences</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci.
<volume>110</volume>(<issue>39</issue>):<fpage>15764</fpage>–<lpage>15769</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24014587</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B31">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Maricic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenzel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kircher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>MH-Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A draft sequence of the Neandertal genome</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>328</volume>:<fpage>710</fpage>–<lpage>722</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20448178</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B32">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shlyakhter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabrizi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Winnicki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Griesemer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Identifying recent adaptations in large-scale genomic data</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>713</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23415221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B33">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halligan</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kousathanas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Harr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Eöry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Keightley</surname><given-names>PD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Contributions of protein-coding and regulatory change to adaptive molecular evolution in murid rodents</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e1003995.</fpage></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B34">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomax</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Foulger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eilbeck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The Gene Ontology (GO) database and informatics resource</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res.
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>D258</fpage>–<lpage>D261</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681407</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B35">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Frankish</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapanari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekhans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokocinski</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Aken</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zadissa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>GENCODE: the reference human genome annotation for the ENCODE project</article-title>. <source/>Genome Res.
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1760</fpage>–<lpage>1774</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B36">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Håvik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Hellard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rietschel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lybæk</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Djurovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattheisen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mhleisen</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Priebe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>The complement control-related genes <italic>CSMD1</italic> and <italic>CSMD2</italic> associate to schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Biol Psychiatry.
<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21439553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B37">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedrick</surname><given-names>PW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Balancing selection and MHC</article-title>. <source/>Genetica
<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B38">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heeney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Koornstra</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubbes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Niphuis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Rienzo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gougeon</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagnier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>The resistance of HIV-infected chimpanzees to progression to AIDS correlates with absence of HIV-related T-cell dysfunction</article-title>. <source/>J Med Primatol.
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8105093</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B39">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubisz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>KS.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Exploring the genesis and functions of human accelerated regions sheds light on their role in human evolution</article-title>. <source/>Curr Opin Genet Dev.
<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25156517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B40">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Generating samples under a Wright-Fisher neutral model of genetic variation</article-title>. <source/>Bioinformatics
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11847089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B41">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguadé</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>A test of neutral molecular evolution based on nucleotide data</article-title>. <source/>Genetics
<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3110004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B42">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeager</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Natural selection at major histocompatibility complex loci of vertebrates</article-title>. <source/>Annu Rev Genet.
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9928486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B43">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>WHI.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Breaking the (un)sound barrier: filaggrin is a major gene for atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source/>J Investig Dermatol.
<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>1200</fpage>–<lpage>1202</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16702964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B44">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachtrog</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Characterizing the influence of effective population size on the rate of adaptation: Gillespie’s Darwin domain</article-title>. <source/>Genome Biol Evol.
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>701</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21705473</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B45">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The KEGG resource for deciphering the genome</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res.
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>D277</fpage>–<lpage>D280</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B46">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Madeoy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Akey</surname><given-names>JM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Genomic signatures of positive selection in humans and the limits of outlier approaches</article-title>. <source/>Genome Res.
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>980</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B47">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Key</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Romagné</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrés</surname><given-names>AM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Human adaptation and population differentiation in the light of ancient genomes</article-title>. <source/>Nat Commun.<volume>18:7</volume>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B48">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Key</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de, Andrés</surname><given-names>AM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Advantageous diversity maintained by balancing selection in humans</article-title>. <source/>Curr Opin Genet Dev. <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25173959</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B49">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<article-title>The neutral theory of molecular evolution</article-title>. <source/>Sci Am.
<volume>241</volume>:<fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">504979</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B50">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1975</year>
<article-title>Evolution at two levels in humans and chimpanzees</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1090005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B51">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudbjartsson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sainz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsdottir</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudjonsson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigurdardottir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallbeck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>A high-resolution recombination map of the human genome</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet.
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12053178</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B52">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chute</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Horan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfenninger</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanford</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scully</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Welcher</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holers</surname><given-names>VM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title><italic>CSMD1</italic> is a novel multiple domain complement-regulatory protein highly expressed in the central nervous system and epithelial tissues</article-title>. <source/>J Immunol. <volume>176</volume>:<fpage>4419</fpage>–<lpage>4430</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B53">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Differential strengths of positive selection revealed by hitchhiking effects at small physical scales in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source/>Mol Biol Evol
<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>804</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24361994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B54">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leffler</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullaughey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matute</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ségurel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Przeworski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Revisiting an old riddle: what determines genetic diversity levels within species?</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Biol.
<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e1001388</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22984349</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B55">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewontin</surname><given-names>RC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1974</year>
<source/>The genetic basis of evolutionary change. 
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B56">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libioulle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansoul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Farnir</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchimont</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermeire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewit</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Demarche</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Novel Crohn disease locus identified by genome-wide association maps to a gene desert on 5p13. 1 and modulates expression of PTGER4</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e58.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17447842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B57">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Worley</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazareth</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzny</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinwalla</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Minx</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitreva</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Comparative and demographic analysis of orang-utan genomes</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>469</volume>(<issue>7331</issue>):<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21270892</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B58">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Adaptive protein evolution at the <italic>Adh</italic> locus in Drosophila</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>351</volume>:<fpage>652</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1904993</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B59">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<chapter-title>The cultured chimpanzee</chapter-title>
<source/>Reflections on cultural primatology. 
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B60">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Veeramah</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Woerner</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevison</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ape Genome Project</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Inference of gorilla demographic and selective history from whole-genome sequence data</article-title>. <source/>Mol Biol Evol.
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>600</fpage>–<lpage>612</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B61">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertsemlidis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavaslar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybjaerg-Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Folsom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Boerwinkle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A common allele on chromosome 9 associated with coronary heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>316</volume>(<issue>5830</issue>):<fpage>1488</fpage>–<lpage>1491</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17478681</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B62">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McVicker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Widespread genomic signatures of natural selection in hominid evolution</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<volume>5</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e1000471</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19424416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B63">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>DuHadaway</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baban</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlo</surname><given-names>LMF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pigott</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Keough</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rust</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title><italic>IDO2</italic> is critical for <italic>IDO1</italic>-mediated T-cell regulation and exerts a non-redundant function in inflammation</article-title>. <source/>Int Immunol.
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24402311</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B64">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichler</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zody</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Enard</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindblad-Toh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Altheide</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Initial sequence of the chimpanzee genome and comparison with the human genome</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>437</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16136131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B65">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>MF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Insights into therapy: tryptophan oxidation and HIV infection</article-title>. <source/>Sci Transl Med.
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>32ps23.</fpage></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B66">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubisz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrés</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrechtsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutenkunst</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cargill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Indap</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Darwinian and demographic forces affecting human protein coding genes</article-title>. <source/>Genome Res. <volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>838</fpage>–<lpage>849</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19279335</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B67">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oji</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckl</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aufenvenne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Natebus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarinski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackermann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Metze</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurnberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Folster-Holst</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Loss of corneodesmosin leads to severe skin barrier defect, pruritus, and atopy: unraveling the peeling skin disease</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet.
<volume>87</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20691404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B68">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oksenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahituv</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The role of <italic>AUTS2</italic> in neurodevelopment and human evolution</article-title>. <source/>Trends Genet.
<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>600</fpage>–<lpage>608</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24008202</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B69">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meade</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). BayesTraits V2. Software and manual. Reading: University of Reading. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.evolution.rdg.ac.uk/BayesTraitsV2Beta.html">http://www.evolution.rdg.ac.uk/BayesTraitsV2Beta.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B70">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardison</surname><given-names>RC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>What fraction of the human genome is functional?</article-title>
<source/>Genome Res.
<volume>21</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1769</fpage>–<lpage>1776</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21875934</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B71">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prado-Martinez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudmant</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorente-Galdos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Veeramah</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Woerner</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Santpere</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Great ape genetic diversity and population history</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>499</volume>:<fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>475</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23823723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B72">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickrell</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The genetics of human adaptation: hard sweeps, soft sweeps, and polygenic adaptation</article-title>. <source/>Curr Biol.
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>R208</fpage>–<lpage>R215</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20178769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B73">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prüfer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Akagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Walenz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Winer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The bonobo genome compared with the chimpanzee and human genomes</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>486</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>531</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22722832</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B74">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prüfer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Racimo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankararaman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Renaud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudmant</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>de Filippo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The complete genome sequence of a Neanderthal from the Altai Mountains</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>505</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24352235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B75">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatusova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maglott</surname><given-names>DR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>NCBI Reference Sequences (RefSeq): current status, new features and genome annotation policy</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res
<volume>2</volume>(<volume>40</volume>):<fpage>D130</fpage>–<lpage>D135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B76">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dall’Olio</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luisi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzkudun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carreño-Torres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Laayouni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertranpetit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelken</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>1000 Genomes Selection Browser 1.0: a genome browser dedicated to signatures of natural selection in modern humans</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res.
<volume>42</volume> (Database issue):<fpage>D903</fpage>–<lpage>D909</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24275494</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B77">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luisi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dall’Olio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzkudun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laayouni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertranpetit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelken</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Hierarchical boosting: a machine-learning framework to detect and classify hard selective sweeps in human populations</article-title>. <source/>Bioinformatics
<volume>31</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>3946</fpage>–<lpage>3952</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26315912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B78">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabeti</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmueller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Varilly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamovsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Positive natural selection in the human lineage</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>312</volume> (<issue>5780</issue>):<fpage>1614</fpage>–<lpage>1620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B79">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scally</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutheil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Insights into hominid evolution from the gorilla genome sequence</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>483</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22398555</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B80">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semendeferi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Damasio</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Humans and great apes share a large frontal cortex</article-title>. <source/>Nat Neurosci.
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850633</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B81">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Functional divergence of the brain-size regulating gene MCPH1 during primate evolution and the origin of humans</article-title>. <source/>BMC Biol.
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>62.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23697381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B82">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>FJD</given-names></name><name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Terron-Kwiatkowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandilands</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Loss-of-function mutations in the gene encoding filaggrin cause ichthyosis vulgaris</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet.
<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16444271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B83">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Südhof</surname><given-names>TC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Neuroligins and neurexins link synaptic function to cognitive disease</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>455</volume>:<fpage>903</fpage>–<lpage>911</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18923512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B84">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sudmant</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Huddleston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Catacchio</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Malig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohajeri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bontrop</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Persengiev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonacci</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Evolution and diversity of copy number variation in the great ape lineage</article-title>. <source/>Genome Res.
<volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1373</fpage>–<lpage>1382</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23825009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B85">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sudmant</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rausch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Abyzov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huddleston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Konkel</surname><given-names>MK.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>An integrated map of structural variation in 2,504 human genomes</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>526</volume>(<issue>7571</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26432246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B86">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomasello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Call</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<source/>Primate cognition. 
<publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B87">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakonarson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res.
<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>e164.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B88">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Molecular evolution of microcephalin, a gene determining human brain size</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet.
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1131</fpage>–<lpage>1137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15056608</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B89">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weißflog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamzow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Groß-Lesch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rujescu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Walitza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal></etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title><italic>KCNIP4</italic> as a candidate gene for personality disorders and adult ADHD</article-title>. <source/>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol.
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22981920</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B90">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Enard</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Autosomal recessive primary microcephaly (MCPH): a review of clinical, molecular, and evolutionary findings</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet.
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>728</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15806441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B91">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>An investigation of the statistical power of neutrality tests based on comparative and population genetic data</article-title>. <source/>Mol Biol Evol. <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18922762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="msw215-B92">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Snoddy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>WebGestalt: an integrated system for exploring gene sets in various biological contexts</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res.
<volume>1</volume>(<issue>33</issue>):<fpage>W741</fpage>–<lpage>W748</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>