<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cold Spring Harb Mol Case Stud</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cold Spring Harb Mol Case Stud</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">cshmcs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">cshmcs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cshmcs</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Cold Spring Harbor Molecular Case Studies</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2373-2873</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27900366</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5111001</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/mcs.a001230</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ColbyMCS001230</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Exome sequencing reveals germline gain-of-function <italic>EGFR</italic> mutation in an adult with Lhermitte–Duclos disease</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Germline <italic>EGFR</italic> mutation in <italic>PTEN</italic> wild-type LDD</alt-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Germline <italic>EGFR</italic> mutation in <italic>PTEN</italic> wild-type LDD</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Colby</surname>
<given-names>Samantha</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">9</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yehia</surname>
<given-names>Lamis</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">9</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Niazi</surname>
<given-names>Farshad</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>JinLian</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ni</surname>
<given-names>Ying</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9374-3185</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Mester</surname>
<given-names>Jessica L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3693-5145</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Eng</surname>
<given-names>Charis</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af8">8</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="af1"><label>1</label>Genomic Medicine Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio 44195, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af2"><label>2</label>Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio 44195, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af3"><label>3</label>Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, Cleveland, Ohio 44195, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af4"><label>4</label>Department of Pathology, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, Cleveland, Ohio 44106, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af5"><label>5</label>Taussig Cancer Institute, Cleveland Clinic Foundation, Cleveland, Ohio 44195, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af6"><label>6</label>Department of Genetics and Genome Sciences, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, Cleveland, Ohio 44106, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af7"><label>7</label>CASE Comprehensive Cancer Center, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio 44106, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af8"><label>8</label>Germline High Risk Focus Group, CASE Comprehensive Cancer Center, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio 44106, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="equal" id="FN1">
<label>9</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp>Corresponding author: <email>engc@ccf.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>a001230</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>28</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>27</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molecularcasestudies.cshlp.org/site/misc/terms.xhtml">© 2016 Colby et al.; Published by Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</ext-link>
</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License</ext-link>, which permits reuse and redistribution, except for commercial purposes, provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="ColbyMCS001230.pdf"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Lhermitte–Duclos disease (LDD) is a rare cerebellar disorder believed to be pathognomonic for Cowden syndrome. Presently, the only known etiology is germline <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation. We report a 41-yr-old white female diagnosed with LDD and wild-type for <italic>PTEN</italic>. Exome sequencing revealed a germline heterozygous <italic>EGFR</italic> mutation that breaks a disulfide bond in the receptor's extracellular domain, resulting in constitutive activation. Functional studies demonstrate activation of ERK/AKT signaling pathways, mimicking <italic>PTEN</italic> loss-of-function downstream effects. The identification of <italic>EGFR</italic> as a candidate LDD susceptibility gene contributes to advancement of molecular diagnosis and targeted therapy for this rare condition with limited treatment options.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>neoplasm of the nervous system</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="funding-1">
<funding-source>National Cancer Institute <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000054</named-content></funding-source>
<award-id>P01CA124570</award-id>
<award-id>R01CA118989</award-id>
</award-group>
<award-group id="funding-2">
<funding-source>American Cancer Society <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000048</named-content></funding-source>
<award-id>RPG-02-151-01-CCE</award-id>
</award-group>
<award-group id="funding-3">
<funding-source>Breast Cancer Research Foundation <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100001006</named-content></funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group id="funding-4">
<funding-source>William Randolph Hearst Foundations</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group id="funding-5">
<funding-source>Doris Duke Distinguished Clinical Scientist</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group id="funding-6">
<funding-source>National Institutes of Health <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</named-content></funding-source>
<award-id>1S10OD019972-01</award-id>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<page-count count="14"></page-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1" sec-type="introduction"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Presently, there are more than 400 hereditary cancer syndromes, accounting for 5%–10% of all cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C22">Nagy et al. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C12">Garber and Offit 2005</xref>). There are 12 million individuals in the United States and 40 million in the world living with heritable cancer, generating a considerable burden of morbidity and mortality as well as substantial societal costs. The continued identification and characterization of cancer-predisposing genes has allowed for the establishment of more accurate risk assessment, predictive testing for family members, and gene-specific tailored clinical management, all of which can aid in early cancer detection or even prevention.</p><p>Lhermitte–Duclos disease (LDD), also known as dysplastic gangliocytoma of the cerebellum, is a hamartomatous lesion characterized by a slowly enlarging mass within the cerebellar cortex that results in global thickening of the cerebellar folia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C27">Nowak et al. 2001</xref>). The presentation of LDD can mimic many common disorders including headache, epilepsy, and stroke. LDD is believed to be a pathognomonic feature of Cowden syndrome (CS), a multisystem autosomal dominant hereditary disorder characterized by multiple hamartomas and an elevated risk for benign and malignant neoplasms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C20">Marsh et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C28">Orloff and Eng 2008</xref>). Presently, the only known etiology for LDD is germline phosphatase and tensin homolog (<italic>PTEN</italic>) mutation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C46">Zhou et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>CS is estimated to affect 1 in 200,000 individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C24">Nelen et al. 1999</xref>), although this is likely an underestimate considering the extensive degree of phenotypic variability observed in this disorder. Indeed, CS is a clinical mimic with individual features resembling normal variation or alternative disorders. Thus, it is difficult to recognize and hence, remains underdiagnosed. In such situations, having a molecular diagnostic would be desirable. The first identified CS susceptibility gene, <italic>PTEN</italic>, encodes a ubiquitously expressed dual specificity phosphatase that regulates critical cellular processes such as cell cycle, cell migration, and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C23">Nelen et al. 1996</xref>). Although the discovery of <italic>PTEN</italic> as a CS susceptibility gene laid the foundation for gene-enabled clinical management of <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation-positive patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C36">Tan et al. 2012</xref>), this subset of patients accounts for only ∼25% of CS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C35">Tan et al. 2011</xref>). Relatedly, even with subsequent identification of germline alterations in <italic>SDHB-D</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C25">Ni et al. 2008</xref>), <italic>PIK3CA</italic>/<italic>AKT1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C29">Orloff et al. 2013</xref>), and <italic>KLLN</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C3">Bennett et al. 2010</xref>) in a subset of <italic>PTEN</italic> wild-type CS patients, ∼50% remain wild-type for all known CS predisposition genes.</p><p>Although adult-onset LDD has been believed to be pathognomonic for <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation, over the years, adults with LDD have been found not to have <italic>PTEN</italic> or pathway (<italic>PIK3CA/AKT1</italic>) alterations. Therefore, despite the rarity of this disease entity (estimated at 1 in 1,000,000), LDD provides a valuable patient population for discovery of other CS-relevant predisposition genes, which like <italic>PTEN</italic>, have far-reaching somatic implications in common sporadic neoplasias.</p><p>In this study, we utilized next-generation sequencing to analyze exomes of eight unrelated CS probands with LDD and who are wild-type for all known CS susceptibility genes. Variant prioritization revealed a pathogenic germline heterozygous variant in the receptor tyrosine kinase epidermal growth factor receptor (<italic>EGFR</italic> NM_005228: c.977G&gt;T, p.Cys326Phe) in one proband that disrupts a disulfide bridge in the extracellular domain of the receptor. We show the <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe variant is an activating mutation resulting in increased EGFR autophosphorylation, indicating enhanced receptor activation. We also observed increased downstream phosphorylation of ERK1/2 and AKT, consistent with pathway activation mimicking loss-of-function of PTEN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C45">Wu et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C9">Dahia et al. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C42">Weng et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C43">2001a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C44">b</xref>). Our findings suggest that activating mutations in <italic>EGFR</italic> contribute to the pathogenesis of <italic>PTEN</italic> wild-type LDD. Finding the underlying molecular etiology of identical phenotypes facilitates specific medical management and correct choice of targeted therapy or in the future, targeted prevention.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Clinical Presentation and Family History</title><p>We discuss a 43-yr-old female patient who presented to the emergency department at age 41 with left arm weakness and slurred speech. Investigation of the underlying cause of the presentation resulted in the incidental finding of a 5.0-cm mass within the right cerebellar hemisphere on a computed tomography (CT) brain scan without contrast. The mass was predominantly low density and demonstrated some mass effect on the fourth ventricle. The mass was further characterized using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with and without contrast, which revealed a striated appearance and thickening of the cerebellar folia, both characteristic of Lhermitte–Duclos disease. The MRI also revealed a focus of restricted diffusion in the right parietal convexity consistent with an area of acute infarction in the distribution of the right middle cerebral artery, which was believed to be the etiology for the patient's chief complaint. The patient was referred to our institution for clinical and genetic workup relevant to CS, because LDD is a pathognomic feature of the disease. She was found to have macrocephaly (occipital frontal circumference of 58.5 cm) but tested negative for germline alterations in genes known to be associated with CS (<italic>PTEN, SDHB-D, PIK3CA/AKT1, KLLN</italic>).</p><p>Family pedigree was notable for overrepresentation of colorectal cancer from the paternal side, as well as the existence of autism spectrum disorder (both CS-related features) in the 14-yr-old daughter of the proband (Supplemental Fig. S1). Unfortunately, no genomic DNA could be obtained from other family members for mutation testing, so we proceeded by whole-exome sequencing (WES) of germline genomic DNA from our patient and seven other unrelated CS probands, also diagnosed with LDD and wild-type for all known CS susceptibility genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="COLBYMCS001230F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The median age at diagnosis of LDD was 35 (range 9–44 yr). The majority of patients presented with other clinical manifestations of CS in addition to the LDD diagnosis (Supplemental Table S2).</p><fig id="COLBYMCS001230F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Experimental design for candidate gene prioritization and functional analysis. The pilot series of eight was selected from a larger pool of Lhermitte–Duclos disease (LDD) patients shown to be wild-type for <italic>PTEN, SDHB-D</italic>, <italic>AKT1</italic>, and <italic>PIK3CA</italic> variants/mutations and <italic>KLLN</italic> hypermethylation. CS/CSL, Cowden syndrome/CS-like; WES, whole-exome sequencing; CNVs, copy-number variants; ACMG, American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ColbyMCS001230_F1"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Genomic Analyses</title><p>Filtration of variants using the ANNOVAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C41">Wang et al. 2010</xref>) variants reduction pipeline (<uri xlink:href="http://www.openbioinformatics.org/annovar/">http://www.openbioinformatics.org/annovar/</uri>) resulted in a prioritized gene variant count ranging 43–127 for each patient. As expected, we found no germline variants in the known CS susceptibility genes in the patient exomes, thus validating our initial mutation scanning results. We also analyzed our exomes for germline mutations in cancer-associated genes according to the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics (ACMG) guidelines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C14">Green et al. 2013</xref>) and other genes known to be associated with hereditary cancer syndromes with clinical phenotypic overlap with Cowden syndrome. This analysis also included exon-level copy-number variant (CNV) analysis using the eXome-Hidden Markov Model (XHMM) algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C10">Fromer and Purcell 2014</xref>). Interestingly, we found no germline mutations or CNVs in these genes within the studied exomes. Accordingly, and because LDD is a highly specific feature of CS, we first looked for variants in genes that are mutated in two or more patients. We found that only two of the eight patients shared germline missense heterozygous variants in TITIN (<italic>TTN</italic>), the largest gene in the human genome that has not been implicated in a protumorigenic overgrowth phenotype. Because <italic>PTEN</italic> is the only known susceptibility gene in LDD, we then hypothesized that LDD patients may be harboring germline variants in genes belonging to the PTEN signaling pathway. Indeed, we observed four missense heterozygous variants in genes that are upstream of or downstream from PTEN (<xref ref-type="table" rid="COLBYMCS001230TB1">Table 1</xref>). Among the four variants, only the epidermal growth factor receptor (<italic>EGFR</italic>) variant (NM_005228: c.977G&gt;T, p.Cys326Phe) has never been reported in known public databases (dbSNP138, 1000 Genomes, NHLBI-ESP6500, and ExAC). We then examined in silico the predicted functional impact and consistently noted a higher index of pathogenicity for the <italic>EGFR</italic> variant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="COLBYMCS001230TB2">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="COLBYMCS001230TB3">3</xref>). Further structural modeling predicted that the <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe variant has a severe impact on protein structure because of breakage of a disulfide bond in the extracellular receptor domain and replacement of a 100% conserved cysteine with a phenylalanine residue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="COLBYMCS001230F2">Fig. 2</xref>A,B). The <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe variant occurred in proband 5436-LDD7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="COLBYMCS001230F1">Fig. 1</xref>) and we found no other <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations in the seven unrelated LDD probands. Moreover, this variant was absent from germline genomic DNA of 28 LDD patients with known germline pathogenic <italic>PTEN</italic> mutations. Finally, exome sequencing and in silico exon-level CNV analysis of 60 unrelated <italic>PTEN</italic> wild-type patients with CS or Bannayan–Riley–Ruvalcaba syndrome (a hamartomatous overgrowth syndrome allelic to CS) without LDD did not reveal other <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations or copy-number alterations.</p><fig id="COLBYMCS001230F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe mutation is conserved and disrupts an extracellular disulfide bridge. (<italic>A</italic>) A sequence chromatogram of the <italic>EGFR</italic> codon affected by the nucleotide mutation and conservation of the C326 amino acid across multiple species. (<italic>B</italic>) The protein structure of EGFR, with an enlarged view of the cysteine residue at position 326 forming the Cys311–Cys326 disulfide bond in wild-type EGFR and the phenylalanine residue and disruption of the same disulfide bond in mutant EGFR. Structural modeling was performed using Swiss-PdbViewer (<uri xlink:href="http://spdbv.vital-it.ch">http://spdbv.vital-it.ch</uri>) and EGFR PDB structure 3NJP.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ColbyMCS001230_F2"></graphic></fig><table-wrap id="COLBYMCS001230TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of four variants identified within the PTEN signaling pathway</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chromosome</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HGVS DNA Reference</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HGVS protein reference</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variant type</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dbSNP ID</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genotype</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>EGFR</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7:55223610</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM_005228</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p.Cys326Phe</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Substitution</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterozygous</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>INSRR</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1:156823922</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM_014215</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p.Arg87Cys</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Substitution</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">rs374390533</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterozygous</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>ILK</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11:6629361</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM_001014795</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p.Arg59Trp</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Substitution</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterozygous</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>MET</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7:116339877</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM_001127500</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p.Ile247Val</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Substitution</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterozygous</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>PTEN, phosphatase and tensin homolog; HGVS, Human Genome Variation Society; dbSNP, Database for Short Genetic Variations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="COLBYMCS001230TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Prioritization of the PTEN signaling pathway candidate genes identified from eight unrelated LDD patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gene</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Database</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>EGFR</italic> c.977G&gt;T, p.Cys326Phe (Patient 5436-LDD7)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>INSRR</italic> c.259C&gt;T, p.Arg87Cys (Patient 4660-LDD6)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>ILK</italic> c.175C&gt;T, p.Arg59Trp (Patient 3249-LDD5)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>MET</italic> c.739A&gt;G, p.Ile247Val (Patient 344-LDD1)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000 Genomes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2/5008 (0.0004)<break></break>rs374390533</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NHLBI-ESP6500</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2/13006 (0.0002)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ExAC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64/120676 (0.0005)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2/121380 (1.648e-05)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5/120756 (4.141e-05)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MutationTaster</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease-causing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease-causing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease-causing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease-causing</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MutPred</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Probability of deleterious mutation: 0.895</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Probability of deleterious mutation: 0.798</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Probability of deleterious mutation: 0.665</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Probability of deleterious mutation: 0.657</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Condel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease-causing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neutral</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neutral</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neutral</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Project HOPE</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Loss of cysteine bridge → severe effect on 3D structure of protein<break></break>Mutation of 100% conserved residue</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disturbance of salt bridge made by original wild-type residue</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disturbance of salt bridge made by original wild-type residue<break></break>Wild-type residue not conserved at this position</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Homologous proteins exist with mutant residue at this position → mutation possibly not damaging</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>PTEN, phosphatase and tensin homolog; LDD, Lhermitte–Duclos disease; NHLBI, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; ExAC, Exome Aggregration Consortium; Condel, Consensus Deleteriousness.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="COLBYMCS001230TB3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Sequencing parameters for the exome-sequenced patient 5436-LDD7</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exome mean coverage</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bases covered ≥10 reads (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Targeted regions without reads (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coverage at <italic>EGFR</italic> reported variant</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">195.9×</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">154× (50% mutated allele)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Functional Analyses</title><p>To investigate the in vitro impact of the <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe variant, we transiently transfected HEK293T cells with empty vector, wild-type, and p.Cys326Phe <italic>EGFR</italic> plasmids. Consistent with in silico predictions, immunoblotting of proteins downstream from EGFR demonstrated significantly increased phosphorylation of ERK1/2 and a slight increase of AKT phosphorylation at serine residue 473 in mutant cells relative to empty vector and <italic>EGFR</italic> wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="COLBYMCS001230F3">Fig. 3</xref>A). Furthermore, we also observed increased phosphorylation of EGFR at its autophosphorylation tyrosine sites Y992, Y1045, and Y1068, providing further evidence supporting enhanced mutant receptor activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="COLBYMCS001230F3">Fig. 3</xref>B). In support of our biochemical data, fluorescent visualization of green fluorescent protein (GFP)-tagged EGFR in transiently transfected HEK293T cells revealed pronounced clustering of EGFR in 293T-<italic>EGFR-</italic>C326F mutant cells relative to wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="COLBYMCS001230F3">Fig. 3</xref>C). Finally, we observed notable hypertrophy of 293T-<italic>EGFR-</italic>C326F mutant cells, a hallmark feature consistent with the pathobiology of human LDD phenotype (Supplemental Fig. S2).</p><fig id="COLBYMCS001230F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Functional analysis of <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe mutation. (<italic>A</italic>) A western blot assessing phospho-AKT, total AKT, phospho-ERK1/2, and total ERK1/2 expression in transiently transfected HEK293T cells. The quantitation bar plot appears below the western blot, with expression of phosphorylated proteins normalized to corresponding total protein. (<italic>B</italic>) A western blot assessing total EGFR, phospho-EGFR-Y992, phospho-EGFR-Y1045, and phospho-EGFR-Y1068 expression in transiently transfected HEK293T cells. The first two lanes represent commercially available cell lysates that serve as negative and positive controls of EGFR activation. The lysates are derived from A431 cells, known to have a large number of EGF binding sites, and representing an epidermal carcinoma of the vulva. The negative control (lane <italic>1</italic>) represents lysates extracted from overnight serum-starved A431 cells, hence signifying nonphosphorylated EGFR. The positive control (lane <italic>2</italic>) represents lysates extracted from A431 cells treated with 100 ng/mL EGF for 5 min, hence signifying active phosphorylated EGFR. Protein lysates from mutant cells (lane <italic>4</italic>) reveal notable EGFR phosphorylation compared with wild-type cells (lane <italic>3</italic>) even in the absence of EGF stimulation, reflecting constitutive receptor activation. (<italic>C</italic>) Confocal microscopy images of transiently transfected wild-type and p.Cys326Phe-mutant HEK293T cells, with the mutant cells demonstrating increased receptor clustering relative to wild-type cells (green). (<italic>D</italic>) The proposed model of the relationship between <italic>PTEN</italic> loss-of-function and <italic>EGFR</italic> gain-of-function mutations in Cowden syndrome (CS)-Lhermitte–Duclos disease (LDD). WT, wild-type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ColbyMCS001230_F3"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>EGFR is a transmembrane growth factor receptor that plays a well-established role in carcinogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C40">Voldborg et al. 1997</xref>). Raised awareness for <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations occurred with the discovery of a subset of non-small-cell lung cancers with specific activating somatic <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations that confer increased sensitivity to tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C18">Lynch et al. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C30">Pao et al. 2004</xref>). Somatic <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations and amplifications occur in multiple cancer types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C8">Ciardiello and Tortora 2008</xref>), whereas germline <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations are rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C7">Centeno et al. 2011</xref>) but most commonly occur in familial lung cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C2">Bell et al. 2005</xref>) and in a small subset of “never-smoking” lung cancer patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C30">Pao et al. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C32">Prim et al. 2014</xref>). Although the germline gain-of-function <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe mutation has not been previously reported, a somatic mutation at the same position (p.Cys326Arg) and with similar predicted gain-of-function effects is reported in The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). Interestingly, this mutation was found in a renal cell carcinoma, a major CS-component cancer.</p><p>Knowing that <italic>PTEN</italic> is the only known LDD susceptibility gene and that LDD is highly pathognomonic of CS, our findings reveal that the <italic>PTEN</italic> wild-type subset of LDD patients indeed represents a genotypically heterogeneous population, especially when variable CS-overlapping clinical phenotypes are present (Supplemental Table S2). This may partly explain the absence of a shared genetic etiology among our pilot series of sequenced LDD patients. This is also confounded by the fact that LDD is rare and often reported as simplex cases—further complicated by the immense difficulty in obtaining cerebellar tissue for functional analyses. However, our data indicate that multiple genes within the PTEN signaling pathway may converge on and contribute to the same downstream signaling effects and, hence, disease etiology (<xref ref-type="table" rid="COLBYMCS001230TB1">Table 1</xref>). We show this biochemically for the <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe mutation, with increased activation of the ERK and AKT signaling pathways, mimicking loss-of-function <italic>PTEN</italic> mutations. Notably, although the proband does not have a family history of LDD, her pedigree shows an overrepresentation of colon cancer (Supplemental Fig. S1). Interestingly, <italic>EGFR</italic> germline mutations have never been reported in colon cancer and somatic mutations are rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C1">Barber et al. 2004</xref>). Nonetheless, EGFR-targeted antibodies (cetuximab) have been FDA-approved for colon cancer treatment, chiefly because of the important role EGFR signaling plays in colon carcinogenesis.</p><p>Our observations here may be pertinent in the context that LDD is surgically difficult to completely resect. Thus, nonsurgical treatment is germane. Typically, a poly ADP ribose polymerase (PARP) inhibitor could be considered for germline <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation positive CS/CSL individuals and individuals with <italic>PTEN</italic>-related LDD. However, if an individual with LDD does not have the typical <italic>PTEN</italic> germline mutation but instead has a germline <italic>EGFR</italic> mutation, then some type of tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) or antibody could be considered. TKIs have been utilized in a subset of lung cancers with somatic <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations with the majority of the latter occurring in the TK domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C18">Lynch et al. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C30">Pao et al. 2004</xref>). Most of these TK domain mutations alter the structure of EGFR such that there is an increased binding affinity of the mutant receptor to the TKI instead of ATP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C5">Carey et al. 2006</xref>). Our LDD-<italic>EGFR</italic> mutation occurs in the extracellular cysteine-rich domain, where constitutive receptor dimerization and activation is predicted to occur. This should not yield the differential affinity of TKI to our mutant EGFR. Thus, in this situation, an antibody might be more appropriate. However, if indeed, as we show there is increased ERK signaling downstream from our <italic>EGFR</italic> mutant, then there is the theoretical possibility of using a mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) inhibitor. Similarly, we also show a modest increase in phospho-AKT downstream from our constitutively activated mutant EGFR and perhaps an AKT inhibitor could also be considered.</p><p>The presence of a germline <italic>EGFR</italic> mutation in LDD, a cerebellar lesion, is particularly relevant because of the critical role EGFR plays in brain development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C26">Novak et al. 2001</xref>). Interestingly, somatic-activating <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations and loss-of-function <italic>PTEN</italic> mutations have both been highly associated with glioblastoma multiforme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C34">Smith et al. 2001</xref>). As an established oncogene, it is not surprising that a gain-of-function mutation will result in an overgrowth phenotype such as LDD. However, this is paralleled by the discovery of somatic-inactivating mutations of <italic>LKB1</italic> (also known as <italic>STK11</italic>, encoding serine/threonine kinase 11) in lung adenocarcinomas and squamous cell carcinomas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C15">Ji et al. 2007</xref>). Intriguingly, germline mutations in <italic>LKB1</italic> result in Peutz–Jeghers syndrome (considered in differential diagnosis for CS) characterized by intestinal hamartomas and increased lifetime cancer risk. Importantly, unlike somatic mutations in such cancer-relevant genes, heritable germline mutations result in elevated cancer lifetime risk across multiple generations. What remains elusive is whether our patient is at increased risk of other extracerebellar tumors known to be associated with <italic>EGFR</italic> aberrations, including head and neck, colon (given family history), or renal cell carcinoma as being associated with a similar mutation in TCGA. This indeed underscores the importance of pursuing genetic testing in individuals with relevant family history. Detection of pathogenic cancer-predisposing germline mutations not only prompts the initiation of gene-informed high-risk surveillance and/or preventive clinical measures but also includes the theoretical possibility of an <italic>EGFR</italic>-targeted therapy.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Research Participants and Clinical Data</title><p>A total of 3399 individuals were accrued prospectively. These patients were recruited from both community and academic medical centers throughout North America, Europe (with &gt;85% originating from these two continents), and Asia using a standard protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C36">Tan et al. 2012</xref>). Eligible probands were CS-LDD patients who tested negative for germline alterations in <italic>PTEN</italic>, <italic>SDHB</italic>, <italic>SDHC</italic>, <italic>SDHD</italic>, <italic>AKT1</italic>, <italic>PIK3CA,</italic> and <italic>KLLN</italic> and met at least the relaxed International Cowden Consortium (ICC) operational diagnostic criteria (Supplemental Table S1). Scanning of genomic DNA for known gene candidate mutations was performed as we previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C25">Ni et al. 2008</xref>), using a combination of denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (<italic>PTEN</italic>), high-resolution melting curve analysis (<italic>PTEN</italic> and <italic>SDHx</italic>), and direct Sanger sequencing (all CS-known genes). Sanger sequencing of the <italic>PTEN</italic> promoter region was also performed, as we previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C37">Teresi et al. 2007</xref>). Deletion analysis was performed for <italic>PTEN</italic> and <italic>SDHx</italic> using the multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA) assay, according to the manufacturer's protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C33">Schouten et al. 2002</xref>). <italic>KLLN</italic> promoter methylation analysis was performed using the Sequenom MassArray assay, as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C19">Mahdi et al. 2015</xref>). For all selected individuals, we reviewed the Cleveland Clinic (CC) score (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C35">Tan et al. 2011</xref>), a semiquantitative score that is based on weighting clinical features and that estimates the pretest probability of finding a germline <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation (<uri xlink:href="http://www.lerner.ccf.org/gmi/ccscore">http://www.lerner.ccf.org/gmi/ccscore</uri>). Given that all individuals are wild-type for <italic>PTEN</italic>, we used the CC score as a surrogate of phenotypic burden. We reviewed medical records, including pathology reports, for each research participant and extracted family history from clinical notes associated with cancer genetics and/or genetic-counseling visits, where applicable and with the individuals’ consent. Cleveland Clinic Institutional Review Board approval (protocol #8458) and written informed consents from all research participants were obtained for this study.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Exome Sequencing and Bioinformatic Analysis</title><p>We subjected germline genomic DNA extracted from peripheral-blood leukocytes of the eligible probands to exome sequencing. Exome enrichment was performed with the TruSeq SBS v.3 Kit (Illumina), and subsequent 100-bp paired-end sequencing was performed with an Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform. Sequencing was performed at an Illumina Sequencing Service Center. Raw sequencing reads were mapped to the human reference haploid genome sequence (UCSC Genome Browser hg19) with the Burrows–Wheeler aligner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C16">Li and Durbin 2009</xref>) (BWA v.0.6.1; <uri xlink:href="http://bio-bwa.sourceforge.net">http://bio-bwa.sourceforge.net</uri>). Insertion or deletion (indel) realignment, base- and quality-score recalibrations, and removal of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) duplicates from the resultant binary alignment map (BAM) files were performed with the Genome Analysis Toolkit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C21">McKenna et al. 2010</xref>) (GATK; <uri xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/">http://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/</uri>), Sequence Alignment/Map (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C17">Li et al. 2009</xref>) (SAMtools), and Picard (<uri xlink:href="http://broadinstitute.github.io/picard/">http://broadinstitute.github.io/picard/</uri>). Variant discovery and genotype calling of single-nucleotide variants (SNVs) and short (&lt;50-bp) indels were performed with the GATK Haplotype Caller.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Variant Filtration and Annotation</title><p>To prioritize causal variants, we applied ANNOVAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C41">Wang et al. 2010</xref>) (<uri xlink:href="http://www.openbioinformatics.org/annovar/">http://www.openbioinformatics.org/annovar/</uri>). First, we discarded synonymous variants and intronic variants &gt;2 bp from exon boundaries. We retained variants in conserved genomic regions on the basis of a 46-species alignment and removed variants existing in segmental duplication regions. We excluded variants with a minor allele frequency (MAF) ≥ 0.0005 (or 0.05%) in the 1000 Genomes Project (August 2015 release) or the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) Exome Sequencing Project (ESP) Exome Variant Server (ESP6500 data set) and variants reported in the Database for Short Genetic Variations (dbSNP)138 nonflagged database (excluding clinically associated single-nucleotide polymorphisms [SNPs]).</p><p>To predict the potential impact of missense variants on protein function, we used the program Consensus Deleteriousness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C13">Gonzalez-Perez and Lopez-Bigas 2011</xref>) (Condel v.1.5; <uri xlink:href="http://bg.upf.edu/fannsdb/">http://bg.upf.edu/fannsdb/</uri>), which combines multiple prediction software algorithms (SIFT [Sorting Intolerant from Tolerant], PolyPhen-2 [Polymorphism Phenotyping v2], and MutationAssessor) into a single weighted score. We inspected all resultant variants through the Integrative Genomics Viewer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C38">Thorvaldsdottir et al. 2013</xref>) (IGV; <uri xlink:href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/igv/home/">https://www.broadinstitute.org/igv/home/</uri>). We also used an in-house database containing variants from 11 individuals with sporadic polyposis and 13 exomes from individuals with unrelated phenotypes (connective-tissue disorders); these were sequenced with our cohort of research participants as an additional internal control filter. We excluded variants that appeared more than once in these in-house exome databases.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Copy-Number Variant Analysis</title><p>We implemented the XHMM algorithm to call CNVs from our exome-sequencing data, using default parameters. XHMM makes use of principal component analysis to normalize sequencing read depth and a hidden Markov model, while providing corresponding quality metrics for downstream prioritization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C11">Fromer et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C31">Poultney et al. 2013</xref>). For the purposes of this study, we extracted data corresponding to cancer-associated genes according to the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics (ACMG) guidelines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C14">Green et al. 2013</xref>), and other genes known to be associated with hereditary cancer syndromes with clinical phenotypic overlap with Cowden syndrome. The mean per-target depth of coverage across all samples was 60. An XHMM quality score (SQ or Q_some) of 60 was used as a cutoff threshold for CNV filtration and prioritization.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Mutation Validation</title><p>Mutations in candidate genes of interest were validated by PCR-based region-specific mutation analysis through Sanger sequencing. In brief, gene-specific primers encompassing exonic regions harboring the particular variations were designed (Supplemental Table S3). Sequencing was performed in the forward and reverse directions with Applied Biosystems ABI 3730xl DNA Analyzers at the Genomics Core of the Lerner Research Institute of the Cleveland Clinic and the Eurofins Genomics DNA-sequencing facility (Louisville). Primer sequences are listed in Supplemental Table S3. Resultant chromatograms were analyzed with Mutation Surveyor DNA Variant Analysis Software (SoftGenetics), and mutations were reported according to the Human Genome Variation Society (HGVS) guidelines. Incidental findings were reported to our genetic counselors to be communicated to the respective affected individuals and physicians of record according to the ACMG guidelines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C14">Green et al. 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Variant Interpretation and In Silico Pathogenicity Predictions</title><p>Variants retained after prioritization were considered potentially pathogenic. Further prioritization was performed through selection of shared genes with variants in multiple patients and variants belonging to genes in the <italic>PTEN</italic> signaling pathway. In silico assessment of the mutations’ effects on protein integrity was performed through a combination of mutation-prediction algorithms, namely Condel (<uri xlink:href="http://bg.upf.edu/fannsdb/">http://bg.upf.edu/fannsdb/</uri>), MutationTaster (<uri xlink:href="http://www.mutationtaster.org/">http://www.mutationtaster.org/</uri>), and MutPred (<uri xlink:href="http://mutpred.mutdb.org/">http://mutpred.mutdb.org/</uri>).</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Predicted Structural Effects of Variants</title><p>We predicted the structural effects of variants by using the HOPE server (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C39">Venselaar et al. 2010</xref>), which integrates a series of standard algorithms to generate predictions. Structural information was obtained from the analysis of PDB structures 4KRP (EGFR), 4HI8 (ILK), 1IGR (INSRR), and 2UZX (MET). Annotations were obtained from UniProt entries EGFR_HUMAN, ILK_HUMAN, INSRR_HUMAN, and MET_HUMAN.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Cell Lines and Culture Conditions</title><p>HEK293T cells (originally purchased from the American Type Culture Collection) in 2011 and obtained in 2014 from the Cleveland Clinic Lerner Research Institute Cell Culture Core were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 1% penicillin and streptomycin. Cell lines were maintained at 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> culture conditions and tested negative upon routine mycoplasma testing with the MycoAlert Mycoplasma Detection Kit (Lonza) at the C.E. lab (luminescence ratios &lt; 0.9). Cell lines used have not been listed as cells known to be misidentified according to the International Cell Line Authentication Committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C4">Capes-Davis et al. 2010</xref>). Cell lines purchased from ATCC after 2010 have been authenticated by short-tandem-repeat PCR analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Plasmids, Mutagenesis, and Cell-Line Transfection</title><p>We generated the <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe mutant plasmid via site-directed mutagenesis of GFP-tagged wild-type <italic>EGFR</italic> plasmid #32751 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COLBYMCS001230C6">Carter and Sorkin 1998</xref>) (Addgene). Wild-type plasmids were mutagenized for the missense mutation of interest with the QuikChange II Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Agilent Technologies). All expression constructs were validated by Sanger sequencing prior to transfection. For transient overexpression, cell lines were transfected with GFP-tagged <italic>EGFR</italic><sup>WT</sup>, <italic>EGFR</italic><sup>C326F</sup>, or empty vector plasmids using Lipofectamine 3000 reagent (Thermo Fisher) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Cells were grown for at least 24 h before harvesting or downstream analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Immunoblotting</title><p>Protein was extracted from whole-cell lysates with the Mammalian Protein Extraction Reagent M-PER (Thermo Scientific Pierce) supplemented with a cocktail of protease and phosphatase inhibitors (Sigma-Aldrich) and was quantified with the BCA Protein Assay Kit (Thermo Scientific Pierce). Lysates were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes. We performed immunoblotting using protein lysates extracted from HEK293T cells expressing empty vector, <italic>EGFR</italic> wild-type, and <italic>EGFR</italic> p.Cys326Phe plasmids. We blotted for anti-phospho-AKT S473 (Cell Signaling #4060), anti-total AKT (Cell Signaling #9272), anti-phospho-ERK1/2 (Cell Signaling #9101), anti-ERK1/2 (Cell Signaling #9102), and anti-GAPDH (Cell Signaling #2118) antibodies, at the recommended dilutions. EGFR control cell extracts (Cell Signaling #5634) were used as negative and positive controls of EGFR phosphorylation/activation. Blots were scanned digitally and quantified with the Odyssey Infrared Imaging System (Li-Cor Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>Cells were seeded on coverslips and were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 5 min at room temperature. Coverslips were mounted with ProLong Gold Antifade mountant with DAPI (Invitrogen). Slides were visualized and images were obtained with a TCS SP8 confocal microscope (Leica).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>ADDITIONAL INFORMATION</title><sec id="s5a"><title>Data Deposition and Access</title><p>Exome-sequencing data has been deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Sequence Read Archive (SRA) (<uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/</uri>) under accession number SRX1802645. The <italic>EGFR</italic> c.977G&gt;T, p.Cys326Phe mutation has been deposited to ClinVar (<uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/</uri>) under accession number SCV000299219.</p></sec><sec id="s5b"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Cleveland Clinic Institutional Review Board approval (protocol #8458) and written informed consent from all research participants were obtained for this study.</p></sec><sec id="s5c"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to the patients who contributed to this study. We thank Todd Romigh and Kaitlin Sesock for technical advice and helpful discussions. We also thank the Genomic Medicine Biorepository of the Cleveland Clinic Genomic Medicine Institute and our database and clinical research teams. L.Y. is an International Fulbright Science and Technology Doctoral Fellow at the Cleveland Clinic Genomic Medicine Institute and recipient of the Dr. Michael H. Fakih predoctoral scholarship. C.E. is the Sondra J. and Stephen R. Hardis Chair of Cancer Genomic Medicine at the Cleveland Clinic and an ACS Clinical Research Professor.</p></sec><sec id="s5d"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>L.Y. and C.E. contributed to study design. J.L.M. and C.E. contributed to patient recruitment, clinical evaluation, and phenotyping. L.Y. and F.N. contributed to raw sequence data analysis. S.C. and L.Y. contributed to variant prioritization, validation, and functional analyses. J.C. contributed to EGFR protein modeling. S.C., L.Y., and C.E. contributed to manuscript preparation. All authors contributed to the revision of manuscript final version.</p></sec><sec id="s5e"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was funded in part by the National Cancer Institute (P01CA124570 and R01CA118989), American Cancer Society (RPG-02-151-01-CCE and Clinical Research Professorship), Breast Cancer Research Foundation, William Randolph Hearst Foundations, and Doris Duke Distinguished Clinical Scientist Award (all to C.E.). This work utilized the Leica SP8 confocal microscope that was purchased with funding from National Institutes of Health SIG grant 1S10OD019972-01.</p></sec><sec id="s5f"><title>Competing Interest Statement</title><p>The authors have declared no competing interest.</p></sec><sec id="s5g"><title>Referees</title><p>Michele Carbone</p><p>Raymond Kim</p><p>Anonymous</p></sec></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="PMC_1">
<caption>
<title>Supplemental Material</title>
</caption>
<media mime-subtype="html" mimetype="text" xlink:href="supp_2_6_a001230__index.html"></media>
<media mime-subtype="msword" mimetype="application" xlink:href="supp_mcs.a001230_Supp_Material.docx" xlink:role="associated-file"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supplementary-material">
<p>[Supplemental material is available for this article.]</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kinzler</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Velculescu</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>. <year>2004</year>
<article-title>Somatic mutations of <italic>EGFR</italic> in colorectal cancers and glioblastomas</article-title>. <source/>N Engl J Med
<volume>351</volume>: <fpage>2883</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15625347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okimoto</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Godin-Heymann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sordella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mulloy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brannigan</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohapatra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Settleman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Inherited susceptibility to lung cancer may be associated with the T790M drug resistance mutation in EGFR</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1315</fpage>–<lpage>1316</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16258541</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mester</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Germline epigenetic regulation of KILLIN in Cowden and Cowden-like syndrome</article-title>. <source/>JAMA
<volume>304</volume>: <fpage>2724</fpage>–<lpage>2731</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Capes-Davis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theodosopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drexler</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reddel</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Check your cultures! A list of cross-contaminated or misidentified cell lines</article-title>. <source/>Int J Cancer
<volume>127</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20143388</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kahler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sliwkowski</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name>. <year>2006</year>
<article-title>Kinetic analysis of epidermal growth factor receptor somatic mutant proteins shows increased sensitivity to the epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor, erlotinib</article-title>. <source/>Cancer Res
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>8163</fpage>–<lpage>8171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sorkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>Endocytosis of functional epidermal growth factor receptor-green fluorescent protein chimera</article-title>. <source/>J Biol Chem
<volume>273</volume>: <fpage>35000</fpage>–<lpage>35007</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9857032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Centeno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santamaria</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Astudillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitiot</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzalez-Arriaga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Menendez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tardon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Germ-line mutations in epidermal growth factor receptor (<italic>EGFR</italic>) are rare but may contribute to oncogenesis: a novel germ-line mutation in <italic>EGFR</italic> detected in a patient with lung adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source/>BMC Cancer
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21575252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ciardiello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tortora</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>EGFR antagonists in cancer treatment</article-title>. <source/>N Engl J Med
<volume>358</volume>: <fpage>1160</fpage>–<lpage>1174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18337605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dahia</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kum</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sill</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stiles</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>PTEN is inversely correlated with the cell survival factor Akt/PKB and is inactivated via multiple mechanisms in haematological malignancies</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9931326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fromer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Using XHMM software to detect copy number variation in whole-exome sequencing data</article-title>. <source/>Curr Protoc Hum Genet
<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>7 23 21</fpage>–<lpage>27 23 21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24763994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fromer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chambert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruderfer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarroll</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Donovan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Discovery and statistical genotyping of copy-number variation from whole-exome sequencing depth</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>91</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>607</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23040492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Offit</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <year>2005</year>
<article-title>Hereditary cancer predisposition syndromes</article-title>. <source/>J Clin Oncol
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15637391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gonzalez-Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopez-Bigas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Improving the assessment of the outcome of nonsynonymous SNVs with a consensus deleteriousness score, Condel</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21457909</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grody</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Daniel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ormond</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>ACMG recommendations for reporting of incidental findings in clinical exome and genome sequencing</article-title>. <source/>Genet Med
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23788249</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozlowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torrice</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>LKB1 modulates lung cancer differentiation and metastasis</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>448</volume>: <fpage>807</fpage>–<lpage>810</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17676035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows–Wheeler transform</article-title>. <source/>Bioinformatics
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1754</fpage>–<lpage>1760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title>. <source/>Bioinformatics
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2078</fpage>–<lpage>2079</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sordella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gurubhagavatula</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okimoto</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brannigan</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haserlat</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Supko</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haluska</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Activating mutations in the epidermal growth factor receptor underlying responsiveness of non-small-cell lung cancer to gefitinib</article-title>. <source/>N Engl J Med
<volume>350</volume>: <fpage>2129</fpage>–<lpage>2139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15118073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahdi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mester</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nizialek</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ngeow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>Germline <italic>PTEN</italic>, <italic>SDHB-D</italic>, and <italic>KLLN</italic> alterations in endometrial cancer patients with Cowden and Cowden-like syndromes: an international, multicenter, prospective study</article-title>. <source/>Cancer
<volume>121</volume>: <fpage>688</fpage>–<lpage>696</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25376524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coulon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lunetta</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rocca-Serra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dahia</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duboue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Mutation spectrum and genotype-phenotype analyses in Cowden disease and Bannayan–Zonana syndrome, two hamartoma syndromes with germline PTEN mutation</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9467011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C21">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sivachenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cibulskis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kernytsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garimella</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The Genome Analysis Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</article-title>. <source/>Genome Res
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1297</fpage>–<lpage>1303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C22">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2004</year>
<article-title>Highly penetrant hereditary cancer syndromes</article-title>. <source/>Oncogene
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>6445</fpage>–<lpage>6470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15322516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C23">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Padberg</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van den Helm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frants</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coulon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Reen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Easton</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Localization of the gene for Cowden disease to Chromosome 10q22–23</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8673088</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Konings</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schoute</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Essen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fryns</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoefsloot</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Novel <italic>PTEN</italic> mutations in patients with Cowden disease: absence of clear genotype–phenotype correlations</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Hum Genet
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10234502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C25">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zbuk</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sadler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patocs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orloff</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Germline mutations and variants in the succinate dehydrogenase genes in Cowden and Cowden-like syndromes</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18678321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C26">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <year>2001</year>
<article-title>Expression of EGFR-family proteins in the brain: role in development, health and disease</article-title>. <source/>J Clin Neurosci
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C27">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trost</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Porr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stolzle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lumenta</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>. <year>2001</year>
<article-title>Lhermitte–Duclos disease (dysplastic gangliocytoma of the cerebellum)</article-title>. <source/>Clin Neurol Neurosurg
<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11516554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C28">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Orloff</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Genetic and phenotypic heterogeneity in the <italic>PTEN</italic> hamartoma tumour syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Oncogene
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>5387</fpage>–<lpage>5397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18794875</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C29">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Orloff</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mester</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Germline <italic>PIK3CA</italic> and <italic>AKT1</italic> mutations in Cowden and Cowden-like syndromes</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23246288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C30">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zakowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Politi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarkaria</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heelan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rusch</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>EGF receptor gene mutations are common in lung cancers from “never smokers” and are associated with sensitivity of tumors to gefitinib and erlotinib</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci
<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>13306</fpage>–<lpage>13311</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15329413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C31">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poultney</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drapeau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harony-Nicolas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kajiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Rubeis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rehnstrom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Identification of small exonic CNV from whole-exome sequence data and application to autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C32">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legrain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mennecier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weingertner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voegeli</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guenot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maugard</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quoix</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beau-Faller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Germ-line exon 21 <italic>EGFR</italic> mutations, V843I and P848L, in nonsmall cell lung cancer patients</article-title>. <source/>Eur Respir Rev
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25176975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C33">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schouten</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McElgunn</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waaijer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zwijnenburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diepvens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pals</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Relative quantification of 40 nucleic acid sequences by multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>e57</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060695</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C34">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tachibana</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Passe</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borell</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iturria</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Fallon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheithauer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>James</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>PTEN mutation, EGFR amplification, and outcome in patients with anaplastic astrocytoma and glioblastoma multiforme</article-title>. <source/>J Natl Cancer Inst
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1246</fpage>–<lpage>1256</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C35">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mester</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rybicki</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Remzi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orloff</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>A clinical scoring system for selection of patients for <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation testing is proposed on the basis of a prospective study of 3042 probands</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C36">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mester</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ngeow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rybicki</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orloff</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Lifetime cancer risks in individuals with germline <italic>PTEN</italic> mutations</article-title>. <source/>Clin Cancer Res
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>400</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22252256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C37">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teresi</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zbuk</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pezzolesi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2007</year>
<article-title>Cowden syndrome-affected patients with <italic>PTEN</italic> promoter mutations demonstrate abnormal protein translation</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>756</fpage>–<lpage>767</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17847000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C38">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thorvaldsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Integrative Genomics Viewer (IGV): high-performance genomics data visualization and exploration</article-title>. <source/>Brief Bioinform
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C39">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Venselaar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Te Beek</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hekkelman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vriend</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Protein structure analysis of mutations causing inheritable diseases. An e-Science approach with life scientist friendly interfaces</article-title>. <source/>BMC Bioinformatics
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>548</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21059217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C40">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Voldborg</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Damstrup</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spang-Thomsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>. <year>1997</year>
<article-title>Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) and EGFR mutations, function and possible role in clinical trials</article-title>. <source/>Ann Oncol
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1197</fpage>–<lpage>1206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9496384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C41">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hakonarson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>. <source/>Nucleic Acids Res
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>e164</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C42">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dahia</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ziebold</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>1999</year>
<article-title>PTEN suppresses breast cancer cell growth by phosphatase activity-dependent G<sub>1</sub> arrest followed by cell death</article-title>. <source/>Cancer Res
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>5808</fpage>–<lpage>5814</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10582703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C43">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2001a</year>
<article-title>PTEN coordinates G(1) arrest by down-regulating cyclin D1 via its protein phosphatase activity and up-regulating p27 via its lipid phosphatase activity in a breast cancer model</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C44">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2001b</year>
<article-title>PTEN inhibits insulin-stimulated MEK/MAPK activation and cell growth by blocking IRS-1 phosphorylation and IRS-1/Grb-2/Sos complex formation in a breast cancer model</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>616</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C45">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Senechal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neshat</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whang</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawyers</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>The PTEN/MMAC1 tumor suppressor phosphatase functions as a negative regulator of the phosphoinositide 3-kinase/Akt pathway</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>15587</fpage>–<lpage>15591</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9861013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="COLBYMCS001230C46">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reifenberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2003</year>
<article-title>Germline inactivation of <italic>PTEN</italic> and dysregulation of the phosphoinositol-3-kinase/Akt pathway cause human Lhermitte–Duclos disease in adults</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>1191</fpage>–<lpage>1198</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14566704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>