<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8918110</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2607</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur. J. Neurosci.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The European journal of neuroscience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0953-816X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-9568</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27564458</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5118072</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejn.13382</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS813685</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A comparative transcriptomic analysis of astrocytes differentiation from human neural progenitor cells</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Magistri</surname>
<given-names>Marco</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Khoury</surname>
<given-names>Nathalie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mazza</surname>
<given-names>Emilia Maria Cristina</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Velmeshev</surname>
<given-names>Dmitry</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Jae K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bicciato</surname>
<given-names>Silvio</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tsoulfas</surname>
<given-names>Pantelis</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Faghihi</surname>
<given-names>Mohammad Ali</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Center for Therapeutic Innovation, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, Florida 33136</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Center for Genome Research, Department of Life Sciences, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Miami Project to Cure Paralysis, Department of Neurological Surgery, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, Florida 33136</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence information for corresponding author: MohammadA. Faghihi, MD, PhD, Center for Therapeutic Innovation &amp; Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, 1501 NW 10th Ave, BRB 508, Miami, FL 33136, USA. <email>mohammad.ali.faghihi@gmail.com</email>. Phone: 305-243-7953</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>All authors indicate no potential conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>1</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>25</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>2858</fpage>
<lpage>2870</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1111/ejn.13382-->
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="P1">Astrocytes are a morphologically and functionally heterogeneous population of cells that play critical roles in neurodevelopment and in the regulation of central nervous system homeostasis. Studies of human astrocytes have been hampered by the lack of specific molecular markers and by the difficulties associated with purifying and culturing astrocytes from adult human brains. Human neural progenitor cells (NPCs) with self-renewal and multipotent properties represent an appealing model system to gain insight into the developmental genetics and function of human astrocytes, but a comprehensive molecular characterization that confirms the validity of this cellular system is still missing. Here we used an unbiased transcriptomic analysis to characterize <italic>in vitro</italic> culture of human NPCs and to define the gene expression programs activated during the differentiation of these cells into astrocytes using FBS or the combination of CNTF and BMP4. Our results demonstrate that <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures of human NPCs isolated during the gliogenic phase of neurodevelopment mainly consist of radial glial cells (RGCs) and glia-restricted progenitor cells. In these cells the combination of CNTF and BMP4 activates the JAK/STAT and SMAD signaling cascades, leading to the inhibition of oligodendrocytes lineage commitment and activation of astrocytes differentiation. On the other hand FBS-derived astrocytes have properties of reactive astrocytes. Our work suggests that in vitro culture of human NPCs represents a valuable cellular system to study human disorders characterized by impairment of astrocytes development and function. Our datasets represent an important resource for researchers studying human astrocytes development and might set the basis for the discovery of novel human-specific astrocyte markers.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="Abs2">
<title>Graphical Abstract</title>
<p id="P2">
<graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="nihms813685u1.jpg"></graphic></p>
<p id="P26">In this study we isolated and cultured neural progenitor cells (NPCs) from human fetal brain, we differentiated NPCs into astrocyte using different protocols and utilized RNA sequencing to define the characteristics of the differentiated astrocytes. Our datasets is an important resource to study human astrocytes development, identify novel human-specific astrocyte markers and represent valuable tool for future studies of human disorders characterized by impairments in astrocytes.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Human astrocytes</kwd>
<kwd>radial glial cells</kwd>
<kwd>neural progenitor cells</kwd>
<kwd>gliogenesis</kwd>
<kwd>astrocyte differentiation</kwd>
<kwd>neurogenesis</kwd>
<kwd>neurodevelopment</kwd>
<kwd>RNAseq</kwd>
<kwd>transcriptomic</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>