<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0376473</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6774</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Psychol Bull</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Psychol Bull</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Psychological bulletin</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0033-2909</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-1455</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27732016</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5118170</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/bul0000073</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS804781</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dispositional negativity: An integrative psychological and neurobiological perspective</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shackman</surname>
<given-names>Alexander J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tromp</surname>
<given-names>Do P. M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">e</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stockbridge</surname>
<given-names>Melissa D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>Claire M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN2">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tillman</surname>
<given-names>Rachael M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN2">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fox</surname>
<given-names>Andrew S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">e</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">f</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Department of Psychology, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742 USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Department of Hearing and Speech Sciences, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742 USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Department of Neuroscience and Cognitive Science Program, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742 USA</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>d</label>Maryland Neuroimaging Center, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742 USA</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>e</label>Department of Psychology, University of California, Davis, CA 95616 USA</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>f</label>California National Primate Research Center, University of California, Davis, CA 95616 USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">ADDRESS CORRESPONDENCE TO: Alexander J. Shackman (<email>shackman@umd.edu</email>), Department of Psychology, 3123G Biology-Psychology Building, University of Maryland, College Park, Maryland 20742 USA</corresp>
<fn fn-type="equal" id="FN2">
<label>*</label>
<p>contributed equally</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN14">
<p>Authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>24</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>142</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>1275</fpage>
<lpage>1314</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1037/bul0000073-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Dispositional negativity—the propensity to experience and express more frequent, intense, or enduring negative affect—is a fundamental dimension of childhood temperament and adult personality. Elevated levels of dispositional negativity can have profound consequences for health, wealth, and happiness, drawing the attention of clinicians, researchers, and policy makers. Here, we highlight recent advances in our understanding of the psychological and neurobiological processes linking stable individual differences in dispositional negativity to momentary emotional states. Self-report data suggest that three key pathways—increased stressor reactivity, tonic increases in negative affect, and increased stressor exposure—explain most of the heightened negative affect that characterizes individuals with a more negative disposition. Of these three pathways, tonically elevated, indiscriminate negative affect appears to be most central to daily life and most relevant to the development of psychopathology. New behavioral and biological data provide insights into the neural systems underlying these three pathways and motivate the hypothesis that seemingly ‘tonic’ increases in negative affect may actually reflect increased reactivity to stressors that are remote, uncertain, or diffuse. Research focused on humans, monkeys, and rodents suggests that this indiscriminate negative affect reflects trait-like variation in the activity and connectivity of several key brain regions, including the central extended amygdala and parts of the prefrontal cortex. Collectively, these observations provide an integrative psychobiological framework for understanding the dynamic cascade of processes that bind emotional traits to emotional states and, ultimately, to emotional disorders and other kinds of adverse outcomes.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>