<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27880801</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5120819</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-53010</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurology</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Epilepsy</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Model Organisms</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Animal Models</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Rats</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Organisms</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Animals</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Vertebrates</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Amniotes</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Mammals</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Rodents</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Rats</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurology</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Epilepsy</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Epileptic Seizures</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Pharmaceutics</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Drug Therapy</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Receptor Antagonist Therapy</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Anatomy</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Brain</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Prefrontal Cortex</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Anatomy</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Brain</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Prefrontal Cortex</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Cell Biology</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Cellular Types</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Animal Cells</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurons</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neuroscience</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Cellular Neuroscience</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurons</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurology</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Epilepsy</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Epileptic Seizures</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Tonic Seizures</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Biochemistry</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurochemistry</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurotransmitters</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Glutamate</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3">
<subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neuroscience</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurochemistry</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Neurotransmitters</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Glutamate</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>AMPA Receptor Antagonist NBQX Decreased Seizures by Normalization of Perineuronal Nets</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">NBQX Decreased Seizures via Perineuronal Nets</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Wen</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Yan-Shuang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Jing</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Xiao-Ying</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Xiao-Hong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Neurology, Jinan Central Hospital, Affiliated to Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong Province, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Neurology, The Affiliated Hospital Of Qingdao University, Qingdao, Shandong Province, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>van Luijtelaar</surname>
<given-names>Gilles</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Radboud Universiteit, NETHERLANDS</addr-line>
</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001">
<p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> WC XHL.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> XYL WC XHL.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> XYL WC.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> XHL.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> WC YSL JG.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> WC YSL JG.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> XHL.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Resources:</bold> WC YSL JG.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Software:</bold> YSL JG.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> XHL.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Validation:</bold> XHL.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> WC XHL.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> XHL XYL YSL JG.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>xiaohong-li@sdu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>23</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<elocation-id>e0166672</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>2</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2016 Chen et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Chen et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0166672.pdf"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Epilepsy is a serious brain disorder with diverse seizure types and epileptic syndromes. AMPA receptor antagonist 2,3-dihydroxy-6-nitro-7-sulfamoyl-benzoquinoxaline-2,3-dione (NBQX) attenuates spontaneous recurrent seizures in rats. However, the anti-epileptic effect of NBQX in chronic epilepsy model is poorly understood. Perineuronal nets (PNNs), specialized extracellular matrix structures, surround parvalbumin-positive inhibitory interneurons, and play a critical role in neuronal cell development and synaptic plasticity. Here, we focused on the potential involvement of PNNs in the treatment of epilepsy by NBQX. Rats were intraperitoneally (i.p.) injected with pentylenetetrazole (PTZ, 50 mg/kg) for 28 consecutive days to establish chronic epilepsy models. Subsequently, NBQX (20 mg/kg, i.p.) was injected for 3 days for the observation of behavioral measurements of epilepsy. The <italic>Wisteria floribundi agglutinin</italic> (<italic>WFA</italic>)-labeled PNNs were measured by immunohistochemical staining to evaluate the PNNs. The levels of three components of PNNs such as tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan were assayed by Western blot assay. The results showed that there are reduction of PNNs and decrease of tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan in the medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC) in the rats injected with PTZ. However, NBQX treatment normalized PNNs, tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan levels. NBQX was sufficient to decrease seizures through increasing the latency to seizures, decrease the duration of seizure onset, and reduce the scores for the severity of seizures. Furthermore, the degradation of mPFC PNNs by chondroitinase ABC (ChABC) exacerbated seizures in PTZ-treated rats. Finally, the anti-epileptic effect of NBQX was reversed by pretreatment with ChABC into mPFC. These findings revealed that PNNs degradation in mPFC is involved in the pathophysiology of epilepsy and enhancement of PNNs may be effective for the treatment of epilepsy.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution>This work was supported in part by a grant from Local Science Foundation of Jinan Central Hospital.</institution>
</funding-source>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Xiao-Hong</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="3"></fig-count>
<table-count count="4"></table-count>
<page-count count="16"></page-count>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<title>Data Availability</title>
<p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Epilepsy is a serious life-shortening neurological disorder, which affects approximately 1% of general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref001">1</xref>] and leads to an increase of disability and mortality in the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref002">2</xref>]. Epilepsy is a diverse phenotype including more than 15 different seizure types and more than 30 epilepsy syndromes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref003">3</xref>]. The core symptom of epilepsy is recurring, unprovoked seizures induced by the abnormal synchronous activity of cerebral neuronal networks. The abnormal hypersynchronous activity induced by impaired inhibition increased extracellular potassium and enhanced excitatory synaptic transmission that are involved in the pathological process in epilepsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref004">4</xref>].</p>
<p>Glutamate is a predominant neurotransmitter released from excitatory neurons related to the fast synaptic excitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref005">5</xref>]. The released glutamates diffuse across the synaptic cleft and generate fast excitatory synaptic potentials (EPSPs) through binding to ionotropic glutamate receptors. The cumulative EPSPs of individual neurons trigger action potentials, which are responsible for epileptic field potentials. Glutamate receptors of the AMPA (a-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid) subtype have been evidenced to play a key role in epileptogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref006">6</xref>]. AMPA receptors regulate the fast synaptic excitation in brain regions that are related to epilepsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref007">7</xref>]. Specifically, AMPA receptor antagonists markedly reduce epileptiform and inhibit spread of epileptic discharges in both animal seizure models and human epilepsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref009">9</xref>]. In addition, growing evidence validate the critical role of AMPA receptors in epileptic seizures, and suggest that AMPA receptors may be a potential target for epilepsy therapy. Rodent models of epilepsy is used and it showed that perampanel, a potent, selective, orally active non-competitive AMPA receptor antagonist, exhibited a strong antiseizure activity in the maximal electroshock seizure test, and the 6 Hz seizure test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref010">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref011">11</xref>]. Moreover, clinical data showed that perampanel with daily dose is effective in patients with refractory partial-onset seizures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref012">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref014">14</xref>]. NBQX (2,3-dihydroxy-6-nitro-7-sulfamoyl-benzoquinoxaline-2,3-dione) is a competitive AMPA receptor antagonist and has a property that suppressed focal electrographic seizures in epileptic mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref009">9</xref>]. Recently, it was described that NBQX blocks the development of spontaneous recurrent seizures when treatment after neonatal seizures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref015">15</xref>]. Consistently, noncompetitive AMPA antagonist perampanel improved the performance of partial seizures, suggesting a remarkable antiepileptogenic effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref016">16</xref>].</p>
<p>Perineuronal nets (PNNs) are condensed extracellular matrix (ECM) structures, which surround parvalbumin-positive inhibitory interneurons and play a critical role in neuronal cell development, activity and growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref017">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref019">19</xref>]. Chondroitin sulfate proteoglycans (CSPGs) are crucial components of PNNs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref020">20</xref>], which have been suggested to be a critical factor regulating synaptic plasticity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref021">21</xref>]. Aberrant PNN signaling was found to induce the dysfunctions of central nervous system such as epilepsy, stroke, Alzheimer’s disease, schizophrenia and addiction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref022">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref023">23</xref>]. The plant lectins <italic>Wisteria floribunda</italic> agglutinin (<italic>WFA</italic>) can be used to visualize PNNs by binding to N-acetylgalactosamine residue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref024">24</xref>]. Therefore, we use <italic>WFA</italic>-labeled neurons to evaluate the numbers of PNNs in the current investigation. The three major ECM components of PNNs are tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan, which are important contributors to formation and stabilization of PNNs functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref025">25</xref>].</p>
<p>Pentylenetetrazole (PTZ), a g-aminobutyric acid antagonist, is widely used to establish experimental models simulate human epilepsy. PTZ administration increased the glutamatergic transmitter and induced generalized tonic–clonic seizures in animals with higher doses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref027">27</xref>]. In the current study, we used PTZ at the dose of 50 mg/kg (i.p.) to induce chronic seizures to observe the anti-epileptic effect of NBQX and the possible involvement of PNNs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Animals</title>
<p>Male Wistar rats that weighed 220–240 g upon arrival were obtained from the Shandong University Experimental Animal Center and were used for all experiments. Rats were individually housed under constant temperature (23±2°C) and humidity (50±5%) and maintained on a 12-hour light/dark cycle with free food and water available. Rats were monitored daily by an experimenter at 8:00–12:00 am each day for eating, drinking, and activity, which were used for the physical health assessment. There are no animals died before the experimental endpoint. All of the animal procedures were performed in accordance with the National Institutes of Health Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. The protocol of current animal experiments was approved by the Ethics of Animal Experiments of Jinan Central Hospital (Permit Number: SA-2014-008). All surgery was performed under sodium pentobarbital anesthesia, and all efforts were made to minimize suffering in animals. All of the behavioral tests and drug administrations were carried out in the dark phase.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Drugs</title>
<p>AMPAR antagonist 2,3-dihydroxy-6-nitro-7-sulfamoyl-benzoquinoxaline-2,3-dione (NBQX), pentylenetetrazole (PTZ) and chondroitinase ABC (ChABC) were supplied from Sigma-Aldrich Chemical Company (Sigma, St Louis, Missouri, USA). NBQX was freshly dissolved in saline as sodium salt. ChABC were dissolved in 0.1 m PBS (vehicle) for microinjection into the medial prefrontal cortex and prepared in stock solutions of 0.02 U/μl.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Seizures induction and behavioral analysis</title>
<p>Rats were deprived of food but not water 12h before the experiments to prevent aspiration of food. Rats in PTZ group were treated with a single 50 mg/kg intraperitoneal (i.p.) administration of PTZ for 28 days. While rats were injected with saline (i.p.) in control group instead. Behavioral tests and neurochemical analysis were performed on day 29 and 30, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g001">Fig 1A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0166672.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Chronic PTZ treatment reduced PNNs (<italic>WFA</italic>), tenascin-R, aggrecan and Neurocan in the medial prefrontal cortex.</title>
<p>(A) Schemes of experimental schedules. (B) Numbers of <italic>WFA</italic>+ PNNs in mPFC of control and PTZ treatment, scale bar is 50 μm, n = 6 per group. Representative <italic>WFA</italic>+ images of immunofluorescence staining are shown on the right. The data are expressed as mean ± SEM. (C) The levels of tenascin-R, aggrecan and Neurocan in mPFC are shown. Representative Western blot images are shown on the right. The data are expressed as a percentage of the values obtained for the rats treated with saline. *<italic>p &lt;</italic> 0.01, different from corresponding saline groups (<italic>n =</italic> 6).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="pone.0166672.g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>To observe anti-epileptic effects of NBQX in PTZ induced epilepsy, we divided rats into four groups: rats in saline + saline group were treated with saline only; rats in PTZ + saline group were treated with 50 mg/kg of PTZ (i.p.) and saline for 28 days; rats in saline + NBQX group were treated with saline for 28 days, and 20 mg/kg of NBQX (i.p.) for next 3 days; rats in PTZ + NBQX group were treated with 50 mg/kg of PTZ (i.p.) for 28 days and were treated with 20 mg/kg of NBQX (i.p.) for next 3 days. Behavioral tests and neurochemical analysis were performed on the following 2 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g002">Fig 2A</xref>). The doses for PTZ and NBQX were selected regarding to previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref028">28</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pone.0166672.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>NBQX increased PNNs (<italic>WFA</italic>), tenascin-R, aggrecan and Neurocan in the medial prefrontal cortex in PTZ-treated rats.</title>
<p>(A) Schemes of experimental schedules. (B) Numbers of <italic>WFA</italic>+ PNNs in mPFC of control and PTZ treatment, scale bar 50 μm, n = 6 per group. Representative <italic>WFA</italic>+ images of immunofluorescence staining are shown on the right. The data are expressed as mean ± SEM. The levels of (C) tenascin-R, (D) aggrecan and (E) Neurocan in mPFC are shown. Representative Western blot images are shown on the right. The data are expressed as a percentage of the values obtained for the rats treated with saline. *<italic>p &lt;</italic> 0.01, different from corresponding saline groups, # <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, compared with PTZ group (<italic>n =</italic> 6).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="pone.0166672.g002"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>To clarify the effects of degradation of PNNs caused by ChABC in mPFC on the seizures, we used four groups of rats: saline + penicillinase group was treated with saline plus penicillinase into mPFC on d24; saline + ChABC group was treated with saline and microinjection of ChABC (0.01 U/μg/side/0.5 μl) into mPFC on d24; PTZ + penicillinase group was treated with PTZ (50 mg/kg) for 28 days and microinjected with penicillinase on d24; PTZ + ChABC group was treated with PTZ for 28 days and microinjected with ChABC on d24. Behavioral tests and neurochemical analysis were performed on the following 2 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g003">Fig 3A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0166672.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>PNNs (<italic>WFA</italic>) were removed by ChABC microinjection into mPFC.</title>
<p>(A) Schemes of experimental schedules. (B) Numbers of <italic>WFA</italic>+ PNNs in mPFC of control and PTZ treatment, scale bar 50 μm, n = 6 per group. Representative <italic>WFA</italic>+ images of immunofluorescence staining are shown on the right. The data are expressed as mean ± SEM. *<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, compared with saline group; # <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, compared with PTZ group.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="pone.0166672.g003"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>To determine whether PNNs degradation by ChABC can reverse the anti-epileptic effect of NBQX, we injected rats with PTZ for 28 days and separated them into four groups: rats in vehicle group were treated with vehicle without NBQX, and were microinjected with penicillinase into mPFC on d 24; rats in vehicle + ChABC group were treated with vehicle plus microinjection of ChABC into mPFC on d24; rats in NBQX + penicillinase group were treated with penicillinase on d24 and were treated with NBQX injection on d 29 to d31; rats in NBQX + ChABC group were treated with microinjection of ChABC into mPFC on d24 plus NBQX (20 mg/kg, i.p.) on d 29 to d31. Behavioral tests were performed on day 32.</p>
<p>The epileptic seizure activity induced by PTZ was evaluated by latency to seizures (s), duration of the minor seizure onset (s), duration of the major seizure onset (s), and scores for the severity of seizures in 1h after PTZ injection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref028">28</xref>]. The minor seizure onset was termed as isolated myoclonic jerks and clonic seizures accompanied by facial and front extremity muscle clonus. While the major seizure following the minimal seizure are characterized by head, neck, and tail extension with the loss of the tonic flexor reflex and tonic flexion–extension following the protracted clonus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref029">29</xref>]. The scores were used to measure the severity of seizures after PTZ administration according to the following level: 0: no changes in behavior; 1: isolated myolonic jerks; 2: only atypical minimal seizures; 3: minimal seizures; 4: major seizures without a tonic phase; and 5:completed tonic–clonic seizures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref030">30</xref>]. The performance of each rat was recorded by a video camera during the entire experimental procedures. The observers for the measurement of seizure scores were blind to the treatment of each group.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Immunofluorescence and image analysis</title>
<p>After the behavioral measurement, rats were deeply anesthetized with sodium pentobarbital (100 mg/kg, i.p.) and were intracardially perfused with 200–250 ml of 0.1M phosphate-buffered saline, pH 7.4, followed by 200–250 ml of 4% paraformaldehyde phosphate buffer, pH 7.4. The brains were then postfixed at 4°C for 24 h and dehydrated in 30% sucrose for at least 4 days. Serial coronal 30 μm brain sections that contained the medial prefrontal cortex were cut on a Leica freezing microtome and stored in a cryoprotectant solution at -20°C. The sections were incubated overnight at 4°C in a solution of biotin-conjugated lectin <italic>wisteria floribunda</italic> (<italic>WFA</italic>, Sigma Aldrich, L1516). All of the sections were then washed 3 times in PBS and then incubated in FITC-conjugated streptavidin (Sigma-Aldrich, S3762) in 25°C for 3 h. Four or five sections from each brain region of each rat were selected. Fluorescence microscope with an image-analysis program was used for measuring the number of <italic>WFA</italic>-positive PNNs. The average number of PNNs on either side of target brain region was taken as the positive immunoreactive cell number for each rat as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref032">32</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Tissue sample preparation</title>
<p>Rats were killed 30 min after the last administration of PTZ. Their brains were extracted and removed. Subsequently, bilateral tissue punches of the mPFC (16 gauge) were obtained from approximately 1 mm thick coronal sections cut in a Reichert-Jung 2800 Frigocut E cryostat at -20°C. The rostral faces of the coronal sections were approximately 3.8 mm from bregma. Tissue punches were homogenized (10–15 s × 3, 5 s interval) with an electrical disperser (Wiggenhauser, Sdn Bhd) after being lysed with RIPA lysis buffer with protease-inhibitor (Beyotime Biotechnology, Beijing, China) for 30 min. Afterward, the homogenate was subjected to 10,000 × <italic>g</italic> centrifugation at 4°C for 20 min. All of the above procedures were performed under low temperature (0–4°C). The protein concentrations of all samples were determined using the BCA assay kit (Beyotime Biotechnology). The protein concentration was normalized by diluting the samples with RIPA lysis buffer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Western blot assays</title>
<p>Samples were subjected to sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (8% acrylamide/0.27% <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N’</italic>-methylenebisacryalamide resolving gel) for approximately 30 min at 80 V in stacking gel and approximately 1 h at 120 V in resolving gel. Proteins were transferred electrophoretically to Immobilon-P transfer membranes (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA) at 0.25 A for 3 h. Membranes were washed with TBST (Tris-buffered saline plus 0.05% Tween-20, pH 7.4) before dipping in blocking buffer (5% skimmed dry milk in TBST) overnight at 4°C. Membranes were then incubated for 1 h at room temperature with anti-tenascin-R (1:400; Santa Cruz, sc-9875), anti-aggrecan (1:400, Santa Cruz, sc-25674), anti-neurocan (1:1000, Sigma Aldrich, N0913), and anti-β-actin antibody (1:2000, A5316; Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) in TBST plus 5% bovine serum albumin. After the membrane was shaken in 4 × 6 min washes in TBST buffer, the blots were incubated for 45 min at room temperature with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody (goat anti-rabbit or mouse IgG; Santa Cruz Biotechnology and Vector Labs, respectively) diluted 1:5000 in blocking buffer. The blots were then shaken in 4 × 6 min washes in TBST. Afterward, the blots were incubated with a layer of Super Signal enhanced chemiluminescence substrate mixture (Pierce Biotechnology, Rockford, IL, USA) for 1 min at room temperature. Finally, the blots were exposed against X-ray film (Eastman Kodak Company). Band intensities were quantified using Quantity One software (version 4.0.3) from Bio-Rad Corporation (Hercules, CA, USA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Intracerebral cannula implantation and intracranial injections</title>
<p>Rats were anesthetized with sodium pentobarbital (60 mg/kg, i.p.), and guide cannulae (23-gauge, Plastics One, Roanoke, VA, USA) were implanted bilaterally 1 mm above the medial prefrontal cortex with the following stereotaxic coordinates: anterior/posterior (A/P), -3.2 mm; medial/lateral (M/L), ± 2.5 mm; dorsal/ventral (D/V), -3.3 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref033">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref035">35</xref>]. The rats were allowed to recover for at least 7 d before intracranial injections. Vehicle or ChABC (0.01 U/μg/side/0.5 μl) were intracranial microinjected using 10 μl Hamilton syringes (Hamilton, Reno, NV, USA) connected via polyethylene-50 tubing to 30-gauge injectors (Plastics One) into the mPFC. The dose of ChABC was used as previously evidenced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref031">31</xref>]. A total volume of 0.5 μl was infused into each side over 1 min, and the injection syringe was left in place for an additional 1 min to allow for diffusion. At the end of the behavioral tests, the rats were anesthetized with sodium pentobarbital (100 mg/kg, i.p.) and transcardially perfused. Cannula placements were assessed using Nissl staining with a thickness of 30 μm under a light microscope to determine the infusion site. Subjects with misplaced cannulae were excluded from the statistical analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The data are expressed as mean ± SEM and were analyzed using one- or two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey’s <italic>post hoc</italic> test (for details, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec011">Results</xref> section). In the two-way ANOVA tests, two factors are involved: 1. PTZ and saline groups, 2. NBQX and saline, or ChABC and vehicle treatment. Values of P &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>The behavioral patterns of epileptic seizures induced by PTZ</title>
<p>Chronic PTZ treatment induced significant changes on latency to seizures, duration of the minor seizure onset, duration of the major seizure onset, and scores for the severity of seizures in rats. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0166672.t001">Table 1</xref>, rats in saline group produced a longer latency (600 s) to seizures than those in PTZ group (102.9 ± 6.5 s, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Additionally, PTZ treatment also induced an increase in the duration of both minor seizure onset (65.1 ± 4.4 s <italic>vs</italic> 0 s, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and major seizure onset (117.8±12.9 s <italic>vs</italic> 0 s, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) compared with saline group, respectively. Similarly, the scores for the severity of seizures were increased by PTZ injection (4.6 ± 0.26). These data suggest that rats chronically treated with PTZ exhibited a marked phenotype of epilepsy model.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0166672.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>PTZ induced significant changes on latency to seizures (s), duration of the minor seizure onset (s), duration of the major seizure onset (s), and scores for the severity of seizures in rats.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0166672.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0166672.t001"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Saline</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTZ</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Latency to seizure (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102.9±6.5</td>
<td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the minor seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.1±4.4</td>
<td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the major seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117.8±12.9</td>
<td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scores for the severity of seizures</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6±0.26</td>
<td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Chronic PTZ treatment reduced WFA, tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan in mPFC</title>
<p>After behavioral analysis, rats were killed and their brains were collected for the following assay for PNNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g001">Fig 1A</xref>). The data from immunofluorescence staining showed that PTZ significantly decreased the number of <italic>WFA</italic>+ PNNs in mPFC compared to saline-treated rats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g001">Fig 1B</xref>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Furthermore, Western blot assay revealed that the levels of three components of PNNs, tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g001">Fig 1C</xref>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) were also reduced in PTZ group compared with saline group, suggesting that the PNNs was impaired by chronic PTZ administration.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX decreased seizures induced by PTZ</title>
<p>Next, we aimed to identify the effect of AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX on the onset of epileptic seizures induced by PTZ. Data from behavioral tests in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0166672.t002">Table 2</xref> showed that the decreased latency to seizure induced by PTZ was increased by NBQX treatment (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Moreover, the increases in duration of the minor seizure onset (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), duration of the major seizure onset (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and the scores for the severity of seizures (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) in PTZ group were completely reduced by NBQX injection. Two-way ANOVA with the between-subjects factors PTZ (0 and 50 mg/kg) and NBQX (0 and 20 mg/kg) revealed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 94.5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 16.5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) on the latency to seizure and a PTZ × NBQX interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 16.5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). In the duration of the minor seizure onset measurement, two-way ANOVA revealed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 163.1, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 13.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and a PTZ × NBQX interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 13.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). In consistent, two-way ANOVA revealed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 234.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 18.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and a PTZ × NBQX interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 18.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) on the duration of the major seizure onset. Two-way ANOVA also showed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 108.8, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 21.5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and a PTZ × NBQX interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 21.5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) on the scores for the severity of seizures. These results indicate that treatment with AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX effectively reversed the behavioral abnormality of epileptic seizures of chronic PTZ administration in rats.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0166672.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<title>NBQX decreased seizures induced by PTZ on latency to seizure (s), duration of the minor seizure onset (s), duration of the major seizure onset (s), and scores for the severity of seizures in rats.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0166672.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0166672.t002"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Saline</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Saline+NBQX</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTZ</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTZ+NBQX</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Latency to seizure (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108.3±8.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178.6±15.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the minor seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.6±6.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.0±5.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the major seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122.0±10.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.1±6.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scores for the severity of seizures</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5±0.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9±0.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001">
<p>* p&lt;0.01, compared with saline group;</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t002fn002">
<p><sup>#</sup> p&lt;0.01, compared with PTZ group.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>NBQX normalized WFA, tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan in mPFC</title>
<p>We further assessed the effects of NBQX on the PNNs in the medial prefrontal cortex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g002">Fig 2A</xref>). Rats exposed to NBQX produced a significant increase in the positive staining of <italic>WFA</italic>-labeled neurons, which was reduced by chronic PTZ treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g002">Fig 2B</xref>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Two-way ANOVA analysis showed that significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,20 = 33.1, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,20 = 9.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and a PTZ × NBQX interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,20 = 6.2, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) on the <italic>WFA</italic> positive stainings. We also measured the three important components of PNNs and found that the reductions of tenascin-R (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), aggrecan (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and neurocan (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) in mPFC of PTZ group were increased by NBQX treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g002">Fig 2C–2E</xref>). The results suggest that the anti-epileptic action of NBQX might be through prevention of the reduction of PNNs by increasing the active components tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>The degradation of PNNs caused by ChABC in mPFC exacerbated seizures</title>
<p>To further examine the regulatory role of PNNs in the development and treatment of epileptic seizures, we used ChABC to degrade PNNs in the mPFC and subsequently measured the behavioral patterns in PTZ-treated rats. ChABC microinjection into mPFC decreased PNNs (<italic>WFA</italic>), and co-treatment with PTZ strengthened this decrease (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0166672.g003">Fig 3A and 3B</xref>). The behavioral results showed that intra-mPFC injection of ChABC alone did induce the onset of seizures with decreased latency to seizure (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), increased duration of the minor (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and major seizure onset (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and increased scores for the severity of seizures (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) in rats (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0166672.t003">Table 3</xref>). Moreover, when ChABC and PTZ were treated simultaneously to one rat, the onset of seizures was more serious than those two drugs were used alone (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0166672.t003">Table 3</xref>). Two-way ANOVA with the between-subjects factors PTZ (0 and 50 mg/kg) and ChABC (0 and 0.02 U) revealed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 78.1, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 23.1, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) on the latency to seizure and a PTZ × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 6.5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the duration of the minor seizure onset measurement, two-way ANOVA revealed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 31.8, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 18.2, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and a PTZ × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 7.4, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). In consistent, two-way ANOVA revealed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 52.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 23.7, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and a PTZ × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 4.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) on the duration of the major seizure onset. Two-way ANOVA also showed significant effects of PTZ (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 66.7, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 51.8, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and a PTZ × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 5.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) on the scores for the severity of seizures. These results revealed that degradation of PNNs in the mPFC exacerbated the epileptic seizure induced by PTZ, suggesting that the dysfunction of PNNs might be involved in the induction of epilepsy.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0166672.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<title>ChABC exacerbated the epileptic seizure induced by PTZ.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0166672.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0166672.t003"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Saline+penicillinase</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Saline+ChABC</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTZ+penicillinase</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTZ+ChABC</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Latency to seizure (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">506.9±25.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110.5±6.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.1±9.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the minor seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.5±1.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.9±5.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.0±3.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the major seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.4±2.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123.6±10.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167.6±7.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scores for the severity of seizures</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6±0.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1±0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001">
<p>* p&lt;0.01, compared with saline group;</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t003fn002">
<p><sup>#</sup> p&lt;0.01, compared with PTZ group.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>ChABC reversed the anti-epileptic effects of NBQX in PTZ-induced seizures</title>
<p>We next examined the potential of degradation of PNNs on the anti-epileptic effects of NBQX in PTZ-induced seizures. ChABC, NBQX and their vehicles were injected into four groups of rats after receiving PTZ treatment. Two-way ANOVA with the between-subjects factors NBQX (0 and 20 mg/kg) and ChABC (0 and 0.02 U) revealed significant effects of NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 30.3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 14.2, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) on the latency to seizure and a NBQX × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 6.7, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the duration of the minor seizure onset measurement, two-way ANOVA revealed significant effects of NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 47.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 29.5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and a NBQX × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 7.1, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). In consistent, two-way ANOVA revealed significant effects of NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 16.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 8.3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and a NBQX × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 5.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) on the duration of the major seizure onset. Two-way ANOVA also showed significant effects of NBQX (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 20.8, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and ChABC (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 10.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and a NBQX × ChABC interaction (<italic>F</italic>1,28 = 5.1, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) on the scores for the severity of seizures. NBQX significantly increased the latency to seizures, and decreased the duration of the minor seizure onset, the duration of the major seizure onset, and the scores for the severity of seizures (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0166672.t004">Table 4</xref>). However, ChABC blocked the anti-epileptic effects of NBQX in PTZ-induced seizures, suggesting that normalization of PNNs in the medial prefrontal cortex might underlie the therapeutic action of NBQX.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0166672.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166672.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label>
<caption>
<title>ChABC reversed the anti-epileptic effects of NBQX in PTZ-induced seizures.</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0166672.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0166672.t004"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vehicle+penicillinase</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vehicle+ChABC</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NBQX+penicillinase</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NBQX+ChABC</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Latency to seizure (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109.3±6.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.1±4.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">184.6±14.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125.4±8.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the minor seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.6±4.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.1±1.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.6±3.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.6±3.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of the major seizure onset (s)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121.0±8.7</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133.9±8.2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.9±7.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111.5±6.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scores for the severity of seizures</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3±0.16</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6±0.18</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1±0.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0±0.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">#</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001">
<p>* p&lt;0.01, compared with saline group;</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t004fn002">
<p><sup>#</sup> p&lt;0.01, compared with PTZ group.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study showed that chronic PTZ treatment induced significant changes of seizures in rats by reducing PNNs (<italic>WFA</italic>) numbers, and the components tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan in mPFC. However, AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX decreased the onset of seizures through increasing PNNS in mPFC. Moreover, degradation of PNNs by ChABC in mPFC exacerbated seizures and reversed the anti-epileptic effects of NBQX in PTZ-treated rats. Thus, the present findings demonstrate the regulatory role of PNNs in mPFC on the development and treatment of epilepsy. The deficits of PNNs measured by reduced <italic>WFA</italic> numbers and decreased tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan protein levels might be related to the pathophysiology of epilepsy induced by PTZ.</p>
<p>The critical roles of the AMPA receptors in epileptic seizures and anti-epileptic treatment have been previously demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref036">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref037">37</xref>]. Several selective AMPA receptor antagonists were demonstrated to have broad spectrum anticonvulsant activity in sound-induced seizures in rats and in amygdala-kindled rats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref038">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref039">39</xref>]. Similarly, a decrease of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0197018615000728#200024272">phosphorylated</ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0197018615000728#200017246">AMPA</ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0197018615000728#200005770">glutamate receptor</ext-link> subunit (GluA1) was found in the dorsal hippocampus of rats after chronic pilocarpine treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref040">40</xref>]. In addition, AMPA receptor antagonists were widely found to be safe and effective in patients with partial-onset seizures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref041">41</xref>], raising a possibility that AMPA receptor can be a novel target for epilepsy therapy. NBQX, a potent and selective AMPA receptor antagonist, produced effective anticonvulsant protection against sound-induced seizures in mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref042">42</xref>]. Furthermore, systematic administration with NBQX at the dose of 10–40 mg/kg exhibited strong antiepileptogenic and anticonvulsant actions on kindling in rats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref043">43</xref>]. In the present study, we used PTZ to induce chronic epileptic seizures in rats and found that NBQX effectively reversed the behavioral abnormality of epileptic seizures. However, NBQX (40 mg/kg, ip) effectively increased latency to seizures, decreased duration of the minor and major seizure onset, and reduced scores for the severity of seizures in rats. AMPA receptors, located at excitatory synapses, are involved in the initiation and synchronization of epileptic discharges by excitatory neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref044">44</xref>]. Therefore, selective blockade of AMPA receptor-related glutamatergic neurotransmission may inhibit neuronal excitability and produce antiepileptic properties in chronic epilepsy.</p>
<p>PNNs inhibit structural rearrangements at synapses, and consequently contribute to the maintenance of neuronal networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref045">45</xref>]. PNN-expressing perisomatic interneurons also express AMPA receptors with specific subunits. The excitatory postsynaptic currents (EPSC) are extremely fast and are mediated by AMPA receptors, thus enabling interneurons to detect and shape synchronous activity of principal cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref046">46</xref>]. It has been evidenced that the charge of the synaptic membrane shapes the AMPAR-mediated current by influencing the clearance of the negatively charged glutamate from the synapse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref047">47</xref>]. The structural and molecular organization of PNNs is heterogeneous and depends on the neuronal cell types consisting of tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan that enwraps the perikaryon of several neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref048">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref049">49</xref>]. PNNs dysfunction has been implicated in several neuropsychiatric disorders, including epilepsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref050">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref051">51</xref>]. Brain-specific CSPG includs aggrecan and neurocan in the developing and mature rat brain and has been demonstrated to control axonal extension or regeneration via inhibition of neuronal cell migration and neurite extension from surviving neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref052">52</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref054">54</xref>]. Tenascin-R, a member of the tenascin gene family of extracellular matrix proteins, is synthesized by oligodendrocytes with high expression levels during the period of active myelination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref055">55</xref>]. It has been demonstrated that tenascin-R is associated with an episode of pilocarpine-induced status epilepticus through modulation of mossy fiber sprouting and astrogliosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref054">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref056">56</xref>]. Furthermore, systemic administration of kainic acid (KA) caused changes in neurocan leading to neuronal degeneration in the limbic structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref051">51</xref>]. We found that PTZ destroyed PNNs in mPFC with epileptic behaviors, while NBQX increased PNNs (<italic>WFA</italic>), tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan and exerted anti-epileptic effects. Our results confirmed previous evidence that prolonged changes in tenascin-R and neurocan in the remodeling of neuronal networks are related to establishment or enhancement of epileptogenesis. This data revealed a relationship between PNNs and epilepsy, and suggested that modulation of PNNs in critical brain region will provide novel therapeutic approaches for epilepsy.</p>
<p>A recent investigation suggested that chondroitin sulfate-degrading enzyme ChABC enhanced the lateral mobility of the AMPA receptor, and consequently promote short-term synaptic plasticity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref057">57</xref>]. ChABC may degrade various PNNs components, and consequently destroy the PNNs structure. In the current study, pretreatment with ChABC blocked the anti-epileptic effects of NBQX in PTZ-induced seizures, suggesting that normalization of PNNs in mPFC might underlie the therapeutic action of AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX. Further study is needed to evaluate the effect of upregulation of PNNs in the mPFC on the epilepsy induced by PTZ and on the treatment benefits of NBQX. The finding that the fast movements of AMPA receptors are involved in the modulation of synaptic transmission suggests that AMPAR mobility regulates the availability of naive receptors for synapses. Previous studies showed that removal of the PNNs leads to an increase of AMPAR exchange between extrasynaptic and synaptic sites, and may modulate synaptic properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0166672.ref057">57</xref>]. Our results revealed that chronic epilepsy induced a reduction of components of PNNs, tenascin-R, aggrecan and neurocan in mPFC, while AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX increased the levels of these proteins, suggesting that PNNs might be essential for the functionality of synaptic transmission. Thus, future studies targeting at PNNs can shed light on development of novel antiepileptic drugs with good efficacy and acceptable tolerability for therapy in epilepsy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In summary, the present data showed that AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX decreased the onset of epileptic seizures induced by PTZ through regulation of PNNs in the medial prefrontal cortex. Degradation of PNNs caused by ChABC in mPFC not only exacerbated seizures but also reversed the anti-epileptic effect of NBQX in PTZ-treated rats. These findings therefore revealed that PNNs in the medial prefrontal cortex is related to the anti-epileptic effect of NBQX and enhancement of PNNs may be effective for the treatment of epilepsy.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref001">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overview of drugs used for epilepsy and seizures: etiology, diagnosis, and treatment</article-title>. <source/>P T. <year>2010</year>;<volume>35</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref002">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ngugi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kariuki</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bottomley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kleinschmidt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Incidence of epilepsy: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/>Neurology. <year>2011</year>;<volume>77</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1005</fpage>–<lpage>1012</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e31822cfc90</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21893672</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref003">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berkovic</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchhalter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Emde Boas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Revised terminology and concepts for organization of seizures and epilepsies: report of the ILAE Commission on Classification and Terminology, 2005–2009</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia. <year>2010</year>;<volume>51</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2010.02522.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20196795</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref004">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rogawski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loscher</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>The neurobiology of antiepileptic drugs</article-title>. <source/>Nat Rev Neurosci. <year>2004</year>;<volume>5</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn1430</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref005">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collingridge</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Excitatory amino acid receptors in the vertebrate central nervous system</article-title>. <source/>Pharmacol Rev. <year>1989</year>;<volume>41</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2558391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref006">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dell'Acqua</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>AKAP signaling complexes in regulation of excitatory synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source/>Neuroscientist. <year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073858410384740</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21498812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref007">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Szczurowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>NMDA and AMPA receptors: development and status epilepticus</article-title>. <source/>Physiol Res. <year>2013</year>;<volume>62</volume>
<issue>Suppl 1</issue>: <fpage>S21</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24329701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref008">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kasteleijn-Nolst Trenite</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenow</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinhoff</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Dose-dependent suppression of human photoparoxysmal response with the competitive AMPA/kainate receptor antagonist BGG492: Clear PK/PD relationship</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia. <year>2015</year>;<volume>56</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>924</fpage>–<lpage>932</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.13008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25963722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref009">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Twele</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bankstahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romermann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loscher</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>The AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX exerts anti-seizure but not antiepileptogenic effects in the intrahippocampal kainate mouse model of mesial temporal lobe epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Neuropharmacology. <year>2015</year>;<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2015.03.014</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25839899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref010">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashizume</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tokuhara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takenaka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohmura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Perampanel: a novel, orally active, noncompetitive AMPA-receptor antagonist that reduces seizure activity in rodent models of epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia. <year>2011</year>;<volume>52</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1331</fpage>–<lpage>1340</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2011.03109.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21635236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref011">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rogawski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Preclinical pharmacology of perampanel, a selective non-competitive AMPA receptor antagonist</article-title>. <source/>Acta Neurol Scand Suppl. <year>2013</year>;(<issue>197</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ane.12100</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref012">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Biton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Squillacote</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurenza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Adjunctive perampanel for refractory partial-onset seizures: randomized phase III study 304</article-title>. <source/>Neurology. <year>2012</year>;<volume>79</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e3182635735</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22843280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref013">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinhoff</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Squillacote</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Evaluation of adjunctive perampanel in patients with refractory partial-onset seizures: results of randomized global phase III study 305</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia. <year>2013</year>;<volume>54</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2012.03638.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22905857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref014">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kerling</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Efficacy of perampanel: a review of clinical trial data</article-title>. <source/>Acta Neurol Scand Suppl. <year>2013</year>;(<issue>197</issue>): <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ane.12101</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref015">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lippman-Bell</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rakhade</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obeid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>AMPA receptor antagonist NBQX attenuates later-life epileptic seizures and autistic-like social deficits following neonatal seizures</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia. <year>2013</year>;<volume>54</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1922</fpage>–<lpage>1932</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.12378</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24117347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref016">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Loscher</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Epilepsy: perampanel-new promise for refractory epilepsy?</article-title>
<source/>Nat Rev Neurol. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume> (<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2012.222</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23147851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref017">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Balmer</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carels</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frisch</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nick</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modulation of perineuronal nets and parvalbumin with developmental song learning</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci. <year>2009</year>;<volume>29</volume> (<issue>41</issue>): <fpage>12878</fpage>–<lpage>12885</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2974-09.2009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref018">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pizzorusso</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berardi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chierzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reactivation of ocular dominance plasticity in the adult visual cortex</article-title>. <source/>Science. <year>2002</year>;<volume>298</volume> (<issue>5596</issue>): <fpage>1248</fpage>–<lpage>1251</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1072699</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12424383</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref019">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Celio</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spreafico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Biasi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vitellaro-Zuccarello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Perineuronal nets: past and present</article-title>. <source/>Trends Neurosci. <year>1998</year>;<volume>21</volume> (<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>510</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9881847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref020">
<label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galtrey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carulli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Distribution and synthesis of extracellular matrix proteoglycans, hyaluronan, link proteins and tenascin-R in the rat spinal cord</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Neurosci. <year>2008</year>;<volume>27</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1373</fpage>–<lpage>1390</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2008.06108.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18364019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref021">
<label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bavelier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hensch</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Removing brakes on adult brain plasticity: from molecular to behavioral interventions</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci. <year>2010</year>;<volume>30</volume> (<issue>45</issue>): <fpage>14964</fpage>–<lpage>14971</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4812-10.2010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21068299</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref022">
<label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morawski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Filippov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tzinia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsilibary</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vargova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>ECM in brain aging and dementia</article-title>. <source/>Prog Brain Res. <year>2014</year>;<volume>214</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-63486-3.00010-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25410360</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref023">
<label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morawski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dityatev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartlage-Rubsamen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blosa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flach</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Tenascin-R promotes assembly of the extracellular matrix of perineuronal nets via clustering of aggrecan</article-title>. <source/>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. <year>2014</year>;<volume>369</volume> (<issue>1654</issue>): <fpage>20140046</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2014.0046</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25225104</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref024">
<label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luth</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Winkelmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Distribution patterns of Wisteria floribunda agglutinin binding sites and parvalbumin-immunoreactive neurons in the human visual cortex: a double-labelling study</article-title>. <source/>J Hirnforsch. <year>1996</year>;<volume>37</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8872558</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref025">
<label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dityatev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruckner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dityateva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grosche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kleene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schachner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Activity-dependent formation and functions of chondroitin sulfate-rich extracellular matrix of perineuronal nets</article-title>. <source/>Dev Neurobiol. <year>2007</year>;<volume>67</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dneu.20361</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17443809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref026">
<label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schroder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lossner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Glutamate binding to brain membranes is increased in pentylenetetrazole-kindled rats</article-title>. <source/>J Neurochem. <year>1993</year>;<volume>60</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1007</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8094739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref027">
<label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ackermann</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maidment</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Pentylenetetrazol-induced kindling: early involvement of excitatory and inhibitory systems</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsy Res. <year>1996</year>;<volume>26</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8985692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref028">
<label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Erdogan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ekici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kesici</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aslan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>The protective effects of endothelin-A receptor antagonist BQ-123 in pentylenetetrazole-induced seizure in rats</article-title>. <source/>Hum Exp Toxicol. <year>2014</year>;<volume>33</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1008</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0960327113520017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref029">
<label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mirvaldova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Belska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Influence of a new antiepileptic drug ORG 6370 on metrazol-induced seizures in rats during ontogenesis</article-title>. <source/>Physiol Bohemoslov. <year>1990</year>;<volume>39</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2145597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref030">
<label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Velisek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stankova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schickerova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pentylenetetrazol-induced seizures in rats: an ontogenetic study</article-title>. <source/>Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch Pharmacol. <year>1992</year>;<volume>346</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1470230</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref031">
<label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Depletion of perineuronal nets in the amygdala to enhance the erasure of drug memories</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci. <year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume> (<issue>19</issue>): <fpage>6647</fpage>–<lpage>6658</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5390-13.2014</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24806690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref032">
<label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gogolla</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caroni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luthi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Perineuronal nets protect fear memories from erasure</article-title>. <source/>Science. <year>2009</year>;<volume>325</volume> (<issue>5945</issue>): <fpage>1258</fpage>–<lpage>1261</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1174146</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19729657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref033">
<label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terzian</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guimaraes</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Anxiolytic-like effects induced by blockade of transient receptor potential vanilloid type 1 (TRPV1) channels in the medial prefrontal cortex of rats</article-title>. <source/>Psychopharmacology (Berl). <year>2009</year>;<volume>205</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19387617</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref034">
<label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paxinos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>. <article-title>AChE-stained horizontal sections of the rat brain in stereotaxic coordinates</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci Methods. <year>1980</year>;<volume>3</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6110810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref035">
<label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Glycine site N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor antagonist 7-CTKA produces rapid antidepressant-like effects in male rats</article-title>. <source/>J Psychiatry Neurosci. <year>2013</year>;<volume>38</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/jpn.120228</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23611177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref036">
<label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rogawski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Revisiting AMPA receptors as an antiepileptic drug target</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsy Curr. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5698/1535-7511-11.2.56</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21686307</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref037">
<label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rogawski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>AMPA receptors as a molecular target in epilepsy therapy</article-title>. <source/>Acta Neurol Scand Suppl. <year>2013</year>;(<issue>197</issue>): <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ane.12099</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480151</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref038">
<label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durmuller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meldrum</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The non-N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor antagonists, GYKI 52466 and NBQX are anticonvulsant in two animal models of reflex epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Pharmacol. <year>1991</year>;<volume>201</volume> (<issue>2–3</issue>): <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1686756</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref039">
<label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Durmuller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Craggs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meldrum</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effect of the non-NMDA receptor antagonist GYKI 52466 and NBQX and the competitive NMDA receptor antagonist D-CPPene on the development of amygdala kindling and on amygdala-kindled seizures</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsy Res. <year>1994</year>;<volume>17</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8194512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref040">
<label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Region-specific alterations of AMPA receptor phosphorylation and signaling pathways in the pilocarpine model of epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Neurochem Int. <year>2015</year>;<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2015.05.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25983036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref041">
<label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Serratosa</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Endziniene</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>French</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Randomized phase III study 306: adjunctive perampanel for refractory partial-onset seizures</article-title>. <source/>Neurology. <year>2012</year>;<volume>78</volume> (<issue>18</issue>): <fpage>1408</fpage>–<lpage>1415</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e318254473a</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref042">
<label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meldrum</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The anticonvulsant effect of the non-NMDA antagonists, NBQX and GYKI 52466, in mice</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsy Res. <year>1991</year>;<volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1794356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref043">
<label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antiepileptogenic and anticonvulsant effects of NBQX, a selective AMPA receptor antagonist, in the rat kindling model of epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Brain Res. <year>1994</year>;<volume>638</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8199874</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref044">
<label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>El Desoky</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>. <article-title>The AMPA receptor antagonist perampanel is a new hope in the treatment for epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Fundam Clin Pharmacol. <year>2014</year>;<volume>28</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/fcp.12081</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24750493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref045">
<label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Celio</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blumcke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Perineuronal nets—a specialized form of extracellular matrix in the adult nervous system</article-title>. <source/>Brain Res Brain Res Rev. <year>1994</year>;<volume>19</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8167657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref046">
<label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lubke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frotscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Submillisecond AMPA receptor-mediated signaling at a principal neuron-interneuron synapse</article-title>. <source/>Neuron. <year>1997</year>;<volume>18</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1023</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9208867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref047">
<label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sylantyev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Savtchenko</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kullmann</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Electric fields due to synaptic currents sharpen excitatory transmission</article-title>. <source/>Science. <year>2008</year>;<volume>319</volume> (<issue>5871</issue>): <fpage>1845</fpage>–<lpage>1849</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1154330</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18369150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref048">
<label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zerillo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tiemeyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hockfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Aggrecan glycoforms contribute to the molecular heterogeneity of perineuronal nets</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci. <year>2002</year>;<volume>22</volume> (<issue>17</issue>): <fpage>7536</fpage>–<lpage>7547</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12196577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref049">
<label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lecticans: organizers of the brain extracellular matrix</article-title>. <source/>Cell Mol Life Sci. <year>2000</year>;<volume>57</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00000690</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref050">
<label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yutsudo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Involvement of chondroitin 6-sulfation in temporal lobe epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Exp Neurol. <year>2015</year>;<volume>274</volume> (<issue>Pt B</issue>): <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.expneurol.2015.07.009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26231575</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref051">
<label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakiyama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kurazono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Kainic acid-induced convulsions cause prolonged changes in the chondroitin sulfate proteoglycans neurocan and phosphacan in the limbic structures</article-title>. <source/>Exp Neurol. <year>2003</year>;<volume>184</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14637091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref052">
<label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chondroitin sulfate proteoglycan expression pattern in hippocampal development: potential regulation of axon tract formation</article-title>. <source/>J Comp Neurol. <year>2000</year>;<volume>424</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>546</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10906718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref053">
<label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katoh-Semba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oohira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Two types of brain chondroitin sulfate proteoglycan: their distribution and possible functions in the rat embryo</article-title>. <source/>Neurosci Res. <year>1998</year>;<volume>31</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9809586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref054">
<label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brenneke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schachner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elger</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lie</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Up-regulation of the extracellular matrix glycoprotein tenascin-R during axonal reorganization and astrogliosis in the adult rat hippocampus</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsy Res. <year>2004</year>;<volume>58</volume> (<issue>2–3</issue>): <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2004.01.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15120744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref055">
<label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wintergerst</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fuss</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bartsch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Localization of janusin mRNA in the central nervous system of the developing and adult mouse</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Neurosci. <year>1993</year>;<volume>5</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8261110</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref056">
<label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schachner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bartsch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pesheva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The perplexing multifunctionality of janusin, a tenascin-related molecule</article-title>. <source/>Perspect Dev Neurobiol. <year>1994</year>;<volume>2</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7530142</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0166672.ref057">
<label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frischknecht</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perrais</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seidenbecher</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choquet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gundelfinger</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain extracellular matrix affects AMPA receptor lateral mobility and short-term synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source/>Nat Neurosci. <year>2009</year>;<volume>12</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>897</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2338</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19483686</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>