<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="case-report" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Pediatr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J Pediatr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJP</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Korean Journal of Pediatrics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1738-1061</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2092-7258</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>The Korean Pediatric Society</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28018443</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5177709</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3345/kjp.2016.59.11.S41</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Maternal 3-methylcrotonyl-coenzyme A carboxylase deficiency with elevated 3-hydroxyisovalerylcarnitine in breast milk</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>Kyung Lae</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>Yeo Jin</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Song Hyun</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>Gu-Hwan</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Jun Hwa</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>M</degrees>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, Samsung Changwon Hospital, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Changwon, Korea.</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Green Cross Reference Laboratory, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Medical Genetics Center, Asan Medical Center Children's Hospital, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp>Corresponding author: Jun Hwa Lee, MD, PhD. Department of Pediatrics, Samsung Changwon Hospital, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, 158 Paryong-ro, Masanhoewon-gu, Changwon 51353, Korea. Tel: +82-55-290-6140, Fax: +82-55-290-6044, <email>ljh3643@hanmail.net</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>30</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>59</volume>
<issue>Suppl 1</issue>
<fpage>S41</fpage>
<lpage>S44</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>27</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>07</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 by The Korean Pediatric Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We report here a case of maternal 3-methylcrotonyl-coenzyme A carboxylase (3-MCC) deficiency in a Korean woman. Her 2 infants had elevated 3-hydroxyisovalerylcarnitine (C5-OH) on a neonatal screening test by liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS), but normal results were found on urine organic acid analysis. The patient was subjected to serial testing and we confirmed a maternal 3-MCC deficiency by blood spot and breast milk spot test by LC-MS/MS, serum amino acid analysis, urine organic acid and molecular genetic analysis that found c.838G&gt;T (p.Asp280Tyr) homozygous mutation within exon 9 of the MCCB gene. Especially, we confirmed marked higher levels of C5-OH on breast milk spot by LC-MS/MS, in the case of maternal 3-MCC deficiency vs. controls.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>3-MCC deficiency</kwd>
<kwd>3-Hydroxyisovalerylcarnitine</kwd>
<kwd>Breast milk</kwd>
<kwd>Korean</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>3-Methylcrotonyl-coenzyme A carboxylase (3-MCC) deficiency is an autosomal recessive disorder of leucine metabolism<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1)</xref>. It is detected in 1 out of 36,000 births, globally<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3)</xref>. With the expansion of newborn screening programs 3-MCC deficiency has become one of the most commonly diagnosed inborn error metabolisms. This has allowed the identification of asymptomatic mothers, who previously would have been undiagnosed for the disease<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4)</xref>. If babies are higher than normal levels of 3-hydroxyisovalerylcarnitine (C5-OH) that is the diagnostic marker for 3-MCC deficiency in normal infants of mothers with 3-MCC deficiency, has been designated maternal 3-MCC deficiency<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5)</xref>. We have reported a case of maternal 3-MCC deficiency in which both her infants were noted to have elevated C5-OH on newborn screening tests, and with normal results on metabolic work up including urine organic acid analysis. We confirmed the diagnosis of maternal 3-MCC deficiency by blood spot and breast milk spot test by liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS), urine organic acid analysis and molecular genetic analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Case report</title>
<p>A 15-day-old male with breastfeeding was transferred to the outpatient department due to increased C5-OH detected by LC-MS/MS. His C5-OH levels had been 6.96 µmol/L (reference range, &lt;0.7 µmol/L) at 3 days old, and were 6.02 at 15 days old. His medical history included a normal vaginal delivery at 39 weeks, with a birth weight of 3.120 g. Family history revealed an elder sister who had had increased C5-OH levels of 4.32 µmol/L (reference range, &lt;0.65 µmol/L) at 3 days and 3.67 µmol/L at 7 days old, with nonspecific results on urine organic acid and serum amino acids analysis. A metabolic work up, including a blood spot test by LC-MS/MS, urine organic and serum amino acids analysis, revealed nonspecific results in the 15-day-old male infant. Also, his elder sister at 24 months revealed normal result of C5-OH levels by LC-MS/MS. Maternal 3-MCC deficiency was suspected, and a full metabolic work up was evaluated. The results revealed that maternal serum ammonia, uric acid, lactate and pyruvic acid were within the normal ranges, but the total carnitine, free carnitine and acylcarnitine levels were at 7.96 µmol/L (reference range, 28.00–84.00 µmol/L), 4.14 µmol/L (reference range, 24.00–66.00 µmol/L) and 3.80 µmol/L (reference range, 4.00–32.00 µmol/L), respectively. High C5-OH levels were observed on the maternal dried blood spot by LC-MS/MS, and high levels of excreted 3-hydroxyisovaleric acid (147.9 mmol/mol Cr; reference range, 6.9–25.0) and 3-methylcrotonylglycine (209.4 mmol/mol Cr; reference range, not detectable) were found by the urine organic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
<p>The C5-OH levels in a dried breast milk spot were especially analyzed by LC-MS/MS. For analysis, dried breast milk spot samples were collected from the infant's mother, and 10 age-matched control mothers. The breast milk spots were prepared as follows: 4 spots were made (volume, 0.05 mL/spot) by dripping (diameter, 1.3 cm/spot), and were dried for 3 hours at room temperature in light protected conditions; breast milks spots were punched out into a 96-well plate, and were quantitated by LC-MS/MS with an API-2000 connected to an Agilent 1100 LC system (AB SCIEX, Toronto, Canada). The results revealed that the maternal breast milk spot contained 27.8 fold higher C5-OH levels than the mean control level (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>The <italic>MCCA</italic> and <italic>MCCB</italic> genes were sequenced for confirmation of mutation. For sequencing, the coding regions of the <italic>MCCA</italic> and <italic>MCCB</italic> genes were first amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) from the maternal genomic DNA. The PCR products were the sequenced using the BigDye Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing kit (Applied biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA), according to the manufacturer's instructions, and analysis was performed using the ABI3130x1 Genetic Analyzer (Applied biosystems). A c.838G&gt;T (p.Asp280Tyr) homozygous mutation within exon 9 of the MCCB gene was found by the gene mutation analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). No mutation within the <italic>MCCA</italic> gene was observed. Therefore, asymptomatic maternal 3-MCC deficiency was confirmed. The patient is currently receiving carnitine supplemental treatment.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>3-MCC deficiency is an autosomal recessive disorder of leucine metabolism. It is caused by mutation in the <italic>MCCA</italic> or <italic>MCCB</italic> gene coding for α and β subunit, respectively. The phenotype is highly variable ranging from asymptomatic adults to acute neonatal onset with fatal outcome. Grunert et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1)</xref> reported that of the 53 cases identified by newborn screening, 5 asymptomatic patients presented with acute metabolic decompensations later. However, neither the genotype nor the biochemical phenotype was helpful in predicting the clinical course. The most common laboratory findings were ketoacidosis and hypoglycemia. The clinical symptoms were variable such as vomiting, encephalopathy with impaired consciousness, seizure, metabolic stroke, hemiparesis, cerebral edema, muscular hypotonia, muscle weakness, muscle pain, failure to thrive, mental retardation, attention deficit hyperactivity disorders, Reye syndrome and Autism Spectrum disorders<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6)</xref>. Maternal 3-MCC deficiency may be found by screening for positive normal neonates who have abnormal C5-OH levels. Persistent elevation in C5-OH in the non 3-MCC deficiency neonate could result from placental transfer of C5-OH, C5-OH transfer via the breast milk, and additionally, due to inefficient clearance mechanisms for the metabolite, early in postnatal development<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7)</xref>. According to a national survey of extended newborn screening by LC-MS/MS in Taiwan, the overall incidence of inborn error metabolism was approximately 1 per 6,219. The number of cases screened for C5-OH was 592,717, and of these, 4 cases of maternal 3-MCC deficiency were detected<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8)</xref>. A single case of maternal 3-MCC deficiency was found among 12,952 cord blood samples in the north of England<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9)</xref>. Therefore, infants who test positive on screening and their mother are recommended to have further metabolic analysis such as urine organic acid, plasma acylcarnitine profile and plasma carnitine analysis. In the event that the maternal and the formula-fed infant metabolite levels are both abnormal, the metabolic work up should be repeated in the infant after one month to verify after one month to verify that the infant's levels are normalizing due to clearance of prenatally transferred metabolites; and metabolic laboratory work up should be repeated again in the infant after weaning, because maternal metabolites may be transferred to the infant via breast milk<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3)</xref>. One study revealed higher levels of C5-OH level on breast milk samples that was diluted five times with methanol prior to sample processing and quantification than blood reference range<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2)</xref>.</p>
<p>We have reported a case of suspected maternal 3-MCC deficiency because of elevated C5-OH levels in two of her infants, by newborn screening with LC-MS/MS and with normal urine organic analysis. We confirmed maternal 3-MCC deficiency by serum and on breast milk spot analysis by LC-MS/MS, urine organic analysis and gene mutation tests. Importantly, we confirmed marked higher levels of C5-OH on breast milk spot by LC-MS/MS, in the case of maternal 3-MCC deficiency vs. controls.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grunert</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stucki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morscher</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Suormala</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burda</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>3-methylcrotonyl-CoA carboxylase deficiency: clinical, biochemical, enzymatic and molecular studies in 88 individuals</article-title>
<source/>Orphanet J Rare Dis
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22642865</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eichhorst</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alcorn</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lepage</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Etter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Antonishyn</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fitterer</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Elevated neonatal 3-OH isovalerylcarnitine due to breast milk sources in maternal 3-MCC deficiency</article-title>
<source/>Mol Genet Metab
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>84</fpage>
<lpage>86</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20619711</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arnold</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koeberl</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Matern</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barshop</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Braverman</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burton</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Delphi-based consensus clinical practice protocol for the diagnosis and management of 3-methylcrotonyl CoA carboxylase deficiency</article-title>
<source/>Mol Genet Metab
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>363</fpage>
<lpage>370</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18155630</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Koeberl</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Millington</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>WE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weavil</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muenzer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCandless</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of 3-methylcrotonyl-CoA carboxylase deficiency detected by tandem mass spectrometry newborn screening</article-title>
<source/>J Inherit Metab Dis
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>25</fpage>
<lpage>35</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12872837</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gibson</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Naylor</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morton</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>3-Methylcrotonyl-coenzyme a carboxylase deficiency in Amish/Mennonite adults identified by detection of increased acylcarnitines in blood spots of their children</article-title>
<source/>J Pediatr
          <year>1998</year>
<volume>132</volume>
<issue>3 Pt 1</issue>
<fpage>519</fpage>
<lpage>523</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9544913</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arnold</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salazar</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Neidich</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Suwannarat</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lichter-Konecki</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Outcome of infants diagnosed with 3-methyl-crotonyl-CoA-carboxylase deficiency by newborn screening</article-title>
<source/>Mol Genet Metab
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>106</volume>
<fpage>439</fpage>
<lpage>441</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22658692</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alcorn</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McNamara</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ontogeny of hepatic and renal systemic clearance pathways in infants: part II</article-title>
<source/>Clin Pharmacokinet
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>1077</fpage>
<lpage>1094</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12403644</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chien</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chiang</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hwu</surname>
<given-names>WL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kao</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Nationwide survey of extended newborn screening by tandem mass spectrometry in Taiwan</article-title>
<source/>J Inherit Metab Dis
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>Suppl 2</issue>
<fpage>S295</fpage>
<lpage>S305</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20567911</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walter</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patterson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Till</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Besley</surname>
<given-names>GT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fleming</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Bloodspot acylcarnitine and amino acid analysis in cord blood samples: efficacy and reference data from a large cohort study</article-title>
<source/>J Inherit Metab Dis
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>95</fpage>
<lpage>101</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19191006</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Fig. 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Urine organic acid analysis of maternal 3-methylcrotonyl-coenzyme A carboxylase deficiency patient who had high levels of excreted 3-hydroxyisovaleric acid and 3-methylcrotonylglycine.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="kjped-59-S41-g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Fig. 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Urine organic acid analysis of maternal 3-methylcrotonyl-coenzyme A carboxylase deficiency patient who had high levels of excreted 3-hydroxyisovaleric acid and 3-methylcrotonylglycine.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="kjped-59-S41-g002"></graphic>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>C5-OH (µmol/L) level in the breast milk spot analyzed by LC-MS/MS</title>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic xlink:href="kjped-59-S41-i001"></graphic>
<table frame="hsides" rules="rows">
<col span="1" width="50%"/>
<col span="1" width="50%"/>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Subject</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">C5-OH level (μmol/L)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Control 1</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.046</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">Control 2</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">0.062</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Control 3</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.080</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">Control 4</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">0.102</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Control 5</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.089</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">Control 6</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">0.051</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Control 7</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.066</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">Control 8</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">0.056</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Control 9</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.025</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">Control 10</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">0.031</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3-MCC deficiency patient</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.694</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">Mean (controls)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(241,242,242)" valign="top">0.061</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn>
<p>Subjects included one maternal 3-MCC deficiency patient and 10 controls. (No reference range).</p>
<p>C5-OH, 3-hydroxyisovalerylcarnitine; 3-MCC, 3-methylcrotonyl-coenzyme A carboxylase; LC-MS/MS, liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry/MS.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>