<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0376363</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">5153</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Pharm Pharmacol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Pharm. Pharmacol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Journal of pharmacy and pharmacology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-3573</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2042-7158</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27364566</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5201450</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jphp.12599</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS796174</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Clinical pharmacology of analgo-sedatives in neonates: <italic>ways to improve their safe and effective use</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smits</surname>
<given-names>Anne</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van den Anker</surname>
<given-names>John N</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Allegaert</surname>
<given-names>Karel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, VU Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, University Hospitals Leuven, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Intensive Care and Department of Surgery, Erasmus MC-Sophia Children's Hospital, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Division of Paediatric Pharmacology and Pharmacometrics, University Children's Hospital Basel, Switzerland</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Division of Pediatric Clinical Pharmacology, Children's National Medical Center, Washington, DC, USA, Departments of Pediatrics, Integrative Systems Biology, Pharmacology &amp; Physiology, George Washington University School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Washington, DC, USA</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Development and Regeneration, KU Leuven, Belgium</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: K Allegaert, MD PhD, Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, University Hospital, Herestraat 49, 3000 Leuven, BELGIUM, Tel 00-32-16-343850, Fax 00-32-16-343209, <email>allegaertkarel@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>22</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>30</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>69</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>350</fpage>
<lpage>360</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1111/jphp.12599-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Objectives</title>
<p id="P1">To propose approaches tailored to the specific needs of neonates, such as structured product development programs, with the ultimate goal to improve the safe and effective use of analgo-sedatives in these fragile patients.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Key findings</title>
<p id="P2">The feasibility and relevance of a structured product development program in neonates (optimal study design based on preliminary data; model development; internal, external and prospective evaluation; an individualized dosing regimen; long term safety; pharmacogenetics) is illustrated for the use of morphine.</p>
<p id="P3">Based on changes in clinical practices, similar development plans are in progress for short acting analgo-sedatives such as propofol, but are in need of tailored pharmacodynamic tools to assess and quantify effects. Furthermore, for drugs like paracetamol where there is already sufficient clinical pharmacology knowledge, attention needs to be given to long-term safety aspects. Finally, new covariates such as pharmacogenetics might further improve neonatal pain management, but clearly need to be integrated with other well established covariates like age or weight.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Summary</title>
<p id="P4">Product development programs for analgo-sedatives in neonates are needed. These programs should be tailored to their specific needs (short acting sedation, pain relief), should include long term safety, and should incorporate the exploration of newer covariates like pharmacogenetics.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>newborn</kwd>
<kwd>pain</kwd>
<kwd>clinical pharmacology</kwd>
<kwd>pharmacogenetics</kwd>
<kwd>pharmacodynamics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>