<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27418134</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5239556</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10566</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.10566</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Paper</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>MicroRNA-184 promotes differentiation of the retinal pigment epithelium by targeting the <italic>AKT2</italic>/mTOR signaling pathway</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Chao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>Bing</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Guohua</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Xiantao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Houxia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>Sijia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Yuan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Meidong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Xue</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Chen</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Department of Ophthalmology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University and State Key Laboratory of Reproductive Medicine, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</aff>
<aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Department of Ophthalmology, The First People's Hospital of Suqian, Suqian, China</aff>
<aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Department of Ophthalmology, Qilu Hospital of Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong, China</aff>
<aff id="A4"><sup>4</sup> Department of Ophthalmology, Children's Hospital of Zhengzhou, Zhengzhou, China</aff>
<aff id="A5"><sup>5</sup> Department of Ophthalmology, Nanjing First Hospital, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</aff>
<aff id="A6"><sup>6</sup> Save Sight Institute, Discipline of Clinical Ophthalmology and Eye Health (CO9), The University of Sydney, Sydney, Australia</aff>
<aff id="A7"><sup>7</sup> Department of Ophthalmology, Eye and ENT Hospital, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</aff>
<aff id="A8"><sup>8</sup> State Key Laboratory of Ophthalmology, Zhongshan Ophthalmic Center, Sun Yat Sen University, Guangzhou, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">
<bold>
<italic>Correspondence to:</italic>
</bold>
<italic>Chen Zhao,</italic>
<email>dr_zhaochen@163.com</email>
</corresp>
<corresp id="cor2">
<italic>Xue Chen,</italic>
<email>drcx1990@163.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<day>9</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>32</issue>
<fpage>52340</fpage>
<lpage>52353</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>14</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>30</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2016 Jiang et al.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Dedifferentiation of retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) cells is a crucial contributing factor to the pathology of retinal degenerative diseases, including age-related macular degeneration (AMD). Herein, we aim to reveal the roles of microRNAs (miRNAs) in RPE dedifferentiation and seek for potential therapeutic targets. Based on the microarray data, miR-184 was sorted out as the most up-regulated signature along with the differentiation from human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSC) to RPE cells, suggesting its potential promotive role in RPE differentiation. <italic>In vitro</italic> study indicated that miR-184 insufficiency suppressed RPE differentiation, typified by reduction of RPE markers, and promoted cell proliferation and migration. The role of miR-184 in maintaining regular RPE function was further proved in zebrafish studies. We also noticed that miR-184 expression was reduced in the macular RPE-choroid from a donor with RPE dysfunction compared to a healthy control. We next demonstrated that RAC-beta serine/threonine-protein kinase (<italic>AKT2</italic>) was a direct target for miR-184. MiR-184 promoted RPE differentiation via suppression of AKT2/mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) signaling pathway. We also found that <italic>AKT2</italic> was up-regulated in macular RPE-choroid of the donor with RPE dysfunction and dry AMD patients. Taken together, our findings suggest that miR-184 insufficiency is involved in the pathogenesis of dry AMD. MiR-184 promotes RPE differentiation via inhibiting the AKT2/mTOR signaling pathway. MiR-184 based supplementary therapeutics and mTOR blocker, like rapamycin, are prospective options for AMD treatment.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>miR-184</kwd>
<kwd>retinal pigment epithelium</kwd>
<kwd>differentiation</kwd>
<kwd>AKT2</kwd>
<kwd>mTOR</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>Retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) is a cuboidal, polarized, and pigmented epithelial cell layer located in the outer retina between the light-sensitive outer segments of photoreceptors and choroidal vasculature forming a part of the blood/retina barrier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]. As a monolayer of pigmented cells, RPE is crucial in maintaining retinal functions, including absorbing light energy focused by the lens onto the retina; transporting nutrients and ions between photoreceptors and choriocapillaris; regulating ion balance in sub-retinal space; exchanging, storing, and enzymatic conversing retinoid essential for visual cycle; phagocytosis of shed photoreceptor membranes; and secretion of a variety of growth factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. Irregular RPE function may interrupt retinal homeostasis, induce photoreceptor degeneration, generate choroidal neovascularization, and result in vision loss. Dysfunction and depletion of RPE are therefore considered as hallmarks for both monogenic and polygenic retinal degenerative disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>].</p>
<p>Age-related macular degeneration (AMD), among the most common polygenic retinal degenerative diseases, is a worldwide leading cause for irreversible visual impairments in people aged over 55 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. AMD can be categorized into two forms, atrophic and exudative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. Abnormal RPE behaviors play a preliminary causative role in both forms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. Atrophic AMD is characterized by subepithelial deposits and degeneration of RPE and photoreceptors involving but not limited to the macular region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. No efficient treatment has been raised for atrophic AMD. Epithelium dedifferentiation, typified by reduction of RPE markers and cellular hypertrophy, has been identified as a crucial process in atrophic AMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. Thus, it is likely that blocking RPE dedifferentiation may permit vision recovery and become potential therapeutic targets for atrophic AMD.</p>
<p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small (19-25 nucleotides) noncoding regulatory RNA molecules that regulate gene expression by binding to particular sites within the 3′-untranslated region (3′-UTR) of their target mRNAs, repressing or seldom activating target gene expression through modulation of mRNA stability or translation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]. Complexity in the regulatory network between miRNAs and their processing factors has, to certain extents, limits comprehensive and thorough investigations. MiRNAs’ roles in the survival and function of RPE cells have been previously annotated, while their roles in RPE differentiation are still unclear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. <italic>MiR-184</italic>, located on 15q25.1, is an evolutionarily conserved non-coding RNA oligo. Mature miR-184, containing 22 nucleotides, shows tissue and developmental stage specific expression patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. It is selectively enriched in mouse brain, mouse corneal epithelium, zebrafish lens and human RPE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>], and is involved in neurological development, apoptosis, and cell differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. Previous study has revealed that miR-184 expression is decreased in RPE of AMD donors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]; however, its role in AMD pathogenesis, especially in RPE dedifferentiation, is still largely unknown. In this study, we aim to analyze the effect of miR-184 in RPE differentiation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>RESULTS</title>
<sec id="s2_1">
<title>Generation of hiPSC-RPE</title>
<p>Pluripotency of the undifferentiated human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSC) colonies was confirmed via positive immunostaining for four pluripotency relevant markers, including octamer-binding protein 4 (Oct-4) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), transcription factor SOX-2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>), stage-specific embryonic antigen-4 (SSEA-4) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>), and Tra-1-60 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). The hiPSC derived RPE (hiPSC-RPE) was obtained using the SFEB/CS method with small molecule compounds CKI-7 and SB-431542 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Pigmented clusters appeared at 30 days post differentiation (dpd) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>), and increased in both volume and quantity along with the differentiation (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1G</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Generation of hiPSC-RPE</title>
<p><bold>A-D.</bold> Immunofluorescent staining of hiPSC. Cell nuclei are presented with DAPI. Images are shown as anti-Oct-4 (A), anti-SOX-2 (B), anti-SSEA-4 (C), and anti-Tra-1-60 (D). <bold>E-G.</bold> Morphological changes of hiPSC-RPE at 30 (E), 60 (F), and 90 (G) days post differentiation (dpd), respectively. <bold>H-R.</bold> mRNA expressions of pluripotent genes, including <italic>NANOG</italic> (H), <italic>POU5F1</italic> (I), and <italic>SOX2</italic> (J), and RPE markers, including <italic>MITF</italic> (K), <italic>PAX6</italic> (L), <italic>RPE65</italic> (M), <italic>RLBP1</italic> (N), <italic>MERTK</italic> (O), <italic>BEST1</italic> (P), <italic>CDH12</italic> (Q), and <italic>TJP1</italic> (R), in hiPSC-RPE at 0, 30, 60, and 90 dpd. *, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>To determine the competence of differentiation, expression levels of pluripotency-related and RPE signature genes were measured in and compared among undifferentiated hiPSC and hiPSC-RPE at 30, 60, and 90 dpd. Reductions in the mRNA levels of three major pluripotency relevant genes, including homeobox protein NANOG (<italic>NANOG</italic>; NM_024865) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1H</xref>), POU domain class 5 transcription factor 1 (<italic>POU5F1</italic>; NM_002701) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1I</xref>), and <italic>SOX2</italic> (NM_003106) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1J</xref>), were noticed in the differentiated hiPSC-RPE, suggesting its loss of pluripotency. RPE markers were gained through differentiation. Expression levels of the following RPE markers consistently elevated along with the differentiation: RPE-related and developmental transcription factors including microphthalmia-associated transcription factor (<italic>MITF</italic>; NM_198159) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1K</xref>) and paired box protein pax-6 (<italic>PAX6</italic>; NM_001127612) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1L</xref>); visual cycle genes including retinoid isomerohydrolase (<italic>RPE65</italic>; NM_000329) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1M</xref>) and retinaldehyde-binding protein 1 (<italic>RLBP1</italic>; NM_000326) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1N</xref>); membrane proteins and channels including tyrosine-protein kinase Mer (<italic>MERTK</italic>; NM_006343) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1O</xref>) and bestrophin-1 (<italic>BEST1</italic>; NM_001139443) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1P</xref>); and junctional integrity and migration relevant genes cadherin-2 (<italic>CDH2</italic>; NM_001792) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1S</xref>) and tight junction protein ZO-1 (<italic>TJP1</italic>; NM_003257) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1T</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2_2">
<title>Expression profiles of miRNAs regulating the RPE differentiation</title>
<p>To study the role of miRNAs in RPE differentiation, we used microarray analysis to characterize the expression profiles of miRNAs in hiPSC and hiPSC-RPE at 30, 60, and 90 dpd, respectively. All identified miRNAs were initially filtered by fold change. Only miRNA with a fold change of over 2 in the 30 dpd hiPSC-RPE compared to the undifferentiated hiPSC was included. MicroRNA expressions changed consistently at all time points along with the differentiation were considered as crucial for hiPSC differentiation and sorted out. A total of 78 differentially expressed miRNAs, including 14 up-regulated and 64 down-regulated, were selected with their chromosomal locations annotated (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A-2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Expression profiling of miRNAs</title>
<p><bold>A.</bold> Hierarchical clustering of all 78 concordantly differentially expressed miRNAs. Hsa-miR-184 was constantly up-regulated along with the differentiation from hiPSC to RPE. Green: down-regulated miRNAs; red: up-regulated miRNAs. <bold>B.</bold> Chromosomal locations of the 78 differentially expressed miRNAs were presented as a Circos plot. <bold>C-F.</bold> Four differentially expressed miRNAs with fold change of over 2 among all time points, including the up-regulated hsa-miR-184 (C), hsa-miR-449a (D), hsa-miR-449b-5p (E), and the down-regulated hsa-miR-302d-3p (F), were selected for validation of the microarray results in hiPSC-RPE at 0, 30, 60, and 90 dpd. (G) Network among all up-regulated miRNAs and their respective experimentally confirmed mRNA targets. The upregulated miRNAs were labeled. Colored nodes: miRNAs; grey nodes: mRNAs; colored edges: miRNA-target interaction.*: p&lt;0.05; **: p&lt;0.01; ***: p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-g002"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>To validate the microarray data, we picked four differentially expressed miRNAs with a consistent fold change of over 2 along with the differentiation and analyzed their expressions using real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Agreed with the microarray data, hsa-miR-184, hsa-miR-449a and hsa-miR-449b-5p were consistently up-regulated along with the differentiation, while hsa-miR-302d-3p was down-regulated (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C-1F</xref>). mRNAs targeted by the up-regulated miRNAs with experimental supports were then obtained using miRTarBase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2G</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. RAC-beta serine/threonine-protein kinase (<italic>AKT2</italic>; NM_001626) was found as a target for hsa-miR-184 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2G</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2_3">
<title>Hsa-miR-184 promotes RPE differentiation</title>
<p>As above mentioned, hsa-miR-184 expression was consistently increased along with RPE differentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>), we then respectively transfected hsa-miR-184 mimic and inhibitor into hiPSC-RPE at 30 dpd to see its role on cell differentiation. Hsa-miR-184 mimic comprises chemically synthesized oligonucleotides identical to the sequence of endogenous hsa-miR-184, which will be loaded into the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC) and silence target genes like endogenous hsa-miR-184 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. Antisense hsa-miR-184 oligonucleotides are used as hsa-miR-184 inhibitor, which binds directly to the single strand mature hsa-miR-184 to block its activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. Exogenous hsa-miR-184 expression was remarkably up-regulated in cells transfected with hsa-miR-184 mimic (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), and endogenous hsa-miR-184 expression was down-regulated in cells transfected with hsa-miR-184 inhibitor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Expressions of several RPE markers were then tested, including mRNA expressions of <italic>RPE65</italic>, <italic>RLBP1</italic>, <italic>MERTK</italic>, <italic>BEST1</italic> and <italic>TJP1</italic>, and protein expressions of MERTK (encoded by <italic>MERTK</italic>; NP_006334), lecithin retinol acyltransferase (encoded by <italic>LRAT</italic>, NM_004744; NP_004735), ZO-1 (encoded by <italic>TJP1</italic>; NP_003248), keratin type I cytoskeletal 18 (encoded by <italic>KRT18</italic>, NM_000224; NP_000215), RLBP1 (encoded by <italic>RLBP1</italic>; NP_000317), and β-catenin (encoded by <italic>CTNNB1</italic>; NP_001895). Ectopic hsa-miR-184 overexpression elevated both mRNA and protein expressions of the RPE markers (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C, 3E-3F</xref>), while hsa-miR-184 insufficiency suppressed their expressions (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D, 3E</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref>). Our findings suggested that hsa-miR-184 promotes the differentiation of hiPSC-RPE.</p>
<fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Hsa-miR-184 promotes cell differentiation</title>
<p><bold>A-B.</bold> Relative miRNA expression of hsa-miR-184 in hiPSC-RPE at 30 dpd transfected with hsa-miR-184 mimic compared to NC mimic (A), and in cells transfected with hsa-miR-184 inhibitor compared to NC inhibitor (B). <bold>C-D.</bold> Relative mRNA expressions of <italic>RPE65</italic>, <italic>RLBP1</italic>, <italic>MERTK</italic>, <italic>BEST1</italic>, and <italic>TJP1</italic> in hiPSC-RPE at 30 dpd transfected with hsa-miR-184 mimic compared to NC mimic (C), and in cells transfected with hsa-miR-184 inhibitor compared to NC inhibitor (D). <bold>E-G.</bold> Relative protein expressions of MERTK, LRAT, ZO-1, Keratin 18, RLBP1, and β-catenin in hiPSC-RPE at 30 dpd transfected with hsa-miR-184 mimic compared to NC mimic (E-F), and in cells transfected with hsa-miR-184 inhibitor compared to NC inhibitor (E, G). *: p&lt;0.05; **: p&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-g003"></graphic>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2_4">
<title>Dre-miR-184 insufficiency suppresses RPE development <italic>in vivo</italic></title>
<p>We next used zebrafish model to investigate the role of dre-miR-184 on RPE development. Embryos at 1- to 2-cell stage were individually injected with dre-miR-184 mimic or inhibitor to modulate its exogenous or endogenous dre-miR-184 expression (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A-4B</xref>). Embryos injected with negative control (NC) inhibitor or mimic were taken as controls. mRNA expression of RPE markers, including <italic>pax6a</italic> (NM_131304), <italic>rpe65c</italic> (NM_001113653), <italic>rlbp1b</italic> (NM_205690), <italic>lrat</italic> (NM_001135971), <italic>mertka</italic> (XM_002664231.4), <italic>best1</italic> (XM_009297704.1), <italic>krt18</italic> (NM_178437), <italic>cdh2</italic> (NM_131081), <italic>tjp1b</italic> (XM_009298138.1), and <italic>ctnnb1</italic> (NM_131059), were tested and compared in zebrafish from all injection groups with normal systemic appearance at 4 day post fertilization (dpf). Q-PCR results indicated that knocking down of dre-miR-184 will suppress the expression of RPE markers, while overexpression of dre-miR-184 can promote RPE development (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C-4D</xref>). Consistent to mRNA findings, immunofluorescence revealed decreased reactivity of retinoid isomerohydrolase (encoded by <italic>rpe65c</italic>; NP_000320), a marker of RPE cells, in the RPE layer of zebrafish injected with dre-miR-184 inhibitor (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4E-4H</xref>) compared to embryos injected with NC inhibitor (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4I-4L</xref>). By contrast, the dre-miR-184 mimic injection group showed robust expression of retinoid isomerohydrolase in the RPE layer (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4M-4P</xref>), similar to the NC mimic injection group (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4Q-4T</xref>). Our findings suggested that dre-miR-184 functions in maintaining the regular function of zebrafish RPE, and its insufficiency would suppress RPE development.</p>
<fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Dre-miR-184 promotes retinal development <italic>in vivo</italic></title>
<p><bold>A-B.</bold> Relative expression of dre-miR-184 in zebrafish injected with dre-miR-184 inhibitor compared to NC inhibitor (A), and in embryos injected with dre-miR-184 mimic compared with NC mimic (B). <bold>C-D.</bold> Relative mRNA expressions of <italic>pax6a</italic>, <italic>rpe65c</italic>, <italic>rlbp1b</italic>, <italic>lrat</italic>, <italic>mertka</italic>, <italic>best1</italic>, <italic>krt18</italic>, <italic>cdh2</italic>, <italic>tjp1b</italic>, and <italic>ctnnb1</italic> in zebrafish injected with dre-miR-184 inhibitor compared to NC inhibitor (C), and in embryos injected with dre-miR-184 mimic compared with NC mimic (D). *: p&lt;0.05; **: p&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-g004"></graphic>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2_5">
<title><italic>AKT2</italic> is a direct target of hsa-miR-184 in RPE cells</title>
<p>Previous study suggested that hsa-miR-184 suppressed <italic>AKT2</italic> expression in neuroblastoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. We then focused on studying whether <italic>AKT2</italic> is a potential target of hsa-miR-184 in RPE cells. Initial assessments were carried out to see whether <italic>AKT2</italic> expression levels are inversely related to hsa-miR-184 levels. <italic>AKT2</italic> expression was found consistently decreased along with the differentiation from hiPSC to RPE as demonstrated in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>, which was inversely correlated to the expression pattern of hsa-miR-184 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). To confirm that <italic>AKT2</italic> was inhibited by hsa-miR-184 in RPE, we next measured the expression of <italic>AKT2</italic> in 30 dpd hiPSC-RPE transfected with hsa-miR-184 mimic. Q-PCR analysis revealed that overexpression of exogenous hsa-miR-184 down-regulates the <italic>AKT2</italic> mRNA level in 30 dpd hiPSC-RPE (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). The same result was observed at protein level (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Hsa-miR-184 targets the <italic>AKT2</italic>/mTOR pathway, and inhibits cell proliferation and migration</title>
<p><bold>A.</bold> Schematic construction of reporter containing a fragment of the wild type and mutant <italic>AKT2</italic> 3′-TUR. <bold>B.</bold> Relative luciferase activities were measured in ARPE-19 cells. Renilla luciferase vector was used as an internal control. <bold>C.</bold> mRNA expression of <italic>AKT2</italic> were analyzed in 30 dpd hiPSC-RPE transfected with NC mimic or hsa-miR-184 mimic, respectively. <bold>D.</bold>
<italic>AKT2</italic> levels were determined in hiPSC-RPE at 30, 60, and 90 dpd. <bold>E-F.</bold>
<italic>AKT2</italic> expression was elevated in ARPE-19 cells transfected with AcFlag-AKT2 (E), and was suppressed in cells transfected with AKT2-siRNA (F). <bold>G-H.</bold> Relative mRNA expressions of <italic>MITF</italic>, <italic>RPE65</italic>, <italic>RLBP1</italic>, <italic>LRAT</italic>, <italic>BEST1</italic>, KRT18, and <italic>CTNNB1</italic> in hiPSC-RPE at 30 dpd transfected with hsa-miR-184 mimic plus empty expression vector compared to hsa-miR-184 mimic plus AcFlag-AKT2 (G), and in cells transfected with hsa-miR-184 inhibitor plus scramble siRNA compared hsa-miR-184 inhibitor plus AKT2-siRNA (H). *: p&lt;0.05; **: p&lt;0.01; ***: p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-g005"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Hsa-miR-184 suppresses the AKT2/mTOR pathway, and inhibits cell proliferation and migration</title>
<p><bold>A.</bold> Immunoblotting of p-AKT2, AKT2, p-mTOR, mTOR, p-p70S6K, p70S6K in 30 dpd hiPSC-RPE transfected with NC mimic/hsa-miR-184 mimic. <bold>B.</bold> Schematic of the hsa-miR-184 regulatory network. <bold>C-F.</bold> Proliferative rates of ARPE-19 cells transfected with NC mimic (C), hsa-miR-184 mimic (C), NC inhibitor (E), and hsa-miR-184 inhibitor (E), and migration of ARPE-19 cells transfected with NC mimic (D), hsa-miR-184 mimic (D), NC inhibitor (F), and hsa-miR-184 inhibitor (F).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-g006"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>We further aimed to tell whether the effect of hsa-miR-184 on <italic>AKT2</italic> expression is a direct effect of hsa-miR-184 targeting <italic>AKT2</italic> 3′-UTR using luciferase reporter assay. A fragment from the 3′-UTR of the <italic>AKT2</italic> gene bearing its binding region with hsa-miR-184 was cloned into the firefly pMIR-GLO™ luciferase vector (pMIR, Invitrogen) to construct the recombinant plasmid AKT2<sup>WT</sup> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Luciferase activity was significantly decreased in ARPE-19 cells co-transfected with the AKT2<sup>WT</sup> plasmid and hsa-miR-184 mimic compared to cells co-transfected with the reporter and NC mimic (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). However, introduction of 3 single nucleotides located in the core binding region of <italic>AKT2</italic> completely abolished the ability of hsa-miR-184 mimic to decrease luciferase activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Altogether, our findings supported that hsa-miR-184 directly targets <italic>AKT2</italic> 3′-UTR and suppresses <italic>AKT2</italic> expression in RPE.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2_6">
<title>Hsa-miR-184 promotes RPE differentiation via suppression of <italic>AKT2</italic></title>
<p>We next tested whether <italic>AKT2</italic> could affect the promotive effect of hsa-miR-184 on RPE differentiation. The efficiency of AcFlag-AKT2 in overexpressing <italic>AKT2</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>) and AKT2-siRNA in silencing <italic>AKT2</italic> were initially confirmed in ARPE-19 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). Expression of several mRNAs were then tested and compared, including <italic>MITF</italic>, <italic>RPE65</italic>, <italic>RLBP1</italic>, <italic>LRAT</italic>, <italic>BEST1</italic>, <italic>KRT18</italic>, and <italic>CTNNB1</italic>. We showed that <italic>AKT2</italic> overexpression abrogated the hsa-miR-184 mediated RPE differentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). Further, silencing of <italic>AKT2</italic> rescued the inhibition on RPE differentiation induced by hsa-miR-184 insufficiency (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). Collectively, our data implied that hsa-miR-184 promotes RPE differentiation via suppression of <italic>AKT2</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2_7">
<title>Hsa-miR-184 suppresses the AKT2/mTOR pathway, and inhibits cell proliferation and migration</title>
<p>We have previously reported that RPE dedifferentiation could arise through stimulation of the AKT/mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. As indicated above, hsa-miR-184 would promote RPE differentiation, and <italic>AKT2</italic> was a direct target of hsa-miR-184. We therefore hypothesized that hsa-miR-184 might promote RPE differentiation via blocking the AKT2/mTOR signaling pathway (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>, western blot analysis revealed decreased phosphorylation of AKT2<sup>Ser474</sup>, mTOR<sup>Ser2448</sup>, and p70S6K<sup>Thr389</sup> in 30 dpd hiPSC-RPE overexpressing hsa-miR-184, suggesting that hsa-miR-184 could inhibit the AKT2/mTOR pathway. Since cellular proliferation and migration can follow the dedifferentiation of postmitotic tissues, including RPE, and activation of mTOR pathway have been reported to enhance cell proliferation and migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>], we next determined whether hsa-miR-184 would inhibit proliferation and migration of ARPE-19 cells. Cell proliferative and migratory rates were continuously detected till 72 hours (hr) post transfection. Both proliferation and migration were inhibited by hsa-miR-184 overexpression at all time points post transfection (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C-6D</xref>), and cell proliferative and migratory rates were increased in cells with endogenous hsa-miR-184 down-regulated (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E-6F</xref>). Taken together, our results suggested that hsa-miR-184 suppresses the AKT2/mTOR signaling pathway, and inhibits cell proliferation and migration.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2_8">
<title>Hsa-miR-184 is decreased in dysfunctional RPE, and <italic>AKT2</italic> is increased in AMD</title>
<p>Activation of mTOR signaling pathway is reported to cause RPE dedifferentiation and retinal degenerative diseases, namely AMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. Since hsa-miR-184 could inhibit mTOR, we, therefore, assumed that hsa-miR-184 expression will be reduced in dysfunctional RPE. To test our hypothesis, we compared the expression of hsa-miR-184 between the macular RPE of a 70-year-old male and a 30-year-old female donor. Although the male donor hadn't been clinically diagnosed with AMD before he passed away, mRNA expressions of RPE markers, including <italic>RPE65</italic>, <italic>RLBP1</italic>, <italic>BEST1</italic> and <italic>LRAT</italic>, were found significantly decreased in his RPE compared to the younger donor, suggesting dysfunction of RPE cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). As expected, hsa-miR-184 level was found remarkably down-regulated in the aged donor with RPE dysfunction (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). Further analysis suggested that, opposite to the decreased hsa-miR-184 level, <italic>AKT2</italic> mRNA was elevated in the macular RPE of the above mentioned aged donor with RPE dysfunction (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>). Our results were consistent with the previous report that hsa-miR-184 expression was inhibited in the RPE of donors with AMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>], and further implied that hsa-miR-184 may play a role in keeping regular function of RPE.</p>
<fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 7</label>
<caption>
<title>Hsa-miR-184 is down-regulated in dysfunctional RPE, and <italic>AKT2</italic> is up-regulated in AMD</title>
<p><bold>A.</bold> Relative RNA expressions of hsa-miR-184, <italic>AKT2</italic>, <italic>RPE65</italic>, <italic>RLBP1</italic>, <italic>BEST1</italic>, and <italic>LRAT</italic> in the macular RPE of an aged donor compared to a young donor. <bold>B-C.</bold> Expressions of <italic>AKT2</italic> were measured and compared in the macular (B) and extramacular (C) RPE-choroid of age related macular degeneration (AMD) patients and the control group. <bold>D.</bold>
<italic>AKT2</italic> expressions were further analyzed and compared in the RPE-choroid of patients with different AMD subtypes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-g007"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Since hsa-miR-184 was reported to present a decreased expression pattern in AMD patients, we next tested and compared the macular and extramacular <italic>AKT2</italic> mRNA levels in RPE-choroid from normal individuals and AMD patients. Summary mRNA data (GSE29801) and sample information (GSM738433 to GSM738607) of 175 independent RPE-choroid samples were downloaded from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) datasets and double-checked. The 175 samples contained 50 macular and 38 extramacular RPE-choroid tissues from normal individuals, and 41 macular and 46 extramacular RPE-choroid samples from AMD patients. <italic>AKT2</italic> was found elevated in the macular RPE-choroid of AMD patients compared to healthy controls (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>), while no expressional difference between the two groups was detected in the extramacular RPE-choroid (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>). Subgroup analysis was next performed to better tell with which AMD subtype <italic>AKT2</italic> is most closely correlated. Clinical diagnostic criterion for each AMD subgroup has been detailed before [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>]. According to our findings, <italic>AKT2</italic> was only found elevated in the dry AMD group (n=16) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7D</xref>), a branch of atrophic AMD. Our results implied a potential role of <italic>AKT2</italic> in atrophic AMD.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<title>DISCUSSION</title>
<p>RPE dedifferentiation, typified and accompanied with morphological and molecular changes of the RPE cells, has been proved as an important contributing factor to the pathophysiology of retinal degenerative disease, like AMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. Thus, inhibition of RPE dedifferentiation could be a potential therapeutic target for such diseases. MicroRNAs are important regulators in gene expression, and their roles in keeping the survival and regular functions of RPE cells have been well established: conditional deletion of the miRNA processing factor Dicer1 in RPE generates cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>], and deficient miR-204/211 levels causes RPE dysfunction and demorphogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. Furthermore, miRNAs-based therapeutic strategies, like miRNA replacement therapies, have inherent advantages over other therapeutics in drug efficiency and delivery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>]. In this study, we generate the hiPSC-RPE model to assess the involvement of miRNAs in modulating RPE differentiation. A total of 78 miRNAs are initially sorted out, among which miR-184 is the most up-regulated signature along with the differentiation, and its crucial role in RPE differentiation is further confirmed in both cellular and zebrafish models. We have also reasoned that miR-184 suppresses the AKT2/mTOR signaling pathway, promotes RPE differentiation, and inhibits RPE proliferation and migration.</p>
<p>The role of miR-184 in AMD pathogenesis, especially in RPE dedifferentiation, is still largely unknown. Herein, consistent to previous findings, we show that miR-184 expression is remarkably reduced in the macular RPE of a donor with RPE dysfunction, indicating its role in maintaining regular functions of RPE cells. The impact of miR-184 on promoting RPE development is further confirmed in zebrafish model. Reduction in RPE markers is observed in embryos with miR-184 silenced. Cellular model also proves that the expression level of miR-184 associates with RPE differentiation. Overexpression of miR-184 promotes RPE differentiation, while miR-184 insufficiency could suppress RPE differentiation.</p>
<p>Ezrin (<italic>EZR</italic>) gene is the only reported target of miR-184 involved in RPE functions. Binding of ezrin to lysosomal-associated membrane protein 1 (LAMP-1) is an important process to form phagocytic vacuoles. Reduction in miR-184 expression will decrease level of EZR-bounded LAMP-1 and interrupt RPE phagocytosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. <italic>AKT2</italic> is homolog 2 of the v-akt oncogene, a major downstream effector of the phosphatidylinositol 3′ kinase (PI3K) pathway that can activate the mTOR pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. Activation of the AKT/mTOR pathway can stimulate RPE dedifferentiation, proliferation, migration and hypertrophy, and is thus supposed to be a crucial disease process for AMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. <italic>AKT2</italic> has been proved as a target for miR-184 in neuroblastoma cell line [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>], while their interaction in RPE cells remains inclusive. In the present study, we confirm that <italic>AKT2</italic> is a direct target for miR-184 in ARPE-19 cells, and miR-184 promotes RPE differentiation via suppression of <italic>AKT2</italic>. <italic>AKT2</italic> is found down-regulated in the macular RPE-choroid of AMD patients, especially in patients with dry AMD. We also demonstrate that miR-184 blocks the AKT2/mTOR signaling pathway and suppresses cell proliferation and migration.</p>
<p>Other than retinopathy, miR-184 seed region mutations are reported to cause EDICT syndrome, presenting familial keratoconus with cataract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>]. The mutated miR-184 antagonizes miR-205 to maintain the expression of the inositol polyphosphate phosphatase-like 1 (<italic>INPPL1</italic>) gene, which generates the disease phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. This finding implies that in order to sustain RPE function and survival, miR-184 may also modulate the expressions of regulatory factors, like other miRNAs and long non-coding RNAs. In addition, abnormal methylation status of <italic>MIR-184</italic> has also been found correlated with Rett syndrome, presented with autism spectrum disorders and involving irregular synaptic plasticity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Thus, deep investigations into the regulatory network and epigenetic regulation of miR-184 in maintaining RPE function may become part of our future work.</p>
<p>Taken together, our study concludes that miR-184 promotes RPE differentiation via inhibiting the AKT2/mTOR signaling pathway, and miR-184 insufficiency plays an important role in the pathogenesis of dry AMD. MiR-184-based supplementary therapeutics and mTOR pathway inhibitor, like rapamycin, can inhibit RPE dedifferentiation in dry AMD and may become prospective options for treating retinal degenerative diseases. Further work is still warranted to better elucidate the role of miR-184 in AMD pathogenesis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
<title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
<sec id="s4_1">
<title>Samples</title>
<p>Post-mortem specimens of a 70-year-old male donor and a 30-year-old female donor were provided by Lions New South Wales Eye Bank through Save Sight Institute, the University of Sydney, Australia. Written informed consents were obtained from all donors before donation. All procedures followed standard procedures of eye donation for research and were approved by the institutional ethical committees conformed to Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_2">
<title>Animals</title>
<p>Tuebingen zebrafish were housed in the Model Animal Research Center (MARC), Nanjing University, in accordance with the IACUC-approved protocol. Rearing and husbandry of zebrafish were maintained at 28.5°C in a 14 hr light/10 hr dark cycle. Embryos were produced by natural mating. Animal experiments were approved by the local ethical committees. All procedures were conformed to the Guide for the Care and Use of laboratory animals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_3">
<title>Culture and differentiation of hiPSC</title>
<p>The hiPSC (IMR90-57, a kind gift from Prof Guoping Fan, Tongji University, Shanghai, China) were cultured on mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs; SiDan-Sai Biotechnology Co., Ltd, Shanghai, China) in six-well tissue culture plates (Corning Glass Works, Corning, New York, USA), and were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium/Ham's F12 nutrient medium 1:1 (DME/F12 medium; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with knockout serum replacement (20%; Gibco, Carlsbad, CA, USA), β-mercaptoethanol (0.1 mM; Sigma-Aldrich; St. Louis, MO, USA), L-glutamine (2mM; Gibco), non-essential amino acids (0.1 mM; Gibco), and zebrafish basic fibroblast growth factor (zbFGF; 100 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems Inc., Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA) at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. <italic>In vitro</italic> differentiation of RPE cells from hiPSC was performed using a previously described SFEB/CS method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. We added low-molecular-weight compounds CKI-7 (5 μM) and SB-431542 (5 μM) during suspension culture to block Wnt and Nodal signaling, respectively. These two small molecules are perfect substitutions for recombinant Dkk1 and Lefty-A proteins which were confirmed to induce the differentiation of ES cells into retinal progenitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_4">
<title>RNA extraction, RT-PCR, and real-time PCR</title>
<p>RNA isolation, cDNA synthesis, and real-time PCR were performed as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>]. Briefly, total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Concentration and quality of RNA samples were measured with Nano-Drop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (Nano-Drop Technologies, Wilmington, DE). One μg of total RNA was used for reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) using PrimeScript RT Kit (Takara, Otsu, Shiga, Japan). Real-time PCR was conducted using FastStart Universal SYBR Green Master (ROX; Roche, Basel, Switzerland) with the StepOne Plus Real-time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Darmstadt, Germany). Primer information was detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table S3</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_5">
<title>Immunofluorescence</title>
<p>Cells were harvested, fixed with paraformaldehyde (4%) for 30 minutes (min), permeabilized with Triton X-100 (0.5%) for 20 min, blocked in bovine serum albumin (BSA; 1%) for 2 hours (hr), and incubated with designated primary antibodies at 4°C overnight. Details for antibodies were provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S4</xref>. Cells were then washed with phosphate buffer saline (PBS; 1X) for 15 min and incubated with corresponding fluorescence-conjugated secondary antibodies (1:1000 diluted in 1X PBS; Invitrogen) for 1 hr at room temperature. Cytoskeleton was counterstained by phalloidin (1:40; Invitrogen) for 30 min, and cell nuclei by 4′, 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Sigma, USA) for 5 min. Images were collected with an inverted fluorescence microscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_6">
<title>miRNA and mRNA expression profiling, and computational analysis</title>
<p>GeneChip® miRNA 3.0 Array (Affymetrix Inc, Santa Clara, CA, USA) covering 100% miRBase v17 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/">www.mirbase.org</ext-link>) in a one-color way was employed to generate the miRNA expression profiles from the following four groups in duet: hiPSC, hiPSC-RPE at 30, 60, and 90 days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. RNA molecules were initially tailed and labeled with a labeling kit as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>]. An Affmerix GCS3000 Gene Array Scanner with a high resolution 6g patch was then applied to scan the fluorescence on the array [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. Thresholding and signaling scaling were generated using appropriate algorithms as detailed before [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>]. Statistical analysis of miRNA arrays were carried out using hypothetical testing with one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) or Student's t-test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>]. mRNAs targeted by miRNAs with strong validation evidence support, including reporter assay, western blot, and qPCR, were obtained from miTarBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mirtarbase.mbc.nctu.edu.tw/">http://mirtarbase.mbc.nctu.edu.tw/</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Summary mRNA data and sample information of 175 independent RPE-choroid samples were downloaded from GEO datasets. The mRNA expression levels were determined with the Agilent Whole Human Genome Microarray <italic>in situ</italic> oligonucleotide array platform (G4112F, Agilent Technologies Inc., Santa Clara, CA, USA). Microarray hybridization, quantification, and normalization were performed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>]. Data were analyzed and categorized according to different AMD subtypes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_7">
<title>Reagents, cell transfection, and luciferase reporter assay</title>
<p>Human and zebrafish miRNA mimics and inhibitors, including NC mimic, NC inhibitor, hsa-miR-184 mimic, hsa-miR-184 inhibitor, dre-miR-184 mimic, and dre-miR-184 inhibitor, were purchased from GenePharma Co., Ltd (Shanghai, China). Scramble siRNA (NControl_05815) and AKT2-siRNA were purchased from Ribobio (Guangzhou, China). Sequences of mimics, inhibitors, and siRNAs were provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S5</xref>. A fragment from the 3′-UTR of the <italic>AKT2</italic> gene bearing its binding region with has-miR-184 were synthesized and cloned into the firefly pMIR-GLO™ luciferase vector (pMIR, Invitrogen) using <italic>SacI</italic> and <italic>XhoI</italic> restriction sites to construct the recombinant plasmid AKT2<sup>WT</sup> and AKT2<sup>MU</sup>. The AKT2<sup>MU</sup> construct contained 3 mutated nucleotides located in the core binding region of <italic>AKT2</italic> as presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>. Primers for plasmid construction were designed to match the wild type (WT) or mutant <italic>AKT2</italic> sequence at their 3′ moiety and carry restriction sites for endonucleases at their 5′ end (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). The open reading frame (ORF) sequence of <italic>AKT2</italic> was synthesized, amplified, and inserted into the expression vector pCMV-C-Flag (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) using <italic>BamHI</italic> and <italic>XbaI</italic> restriction sites to generate the AcFlag-AKT2 plasmid. Primer information was provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table S3</xref>. Sequences of the constructed plasmids were confirmed by Sanger sequencing.</p>
<p>For transfection assay, cells were seeded into 6-well templates and transfected with 100 pmol mimic/inhibitor/siRNA, and/or 4 μg expression vector, using Lipofectamine<sup>TM</sup> 2000 Transfection reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) per the manufacturers’ protocol. Cells were harvested at 48 hr post transfection for RNA isolation, and at 72 hr post transfection for protein extraction.</p>
<p>Luciferase reporter assay was conducted in previously described way [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>]. For luciferase reporter assay, cells were seeded into 24-well templates and transfected with 16 ng cytomegalovirus (CMV)-Renilla (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), 20 pmol miR-184 mimic or NC-mimic, and 800 ng AKT2<sup>WT</sup> or AKT2<sup>MU</sup>. Cells were collected 72 hr after transfection for luciferase activities measuring with the dual luciferase system (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and a GloMax-96 luminometer. Renilla luciferase activities were taken as internal standard indicators for transfection efficiency. Firefly luciferase activities were then normalized to Renilla luciferase activities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_8">
<title>Immunoblotting</title>
<p>Cells were harvested 72 hr post transfection in ice-cold RIPA buffer (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) containing protease inhibitors cocktail (Roche) for protein extraction. The extracted proteins were then separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE; 10%) and transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride membrane (PVDF; Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). Membranes were blocked for 2 hr at 37°C with 5% skim milk in Tris-buffered saline containing 0.05% Tween 20 (TBST), incubated with designate primary antibodies at 4°C overnight (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>), washed with tris buffered saline with Tween (TBST) for 15 min, and probed with corresponding horse reddish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated secondary antibodies (1:10000 diluted in 1X PBS; ICL Inc., Newberg, OR) for 1 hr at room temperature. After 5 times wash with 1X PBS, the blots were then developed by autoradiography with the ECL-Western blotting system (BioRad, Hercules, CA, USA) according to the manufacturers’ protocols. Protein expressions were determined and quantified using Image J software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/index.html">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/index.html</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_9">
<title>Zebrafish manipulation</title>
<p>Zebrafish manipulation was performed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>]. Embryos at 1- to 2-cell stage (0 dpf) were grouped and injected with 1 nl solution containing 4 μM the abovementioned NC mimic, NC inhibitor, dre-miR-184 mimic, or dre-miR-184-inhibitor, respectively. Embryos died within 24 hours post injection were excluded. At 4 dpf, only zebrafish with relative normal morphology were included for further investigations. Ninety zebrafish from each injected group was collected and pooled for expressional analyses. RNA isolation, RT-PCR, and real-time PCR were carried out to determine the expression levels of dre-miR-184 and several RPE markers. Primer information was provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. Immunofluorescent staining was further employed to determine the expression pattern of the RPE specific protein retinoid isomerohydrolase, which was encoded by the <italic>rpe65</italic> gene. Information of antibody was detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. Thirty zebrafish with normal systemic appearance were randomly selected from each injected group for immunofluorescent staining assay. Fish was fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) overnight at 4°C and dehydrated in 30% sucrose. We then embedded the embryos with optimal cutting temperature solution, frozen in liquid nitrogen for one min, and sectioned using Leica CM1900 cryostat (Leica, Germany). Slides were then used for immunofluorescent staining as mentioned above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_10">
<title>Monitoring cell proliferation and migration</title>
<p>Rates of cell proliferation and migration were monitored in real-time with the xCELLigence system E-Plate (Roche) per the manufacturer's protocol. For proliferation assay, 5000 ARPE-19 cells were seeded into each well and transfected with corresponding mimic/inhibitor at 24 hr post plantation, whereas, for migration analyses, 40000 cells were planted into each well of the CIM-Plate right after transfection. All cells were cultured with fresh DME/F12 medium. Impedance values for all wells were automatically monitored with the xCELLigence system for duration of 48 hr post transfection and expressed as a CI value. Cell proliferative rates were determined by calculating the slope of the line between two given time points.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4_11">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>GraphPad Prism (version 4.0; GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA) was applied for statistical analysis. All presented data were based on biological triplicates. Student's T-test was used for comparison between different groups. Data were shown as mean ± standard deviation (SD), and P value &lt; 0.05 was considered as statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s5" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>SUPPLEMENTARY TABLES</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<media id="d35e1409" mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-s001.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2">
<media id="d35e1411" mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-s002.docx" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3">
<media id="d35e1413" mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-52340-s003.docx" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p>
<bold>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</bold>
</p>
<p>None</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="supported-by">
<p>
<bold>GRANT SUPPORT</bold>
</p>
<p>This work was supported by National Key Basic Research Program of China (2013CB967500 to Chen Zhao); National Natural Science Foundation of China (81525006); Jiangsu Province's Innovation Team (to Chen Zhao); the Fundamental Research Funds of the State Key Laboratory of Ophthalmology (to Chen Zhao); and A Project Funded by the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yasumura</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Matthes</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lloyd</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahern</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bok</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dunaief</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LaVail</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vollrath</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>mTOR-mediated dedifferentiation of the retinal pigment epithelium initiates photoreceptor degeneration in mice</article-title>
<source/>J Clin Invest
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>369</fpage>
<lpage>383</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21135502</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Strauss</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The retinal pigment epithelium in visual function</article-title>
<source/>Physiol Rev
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>845</fpage>
<lpage>881</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987797</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bellur</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grassi</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bowne</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daiger</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pang</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Staley</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Larsson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autosomal-dominant retinitis pigmentosa caused by a mutation in SNRNP200, a gene required for unwinding of U4/U6 snRNAs</article-title>
<source/>Am J Hum Genet
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>617</fpage>
<lpage>627</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19878916</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ambati</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fowler</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of age-related macular degeneration</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>26</fpage>
<lpage>39</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22794258</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Langton</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McKie</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sorsby's fundus dystrophy mutations impair turnover of TIMP-3 by retinal pigment epithelial cells</article-title>
<source/>Hum Mol Genet
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>3579</fpage>
<lpage>3586</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16223891</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gehrs</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>LV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hageman</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Age-related macular degeneration--emerging pathogenetic and therapeutic concepts</article-title>
<source/>Ann Med
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>450</fpage>
<lpage>471</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17101537</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bressler</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Age-related macular degeneration is the leading cause of blindness</article-title>
<source/>JAMA
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>291</volume>
<fpage>1900</fpage>
<lpage>1901</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15108691</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jager</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mieler</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Age-related macular degeneration</article-title>
<source/>N Engl J Med
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>358</volume>
<fpage>2606</fpage>
<lpage>2617</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18550876</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seddon</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holz</surname>
<given-names>FG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Age-related macular degeneration</article-title>
<source/>Lancet
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>379</volume>
<fpage>1728</fpage>
<lpage>1738</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22559899</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dunaief</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dentchev</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ying</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Milam</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The role of apoptosis in age-related macular degeneration</article-title>
<source/>Arch Ophthalmol
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>120</volume>
<fpage>1435</fpage>
<lpage>1442</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12427055</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zarbin</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Current concepts in the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration</article-title>
<source/>Arch Ophthalmol
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>122</volume>
<fpage>598</fpage>
<lpage>614</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15078679</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bartel</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>116</volume>
<fpage>281</fpage>
<lpage>297</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744438</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vasudevan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steitz</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Switching from repression to activation: microRNAs can up-regulate translation</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>318</volume>
<fpage>1931</fpage>
<lpage>1934</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048652</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>MicroRNAs Activate Gene Transcription Epigenetically as an Enhancer Trigger</article-title>
<source/>RNA Biol
          <year>2016</year>
<fpage>0</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>ZY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>XR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development of retinal pigment epithelium from human parthenogenetic embryonic stem cells and microRNA signature</article-title>
<source/>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>5334</fpage>
<lpage>5343</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22736612</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adijanto</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Castorino</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>ZX</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maminishkis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grunwald</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Philp</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Microphthalmia-associated transcription factor (MITF) promotes differentiation of human retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) by regulating microRNAs-204/211 expression</article-title>
<source/>J Biol Chem
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>287</volume>
<fpage>20491</fpage>
<lpage>20503</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22523078</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oliveira-Fernandes</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lavker</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>MicroRNAs of the mammalian eye display distinct and overlapping tissue specificity</article-title>
<source/>Mol Vis
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>1175</fpage>
<lpage>1184</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17102797</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nomura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kimura</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Horii</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morita</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soejima</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kudo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hatada</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>MeCP2-dependent repression of an imprinted miR-184 released by depolarization</article-title>
<source/>Hum Mol Genet
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>1192</fpage>
<lpage>1199</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18203756</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murad</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kokkinaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gunawardena</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gunawan</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hathout</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Janczura</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Theos</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Golestaneh</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>miR-184 regulates ezrin, LAMP-1 expression, affects phagocytosis in human retinal pigment epithelium and is downregulated in age-related macular degeneration</article-title>
<source/>FEBS J
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>281</volume>
<fpage>5251</fpage>
<lpage>5264</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25251993</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shalom-Feuerstein</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Serror</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De La Forest Divonne</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petit</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aberdam</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Camargo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Damour</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vigouroux</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Solomon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gaggioli</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Itskovitz-Eldor</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aberdam</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pluripotent stem cell model reveals essential roles for miR-450b-5p and miR-184 in embryonic corneal lineage specification</article-title>
<source/>Stem Cells
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>898</fpage>
<lpage>909</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22367714</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Localized expression pattern of miR-184 in Drosophila</article-title>
<source/>Mol Biol Rep
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>355</fpage>
<lpage>358</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20339929</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Osakada</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>ZB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hirami</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ikeda</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Danjyo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sasai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>In vitro differentiation of retinal cells from human pluripotent stem cells by small-molecule induction</article-title>
<source/>J Cell Sci
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>122</volume>
<fpage>3169</fpage>
<lpage>3179</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19671662</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chou</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>NW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shrestha</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tu</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jian</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>miRTarBase 2016: updates to the experimentally validated miRNA-target interactions database</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>D239</fpage>
<lpage>247</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590260</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Foley</surname>
<given-names>NH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bray</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tivnan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bryan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buckley</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O'Meara</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O'sullivan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stallings</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>MicroRNA-184 inhibits neuroblastoma cell survival through targeting the serine/threonine kinase AKT2</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cancer
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20409325</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shykind</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Approaches to manipulating microRNAs in neurogenesis</article-title>
<source/>Front Neurosci
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>196</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23335878</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martinez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patkaniowska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Urlaub</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luhrmann</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuschl</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Single-stranded antisense siRNAs guide target RNA cleavage in RNAi</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>563</fpage>
<lpage>574</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12230974</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aitken</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tolg</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Panchal</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leslie</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Elkelini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sabha</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lorenzo</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hassouna</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bagli</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) induces proliferation and de-differentiation responses to three coordinate pathophysiologic stimuli (mechanical strain, hypoxia, and extracellular matrix remodeling) in rat bladder smooth muscle</article-title>
<source/>Am J Pathol
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>176</volume>
<fpage>304</fpage>
<lpage>319</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20019183</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De Santis</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Braccini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gulluni</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hirsch</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>PI3K/AKT signaling pathway and cancer: an updated review</article-title>
<source/>Ann Med
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>372</fpage>
<lpage>383</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24897931</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Petrulea</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Plantinga</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smit</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Georgescu</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Netea-Maier</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>PI3K/Akt/mTOR: A promising therapeutic target for non-medullary thyroid carcinoma</article-title>
<source/>Cancer Treat Rev
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>707</fpage>
<lpage>713</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26138515</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dean</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Taz-tead1 links cell-cell contact to zeb1 expression, proliferation, and dedifferentiation in retinal pigment epithelial cells</article-title>
<source/>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>3372</fpage>
<lpage>3378</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20207963</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<label>31</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gallo</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hancox</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radeke</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maloney</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hageman</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>LV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radeke</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Systems-level analysis of age-related macular degeneration reveals global biomarkers and phenotype-specific functional networks</article-title>
<source/>Genome Med
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>16</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22364233</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<label>32</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dridi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hirano</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tarallo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fowler</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ambati</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bogdanovich</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chiodo</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hauswirth</surname>
<given-names>WW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kugel</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goodrich</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ponicsan</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hinton</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kleinman</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baffi</surname>
<given-names>JZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gelfand</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>ERK1/2 activation is a therapeutic target in age-related macular degeneration</article-title>
<source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>13781</fpage>
<lpage>13786</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22869729</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<label>33</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sundermeier</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Palczewski</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The impact of microRNA gene regulation on the survival and function of mature cell types in the eye</article-title>
<source/>FASEB J
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>
<lpage>33</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26399786</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<label>34</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>SX</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>LZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>YZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>RZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>CZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yun</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>FoxD3-regulated microRNA-137 suppresses tumour growth and metastasis in human hepatocellular carcinoma by targeting AKT2</article-title>
<source/>Oncotarget
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>5113</fpage>
<lpage>5124</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.2089</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24970808</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<label>35</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hughes</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bradley</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lechner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dash</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Willoughby</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mutation altering the miR-184 seed region causes familial keratoconus with cataract</article-title>
<source/>Am J Hum Genet
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>628</fpage>
<lpage>633</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21996275</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<label>36</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lechner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bae</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guduric-Fuchs</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Govindarajan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Siddiqui</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abi Farraj</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yip</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yap</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Souzeau</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coster</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lindsay</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mutational analysis of MIR184 in sporadic keratoconus and myopia</article-title>
<source/>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>5266</fpage>
<lpage>5272</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23833072</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R37">
<label>37</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ikeda</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osakada</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mizuseki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haraguchi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miyoshi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kamiya</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Honda</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sasai</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yoshimura</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sasai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Generation of Rx+/Pax6+ neural retinal precursors from embryonic stem cells</article-title>
<source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>11331</fpage>
<lpage>11336</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16076961</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R38">
<label>38</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sheng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tam</surname>
<given-names>PO</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rong</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vollrath</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pang</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>PRPF4 mutations cause autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa</article-title>
<source/>Hum Mol Genet
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>2926</fpage>
<lpage>2939</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24419317</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R39">
<label>39</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calin</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meloon</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gamliel</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sevignani</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferracin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dumitru</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shimizu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zupo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dono</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alder</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bullrich</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Negrini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Croce</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>An oligonucleotide microchip for genome-wide microRNA profiling in human and mouse tissues</article-title>
<source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>9740</fpage>
<lpage>9744</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15210942</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R40">
<label>40</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vos</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bonnerup</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Atkins</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Casey</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nuovo</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Naziri</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wiley</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mota</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Allison</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Diagnostic microRNA markers to screen for sporadic human colon cancer in stool: I. Proof of principle</article-title>
<source/>Cancer Genomics Proteomics
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>93</fpage>
<lpage>113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23741026</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R41">
<label>41</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Microarray RNA transcriptional profiling: part II. Analytical considerations and annotation</article-title>
<source/>Expert Rev Mol Diagn
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>703</fpage>
<lpage>715</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17009905</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R42">
<label>42</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Staley</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Knocking Down Snrnp200 Initiates Demorphogenesis of Rod Photoreceptors in Zebrafish</article-title>
<source/>J Ophthalmol
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>2015</volume>
<fpage>816329</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26137319</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R43">
<label>43</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tam</surname>
<given-names>PO</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vollrath</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pang</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SPP2 Mutations Cause Autosomal Dominant Retinitis Pigmentosa</article-title>
<source/>Sci Rep
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>14867</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26459573</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>