<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9815831</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">22061</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genet Med</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genet. Med.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Genetics in medicine : official journal of the American College of Medical Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1098-3600</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-0366</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27441995</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5253131</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/gim.2016.83</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS791388</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Macrocephaly associated with the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>Nicholas E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bauer</surname>
<given-names>Andrew J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Doros</surname>
<given-names>Leslie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>Kris Ann P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Decastro</surname>
<given-names>Rosamma M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harney</surname>
<given-names>Laura A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kase</surname>
<given-names>Ron G.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carr</surname>
<given-names>Ann G.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>Anne K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>Gretchen M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dehner</surname>
<given-names>Louis P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Messinger</surname>
<given-names>Yoav H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>Douglas R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Clinical Genetics Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, Rockville, MD</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Children's National Medical Center, Washington, D.C.</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>International Pleuropulmonary Blastoma Registry, Minneapolis, MN</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>International Ovarian and Testicular Stromal Tumor Registry, Minneapolis, MN</aff>
<aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Westat Inc., Rockville, MD</aff>
<aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Washington University, St. Louis, MO</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author and person to whom reprint requests should be addressed: Douglas R Stewart, MD, 9609 Medical Center Drive Rm 6E450, Bethesda, MD, 20892; Phone: 240-276-7238, Fax: 240-276-7836, <email>drstewart@mail.nih.gov</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>13</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>21</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>06</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>244</fpage>
<lpage>248</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/gim.2016.83-->
<permissions>
<license xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">
<license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Background</title>
<p id="P1">Germline mutations in <italic>DICER1</italic> increase the risk of various tumors, including pleuropulmonary blastoma. Macrocephaly and symmetric overgrowth has been reported in some, but not all, patients with mosaic <italic>DICER1</italic> RNase IIIb mutations; the prevalence of these features in individuals with constitutional germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations is unknown.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P2">We analyzed prospectively collected auxology data from 67 <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers and 43 family controls. We assessed differences between groups using an exact test for proportions and generalized estimating equations for continuous dependent variables.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">Twenty-eight <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers (42%) were macrocephalic, and none had an occipital-frontal circumference (OFC) below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile, which significantly differed from family controls, of whom five were macrocephalic (12%) and two had OFC below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile (5%) (P&lt;0.001). <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers were taller than familial controls after controlling for gender (P=0.048), but similar proportions of both groups were above the 97<sup>th</sup> centile of population norms. Head circumference remained increased after adjusting for differences in height.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P4">For the first time, we establish macrocephaly as a common finding in the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome. Like some of the other tumor-predisposition disorders, macrocephaly may be a useful, albeit a subtle, clinical clue to the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome diagnosis.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<title>Key terms</title>
<kwd>
<italic>DICER1</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>macrocephaly</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S5" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="P5">Pleuropulmonary blastoma (PPB), an embryonal sarcoma and the most common pediatric primary lung malignancy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>, is the hallmark tumor of the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. Somatic second hits in one of five “hotspot” amino acids of the <italic>DICER1</italic> RNase IIIb domain are necessary for malignant transformation of PPB and other <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated tumors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. Germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations are also associated with a variety of other neoplasms, including cystic nephroma, nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma, ciliary body medulloepithelioma, pituitary blastoma, as well as Sertoli-Leydig cell tumor and other ovarian sex cord-stromal tumors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="P6">PPB is a serious complication of the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome. PPB progresses through stages of malignant transformation, from type I (cystic) to type II (partially cystic/solid) and type III (solid). The 5-year overall survival for later-stage patients is 71% (type II) and 53% (type III). Relapse and metastasis, primarily to the central nervous system, is responsible for much of the mortality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. Fortunately, early detection and subsequent surgical resection of PPB can be curative<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. However, this is feasible only if <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers are identified, and screened (by chest CT), as early in life as possible.</p>
<p id="P7">The presence of easily detected, non-malignant phenotypic features can prompt alert clinicians to consider the diagnosis of an occult tumor-predisposition disorder in an otherwise healthy child. For example, the distinctive skin findings and increased head circumference in neurofibromatosis type 1 and Cowden syndrome may appear prior to any syndrome-associated neoplasia. In the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome, lung cysts, cystic nephroma or family history of multinodular goiter have been used to identify <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers (hereafter, “<italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers”) prior to the development of malignancy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. Since the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome was relatively recently recognized, systematic evaluations of growth have not been reported, although there have been accounts of developmental delay, macrocephaly and overgrowth in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> patients with mosaic <italic>DICER1</italic> “hotspot” RNase IIIb mutations. Other accounts have not reported overgrowth or developmental delay in these patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. In our natural history study of the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome, we comprehensively evaluated individuals with germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations and family controls. We analyzed auxology data, particularly head circumference and height measurements, from our cohort to characterize previously unrecognized <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated disease features that may be useful in identifying individuals and families at risk of PPB.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="S7">
<title>Study participants</title>
<p id="P8">The National Cancer Institute protocol “<italic>DICER1</italic>-related pleuropulmonary blastoma cancer predisposition syndrome: a natural history study” (NCI protocol 11-C-0034; NCT #01257597) is open to individuals with <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated tumors and their family members. One hundred thirty-four participants from 31 families were evaluated at the NIH Clinical Center (CC) between November 2011 and December 2014. CLIA-certified germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation testing was conducted at Ambry Genetics (Aliso Viejo, CA) and Children’s National Medical Center (Washington, DC). Five children without detectable germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations but who harbored <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated tumors were considered separately. We compared individuals carrying pathogenic germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations (n=76) with unaffected family members lacking pathogenic <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations (n=53). The study was approved by the National Cancer Institute’s institutional review board, and all participants, or their parents or guardians, provided written, informed consent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Dysmorphology and reference curves</title>
<p id="P9">Height was measured by clinical staff at the NIH CC using stadiometers. Head occipitofrontal circumference (OFC), arm span, and lower segment length were recorded using measuring tapes, as described by Gripp <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Upper segment length was calculated by subtracting lower segment length (distance from top of pubic symphysis to floor) from height. The upper segment length/lower segment length (US/LS) ratio was then calculated. We compared observed measurements with age- and gender-appropriate reference charts for height<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> and OFC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. OFC and height are strongly correlated, and we used OFC-for-height references for those age 18 years and older<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. We considered abnormal height to be below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile or above the 97<sup>th</sup> centile, and macrocephaly as greater than the 97<sup>th</sup> centile in published reference populations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S9">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p id="P10">We tested differences in proportions using either a chi-squared test or an exact test when frequencies were low (n&lt;5). We assessed differences in continuous descriptive characteristics using the Wilcoxon rank-sum test. We fit generalized estimating equations (GEE) to the continuous measurements of OFC and height in adults to account for correlation within families, and used robust standard errors. All tests were two-sided; we considered P&lt;0.05 significant, and analyses were performed using Stata/SE 13.1 (Stata Corp., College Station, TX, USA).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S10" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P11">Individuals (n=19) were excluded from our analyses due to missing data on any of the following: OFC (n=14), US/LS ratio (n=11), or arm span (n=9). The remaining 110 participants comprised the analytic dataset. Cohort demographics are described in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Table 1</xref>.</p>
<sec id="S11">
<title>Macrocephaly was more frequent in DICER1-carriers compared with family controls</title>
<p id="P12"><italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers differed from family controls in the distribution of head circumference (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>): 28 <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers (42%) were macrocephalic, and none had an OFC below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile, <italic>versus</italic> family controls, of whom five were macrocephalic (12%) and two had OFC below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile (5%) (P&lt;0.001). This difference between <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers and controls remained significant after stratification by gender. Seventeen females with a <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation (50%) were macrocephalic, and none had an OFC below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile, <italic>versus</italic> three controls with macrocephaly (20%) and two with OFC &lt;3<sup>rd</sup> centile (13%) (P=0.024). Similarly, 11 males with a <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation (33%) were macrocephalic compared with only two controls (7%) (P=0.026). When plotted against the reference curves published in Rollins <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>, OFC was systematically increased in <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers compared with both population norms and family controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B–C</xref>). Among those age ≥ 18 years, <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers had a 2.25 cm increase in OFC (95% CI=1.2 - 3.3; P&lt;0.001), after adjusting for gender. We did not estimate the magnitude of the increase in children because the small number of pediatric controls precluded modeling of the non-linear relationship between age and OFC. However, 8 <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers age &lt; 18 years (25%) were macrocephalic compared with one control age &lt; 18 years (10%), though the difference was not statistically significant (P=0.219). The five children with a <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated tumor but no detectable <italic>DICER1</italic> germline mutation had a distribution of OFC similar to that of family controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B–C</xref>). OFC did not correlate with <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation location or type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure S1 and Supplemental Table S2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S12">
<title>There were no differences in height between DICER1-carriers and controls</title>
<p id="P13">Although <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers were taller than familial controls after controlling for gender (P=0.048), the proportion of individuals with height &gt;97<sup>th</sup> general population centile was similar between <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers (12%) and controls (7%) (P=0.52) (data not shown). Tall stature was not more prevalent in either females (P=0.414) or males (P=1.0) with the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome. The <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome in adults was not associated with greater height after adjusting for gender (difference=2.5cm, 95% CI=−1.0 – 6.1; P=0.160).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S13">
<title>Larger head circumference in DICER1-carriers was independent from differences in height</title>
<p id="P14">As noted above, OFC and height are strongly correlated in the general population. Using the reference curves from Bushby <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> that adjust for height among those age ≥16 years, the distribution of OFC-for-height among adults (age ≥18 years) with <italic>DICER1</italic> differed significantly from that of family controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). Ten adults with the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome (29%) had an OFC &gt; 97<sup>th</sup> centile and none had an OFC &lt;3<sup>rd</sup> centile, <italic>versus</italic> two controls with OFC &gt; 97<sup>th</sup> centile (6%) and two controls with OFC &lt;3<sup>rd</sup> centile (6%) (P=0.017). Stratifying by gender did not detect significant differences between groups. Eight women with <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome (33%) had an OFC&gt;97<sup>th</sup> centile and none with OFC &lt;3<sup>rd</sup> centile compared with one woman control (9%) with OFC&gt;97<sup>th</sup> centile and two (18%) with OFC &lt;3<sup>rd</sup> centile (P=0.065). Two males with the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome had OFC &gt;97<sup>th</sup> centile (18%) compared with one male control (5%) (P=0.25). Qualitatively, OFC-for-height in <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers was larger than expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B–C</xref>). Among adults, the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome was associated with an average increase in OFC of 1.92 cm (95% CI=1.1–2.8; P&lt;0.001) after adjusting for gender and height.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S14">
<title>Arm span/height ratio and long bone growth in the DICER1 syndrome were proportional</title>
<p id="P15">No significant differences in the US/LS or arm span/height ratios were observed. The US/LS ratio of <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers (mean = 0.977; SD=0.087) was similar to that of family controls (mean=0.950; SD=0.087) (P=0.443) among those age 18 years and older. The relationship between arm span and height were linear, as is expected in the general population, and no significant differences were observed between <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers (mean=1.022; SD=0.043) and controls (mean= 1.024; SD=0.028) (P=0.747). Neither adjustment for gender or age meaningfully affected the results (data not shown).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S15" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="P16">In our study, macrocephaly was observed in 42% of <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers evaluated at the NIH CC. Other growth measurements were normal relative to the general population, <italic>i.e., DICER1</italic>-carriers were not abnormally tall, but adults with <italic>DICER1</italic> were taller on average compared with family controls. After adjusting for these differences in height, the association between macrocephaly and <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation status persisted. Measurements of long bone growth (arm span/height and US/LS ratios) were within normal ranges.</p>
<p id="P17">In mice <italic>Dicer1</italic> is a haploinsufficient tumor-suppressor gene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>; our data show for the first time that human macrocephaly is a phenotype significantly associated with <italic>DICER1</italic> haploinsufficiency. In the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome, the macrocephaly is relatively (but not disproportionately) increased and is not associated with somatic overgrowth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. Klein <italic>et al.</italic> reported macrocephaly and symmetric overgrowth in two children with mosaic missense “hotspot” mutations in the RNase IIIb domain of <italic>DICER1</italic>, along with developmental delay and Wilms tumor, in a constellation of findings they termed the “GLOW” (Global developmental delay, Lung cysts, Overgrowth and Wilms tumor) syndrome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. The authors also identified ten candidate dysregulated 3p microRNAs that target negative regulators of the mTOR, TGF-β and MAPK signaling pathways, including <italic>PTEN, TSC</italic> and <italic>NF1</italic>. They hypothesize that an imbalance in specific 3p microRNAs arising from the <italic>DICER1</italic> RNase IIIb mutations lead to excessive cell and tissue growth and tumor predisposition. Mosaic <italic>DICER1</italic> RNase IIIb domain mutations are associated with a more severe neoplastic phenotype<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. Many of the “GLOW” phenotype features, including macrocephaly and overgrowth, were not observed in a set of four patients with mosaic <italic>DICER1</italic> RNase IIIb mutations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. The differences in these studies may be attributable to the pleiotropy and phenotypic variability inherent in mosaicism and highlight the need for a systematic, statistically-grounded approach to syndrome delineation.</p>
<p id="P18">It is well-known that haploinsufficiency of <italic>PTEN</italic> (Cowden, Bannayan-Riley-Ruvalcaba syndromes) and <italic>NF1</italic> (neurofibromatosis type 1) is associated with macrocephaly. It is interesting to note that these genes are also dysregulated in <italic>DICER1</italic> mosaicism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. Increased head circumference in NF1 is hypothesized to be a secondary skeletal manifestation of brain overgrowth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>, presumably due to dysregulation of key growth pathways. The often-pronounced macrocephaly in these disorders can be a useful clinical clue to their diagnosis. The role of these genes as intermediaries of posited brain overgrowth with secondary skeletal growth in the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome phenotype merits further study.</p>
<p id="P19">Our analysis is limited by the biases inherent in using cross-sectional data to assess growth. Longitudinal analyses are needed to discern when OFC increases, and would inform future studies into the underlying mechanism of this growth. Moreover, families enrolled in the study were accessioned because of a history of a <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated tumor. Ascertainment bias may have missed clinically asymptomatic <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers with milder phenotypes. Lastly, measurements were made by multiple observers rather than a single physician. However, the measurements of OFC, arm span, and height are unlikely to vary substantially enough between observers to account for the large difference observed in <italic>DICER1</italic>-carriers in this study.</p>
<p id="P20">In summary, our study is the first to document macrocephaly as a non-neoplastic feature of the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome. Further analyses of longitudinal data may shed light on the developmental processes underlying the macrocephaly, and point to the role of <italic>DICER1</italic> in auxology. Like other better-known tumor-predisposition disorders, macrocephaly may be a useful, if subtle, clinical clue to the diagnoses of the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="SM" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<label>Supplementary _Appendix_ online only material_ etc.__1</label>
<media id="d36e756" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS791388-supplement-Supplementary___Appendix__online_only_material__etc___1.doc" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2">
<label>Supplementary _Appendix_ online only material_ etc.__2</label>
<media id="d36e760" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS791388-supplement-Supplementary___Appendix__online_only_material__etc___2.pptx" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN1">
<p id="P21"><bold>Disclosure Statement:</bold> The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ack id="S16">
<p id="P22">We thank D. Ashley Hill, MD (Children’s National Medical Center, Washington, DC) for <italic>DICER1</italic> sequencing. This work was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics of the National Cancer Institute, Rockville, MD.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dishop</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuruvilla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Primary and metastatic lung tumors in the pediatric population: a review and 25-year experience at a large children's hospital</article-title>
<source/>Arch Pathol Lab Med
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>132</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>1079</fpage>
<lpage>1103</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18605764</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ivanovich</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Priest</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>DICER1 mutations in familial pleuropulmonary blastoma</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>325</volume>
<issue>5943</issue>
<fpage>965</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19556464</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pugh</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Exome sequencing of pleuropulmonary blastoma reveals frequent biallelic loss of TP53 and two hits in DICER1 resulting in retention of 5p-derived miRNA hairpin loop sequences</article-title>
<source/>Oncogene
          <year>2014</year>
<comment>0</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Messinger</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartomas arise secondary to germline and somatic mutations of DICER1 in the pleuropulmonary blastoma tumor predisposition disorder</article-title>
<source/>Hum Genet
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>133</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>1443</fpage>
<lpage>1450</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25118636</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Doros</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Pagon</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title><italic>DICER1</italic>-related disorders</article-title>
<source/>GeneReviews
          <year>2014</year>
<publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>University of Washington</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Messinger</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Priest</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pleuropulmonary blastoma: a report on 350 central pathology-confirmed pleuropulmonary blastoma cases by the International Pleuropulmonary Blastoma Registry</article-title>
<source/>Cancer
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>121</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>276</fpage>
<lpage>285</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25209242</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Priest</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Magnuson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cerebral metastasis and other central nervous system complications of pleuropulmonary blastoma</article-title>
<source/>Pediatr Blood Cancer
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>49</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>266</fpage>
<lpage>273</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16807914</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Judicious DICER1 testing and surveillance imaging facilitates early diagnosis and cure of pleuropulmonary blastoma</article-title>
<source/>Pediatr Blood Cancer
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>61</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<fpage>1695</fpage>
<lpage>1697</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24821309</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rath</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bartley</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Charles</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Multinodular Goiter in children: an important pointer to a germline DICER1 mutation</article-title>
<source/>The Journal of clinical endocrinology and metabolism
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>99</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1947</fpage>
<lpage>1948</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24628552</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ghahremani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Expanding the phenotype of mutations in DICER1: mosaic missense mutations in the RNase IIIb domain of DICER1 cause GLOW syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J Med Genet
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>294</fpage>
<lpage>302</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24676357</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Kock</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Revil</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>High-sensitivity sequencing reveals multi-organ somatic mosaicism causing DICER1 syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J Med Genet
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>53</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>43</fpage>
<lpage>52</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26475046</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gripp</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Slavotinek</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Allanson</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source/>Handbook of Physical Measurements
          <year>2013</year>
<publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ogden</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuczmarski</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flegal</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention 2000 growth charts for the United States: improvements to the 1977 National Center for Health Statistics version</article-title>
<source/>Pediatrics
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>109</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>60</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11773541</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rollins</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Collins</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holden</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>United States head circumference growth reference charts: birth to 21 years</article-title>
<source/>J Pediatr
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>156</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>907</fpage>
<lpage>913</lpage>
<comment>913 e901-902</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20304425</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bushby</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goodship</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Centiles for adult head circumference</article-title>
<source/>Arch Dis Child
          <year>1992</year>
<volume>67</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>1286</fpage>
<lpage>1287</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1444530</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pester</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dicer1 functions as a haploinsufficient tumor suppressor</article-title>
<source/>Genes Dev
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>23</issue>
<fpage>2700</fpage>
<lpage>2704</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19903759</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sharifi-Hannauer</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martinez-Agosto</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Macrocephaly as a clinical indicator of genetic subtypes in autism</article-title>
<source/>Autism Res
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>56</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23361946</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brenneman</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Temporal order of RNase IIIb and loss-of-function mutations during development determines phenotype in DICER1 syndrome: a unique variant of the two-hit tumor suppression model</article-title>
<source/>F1000 Research
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>214</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26925222</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gutmann</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacCollin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riccardi</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source/>Neurofibromatosis: Phenotype, Natural History and Pathogenesis
          <year>1999</year>
<edition>Third</edition>
<publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p id="P23">Occipital-frontal circumference-for-age in the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome. (A) Abnormal OFC-for-age. Proportions between the 3<sup>rd</sup> and 97<sup>th</sup> centiles (white), below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile (gray), or above the 97<sup>th</sup> centile (black) in <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers and family controls. P values are for Fisher’s exact test of differences between groups. (B) Females. Red triangles indicate <italic>DICER1</italic>-mutation carriers. White diamonds represent family controls. Blue circles represent girls without a detectable germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation but who harbor a <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated tumor (7-year-old: type II PPB; 15.5-year-old: Sertoli-Leydig cell tumor; 17-year-old: type II PPB). The dashed lines indicate the 97<sup>th</sup>, 50<sup>th</sup>, and 3<sup>rd</sup> centiles of OFC-for-age reported in Rollins, 2010. The vertical dashed line at age 10 years indicates a change in the scale of the x-axis to allow for better resolution of children’s values. (C) Males. Blue circles represent boys without a detectable germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation but who harbor at least one <italic>DICER1</italic>-associated tumor (4-year-old: type I PPB and cystic nephroma; 7.7-year-old: type II PPB only). OFC = occipital-frontal circumference.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms791388f1a"></graphic>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms791388f1b"></graphic>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms791388f1c"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p id="P24">Occipital-frontal circumference-for-height in the <italic>DICER1</italic> syndrome (mutation carriers and controls ≥ 18 years). (A) Abnormal head circumference-for-height. Proportions between the 3<sup>rd</sup> and 97<sup>th</sup> centiles (white), below the 3<sup>rd</sup> centile (gray), or above the 97<sup>th</sup> centile (black) in <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers and family controls. P values are for Fisher’s exact test of differences between groups. (B) Females. Red triangles indicate <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation carriers. White diamonds represent family controls. The dashed lines indicate the 97<sup>th</sup>, 50<sup>th</sup>, and 3<sup>rd</sup> centiles of OFC-for-height reported in Bushby <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992. (C) Males. OFC = occipital-frontal circumference.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms791388f2a"></graphic>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms791388f2b"></graphic>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms791388f2c"></graphic>
</fig>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>