<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="letter" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hum Genome Var</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hum Genome Var</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Human Genome Variation</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2054-345X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28224041</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5298938</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pii">hgv20171</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hgv.2017.1</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Data Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A 7q31.33q32.1 microdeletion including <italic>LRRC4</italic> and <italic>GRM8</italic> is associated with severe intellectual disability and characteristics of autism</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running">A 7q31.33q32.1 microdeletion including <italic>LRRC4</italic> and <italic>GRM8</italic></alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sangu</surname>
<given-names>Noriko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shimojima</surname>
<given-names>Keiko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>Yuya</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ohashi</surname>
<given-names>Tsukasa</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tohyama</surname>
<given-names>Jun</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yamamoto</surname>
<given-names>Toshiyuki</given-names>
</name>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9484-3505</contrib-id>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Medical Genetics, Tokyo Women’s Medical University</institution>, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Tokyo Women’s Medical University</institution>, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Pediatrics, Nagaoka Red Cross Hospital</institution>, Nagaoka, <country>Japan</country></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Pediatrics, Niigata University Medical and Dental Hospital</institution>, Niigata, <country>Japan</country></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Child Neurology, Epilepsy Center, Nishi-Niigata Chuo National Hospital</institution>, Niigata, <country>Japan</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>
(<email>yamamoto.toshiyuki@twmu.ac.jp</email>)</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>09</day>
<month>02</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>17001</fpage>
<lpage></lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>21</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>17</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--author-paid-->
<license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A 4-year-old boy with severe intellectual disability (ID) and characteristics of autism was found to have a <italic>de novo</italic> 1.9-Mb microdeletion in 7q31.33q32.1, in which <italic>LRRC4</italic>, <italic>GRM8</italic>, and 11 other genes were included. <italic>GRM8</italic> is associated with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. <italic>LRRC4</italic> is related to synaptic cell adhesion molecules, some of which are associated with autism. The deletion of <italic>LRRC4</italic> may be responsible for the severe ID and characteristics of autism observed in the present patient.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Interstitial deletions encompassing the 7q31 region are rare, and there are few reports of affected patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup> We identified a <italic>de novo</italic> 1.9-Mb deletion in a patient with severe intellectual disability and characteristics of autism. Here, we report the patient’s clinical characteristics and discuss the genotype–phenotype correlation.</p>
<p>The boy, who was 4 years and 7 months old, was born to non-consanguineous healthy Japanese parents. There were no remarkable episodes during pregnancy. There was no family history of neurodevelopmental disorders. His two older sisters are healthy. He was born at 38 weeks and 5 days of gestation by cesarean section and weighed 4,180 g (&gt;97th percentile). Just after birth, he showed poor sucking. Developmental delays had been noted since early infancy; head control occurred at 7 months, sitting occurred at 18 months, and walking alone occurred at 2 years and 3 months. On the basis of the Enjoji developmental test, his developmental quotient was evaluated as 19 at 3 years of age, thus indicating severe intellectual disability. Behaviors related to attention deficit and/or hyperkinetic disorder was rarely observed. Instead, he exhibited stereotyped motions, with head swinging, turning around in circles in the same place, and self-injuring by banging his head on the floor. He often exhibited a panicked state when he did not get things in the way that he wanted. He was not shy, but he showed poor eye contact. Sleep disturbance was frequently observed. These findings were considered to be characteristics of autism (a formal examination could not be performed, owing to severe intellectual disability). He experienced an episode of afebrile seizure with generalized tonic convulsion at the age of 3 years and 4 months.</p>
<p>At present, his height is 102.1 cm (25–50th percentile), his weight is 16.2 kg (25–50th percentile), and his occipitofrontal circumference is 50.0 cm (25–50th percentile), thus indicating proportional stature. His facial features are not distinctive. He still cannot speak any meaningful words. He uses diapers because of incontinence. Assistance in his daily life activities, including getting dressed and eating, is required.</p>
<p>This study was approved by the ethics committee of Tokyo Women’s Medical University. After written informed consent had been obtained from the patient’s family, peripheral blood samples were obtained from the patient and his parents. Genomic DNA was extracted with a QIAquick DNA extraction kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). Chromosomal microarray testing was performed with an Agilent 60 K Human Genome CGH Microarray platform (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA), as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup> Next, a genomic copy number loss at the 7q31.33 region [arr 7q31.33q32.1(125,875,286–127,816,631)×1] was identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). The deletion length was 1.9 Mb, and 13 RefSeq genes were included in the deletion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). The same deletion was not detected in the parental samples through microarray testing, thus indicating a <italic>de novo</italic> occurrence. These data have been registered as #332875 in the DECIPHER database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://decipher.sanger.ac.uk/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://decipher.sanger.ac.uk/</ext-link>). The data presented by the UCSC genome browser are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> for comparison.</p>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, there were some overlapping deletions in the DECIPHER database; however, informed consent and detailed clinical information of the registered patients were unavailable. Therefore, we were not able to perform a genotype–phenotype correlation study using the data included in the DECIPHER database. In addition, we found only two reports of overlapping deletions in the literature. One of the deletions was derived from complex chromosomal translocations;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> the deletion was large and included the deletion region identified in the present patient. The other overlapping deletion coexisted with a 17q21.31 microduplication.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup> The phenotypic features of these patients with complicated chromosomal abnormalities were inappropriate for use in a genotype–phenotype correlation study.</p>
<p>The deletion identified in this study included 13 RefSeq genes. According to RefSeq gene information (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>), only the paired box 4 gene (<italic>PAX4</italic>) is related to the OMIM phenotype (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://omim.org/</ext-link>); the <italic>PAX4</italic> mutation is related to autosomal dominant diabetes mellitus type 2 (MIM #125853).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup> At present, there have been no symptoms of diabetes mellitus in this patient. Careful observation is required to identify these symptoms.</p>
<p>In addition to <italic>PAX4</italic>, the leucine-rich repeat containing 4 gene (<italic>LRRC4</italic>) and the glutamate receptor metabotropic 8 gene (<italic>GRM8</italic>) showed some functional relevance to neurological features. Elia <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref></sup> have performed a large cohort study on patients with attention deficit and/or hyperkinetic disorder, and have identified statistically significant findings of copy number variations, including genes related to glutamate receptor gene networks and G-protein-coupled receptors involved in modulating excitatory synaptic transmission. Some reports have also suggested a relationship between copy number variations in glutamate receptor gene regions and attention deficit and/or hyperkinetic disorder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> A partial duplication of <italic>GRM8</italic> has been identified in an individual with autism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> On the basis of these findings, copy number changes in <italic>GRM8</italic> may be related to neurodevelopmental disorders. More recently, <italic>GRM8</italic> has been reported to be associated with psychiatric disorders.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9 bib10 bib11">9–11</xref></sup> However, the clinical features of the present patient are more severe than those observed in patients with such neuropsychiatric disorders.</p>
<p>Another candidate gene, <italic>LRRC4</italic>, consists of only one exon, and encodes a 653-amino-acid-long protein. <italic>LRRC4</italic> is a member of the synaptic cell adhesion molecule family. The netrin-G ligands (NGLs) belong to the superfamily of leucine-rich repeat (LRR) proteins. Three known members of the NGL family, NGL-1 (LRRC4C), NGL-2 (LRRC4), and NGL-3 (LRRC4B), localize mainly to the postsynaptic side of the excitatory synapse and interact with the presynaptic ligands including netrin-G1, netrin-G2, and leukocyte antigen-related.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup> The NGL-dependent adhesion system is important for the development of axons, dendrites, and synapses. Consistently with these functions, defects in NGLs and their ligands are associated with impaired learning/memory and hyperactivity. Many synaptic proteins and receptors are defective in patients with autism, thus strongly suggesting that the heterozygous deletion of <italic>LRRC4</italic> is a possible explanation for the severe intellectual disability and characteristics of autism observed in the present patient.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>In conclusion, the identified 7q31.33 deletion was considered to be a pathogenic copy number loss in the present patient.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to express our gratitude to the patient and his parents for their cooperation. We also acknowledge the DECIPHER database for checking overlapping deletions. We are grateful to the technicians from our laboratories, including Ms Yumiko Ondo for her skillful help. This research was supported by the Practical Research Project for Rare/Intractable Diseases from the Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development (AMED), and the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) KAKENHI grant number 15K09631 (TY).</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="bib1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tyson C, McGillivray B, Chijiwa C, Rajcan-Separovic E. <article-title>Elucidation of a cryptic interstitial 7q31.3 deletion in a patient with a language disorder and mild mental retardation by array-CGH</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet A
<year>2004</year>; <volume>129A</volume>: <fpage>254</fpage>–260.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15326624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mc Cormack A, Taylor J, Te Weehi L, Love DR, George AM. <article-title>A case of 17q21.31 microduplication and 7q31.33 microdeletion, associated with developmental delay, microcephaly, and mild dysmorphic features</article-title>. <source/>Case Rep Genet
<year>2014</year>; <volume>2014</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sangu N, Okamoto N, Shimojima K, Ondo Y, Nishikawa M, Yamamoto T. <article-title>A <italic>de novo</italic> microdeletion in a patient with inner ear abnormalities suggests that the 10q26.13 region contains the responsible gene</article-title>. <source/>Hum Genome Var
<year>2016</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>16008</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27274859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mauvais-Jarvis F, Smith SB, Le May C, Leal SM, Gautier JF, Molokhia M et al. <article-title>PAX4 gene variations predispose to ketosis-prone diabetes</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<year>2004</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>3151</fpage>–3159.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509590</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Elia J, Glessner JT, Wang K, Takahashi N, Shtir CJ, Hadley D et al. <article-title>Genome-wide copy number variation study associates metabotropic glutamate receptor gene networks with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet
<year>2012</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>–84.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Akutagava-Martins GC, Salatino-Oliveira A, Genro JP, Contini V, Polanczyk G, Zeni C et al. <article-title>Glutamatergic copy number variants and their role in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet
<year>2014</year>; <volume>165B</volume>: <fpage>502</fpage>–509.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24985920</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Asadollahi R, Oneda B, Joset P, Azzarello-Burri S, Bartholdi D, Steindl K et al. <article-title>The clinical significance of small copy number variants in neurodevelopmental disorders</article-title>. <source/>J Med Genet
<year>2014</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>677</fpage>–688.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25106414</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Serajee FJ, Zhong H, Nabi R, Huq AH. <article-title>The metabotropic glutamate receptor 8 gene at 7q31: partial duplication and possible association with autism</article-title>. <source/>J Med Genet
<year>2003</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>e42</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Li W, Ju K, Li Z, He K, Chen J, Wang Q et al. <article-title>Significant association of GRM7 and GRM8 genes with schizophrenia and major depressive disorder in the Han Chinese population</article-title>. <source/>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol
<year>2016</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>–146.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26655190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Long EC, Aliev F, Wang JC, Edenberg HJ, Nurnberger J Jr, Hesselbrock V et al. <article-title>Further analyses of genetic association between GRM8 and alcohol dependence symptoms among young adults</article-title>. <source/>J Stud Alcohol Drugs
<year>2015</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>414</fpage>–418.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25978827</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhang L, Zhong X, An Z, Han S, Luo X, Shi Y et al. <article-title>Association analysis of the GRM8 gene with schizophrenia in the Uygur Chinese population</article-title>. <source/>Hereditas
<year>2014</year>; <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>–144.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25588301</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Woo J, Kwon SK, Kim E. <article-title>The NGL family of leucine-rich repeat-containing synaptic adhesion molecules</article-title>. <source/>Mol Cell Neurosci
<year>2009</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19467332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Xu G, Wang R, Wang Z, Lei Q, Yu Z, Liu C et al. <article-title>NGL-2 is a new partner of PAR complex in axon differentiation</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci
<year>2015</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>7153</fpage>–7164.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25948265</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chen J, Yu S, Fu Y, Li X. <article-title>Synaptic proteins and receptors defects in autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source/>Front Cell Neurosci
<year>2014</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25309321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<ref-list content-type="data-citations">
<title>Data Citations</title>
<ref id="d1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="data"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Toshiyuki</given-names></name></person-group><data-title>HGV Database</data-title>. <year>2016</year>. <pub-id assigning-authority="figshare" pub-id-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.923" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.923</pub-id>. </mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="d2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="data"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Toshiyuki</given-names></name></person-group><data-title>HGV Database</data-title>. <year>2016</year>. <pub-id assigning-authority="figshare" pub-id-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.926" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.926</pub-id>. </mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="fig1">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of the chromosomal microarray testing superimposed with genes located in this region. Chromosome view (top) and gene view (middle) created by Agilent Genomic Workbench (Agilent Technologies), showing an interstitial 1.9-Mb deletion at 7q31.33q32.1. The web image of the UCSC genome browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genome.ucsc.edu/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://genome.ucsc.edu/</ext-link> (visited 20 September 2016)), in which the DECIPHER data in the region of interest are shown, was captured and pasted (bottom). The <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> axes indicate genomic location and signal log<sub>2</sub> ratio, respectively. The deleted region (shown by blue translucent rectangle) includes 13 RefSeq genes, which are depicted with gene symbols. Black bars indicate the gene locations. Red and blue bars in DECIPHER data indicate the loss and the gain of genomic copy numbers, respectively.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="hgv20171-f1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="tbl1">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>List of genes included in the deletion region</title>
</caption>
<table border="1" frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead valign="bottom">
<tr>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Gene symbol</italic>
</th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Description</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" char="." charoff="50" colspan="2" valign="top">
<italic>Position<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></italic>
<hr/>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Gene/locus MIM number</italic>
</th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Phenotype</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Phenotype MIM number</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Inheritance trait</italic>
</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </th>
<th align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Start</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>End</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>GRM8</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Glutamate receptor, metabotropic 8</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">126,078,652</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">126,883,569</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#601116</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">ADHD</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>MIR592</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">MicroRNA 592</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">126,698,142</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">126,698,238</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>LOC101928333</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">126,855,181</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">126,869,975</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>ZNF800</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Zinc-finger protein 800</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,010,354</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,032,323</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>LOC100506682</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,116,937</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127125858</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>GCC1</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">GRIP and coiled-coil domain containing 1</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,220,682</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,225,654</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#607418</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>ARF5</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">ADP-ribosylation factor 5</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,228,406</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,231,759</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#103188</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>FSCN3</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Fascin homolog 3, actin-bundling protein, testicular</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,231,463</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,236,057</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#615800</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>PAX4</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Paired box 4</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,250,346</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,255,780</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#167413</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Diabetes mellitus, type 2</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#125853</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">AD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Maturity-onset diabetes of the young, type IX</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#612225</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>SND1</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Staphylococcal nuclease and tudor domain containing 1</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,292,202</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,732,659</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#602181</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>SND1-IT1</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">SND1 intronic transcript 1 (non-protein coding)</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,637,562</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,640,130</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>LRRC4</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Leucine-rich repeat containing 4</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,667,124</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,671,002</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">#610486</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>MIR593</italic>
</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">MicroRNA 593</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,721,913</td>
<td align="center" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127,722,012</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t1-tfoot1">
<p>Abbreviations: AD, autosomal dominant; ADP, adenosine diphosphate; ADHD, attention deficit/hyperkinetic disorder; MIM, Mendelian inheritance in man.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t1-fn1">
<label>a</label>
<p>Genomic positions are referred to build19.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>