<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Translational Psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2158-3188</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28140404</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5299391</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pii">tp2016280</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2016.280</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Particulate air pollutants, APOE alleles and their contributions to cognitive impairment in older women and to amyloidogenesis in experimental models</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running">Ambient particles accelerate neurodegenerative processes of AD</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cacciottolo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Driscoll</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Woodward</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saffari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reyes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Serre</surname>
<given-names>M L</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vizuete</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sioutas</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>T E</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gatz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chui</surname>
<given-names>H C</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shumaker</surname>
<given-names>S A</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Resnick</surname>
<given-names>S M</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Espeland</surname>
<given-names>M A</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">11</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Finch</surname>
<given-names>C E</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J C</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf2">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Leonard Davis School of Gerontology, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Preventive Medicine, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Psychology, University of Wisconsin</institution>, Milwaukee, WI, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>USC Viterbi School of Engineering, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Environmental Sciences and Engineering, Gillings School of Global Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</institution>, Chapel Hill, NC, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Psychology, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution>Memory and Aging Center, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California,</institution>, Los Angeles, CA, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><institution>Department of Social Sciences and Health Policy, Wake Forest School of Medicine</institution>, Winston-Salem, NC, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><institution>Laboratory of Behavioral Neuroscience, National Institute on Aging, National Institutes of Health</institution>, Baltimore, MD, <country>USA</country></aff>
<aff id="aff11"><label>11</label><institution>Division of Public Health Services, Department of Biostatistical Sciences, Wake Forest School of Medicine</institution>, Winston-Salem, NC, <country>USA</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label><institution>University of Southern California, Davis School of Gerontology</institution>, 3715 McClintock Avenue GERO 336, Los Angeles, CA 90089-0191, <country>USA</country> E-mail: <email>cefinch@usc.edu</email></corresp>
<corresp id="caf2"><label>*</label><institution>Department of Preventive Medicine, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California</institution>, 2001N Soto Street SSB 225P, M/C 9237 Los Angeles, CA 90089-9237, <country>USA</country>. E-mail: <email>jcchen@usc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>01</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>31</day>
<month>01</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>1</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>e1022</fpage>
<lpage></lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>27</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--author-paid-->
<license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Exposure to particulate matter (PM) in the ambient air and its interactions with APOE alleles may contribute to the acceleration of brain aging and the pathogenesis of Alzheimer's disease (AD). Neurodegenerative effects of particulate air pollutants were examined in a US-wide cohort of older women from the Women's Health Initiative Memory Study (WHIMS) and in experimental mouse models. Residing in places with fine PM exceeding EPA standards increased the risks for global cognitive decline and all-cause dementia respectively by 81 and 92%, with stronger adverse effects in APOE ɛ4/4 carriers. Female EFAD transgenic mice (<italic>5xFAD</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup><italic>/human APOE</italic> ɛ<italic>3</italic> or ɛ<italic>4</italic><sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>) with 225 h exposure to urban nanosized PM (nPM) over 15 weeks showed increased cerebral β-amyloid by thioflavin S for fibrillary amyloid and by immunocytochemistry for Aβ deposits, both exacerbated by <italic>APOE</italic> ɛ4. Moreover, nPM exposure increased Aβ oligomers, caused selective atrophy of hippocampal CA1 neurites, and decreased the glutamate GluR1 subunit. Wildtype C57BL/6 female mice also showed nPM-induced CA1 atrophy and GluR1 decrease. <italic>In vitro</italic> nPM exposure of neuroblastoma cells (N2a-APP/swe) increased the pro-amyloidogenic processing of the amyloid precursor protein (APP). We suggest that airborne PM exposure promotes pathological brain aging in older women, with potentially a greater impact in ɛ4 carriers. The underlying mechanisms may involve increased cerebral Aβ production and selective changes in hippocampal CA1 neurons and glutamate receptor subunits.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Environmental influences on Alzheimer's disease (AD) and related dementias (ADRD) are poorly documented.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> Apolipoprotein E (<italic>APOE</italic>) ɛ4 and other loci identified by large GWAS account for less than 50% of heritable AD risk.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup> Thus, attention is drawn to environmental risk factors, including common neurotoxins and their interactions with APOE and other genes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>Ambient fine particles (PM<sub>2.5</sub>: particulate matter (PM) with aerodynamic diameters&lt;2.5 μm) from traffic emissions are a major source of urban air pollution, accounting globally for 25% of ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup> Epidemiologic evidence associates cognitive deficits with PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure among the elderly.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref></sup> Rodent models also show long-term neurotoxic effects of air pollutants, including memory impairment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup> and selective atrophy of CA1 hippocampal neurons observed in pre-clinical AD;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> decreased glutamate receptor subunit GluR1;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> and increased endogenous soluble Aβ.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref></sup> However, we lack prospective studies of PM exposure on ADRD risk and interaction with <italic>APOE</italic> alleles.</p>
<p>We hypothesized that long-term PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure increases the risk for accelerated global cognitive decline and dementia, further exacerbated by APOE ɛ4. These hypotheses were tested within the Women's Health Initiative Memory Study (WHIMS), a well-characterized, nationwide prospective cohort of older US women, for which we recently reported associations between elevated PM<sub>2.5</sub> and smaller white matter volumes in multiple brain regions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup> Neurotoxic effects of PM were studied with transgenic mice (EFAD) carrying human APOE alleles and familial AD genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> which model pre-clinical accumulations of Aβ amyloid and its exacerbation in APOE ɛ4 carriers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup> We focused on female mice, because ɛ4 confers a greater AD risk in women than in men<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> and because women also incur worse cardiopulmonary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup> and neurological<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref></sup> consequences from residential exposure to ambient PM.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup> To model the human subpopulation with low to negligible Aβ plaque and without familial AD genes, we examined C57BL/6J mice (wildtype), which do not develop amyloid aggregates at any age, because murine Aβ differs from the human in 3 residues that reduce its aggregation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref></sup> Nonetheless, sAPPα, derived from the endogenous amyloid precursor protein (APP), modulates synaptic remodeling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup> We also examined responses of mouse neuroblastoma N2a cells expressing Swedish mutant APP (N2a-APP/swe) to <italic>in vitro</italic> nPM as a model for direct effects of PM on APP processing.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec>
<title>The neuroepidemiologic study</title>
<p>WHIMS participants were community-dwelling (&gt;95% in urban areas) across 48 states, aged 65 to 79 years, and free of dementia when enrolled, 1995–1999. Of 4504 with APOE genotypes, we excluded 717 with ɛ2/2, ɛ2/3 or ɛ2/4 allele plus 140 with missing PM<sub>2.5</sub> data. The remainder of 3647 older women with APOE alleles ɛ3/3 (<italic>n</italic>=2644), ɛ3/4 (<italic>n</italic>=922) or ɛ4/4 (<italic>n</italic>=81), were of European ancestry (primarily non-Hispanic whites) and had complete PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure estimates. The standardized WHIMS outcome ascertainment protocols<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref></sup> consisted of annual screening of global cognitive function, neuropsychological and functional assessment, with clinical data to exclude possible reversible causes of cognitive impairment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref>), all concluded with the final classification of dementia (vs non-demented) by central adjudication blind to estimated PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure. Accelerated decline in global cognitive function was defined by an 8-point (~2 s.e.) loss in Modified Mini-Mental State (3MS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> during two consecutive assessments. Decrease of 3MS by 5–10 points was considered a clinically significant decline in global cognitive functions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>Using the Bayesian Maximum Entropy method (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Information</xref>), we constructed spatiotemporal models to estimate the ambient concentration of PM<sub>2.5</sub> at all WHIMS residential locations in 1999–2010.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> This method integrates nationwide monitoring data from the U.S. EPA Air Quality System (AQS) and the output of chemical transport models to characterize spatiotemporal interdependence of environmental data to estimate mean trends and covariance of the air pollution fields over space and time. The resulting BME estimates of daily PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposures correlated with levels recorded at local AQS monitoring sites (cross-validation Pearson's <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.70). This statistically-validated BME model was applied to each geocoded residential location to generate a yearly time-series of PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure, and then combined with residential histories including relocations to calculate the 3-year moving average PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposures.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>We conducted time-to-event analyses to examine associations between long-term residential exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and adverse neurocognitive outcomes. Cox proportional hazard models were used to estimate hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for adverse events associated with estimated time-varying 3-year average PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposures, adjusting for potential confounders, including age, geographic region, education, income, employment status, lifestyle factors (smoking; alcohol use; physical activities) and clinical characteristics (use of hormone treatment; depression; body mass index; hypercholesterolemia; hypertension, diabetes; and histories of cardiovascular disease). Characterization of these covariates and rationale for their selection were given in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Information</xref>. Follow-up time for each woman was calculated from WHI randomization (baseline) to the screening date triggering the ultimate classification of defined outcome end points, or the last date of completing annual cognitive assessment before 31 December 2010, whichever came first. Data on global cognitive decline and incidence of dementia were analyzed separately. For analyses of global cognitive decline, dementia cases were excluded if ascertained before subjects lost 8 points on 3MS. We used time on study as the timescale in the constructed Cox regression models, because simulation studies suggested that such approaches were less subject to potential biases in estimating effects of environmental factors (for example, PM exposures) with prominent secular trends,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref></sup> as compared with the other alternatives (for example, attained age; calendar time). The assumed proportional hazards of Cox models were supported by the proportionality test based on weighted residuals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup> To evaluate the effect measure modification, we further stratified the effect estimates by examining whether the putative neurotoxic effects differed by APOE alleles, by Wald tests of interaction. Statistical analyses used SAS System for Windows, Version 9.3 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA).</p>
<p>The institutional review boards of all institutes involved in the air pollution neuroepidemiologic study and its parent projects approved the established protocols of human subject protection and informed consent.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Mouse experiments</title>
<sec>
<title>Animals</title>
<p>EFAD mice carrying transgenes for human APOE ɛ3 or ɛ4 alleles in combination with five familial AD mutations (<italic>5xFAD</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup><italic>/human APOE</italic><sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>) (APP K670N/M671L+ I716V+ V717I and PS1 M146L+L286V)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup> were generously given by Dr Mary Jo LaDu (University of Illinois, Chicago, IL, USA). Experimental logistics limited the exposure study to 20 female mice: 10 per group of E3- and E4FAD, were randomly assigned to either nPM exposure or control air for 15 weeks. One E3FAD control died during the experiment. As a model for the human subpopulation with low to negligible Aβ plaque and without AD genes, we exposed wild-type C57BL/6J females (<italic>n</italic>=18) to nPM for 10 weeks corresponding to our prior study of wild-type male mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> The 15-week exposure for EFAD was chosen to initiate exposure at 2 months, corresponding to the onset of Aβ deposition,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup> with brains collected at age of 7 months, the same age in our initial study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> Data analysis was blinded for nPM and genotype. Mouse husbandry and procedures were approved by the University of Southern California Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Experimental exposures</title>
<p>A nano-scale subfraction of urban PM<sub>2.5</sub>, designated as nPM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> with well-characterized particle size and chemical composition,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup> was used for <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> exposure. Female mice were randomly assigned to nPM or filtered air (control), 5 h per day, 3 days per week, delivered to the sealed exposure chambers. For timelines of exposures see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Tissue collection</title>
<p>Mice were killed by isoflurane anesthesia and perfused transcardially with phosphate-buffered saline. Brains were hemi-sected for sagittal sectioning 0.5–2 m<sc>m</sc> from midline. Brains were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde, cryoprotected in sucrose and frozen on dry ice. The other hemisphere was chilled and dissected (hippocampus and cerebral cortex) and frozen on dry ice.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Oligomeric Aβ ELISA</title>
<p>Aβ peptides were assayed in brain supernates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> Cerebral half-cortexes were homogenized in DEA buffer (0.2% diethylamine, 50 m<sc>M</sc> NaCl; 1 ml per 200 mg tissue) with Complete Protease Inhibitor (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA). After centrifugation (20 800 <italic>g</italic> × 30 min), supernatants were neutralized with Tris-HCl, pH 6.2. Oligomeric Aβ was assayed by MOAB-2 ELISA kit (BEK-2215-1P, Biosensis, Thebarton, SA, Australia).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Aβ Immunohistochemistry (4G8)</title>
<p>Aβ amyloid was immunostained with 4G8 antibody (residues 17–24 at N-terminal of APP, SIG-39220, Covance, Princeton, NJ, USA).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> Briefly, sections were immersed in 70% formic acid/5 min. Endogenous peroxidases were blocked by 3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and 10% methanol in TRIS-buffered saline (TBS), 30 min/22 °C. Sections were permeabilized in 0.1% Triton X-100/15 min, blocked by 30 min incubation in TBS with 2% BSA and 0.1% Triton, and probed with primary antibodies. After 0.1% Triton and TBS rinses, sections were incubated with biotinylated anti-mouse secondary antibodies (1:250) for 1 h, followed by ABC peroxidase and 3,3'-diaminobenzidine (DAB; Vector, Burlingame, CA, USA). Bright-field microscope images were converted to 8-bit grayscale and thresholded to highlight plaques and to diminish background. The objects identified were inspected individually to confirm plaque identity. The cerebral cortex in each image was outlined for analysis by ‘analyze particles' function in NIH ImageJ software. Aβ plaque load was evaluated as % area covered by 4G8-stained plaques.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Thioflavin S staining</title>
<p>Sections were air-dried, rehydrated in Milli-Qwater for 2 min and stained in 0.1% thioflavin S (ThioS) (in 50% ethanol-phosphate-buffered saline) for 5 min in the dark. Sections were destained twice for 5 min in 80% EtOH in the dark and mounted with Fluoromount Aqueous (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). Amyloid load was quantified as above for 4G8 immunostaining.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Silver staining</title>
<p>Silver staining Bielschowsky technique was used to assess neuropil density.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> Sections were dried at room temperature and briefly washed in distilled water before preimpregnation. Sections were incubated in preheated 20% (1.0 <sc>m</sc>) silver nitrate at 37 °C/15 min, washed 3 × in distilled water, and incubated in ammoniacal silver solution (20% silver nitrate in 148 m<sc>m</sc> ammonia water) for 10 min at 37 °C. Sections were developed for 3 min (8% formaldehyde, 1% nitric acid, 26 m<sc>m</sc> citric acid, diluted 1:50 in ammonia water), followed by washing in ammonia water and distilled water to reduce background. Slides were then placed in 5% sodium thiosulfate solution for 2 min, rinsed 5 × in distilled water, dehydrated, cleared and mounted. Bright-field images of CA1, CA2/3 and dentate gyrus region, were analyzed by NIH ImageJ software. Images were converted to 8-bit grayscale, thresholded for binary separation of neuronal cell bodies (dark round objects) from neurites and neurite density calculated as percentage of positive staining in area of interest.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Immunoblotting</title>
<p>Hippocampus was homogenized by motor-driven pestle in cold RIPA buffer (20–188, Millipore, Temecula, CA, USA) and centrifuged 5 min/20 000 <italic>g</italic>. Supernate protein (20 μg) was electrophoresed on 10% SDS polyacrylamide gels and transferred to polyvinylidene fluoride membranes. The polyvinylidene fluoride membranes were blocked with 5% BSA for 1 h and probed with primary antibodies overnight at 4 °C: anti-GluR1 (glutamate receptor subunit 1; 1:3000, AB31232, rabbit; Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA), anti-GluR2 (glutamate receptor subunit 2; 1:2000, AB1768, rabbit; Millipore), anti-NR2A (NMDA receptor, subunit 2A, 1:1000, 07-632, rabbit; Millipore), anti-NR2B (NMDA receptor, subunit 2B, 1:1000, 06-600, rabbit; Millipore) anti-PSD95 (1:1000, AB2723, mouse; Abcam), anti-synaptophysin (1:5000, MAB368, mouse; Stressgene; Enzo, Plymouth Meeting, PA, USA), and anti-NueN (loading control; 1:1000, MAB377, mouse, Millipore). After washing, membranes were probed with secondary antibodies conjugated with IRDye 680 (92632210, rabbit, LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE, USA) and IRDye 800 (92632210, mouse, LI-COR). Signal was detected by infrared imaging (Odyssey, LI-COR).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title><italic>In vitro</italic> nPM exposure and APP/Aß measurements</title>
<p>Mouse neuroblastoma N2a cells expressing Swedish mutant APP (K595N/M596L) (N2a-APP/swe) were generously gifted by Dr Huaxi Xu (Sanford/Burnham Medical Research Institute, La Jolla, CA, USA) and tested for mycoplasma contamination before use. Cells were treated with nPM (10 μg ml<sup>−1</sup>) in culture media (Optimem/DMEM medium, 5% FBS, 500 μg ml<sup>−1</sup> G418) for 24 h. RIPA buffer cell lysates were probed with 22C11 antibody (1:100, Millipore), which recognizes both sAPPα and sAPPβ. Media were analyzed for Aβ42 by MSD Multiplex ELISA (Meso Scale Discovery, Rockville, MD, USA). Three independent experiments were performed, with three sample replicates each.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>For the statistical analyses examining the putative effects on continuous response variables, we used multiple linear regression analysis in STATA14, including both nPM exposure and APOE genotype. We also conducted subgroup data analyses on nPM exposure effect, stratified by genotype. Silver staining analysis used repeated measurements of a clustered linear regression. All two-sided tests of statistical significance were set at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Results</title>
<sec>
<title>The neuroepidemiologic study</title>
<p>Women in the highest PM<sub>2.5</sub> quartile (14.34–22.55 μg m<sup>−3</sup>) were older (aged ⩾75 years); more likely to reside in the South/Midwest and use hormonal treatment; but engage less in physical activities and consume less alcohol, relative to counterparts (all <italic>P</italic>-values&lt;0.05; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure estimates did not differ by APOE genotype. There were 173 subjects classified as incident cases of all-cause dementia over an average follow-up of 9.9 years and 329 had global cognitive decline (including 87 cases subsequently classified as or progressing to all-cause-dementia) over an average follow-up of 8.3 years. The observed incidence rates of accelerated global cognitive decline and all-cause dementia differed significantly by APOE genotype (both <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001 with ɛ4/4&gt;ɛ3/4&gt;ɛ3/3 by log-rank test).</p>
<sec>
<title>Associations between PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure and adverse events</title>
<p>The 3-year average exposure preceding the incident event time was <italic>a priori</italic> classified as ‘high' if exceeding the current National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) for PM<sub>2.5</sub> (&gt;12 μg m<sup>−3</sup>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> Residence in high PM<sub>2.5</sub> locations was associated with increased risks of global cognitive decline and all-cause dementia. These adverse PM<sub>2.5</sub> effects were exacerbated among women of ɛ4/4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). For residence in locations with high PM<sub>2.5</sub> at any time during 1999–2000, the hazard ratio (HR) for accelerated global cognitive decline and all-cause dementia were increased by 81% and 92%, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). These adverse PM<sub>2.5</sub> effects varied by APOE allele, with ɛ3/3&lt;ɛ3/4&lt;ɛ4/4 for both global cognitive decline (ɛ3/3: HR=1.65; ɛ3/4: HR=1.93; ɛ4/4: HR=3.95) and all-cause dementia (ɛ3/3: HR=1.68; ɛ3/4: HR=1.91; ɛ4/4: HR=2.95).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Mouse experimental studies</title>
<p>Female EFAD mice (<italic>5xFAD</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup><italic>/human APOE</italic> ɛ<italic>3/</italic>ɛ<italic>3/</italic> or ɛ4/ɛ<italic>4</italic>) were chronically exposed to nPM during 15 weeks. We observed increased amyloid deposits as fibrillar amyloid by ThioS binding and by 4G8 plaque immunohistochemistry that were greater for E4FAD mice than E3FAD. For ThioS, nPM exposure increased amyloid load by +60% in E4FAD above non-exposed controls (<italic>P</italic>=0.048), whereas E3FAD did not respond (<italic>P</italic>=0.79; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2a</xref>). For 4G8, nPM exposure in E4FAD increased Aβ plaque load by +30% above controls (<italic>P</italic>=0.04; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2b</xref>); its effect size was 2.8-fold greater than for E3FAD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). Levels of ThioS and 4G8 were highly correlated (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.78, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.0001; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<p>Aβ oligomers were increased by nPM for both APOE alleles, with an overall nPM effect (<italic>P</italic>=0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c</xref>): +15% in E4FAD mice (<italic>P</italic>=0.03) and +60% in E3FAD (<italic>P</italic>=0.07).</p>
<p>The increased amyloid from nPM exposure suggests direct effects of nPM on APP processing. As an acute <italic>in vitro</italic> model, mouse neuroblastoma cells (N2a-APP/Swe) were exposed to nPM; pro-amyloidogenic APP processing was assessed as the ratio (sAPPβ/α) of soluble fragments from β-secretase (sAPPβ, pro-amyloidogenic) and α-secretase (sAPPα, non-amyloidogenic). nPM increased the sAPPβ/α ratio by 35% (<italic>P</italic>=0.02, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2d</xref>), with 2-fold increase of Aβ42 peptide (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2e</xref>).</p>
<p>Neuronal consequences of the elevated Aβ and sAPPβ/α ratio include synaptic remodeling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref></sup> and effects of Aβ on glutamate receptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref></sup> The hippocampus of female EFAD and C57BL/6 mice showed selective neuronal atrophy in response to nPM, which was restricted to CA1 hippocampal neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3a and d</xref>): E3FAD (−45%, <italic>P</italic>=0.03) and C57BL/6 (−25%, <italic>P</italic>=0.003), without CA2/3 layer or dentate gyrus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3d</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>).</p>
<p>Synaptic proteins that mediate hippocampal-based memory were analyzed in whole hippocampus extracts. The nPM exposure decreased GluR1 protein by −25% in E3FAD (<italic>P</italic>=0.01), −35% in E4FAD (<italic>P</italic>=0.01) and −40% in C57BL/6J (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.002; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4a</xref>). No changes were detected in other glutamatergic receptor subunits (GluR2, NR2A and NR2B; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4b–d</xref>) or other synaptic proteins (pre-synaptic: synaptophysin; post-synaptic: PSD95; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our data combine an air pollution-neuroepidemiologic study of older women and inhalation neurotoxicological experiments with mice. Together, we show the contribution of particulate air pollutants to neurodegenerative changes, with potentially a greater impact on APOE ɛ4 carriers. Overall, the evidence supports the schema that airborne PM accelerates neurodegenerative processes of ADRD through multiple pathways, including pro-amyloidogenic APP processing and other pathways independent of amyloid deposits.</p>
<p>In the geographically diverse WHIMS cohort, increased risks for both all-cause dementia and clinically significant declines in global cognitive function (with &gt;8-point loss in 3MS scores) were associated with residential exposure to high levels of ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub>. In female EFAD mice, the chronic exposure to nPM, a neurotoxic subfraction of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, increased both the cerebral Aβ-amyloid plaque load and neurotoxic Aβ oligomers. Mice carrying ɛ4 had more nPM-induced Aβ-amyloid plaque. These experimental data are consistent with our epidemiologic observation of stronger associations between PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure and increased risks for dementia and global cognitive decline in women homozygous for APOE ɛ4 vs ɛ3. These findings provide the first experimental evidence for gene-environment interactions involving airborne PM and APOE in neurodegenerative processes.</p>
<p>Our study of the WHIMS cohort provides new evidence for late-life exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub> as a common environmental risk factor for ADRD. Previous studies showed older adults living in areas with higher ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> had lower performance in various cognitive functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> and accelerated cognitive aging.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> However, unlike our defined global decline (&gt;8-point loss in 3MS), the clinical significance was unclear for these reported cognitive deficits associated with air pollution exposure. Five studies that reported associations of ADRD with exposure to ambient air pollution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup> had notable methodological limitations. Three of these studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref></sup> used claims data to determine incident dementia/AD (an approach with questionable validity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref></sup>) and included only aggregated exposures prone to ecological biases. Four studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref></sup> were retrospective and subject to selection biases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref></sup> The only prospective cohort study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref></sup> employed a spatial model towards the end of study follow-up to estimate the NO<sub>x</sub> exposure in earlier years, which obscured the temporality of the reported association. Our study within the prospective WHIMS cohort used the incident dementia cases adjudicated with well-validated protocols and a sophisticated spatiotemporal model to estimate residence-specific exposure to ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> preceding the ascertained end points. The comprehensive list of covariates data (including APOE genotype) allowed us to carefully assess and adjust for potential confounding. These observed neurodegenerative effects of PM<sub>2.5</sub> (with the relative risk for global cognitive decline and all-cause dementia, respectively, increased by 81% and 92%) were not explained by differences in socioeconomic status, lifestyle, vascular risk factors and APOE alleles. The average PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations have decreased over time in the US (for example, 34% reduction in 2000–2013), which coincided with decreased age-specific risk for dementia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref></sup> Assuming 30% of older women in the US were residing in locations with high PM<sub>2.5</sub> before the US EPA set its current US NAAQS standard ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> in 2012, if the observed adverse effects in WHIMS were generalizable, we estimate that ~21% of accelerated cognitive decline and all-cause dementia are attributable to residential exposure to high ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup></p>
<p>The experimental findings with EFAD and C57BL/6J mice suggest possible mechanisms for the PM-associated cognitive impairment observed in the WHIMS cohort. We show that nPM exposure of EFAD mice increased fibrillary amyloid and Aβ plaque and soluble oligomeric Aβ, together with neuronal changes in hippocampus (discussed below). These are the first studies on the neurotoxicity of airborne particles using transgenic mice carrying human APOE alleles and familial AD genes. Three reports of wild-type rodents, including two with exposure to diesel particles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup> and one with concentrated ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11"><sup>11</sup></xref> showed increased endogenous soluble Aβ in cerebral cortex. We also introduce an <italic>in vitro</italic> model for PM effects on APP processing. <italic>In vitro</italic> nPM short-term exposure of neuronal N2a-APP/Swe cells enhanced pro-amyloidogenic APP processing, with increased sAPPβ/α ratio and Aβ42 production. This finding concurs with the rapid rise of brain Aβ40–42 in wild-type mice exposed to nickel-PM enriched ambient air.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref></sup> In EFAD mice, Aβ plaques begin to form in cerebral cortex by 2 months,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup> which models the pre-clinical accumulation of Aβ plaque in humans. We showed that nPM exposure increased both plaque formation and neurotoxic Aβ oligomers in cerebral cortex at 7 months (approximately equivalent to 35 years of human age, approaching peri-menopause). This implies that Aβ-dependent neurodegenerative processes in women with increased long-term PM exposure may precede cognitive declines or diagnosis of dementia, which is consistent with neuroimaging evidence for Aβ deposition even among cognitively intact individuals in their 50–60s.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup></p>
<p>Importantly, nPM-exposed EFAD mice showed selective neuritic changes that parallel human AD, with selective atrophy of hippocampal CA1 neurons, but not of neighboring neurons of the same memory circuit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> The nPM exposure also decreased the GluR1 subunit of glutamatergic synapses for both APOE alleles. Female wild-type C57BL/6 mice also showed selective CA1 atrophy with decreased GluR1, extending our prior findings of GluR1 with male C57BL/6J mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> Together, these results suggest that the nPM-associated early neurodegenerative changes in hippocampus may occur to a broader population regardless of underlying genetic risks.</p>
<p>The CA1 neurite atrophy in female C57BL/6J mice after 10 weeks of nPM exposure corroborates dendritic spine loss in CA1 neurons of male C57BL/6 mice exposed to concentrated ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> for 10 months shown by others.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup> Thus, the selective vulnerability of CA1 neurons to airborne PM does not depend on the presence of human Aβ. As noted in the Introduction, wild-type murine sAPPα, derived from the endogenous mouse APP, modulates synaptic remodeling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup> The selective CA1 attrition by PM exposure without Aβ accumulation implies that PM exposure before older ages could contribute to accelerated cognitive decline and increased AD risk in late life by reducing the CA1 synapses, possibly via direct interactions of Aβ oligomers with glutamatergic neurons.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref></sup> Moreover, the nPM-driven increase of sAPPβ/α implies deficits of the neurotrophic sAPPα, which can rescue deficits of synaptic plasticity (LTP) in CA1 neurons of APP-knockout mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup></p>
<p>Given the growing literature linking air pollution with cognitive deficits across the life course, the selective neurotoxic effects on CA1 neurons underscores the possibility that PM exposure may differentially damage the medial temporal lobe-hippocampus memory system,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup> a vulnerable neural network in both brain aging and neurodegenerative disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">49</xref></sup> Neurotoxicological and neuroimaging studies also show white matter vulnerability to PM neurotoxicity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">51</xref></sup> The WHIMS-MRI subcohort shows associations between PM<sub>2.5</sub> and smaller volumes of normal-appearing white matter in frontal and temporal lobes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref></sup> Total hippocampal volume did not differ by PM<sub>2.5,</sub> but CA1 hippocampal subfields were not resolved. From a systems neurotoxicity perspective, these findings suggest the hypothesis that airborne PM-induced pathological brain aging may be initiated by white matter neurodegeneration, with ensuing neuroanatomical progression of AD from the entorhinal cortex in the medial temporal lobe to the hippocampus via the myelinated perforant path.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">54</xref></sup></p>
<p>Our epidemiologic and experimental findings suggest that APOE ɛ4 may increase susceptibility to the adverse effects of particulate air pollutants. We followed an expert-proposed framework combining epidemiologic and toxicological evidence to make causal inference,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref></sup> focusing on the comparison of PM effect sizes, rather than the interaction <italic>P</italic>-value, which can be misleading.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">56</xref></sup> The adverse effects of high ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> on global cognitive decline and dementia risk were several fold greater in APOE ɛ4/4 than ɛ3/3 carriers. Because APOE4 frequencies vary widely by populations,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> their potential interactions with spatially varying ambient PM exposure to accelerate pathological brain aging may explain the geographic disparities in dementia incidence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup> Possible interactions of air pollution exposure and APOE ɛ4 on accelerated brain aging are also suggested by postmortem findings from a study in Mexico,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">59</xref></sup> which lacked comparison with APOE ɛ4 carriers residing in cleaner air. Neurocognitive effects of airborne particles interacting with APOE alleles were also reported for a cross-sectional study in older German women for their joint effect on constructional praxis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">60</xref></sup> Interpretation is difficult because overall there were no associations across all tested domains (including episodic memory and executive function) and no adjustment for multiple comparisons. A recent case–control study in Taiwan reported an increased risk for AD associated with high ambient PM<sub>10</sub>, with the observed association not varying by APOE genes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref></sup> This study was limited for its retrospective design prone to selection biases (for example, possible oversampling of ɛ4 carriers in controls).</p>
<p>We recognize several limitations of our study. First, this study of older women may not be generalized to men. Second, our study examined the association with PM<sub>2.5</sub> mass, but had no information on particle constituents, emission sources, or interactions with other pollutants. Although research on cardiopulmonary end points is beginning to include these complexities of PM exposures, such data are both costly and limited for nationwide cohorts. Third, the employed spatiotemporal models only allowed estimates of late-life exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub> after 1999. As air pollution levels have been declining over the past 20 years, long-term exposure, especially during mid- or earlier life, may impart a greater risk. Finally, male mice warrant study for nPM effects on amyloid processing.</p>
<p>In summary, we provide clear evidence that the hazards of particulate air pollutants for brain health extend to dementia risk in a US-wide sample of older women and give, we believe, the first evidence from AD transgenic mice that exposure to urban airborne particulates can intensify amyloid accumulation and neurodegeneration. Moreover, these joint data from humans and mice provide the first evidence that neurodegenerative effects of airborne PM may involve gene-environment interactions with APOE ɛ4, the major genetic risk factor for pathological brain aging and AD. The association between PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure and increased dementia risk suggests that the global burden of disease attributable to PM<sub>2.5</sub> pollution has been underestimated, especially in regions with large populations exposed to high ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The WHI program is funded by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NIH) through contracts HHSN268201100046C, HHSN268201100001C, HHSN268201100002C, HHSN268201100003C, HHSN268201100004C and HHSN271201100004C. The WHIMS was funded by Wyeth Pharmaceuticals, St Davids, PA, USA, and Wake Forest University. This study was supported by NIH awards R01AG033078, R01AG051521, R21AG040753, R21AG040683 and R00AG032361. This study was supported by awards to J.C. Chen (R01AG033078; RF1AG054068), to I. Driscoll (R00AG032361) and to C.E. Finch (R01AG051521, R21AG040753, R21AG040683, R21AG0500201 and by the Cure Alzheimer's Fund). The research was also supported by the Southern California Environmental Health Sciences Center (5P30ES007048). We are grateful for dedicated efforts by all investigators and staff at the WHI and WHIMS clinical centers, and at the WHI &amp; WHIMS clinical coordinating center:: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.whi.org/researchers/Documents%20%20Write%20a%20Paper/WHI%20Investigator%20Short%20List.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.whi.org/researchers/Documents%20%20Write%20a%20Paper/WHI%20Investigator%20Short%20List.pdf</ext-link>.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Information</xref> accompanies the paper on the <italic>Translational Psychiatry</italic> website (http://www.nature.com/tp)</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="bib1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Selkoe DJ. <article-title>Preventing Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Science
<year>2012</year>; <volume>337</volume>: <fpage>1488</fpage>–1492.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22997326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Farrer LA. <article-title>Expanding the genomic roadmap of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Lancet Neurol
<year>2015</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>783</fpage>–785.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26141618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dekosky ST, Gandy S. <article-title>Environmental exposures and the risk for Alzheimer disease: can we identify the smoking guns</article-title>? <source/>JAMA Neurol
<year>2014</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>–275.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24473699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Karagulian F, Belis CA, Dora CFC, Pruss-Ustun AM, Bonjour S, Adair-Rohani H et al. <article-title>Contributions to cities' ambient particulate matter (PM): A systematic review of local source contributions at global level</article-title>. <source/>Atmos Environ
<year>2015</year>; <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–483.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Block ML, Elder A, Auten RL, Bilbo SD, Chen H, Chen JC et al. <article-title>The Outdoor Air Pollution and Brain Health Workshop</article-title>. <source/>Neurotoxicology
<year>2012</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>972</fpage>–984.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22981845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fonken LK, Xu X, Weil ZM, Chen G, Sun Q, Rajagopalan S et al. <article-title>Air pollution impairs cognition, provokes depressive-like behaviors and alters hippocampal cytokine expression and morphology</article-title>. <source/>Mol Psychiatry
<year>2011</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>–995, 973.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21727897</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">West MJ, Kawas CH, Stewart WF, Rudow GL, Troncoso JC. <article-title>Hippocampal neurons in pre-clinical Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Neurobiol Aging
<year>2004</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1205</fpage>–1212.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15312966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Morgan TE, Davis DA, Iwata N, Tanner JA, Snyder D, Ning Z et al. <article-title>Glutamatergic neurons in rodent models respond to nanoscale particulate urban air pollutants <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source/>Environ Health Perspect
<year>2011</year>; <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>1003</fpage>–1009.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21724521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Durga M, Devasena T, Rajasekar A. <article-title>Determination of LC and sub-chronic neurotoxicity of diesel exhaust nanoparticles</article-title>. <source/>Environ Toxicol Pharmacol
<year>2015</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>–625.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26363131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Levesque S, Surace MJ, McDonald J, Block ML. <article-title>Air pollution &amp; the brain: Subchronic diesel exhaust exposure causes neuroinflammation and elevates early markers of neurodegenerative disease</article-title>. <source/>J Neuroinflamm
<year>2011</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bhatt DP, Puig KL, Gorr MW, Wold LE, Combs CK. <article-title>A pilot study to assess effects of long-term inhalation of airborne particulate matter on early Alzheimer-like changes in the mouse brain</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e0127102</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25992783</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chen JC, Wang X, Wellenius GA, Serre ML, Driscoll I, Casanova R et al. <article-title>Ambient air pollution and neurotoxicity on brain structure: Evidence from women's health initiative memory study</article-title>. <source/>Ann Neurol
<year>2015</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>466</fpage>–476.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26075655</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Youmans KL, Tai LM, Nwabuisi-Heath E, Jungbauer L, Kanekiyo T, Gan M et al. <article-title>APOE4-specific changes in Abeta accumulation in a new transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer disease</article-title>. <source/>The Journal of biological chemistry
<year>2012</year>; <volume>287</volume>: <fpage>41774</fpage>–41786.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23060451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Oakley H, Cole SL, Logan S, Maus E, Shao P, Craft J et al. <article-title>Intraneuronal beta-amyloid aggregates, neurodegeneration, and neuron loss in transgenic mice with five familial Alzheimer's disease mutations: potential factors in amyloid plaque formation</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci
<year>2006</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>10129</fpage>–10140.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17021169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cacciottolo M, Christensen A, Moser A, Liu J, Pike CJ, Smith C et al. <article-title>The APOE4 allele shows opposite sex bias in microbleeds and Alzheimer's disease of humans and mice</article-title>. <source/>Neurobiology of aging
<year>2016</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–57.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26686669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu DS, Pan XD, Zhang J, Shen H, Collins NC, Cole AM et al. <article-title>APOE4 enhances age-dependent decline in cognitive function by down-regulating an NMDA receptor pathway in EFAD-Tg mice</article-title>. <source/>Mol Neurodegener
<year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25871877</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Clougherty JE. <article-title>A growing role for gender analysis in air pollution epidemiology</article-title>. <source/>Environ Health Perspect
<year>2010</year>; <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–176.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu R, Young MT, Chen JC, Kaufman JD, Chen H. <article-title>Ambient Air Pollution Exposures and Risk of Parkinson Disease</article-title>. <source/>Environ Health Perspect
<year>2016</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1759</fpage>–1765.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27285422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Boyd-Kimball D, Sultana R, Mohmmad-Abdul H, Butterfield DA. <article-title>Rodent Abeta(1-42) exhibits oxidative stress properties similar to those of human Abeta(1-42): Implications for proposed mechanisms of toxicity</article-title>. <source/>J Alzheimers Dis
<year>2004</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>–525.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15505374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hick M, Herrmann U, Weyer SW, Mallm JP, Tschape JA, Borgers M et al. <article-title>Acute function of secreted amyloid precursor protein fragment APPsalpha in synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source/>Acta Neuropathol
<year>2015</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–37.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25432317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib21">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Weyer SW, Zagrebelsky M, Herrmann U, Hick M, Ganss L, Gobbert J et al. <article-title>Comparative analysis of single and combined APP/APLP knockouts reveals reduced spine density in APP-KO mice that is prevented by APPsalpha expression</article-title>. <source/>Acta Neuropathol Commun
<year>2014</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24684730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib22">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shumaker SA, Legault C, Kuller L, Rapp SR, Thal L, Lane DS et al. <article-title>Conjugated equine estrogens and incidence of probable dementia and mild cognitive impairment in postmenopausal women: Women's Health Initiative Memory Study</article-title>. <source/>JAMA
<year>2004</year>; <volume>291</volume>: <fpage>2947</fpage>–2958.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15213206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib23">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Teng EL, Chui HC. <article-title>The Modified Mini-Mental State (3MS) examination</article-title>. <source/>J Clin Psychiatry
<year>1987</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>–318.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3611032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rapp SR, Espeland MA, Shumaker SA, Henderson VW, Brunner RL, Manson JE et al. <article-title>Effect of estrogen plus progestin on global cognitive function in postmenopausal women: the Women's Health Initiative Memory Study: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source/>JAMA
<year>2003</year>; <volume>289</volume>: <fpage>2663</fpage>–2672.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12771113</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib25">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">Christakos G, BP SMB. <source/>Temporal GIS: Advanced Functions for Field-based Applications. Springer: New York, <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib26">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Griffin BA, Anderson GL, Shih RA, Whitsel EA. <article-title>Use of alternative time scales in Cox proportional hazard models: implications for time-varying environmental exposures</article-title>. <source/>Stat Med
<year>2012</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>3320</fpage>–3327.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22531976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib27">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Grambsch PM, Therneau TM. <article-title>Proportional hazards tests and diagnostics based on weighted residuals</article-title>. <source/>Biometrika
<year>1994</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>–526.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib28">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu Q, Babadjouni R, Radwanski R, Cheng H, Patel A, Hodis DM et al. <article-title>Stroke damage is exacerbated by nano-size particulate matter in a mouse model</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<year>2016</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e0153376</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27071057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib29">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">de Olmos JS, Beltramino CA, de Olmos de Lorenzo S. <article-title>Use of an amino-cupric-silver technique for the detection of early and semiacute neuronal degeneration caused by neurotoxicants, hypoxia, and physical trauma</article-title>. <source/>Neurotoxicol Teratol
<year>1994</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>–561.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7532272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib30">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) National Ambient Air Quality Standards for Particulate Matter; Proposed Rule, Vol. 77. Federal Register: Washington, DC, 2012, pp 38890–39055.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib31">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Whitcomb DJ, Hogg EL, Regan P, Piers T, Narayan P, Whitehead G et al. <article-title>Intracellular oligomeric amyloid-beta rapidly regulates GluA1 subunit of AMPA receptor in the hippocampus</article-title>. <source/>Sci Rep
<year>2015</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>10934</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib32">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ailshire JA, Crimmins EM. <article-title>Fine particulate matter air pollution and cognitive function among older US adults</article-title>. <source/>Am J Epidemiol
<year>2014</year>; <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–366.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24966214</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib33">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gatto NM, Henderson VW, Hodis HN St, John JA, Lurmann F, Chen JC et al. <article-title>Components of air pollution and cognitive function in middle-aged and older adults in Los Angeles</article-title>. <source/>Neurotoxicology
<year>2014</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24148924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib34">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tonne C, Elbaz A, Beevers S, Singh-Manoux A. <article-title>Traffic-related air pollution in relation to cognitive function in older adults</article-title>. <source/>Epidemiology
<year>2014</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>674</fpage>–681.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25036434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib35">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Weuve J, Puett RC, Schwartz J, Yanosky JD, Laden F, Grodstein F. <article-title>Exposure to particulate air pollution and cognitive decline in older women</article-title>. <source/>Arch Intern Med
<year>2012</year>; <volume>172</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–227.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22332151</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib36">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wu Y-C, Lin Y-C, Yu H-L, Chen J-H, Chen T-F, Sun Y et al. <article-title>Association between air pollutants and dementia risk in the elderly</article-title>. <source/>Alzheimers Dement
<year>2015</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–228.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib37">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Oudin A, Forsberg B, Adolfsson AN, Lind N, Modig L, Nordin M et al. <article-title>Traffic-related air pollution and dementia incidence in Northern Sweden: a Longitudinal Study</article-title>. <source/>Environ Health Perspect
<year>2016</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>306</fpage>–312.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26305859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib38">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kioumourtzoglou MA, Schwartz JD, Weisskopf MG, Melly SJ, Wang Y, Dominici F et al. <article-title>Long-term PM2.5 Exposure and Neurological Hospital Admissions in the Northeastern United States</article-title>. <source/>Environ Health Perspect
<year>2016</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–29.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25978701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib39">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jung CR, Lin YT, Hwang BF. <article-title>Ozone, particulate matter, and newly diagnosed Alzheimer's disease: a population-based cohort study in Taiwan</article-title>. <source/>Journal of Alzheimer's disease: JAD
<year>2015</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–584.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25310992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib40">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chang KH, Chang MY, Muo CH, Wu TN, Chen CY, Kao CH. <article-title>Increased risk of dementia in patients exposed to nitrogen dioxide and carbon monoxide: a population-based retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<year>2014</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e103078</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib41">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kioumourtzoglou MA, Schwartz JD, Weisskopf MG, Melly SJ, Wang Y, Dominici F et al. <article-title>Long-term PM exposure and neurological hospital admissions in the Northeastern United States</article-title>. <source/>Environ Health Perspect
<year>2015</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–29.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25978701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib42">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Taylor DHJr, Fillenbaum GG, Ezell ME. <article-title>The accuracy of medicare claims data in identifying Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>J Clin Epidemiol
<year>2002</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>929</fpage>–937.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12393082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib43">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hayden KM, Farmer KM. <article-title>Invited commentary: The importance of studying environmental risk factors for dementia</article-title>. <source/>Alzheimers Dement
<year>2015</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>–269.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib44">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Langa KM. <article-title>Is the risk of Alzheimer's disease and dementia declining</article-title>? <source/>Alzheimers Res Ther
<year>2015</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25815064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib45">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Barendregt JJ, Veerman JL. <article-title>Categorical versus continuous risk factors and the calculation of potential impact fractions</article-title>. <source/>J Epidemiol Community Health
<year>2010</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–212.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19692711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib46">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kim SH, Knight EM, Saunders EL, Cuevas AK, Popovech M, Chen LC et al. <article-title>Rapid doubling of Alzheimer's amyloid-beta40 and 42 levels in brains of mice exposed to a nickel nanoparticle model of air pollution</article-title>. <source/>F1000Research
<year>2012</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24358824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib47">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Villemagne VL, Burnham S, Bourgeat P, Brown B, Ellis KA, Salvado O et al. <article-title>Amyloid beta deposition, neurodegeneration, and cognitive decline in sporadic Alzheimer's disease: a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source/>Lancet Neurol
<year>2013</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–367.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23477989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib48">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Squire LR, Zola-Morgan S. <article-title>The medial temporal lobe memory system</article-title>. <source/>Science
<year>1991</year>; <volume>253</volume>: <fpage>1380</fpage>–1386.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1896849</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib49">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jagust W. <article-title>Vulnerable neural systems and the borderland of brain aging and neurodegeneration</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<year>2013</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–234.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23352159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib50">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Allen JL, Oberdorster G, Morris-Schaffer K, Wong C, Klocke C, Sobolewski M et al. <article-title>Developmental neurotoxicity of inhaled ambient ultrafine particle air pollution: parallels with neuropathological and behavioral features of autism and other neurodevelopmental disorders</article-title>. <source/>Neurotoxicology
<year>2015</year>. pii: S0161-813X(15)30048-6. doi: 10.1016/j.neuro.2015.12.014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib51">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Peterson BS, Rauh VA, Bansal R, Hao X, Toth Z, Nati G et al. <article-title>Effects of prenatal exposure to air pollutants (polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons) on the development of brain white matter, cognition, and behavior in later childhood</article-title>. <source/>JAMA Psychiatry
<year>2015</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>–540.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25807066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib52">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Casanova R, Wang X, Reyes J, Akita Y, Serre ML, Vizuete W et al. <article-title>A voxel-based morphometry study reveals local brain structural alterations associated with ambient fine particles in older women</article-title>. <source/>Front Hum Neurosci
<year>2016</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27790103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib53">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Braak H, Thal DR, Ghebremedhin E, Del Tredici K. <article-title>Stages of the pathologic process in Alzheimer disease: age categories from 1 to 100 years</article-title>. <source/>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol
<year>2011</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>960</fpage>–969.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib54">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zarow C, Vinters HV, Ellis WG, Weiner MW, Mungas D, White L et al. <article-title>Correlates of hippocampal neuron number in Alzheimer's disease and ischemic vascular dementia</article-title>. <source/>Ann Neurol
<year>2005</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>896</fpage>–903.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15929035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib55">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Adami HO, Berry SC, Breckenridge CB, Smith LL, Swenberg JA, Trichopoulos D et al. <article-title>Toxicology and epidemiology: improving the science with a framework for combining toxicological and epidemiological evidence to establish causal inference</article-title>. <source/>Toxicol Sci
<year>2011</year>; <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–234.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21561883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib56">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Matthews JN, Altman DG. <article-title>Statistics notes. Interaction 2: Compare effect sizes not <italic>P</italic> values</article-title>. <source/>BMJ
<year>1996</year>; <volume>313</volume>: <fpage>808</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8842080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib57">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ward A, Crean S, Mercaldi CJ, Collins JM, Boyd D, Cook MN et al. <article-title>Prevalence of apolipoprotein E4 genotype and homozygotes (APOE e4/4) among patients diagnosed with Alzheimer's disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/>Neuroepidemiology
<year>2012</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–17.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22179327</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib58">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Prince M, Acosta D, Ferri CP, Guerra M, Huang Y, Llibre Rodriguez JJ et al. <article-title>Dementia incidence and mortality in middle-income countries, and associations with indicators of cognitive reserve: a 10/66 Dementia Research Group population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source/>Lancet
<year>2012</year>; <volume>380</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>–58.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22626851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib59">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Calderon-Garciduenas L, Kavanaugh M, Block M, D'Angiulli A, Delgado-Chavez R, Torres-Jardon R et al. <article-title>Neuroinflammation, hyperphosphorylated tau, diffuse amyloid plaques, and down-regulation of the cellular prion protein in air pollution exposed children and young adults</article-title>. <source/>J Alzheimers Dis
<year>2012</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–107.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21955814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib60">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schikowski T, Vossoughi M, Vierkotter A, Schulte T, Teichert T, Sugiri D et al. <article-title>Association of air pollution with cognitive functions and its modification by APOE gene variants in elderly women</article-title>. <source/>Environ Res
<year>2015</year>; <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26092807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="sup1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob1">
<label>Supplementary Figure 1</label>
<media xlink:href="tp2016280x1.tif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob2">
<label>Supplementary Figure 2</label>
<media xlink:href="tp2016280x2.tif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob3">
<label>Supplementary Figure 3</label>
<media xlink:href="tp2016280x3.tif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob4">
<label>Supplementary Methods</label>
<media xlink:href="tp2016280x4.docx" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="fig1">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Adverse effects of PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure on cognitive impairment in older women, stratified by APOE alleles. Horizontal bars represent the effect measures (hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals) estimated from the Cox proportional hazard models, comparing high (exceeding the US National Ambient Air Quality Standard with 3-year averages PM<sub>2.5</sub>&gt;12 μg m<sup>−3</sup>) versus low exposure for their associated incidence rates of global cognitive decline (<bold>a</bold>) and all-cause dementia (<bold>b</bold>), stratified by APOE alleles (ɛ3/3 vs ɛ3/4 vs ɛ4/4). The dotted vertical lines denote no statistically significant adverse effects (with HR=1). The presented crude estimates were adjusted for APOE alleles. The adjusted estimates further accounted for age, geographic region, spatial random effect, years of education, household income, employment status, lifestyle factors (smoking; alcohol use; physical activities) and clinical characteristics (use of hormone treatment; depression; body mass index; hypercholesterolemia; hypertension, diabetes; and histories of cardiovascular disease). At any time during 1999–2010, if older women were residing at locations with high PM<sub>2.5</sub>, their hazards for accelerated global cognitive decline and all-cause dementia respectively would be 81% (HR=1.81; 1.42–2.32) and 92% (HR=1.92; 1.32–2.80) greater than if they had low exposure. This increase in hazard for all-cause dementia associated with high PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure was 68% (HR=1.68; 0.97–2.92), 91% (HR=1.91; 1.17–3.14), and 295% (HR=3.95; 1.18–13.19), respectively, in ɛ3/3, ɛ3/4, and ɛ4/4 carriers. High PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure also increase the hazard for global cognitive decline by 65% (HR=1.65; 1.23–2.23), 93% (HR=1.93; 1.29–2.90), and 264% (HR=3.64; 1.36–9.69) in women of ɛ3/3, ɛ3/4, and ɛ4/4 alleles.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="tp2016280f1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p><italic>In vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> nPM exposure on Aβ levels. (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>b</bold>) <italic>In vivo</italic> nPM exposure of female EFAD mice (<italic>N</italic>=5 mice per experimental group). (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold>). Cerebral cortex sagittal sections were analyzed for Aβ plaque load using two independent staining: (<bold>a</bold>) Thioflavin S, (<bold>b</bold>) 4G8 antibody. Both reagents showed responses to nPM in E4FAD mice but not in E3FAD. For Thioflavin S, E3FAD coeff, −0.09, <italic>P</italic>=0.79; E4FAD, coeff 1.06, <italic>P</italic>=0.048. E4FAD mice had 2.8-fold greater increased total plaque load after nPM than E3FAD mice (E3FAD coeff, 0.49, <italic>P</italic>=0.27; E4FAD, coeff 1.39, <italic>P</italic>=0.04). (<bold>c</bold>) Aβ oligomers in soluble extracts of cerebral cortex were increased by nPM exposure in E4FAD mice (coeff 0.03, <italic>P</italic>=0.03), with trend of increase in E3FAD (coeff 0.07, <italic>P</italic>=0.07). (<bold>d</bold>,<bold>e</bold>) <italic>In vitro</italic> nPM exposure (N2a-APP/swe cells). Cells exposed to 10 μg ml<sup>−1</sup> nPM for 24 h showed 35% increased sAPPβ/α ratio (<italic>P</italic>=0.02). Culture media Aβ42 levels increased twofold (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). White bar, control; black bar, nPM exposed. Mean±s.e. *<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, ***<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.0001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="tp2016280f2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p><italic>In vivo</italic> nanosized particulate matter (nPM) exposure decreased hippocampal CA1 neurite density. (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>d</bold>) Silver histochemistry for neurodegeneration in hippocampal subregions CA1 pyramidal neuron layer and dentate gyrus (DG). EFAD mice, <italic>N</italic>=5 mice per group; B6 mice, <italic>N</italic>=9 mice/group. (<bold>a</bold>) Whole hippocampus; scale bar, 500 μm. (<bold>b</bold>) Hippocampal subregions: scale bar, 100 μm; left panel: CA1, Nissl-stained CA1 neuron layer; center, detail of silver staining from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3a</xref> to show neurites; right, density filtered to resolve neurites. (<bold>c, d</bold>) nPM caused decreased neurite density in CA1 neurons of EFAD and wild-type mice (C57BL/6J) without affecting dentate gyrus neurons. Overall nPM effects on CA1, combining E3FAD and E4FAD, was significant (<italic>P</italic>=0.02, adjusting for genetic effect): E3FAD (coeff=−0.09, <italic>P</italic>=0.03); C57BL/6J, (coeff=−0.25 <italic>P</italic>=0.003). White bar, control; black bar, nPM exposed. Mean±s.e. *<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, ***<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.005.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="tp2016280f3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4">
<label>Figure 4</label>
<caption>
<p>Chronic nPM exposure of female EFAD and C57BL/6J mice alters the GluR1 receptor subunit, but not other synaptic proteins. (<bold>a</bold>) Hippocampus glutamatergic receptor protein subunit GluR1 was decreased by nPM in both E3FAD (coeff=−0.26, <italic>P</italic>=0.01), E4FAD (coeff=−0.32, <italic>P</italic>=0.01) and C57BL/6J (coeff=−0.42, <italic>P</italic>=0.002) mice. (<bold>b</bold>–<bold>d</bold>) GluR2, NR2A and NR2B were unchanged. White bar, control; black bar, nPM exposed. EFAD, <italic>N</italic> = 5 mice per experimental group; B57BL/6, <italic>N</italic> = 9 mice per experimental group. Mean±s.e. **<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01, ***<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.005.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="tp2016280f4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>