<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101698480</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">46077</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Virol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Virol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>American journal of virology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1949-0097</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1949-0100</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28203321</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5304422</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS840478</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Practical Consideration of Poliovirus as an Oncolytic
Virotherapy</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Denniston</surname>
<given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Crewdson</surname>
<given-names>Hannah</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rucinsky</surname>
<given-names>Nicole</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stegman</surname>
<given-names>Andrew</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Remenar</surname>
<given-names>Diana</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moio</surname>
<given-names>Katherine</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>Brianne</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Higginbotham</surname>
<given-names>Alexandra</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Keffer</surname>
<given-names>Ross</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brammer</surname>
<given-names>Sarah</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Horzempa</surname>
<given-names>Joseph</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Graduate Health Sciences, West Liberty
University, West Liberty, WV, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Natural Sciences and Mathematics, West
Liberty University, West Liberty, WV, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">Corresponding Author: Joseph Horzempa, Department of Graduate
Health Sciences, West Liberty University, West Liberty, WV, USA and Department
of Natural Sciences and Mathematics, West Liberty University, West Liberty, WV,
USA, Tell: 304-336-8284, Fax: 304-336-8266,
<email>joseph.horzempa@westliberty.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>26</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>3</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>13</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<permissions>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
<license-p>This open access article is distributed under a Creative Commons
Attribution (CC-BY) 3.0 license.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p id="P1">The inauguration of novel treatment strategies into the clinical setting
faces a number of hurdles. In addition to treatment efficacy and safety,
acceptance by doctors and patients is paramount to the success of novel
therapies. Although viruses are the cause of numerous infectious diseases, these
acellular entities have been harnessed over the years to benefit mankind.
Recently, a recombinant Poliovirus-Rhinovirus Chimera (PVSRIPO) has shown
promise for the treatment of glioblastoma in clinical trials as well as other
cancer types in animal models. In this literature review, we discuss the use of
PVSRIPO as an oncolytic virotherapy. In addition to being a potential treatment
for glioblastoma, this recombinant virus could possibly be used against other
cancers because many tumor cells express the PVSRIPO receptor antigens (CD155)
and have a limited ability to control viral replication. Moreover, virus-induced
immune responses contribute to the efficacy of PVSRIPO. Given the current
trajectory of this experimental therapy, the possibility exists that PVSRIPO
will soon be a viable treatment option for various cancer types. While many
healthcare providers and cancer patients likely welcome this new viral based
treatment, history has taught us that some may be skeptical and avoid its use
because of the viral composition of this therapy.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Oncolytic Virology</kwd>
<kwd>Poliovirus</kwd>
<kwd>PVSRIPO</kwd>
<kwd>Glioblastoma</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S1" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Risks and Benefits of Current Cancer Treatments</title>
<p id="P2">Current cancer treatment is dominated by chemotherapy, radiation therapy
and surgery. Cancer treatments are directed to target mild cancers, or to
prolong the survival time and preserve the quality of life in patients with
advanced disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Chan and McFadden, 2014</xref>;
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel <italic>et al</italic>.,
2012</xref>). Overall, 5-year cancer survival rates have increased over the past
40 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel <italic>et al</italic>.,
2012</xref>). For instance, breast cancer survival rates have increased from
75.1 to 90%, childhood cancer survival rates have increased from 58.1 to
82.5% and Hodgkin’s Lymphoma survival rates have increased from
72.0 to 86.3% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel <italic>et
al</italic>., 2012</xref>).</p>
<p id="P3">Chemotherapy uses cytotoxic agents most often given intravenously to slow
growth or kill rapidly dividing cells. While rapid division is a characteristic
of cancer cells, other cells in the human body, including those in the bone
marrow, gastrointestinal system and hair follicles also divide rapidly. These
noncancerous mitotic cells are therefore often casualties of anticancer
chemotherapies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Sugerman, 2013</xref>). Due to
this collateral damage, common side effects associated with chemotherapy include
reduced bone density, cognitive deficits including change in concentration,
memory and mental speed and fatigue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel
<italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Other side effects include
infertility, impaired pulmonary function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel
<italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>), nausea and vomiting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Rapoport <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>),
peripheral neuropathy and pain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Reyes-Gibby
<italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>), neutropenia and associated
immunosuppression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Hashiguchi <italic>et
al</italic>., 2015</xref>), cardiotoxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>) and sexual
dysfunction.</p>
<p id="P4">Radiation therapy and surgery target cancer tissue more specifically.
Radiation therapy uses different types of high-energy radiation delivered either
externally via a machine or internally via a radioactive material to kill target
cancer cells by initiating DNA damage. This damage prevents the cell from
replicating effectively which eventually causes cell death. This type of
treatment can also damage cells in the surrounding area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Baskar <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Common side effects
of radiation therapy include diarrhea, fatigue, mucositis, skin toxicity and
xerostomia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Stubbe and Valero, 2013</xref>).</p>
<p id="P5">Surgery as a form of treatment is even more localized and aims to remove
the cancerous tissue directly. While this is the most confined of the
treatments, surgery is also the most invasive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Chi <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Goldfarb <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Surgical treatment
complications include lymphedema, pain, bowel complications, incontinence,
sexual dysfunction and impaired lung function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Siegel <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>).</p>
<p id="P6">More recently, recombinant virotherapy has emerged as an alternative to
standard anti-cancer therapies. The objective of this literature review is to
collect relevant information regarding the innovative process of virotherapy
development, the current application of this therapy and the possibility of
future use. Relevant articles were retrieved from the PubMed database. The
novelty of this topic limited us to review those articles that were published
between 2002 and the date of the submission of this manuscript. References lists
were also reviewed to retrieve supplementary articles. Included articles
encompass both primary and secondary literature.</p>
<p id="P7">Despite advances in chemotherapy, radiation and surgery, cancer continues
to be a top cause of death worldwide. Therefore, it is appropriate for the
healthcare community to explore diverse options of cancer treatment. The use of
oncolytic virotherapy shows encouraging results for applicable clinical use in
cancer treatment for future cancer patients.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Main Text</title>
<sec id="S4">
<title>A Brief History of Oncolytic Virotherapy</title>
<p id="P8">The linkage of viral discovery to therapeutic treatment began in 1904,
when Dr. George Dock hypothesized that viruses could be beneficial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Larson <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). This
premise was founded on a case report of a female leukemia patient who entered a
period of remission after undergoing an active infection with the influenza
virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Larson <italic>et al</italic>.,
2015</xref>). In the 1950’s, additional case reports amassed,
including a vignette about a cervical cancer patient who showed tumor size
reduction after being injected with an attenuated rabies virus as a
precautionary treatment for a dog bite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Larson
<italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). These case reports initiated
clinical trials with attenuated viruses for the purpose of cancer treatment. A
variety of viruses were used in these trials, including adenoviruses, hepatitis,
yellow fever and West Nile, among others, but since the standards of clinical
trials are not comparable to those of scientific research today the success of
these clinical trials is difficult to ascertain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Larson <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). As technology continued to
progress, specifically genetic engineering, the possibility exists for an array
of viruses to be manipulated and subsequently adapted for clinical use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Larson <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title>The Premise of Oncolytic Virotherapy</title>
<p id="P9">The practice of oncolytic virotherapy includes selecting a virus that
meets defined criteria for safety and efficacy in humans. First, the virus must
exhibit selectivity for cancer cells, while avoiding normally functioning human
cells. Some viruses have the innate ability to target cancer cells, such as
human orphan viruses (viruses not associated with disease) and animal viruses
that lack specificity for human cells, like the myxoma virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Goetz and Gromeier, 2010</xref>). Other viruses,
including poliovirus, adenovirus and herpes simplex virus, have the natural
ability to target cancer cells, but must be genetically modified to remove
virulence potential and protect the safety of the host (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Goetz and Gromeier, 2010</xref>). For oncolytic polioviruses, this
was accomplished in part by replacing an intrinsic genetic component critical
for viral protein translation (IRES element) with an equivalent component of
human rhinovirus type 2. This change prohibited viral replication in normal
neuronal cells, but supported replication in tumors of the central nervous
system and elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Goetz and Gromeier,
2010</xref>).</p>
<p id="P10">Secondly, the recombinant virus must be genetically stable and be
incapable of reverting back to its wild-type form while replicating inside tumor
cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>.,
2014</xref>). In addition, the genetically modified virus must effectively
destroy tumor cells and evade or remain functional during immune responses
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).
Oncolytic viruses must be able to bind to and infect target cancer cells. The
poliovirus naturally binds to CD155 (Necl-5, nectin-like molecule 5) which is
expressed in abundance on many malignant cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Virotherapies have
been administered in a number of routes experimentally over the years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Southam, 1960</xref>). Recent studies with
recombinant polioviruses indicate that direct intratumoral administration is
promising. After administration and viral entry, replication ensues within the
cancerous cells which leads to tumor cell lysis and death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Goetz and Gromeier, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Newly replicated viruses
freely invade additional local tumor cells and can circulate to metastatic cells
elsewhere in the body, repeating the replication-lysis process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Sze <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>).</p>
<p id="P11">The host immune response is critical for the success of oncolytic
virotherapies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>.,
2014</xref>). The type 1 interferons, INFA and B, are cytokines produced in
response to viral infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et
al</italic>., 2014</xref>). These molecules normally lead to a cascade
of events aimed to limiting viral replication. However, antiviral responses are
often inadequate in cancerous cells, limiting the effectiveness of these
cytokines to initiate viral clearance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown
<italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Conversely, type 1 interferons
are important for the development of anti-cancer adaptive immunity, a scenario
that benefits the efficacy of oncolytic virotherapies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6">
<title>Normal Infectious Processes of Polioviruses</title>
<p id="P12">The poliovirus is a small, single stranded RNA virus with an icosahedral
protein coat that causes disease in both animals and humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Kotla and Gustin, 2015</xref>). This virus is
inhaled through the nasal and pharyngeal passageways and multiplies rapidly in
the epithelial cells within the pharynx and GI tract. Infection is initiated
upon viral attachment of capsid proteins VP1, VP2 and VP3 to CD155 receptors on
host cells. Subtle conformational changes take place within the major viral
capsid proteins (VP1, VP2 and VP3) that allow the virus to attach to the
membrane, create a pore and release the viral RNA into the cytoplasm. The viral
RNA is then replicated and translated to synthesize viral proteins within the
host cell. Translation results in a polyprotein that is then configured into
multiple intermediate forms before ultimately producing the infectious virus
form known as a virion. These viral proteins also produce another capsid for the
virus to exit and infect nearby host cells as a virion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Hogle, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p id="P13">Viral RNA is recognized in infected cells by receptors both on the
membrane and in the cytoplasm of the host cells. These receptors include TLRs
and RIG-like receptors, RIG-I and MDA-5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Hogle,
2002</xref>). Once viral RNA is recognized via RIG-like receptors, cellular
signaling leads to activation of specific transcription factors, one being IRF-3
which activates the type I interferon response. The activation of the type I
interferon response play a key role in slowing disease progression and spread.
Poliovirus contains many mechanisms to inhibit this type I interferon response.
For instance, poliovirus blocks the activation of IRF-3 thereby inhibiting the
type I interferon response. Studies suggest the virus modulates stress granules
formed in cellular cytoplasm in response to a viral infection which in turn may
contribute to blocking IRF-3 activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Kotla
and Gustin, 2015</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S7">
<title>Mechanism and Therapeutic Benefit of PVSRIPO</title>
<p id="P14">Through genetic manipulation, polioviruses have been engineered to be
highly attenuated to ensure safety and proper oncolytic function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Goetz <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). One
such recombinant poliovirus, the polio: Rhinovirus chimera (PVSRIPO) has shown
promise for glioblastoma treatment. To attenuate PVSRIPO, the Internal Ribosomal
Entry Site (IRES) of the PVSRIPO was substituted with the IRES from Human
Rhinovirus type 2 (HRV2), which is an enterovirus specific to the respiratory
system. The IRES is a nucleotide sequence located within the middle segment of
messenger RNA (mRNA) used to initiate translation. These IRES elements are
features paramount to viral protein synthesis. Changing the IRES of the PVSRIPO
allows this recombinant virus to replicate in transformed or cancerous cells.
However, the HRV2 IRES precludes replication in normal neurons, preventing
adverse neural effects, but still rendering the PVSRIPO cytotoxic to cancer
cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Goetz and Gromeier, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Brown and Gromier, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Goetz <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).
Specifically, attenuation of the IRES causes an inability of the PVSRIPO mRNA to
recruit eukaryotic Initiation Factor 4G (eIF4G). Lack of eIF4G recruitment,
which is a cap-binding protein that bridges ribosomal subunits to initiate
protein synthesis, prevents viral protein translation which causes the
attenuated PVSRIPO to be non-cytolytic in the central nervous system cells of
the host (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Goetz <italic>et al</italic>.,
2011</xref>). This attenuation of PVSRIPO in normal host cells allows for
the specificity of cytotoxicity in cancerous tissue.</p>
<p id="P15">Many attributes of PVSRIPO make this virus capable of lysing cancerous
cells but incapable of infecting and replicating in non-malignant host cells
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Brown and Gromier, 2015</xref>). PVSRIPO has
a natural affinity for CD155 antigens, which are specific surface markers
abundant on glioblastoma cells. CD155 is also expressed on antigen presenting
cells such as dendritic cells and macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Unlike cancer cells that have
a weakened antiviral response, macrophages and dendritic cells exposed to
PVSRIPO are capable of limiting viral replication and can engage T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).
PVSRIPO has potential to be used as a treatment against a multitude of cancers
as many diverse tumor cells exhibit abundant surface expression of CD155 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Merrill <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). The
PVSRIPO affinity for CD155 coupled with the attenuation of this virus- which
blocks the viral cytotoxicity in normal host cells- are central to the
selectivity of cancerous tissue by this virotherapy.</p>
<p id="P16">Many cancers can suppress immune responses, thereby prolonging the
longevity of the associated disease. PVSRIPO has the ability to activate the
host innate immune response within tumor cells, even those that elicit
immunosuppression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Brown and Gromier,
2015</xref>). In addition to viral molecules activating type I interferons, this
is also accomplished by the PVSRIPO-induced lysis of tumor cells which leads to
the release of Danger-Associated Molecular Patterns (DAMPs) that activate
inflammatory responses. Moreover, tumor cell lysis results in the exposure of
tumor antigens to antigen presenting cells and subsequently the adaptive immune
response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Brown <italic>et al</italic>.,
2014</xref>). These adaptive responses include activation of NK and Th1
cells, which target and destroy the tumor cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Goetz <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Current Application</title>
<p id="P17">Oncolytic virotherapy using PVSRIPO has been experimentally successful
in targeting glioblastoma and neuroblastoma cells, but has been ineffective in
the treatment of Burkitt’s Lymphoma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Toyoda <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Gromeier <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). The use of
polioviruses to treat neuroblastoma in mice yielded favorable results,
identifying the possibility for clinical application for similar types of
cancers, especially those prominent in childhood. Neuroblastoma is one of the
most frequent cancers in children and treatment is invasive and of high risk
with poor outcomes, so the use of PVSRIPO could be a significant new treatment
option (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Toyoda <italic>et al</italic>.,
2007</xref>).</p>
<p id="P18">Currently, several studies using mice suggested that PVSRIPO is an
effective treatment methodology. In one study, subcutaneous implantation of
neuroblastoma followed by direct tumoral administration of attenuated poliovirus
resulted in complete eradication of the tumor. Immunological analyses indicated
that this tumor was eliminated, in part, by CD8(+) T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Toyoda <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). In
another study, twelve athymic mice were implanted with glioma xenographs
<italic>in vivo</italic>. After a period of time to allow for tumor growth,
PVSRIPO inoculation was administered. Ten days after PVSRIPO inoculation, the
median tumor size had shrunk by approximately 45%. After another 18
days, tumors were destroyed in these mice indicating that even in the absence of
T cells, the PVSRIPO is effective in eliminating tumor cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Dobrikova <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>).
Phase I clinical trials for treatment of human glioblastoma by PVSRIPO are
currently in progress with continued patient recruitment at Duke University
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Gromeier <italic>et al</italic>.,
2014</xref>). In this clinical trial, upon biopsy confirmation of a viable
tumor, a catheter is implanted into the tumor that directly delivers the PVSRIPO
suspension to the glioblastoma. The catheter is then removed immediately after
inoculation and the patients are radiographically evaluated after treatment for
tumor changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Friedman, 2000</xref>). PVSRIPO
induces a lethal and irreversible virolytic effect and host immune response
cytotoxic to the tumor as early as one hour post administration and favorable
outcomes have thus far been recorded as many as 20 months after treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Gromeier <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).
Should the results of this trial remain positive, further clinical trials using
PVSRIPO to treat other types of cancer are warranted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S9">
<title>Risks and Benefits of Oncolytic Virotherapy</title>
<p id="P19">Oncolytic virotherapy as a treatment is in its infancy. Therefore,
factors regarding the overall safety and optimization of this therapy have not
yet been fully vetted. Relative to the current standard of care, virotherapy is
much less invasive and debilitating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fong,
2015</xref>). Moreover, this form of oncolytic therapy is highly selective.
Injections can be administered locally, which ensure an increased uptake by
tumor cells. The viral machinery has been engineered to allow for selection and
replication within tumor cells, limiting infection of non-cancer cells of the
patient. The poliovirus itself has added benefits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fong, 2015</xref>). The poliovirus has a large RNA size capability
making this virus amenable to genetic manipulations. Virotherapies such as
PVSRIPO have the ability to specifically target cancer cells and efficiently
induce lysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">David <italic>et al</italic>.,
2009</xref>). However, this efficiency necessitates the development of
patient selection criteria. Currently, there is no standard dose for virotherapy as
certain viruses and tumors require different dosage paradigms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">David <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).
Ultimately, a dosing strategy will be created that maximizes effectiveness and
minimizes risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fong, 2015</xref>). The
optimization of viral production will also be a challenge; little information
about cost is currently available. Hospitals will also face challenges with
administration, transport, storage and disposal of these viral agents. Although
these viruses are attenuated, they pose a potential threat to immuno-compromised
patients. Many challenges lie ahead involving the potential implementation of
these treatments. However, PVSRIPO serves as a promising treatment option for
the future of cancer therapy and may usher in a wave of virus-based therapeutics
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fong, 2015</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S10">
<title>Significance</title>
<p id="P20">According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)
National Program of Cancer Registries (NPCR) most recent report of national
cancer trends, 426.6 of every 100,000 of people who obtained medical attention
in 2010 registered as a cancer patient28 These cancers included types such as
prostate cancers, lung cancers, leukemia, esophageal and stomach cancers, to
breast and lymphatic cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Edwards <italic>et
al</italic>., 2014</xref>). The number of patients who have cancer in
the United states, in addition to the broad spectrum of body systems that cancer
can affect, impresses the importance of exploring safe and effective new
treatments of all cancers. Additionally, the process of a cell becoming
malignant is dynamic and unique, much like the patients who will be receiving
treatment. Therefore, treatment should be able to meet the demands of the
dynamic process of cancer development without harming the healthy cells within
the host.</p>
<p id="P21">Cancers arise from an accumulation of genetic mutations that transform a
healthy cell into one that causes disease. Because cancer cells are nearly
identical to healthy cells, selective toxicity with current standard therapies
is difficult to attain. Further, difficulty arises from the inability to
determine the specific changes the cancers undergo to create malignancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Workenhe and Mossman, 2014</xref>). Due to the
rapid ability of a virus to be changed by recombinant RNA technology,
researchers may be able to make “designer viruses” specific to a
patient's treatment needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Parato
<italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). Viruses can be modified to invade
cancer cells depending on status and speed of growth, receptor type displayed on
cancer cell surface, or transcriptional and translational pathway targets within
the specific cancer type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Parato <italic>et
al</italic>., 2005</xref>). By targeting these specific mechanisms,
viruses can potentially be designed to target the unique process that culminate
in malignancy. Recombinant genetic technology may allow oncologists to create an
oncolytic virus that targets the specific cancer cell type and location. A
virus’ propensity to replicate within a host cell and to target cells
specifically provides oncolytic virotherapy a pharmacokinetic advantage over
conventional cancer therapies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Parato <italic>et
al</italic>., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p id="P22">As previously mentioned, oncolytic viruses have the ability to stimulate
the patient’s immune system while replicating within the tumor cells.
Replication within the tumor cells leads to a recruitment of immune cells to
this area. In addition to enhancing the cancer fighting ability of the body,
this immune activation may benefit patients that have developed immuno-tolerance
to their current standard of care chemotherapeutic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Workenhe and Mossman, 2014</xref>). Continued use of
chemotherapies can lead to cancer cells that are drug resistant or tolerant to
these conventional therapies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Workenhe and
Mossman, 2014</xref>). By using a viral modality to trigger cancer death
which involves activation of the host immune response in combination with the
use of conventional cancer-targeting treatment, drug resistance and tolerance
may be limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Workenhe and Mossman,
2014</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S11">
<title>Clinical Perspective</title>
<p id="P23">Given the current progress of the experimental and clinical phases of
PVSRIPO therapy, the possibility exists that this recombinant virus will soon be
a viable treatment option for glioblastoma and various other cancer types. While
many healthcare providers and cancer patients may embrace this new virotherapy,
history suggests that some may be skeptical and avoid the use because of the
viral composition of this treatment. For instance, attenuated viruses have been
used safely for decades to vaccinate individuals preventing countless cases of
polio, mumps, measles, rubella and other viral diseases. However, due to a
fraudulent study and a media explosion, some individuals falsely believe that
vaccines cause autism. We suspect that cancer patients and even some physicians
may be skeptical of PVSRIPO due to the viral nature of this therapy. Then again,
the imminent threat of cancer may offset any fears. Patient education efforts
and physician outreach may be necessary to establish virotherapy as a safe
cancer treatment option.</p>
<p id="P24">The very first oncolytic virotherapy has just recently been approved by
the FDA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Greig, 2016</xref>). This
therapy-talimogene laherparepvec (Imlygic) can be used to treat patients with
skin and lymph node melanoma lesions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Greig,
2016</xref>). Talimogene laherparepvec is comprised of an attenuated herpes
virus that causes cancer cells to produce GM-CSF, a potent cytokine that acts as
a growth factor for white blood cells and induces differentiation of monocytes.
Lessons learned from the use of talimogene laherparepvec will undoubtedly
contribute to the education efforts and implementation of forthcoming
virotherapies such as PVSRIPO.</p>
<p id="P25">Based on a cohort study of FDA trends of expedited drug development and
approval programs, the novelty and aforementioned advantages of PVSRIPO indicate
that this treatment has the potential to be approved for patient use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Kesselheim <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>).
Pending FDA approval, physicians will have the option to implement this novel
form of therapy for their patients. As with all initiative therapies, the
physician needs to play an active role in patient education. The patient should
be informed of the mechanism of action of this form of therapy to fully
understand the oncolytic role PVSRIPO will play in the treatment of the
patient’s cancer. Additionally, all potential adverse reactions should
be fully disclosed to all potential patients. Although evidence suggests that
PVSRIPO has the potential to provide great therapeutic benefit to cancer
patients, we hypothesize that use in clinical practice will rely heavily on
physician acceptance and patient education.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S12">
<p id="P26">
<bold>Funding Information</bold>
</p>
<p id="P27">This work was supported in part from a grant by an Institutional Development
Award (IDeA) from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences of the National
Institutes of Health (P20GM103434).</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P28">
<bold>Author’s Contributions</bold>
</p>
<p id="P29">Risk and benefit constructed by Hannah Crewdson and Alexandra
Higginbotham. Methods contructed by Hannah Crewdon. The brief history and the
premise of Oncolytic Therapy created by Katherine Moio. The normal infectious
process of polioviruses constructed by Nicole Rucinsky. Ross Keffer constructed
mechanism and therapeutic benefit of PVSRIPO. Diana Remenar and Brianne Clark
contributed the sections Current Application. Andrew Stegmen contributed the
section Risk and Benefits of Oncolytic Virothereapy. Significance written by
Elizabeth Dennistion. Sarah Brammer corresponded with the medical team at Ohio
Valley Medical Center, acted as a consult for the clinical application section
and edited the manuscript. Joseph Horzempa constructed the abstract, edited and
contributed writing to all sections.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN2">
<p id="P30">
<bold>Ethics</bold>
</p>
<p id="P31">The authors do not make any recommendation for or against the use of
recombinant virotherapy. A physician should be consulted regarding cancer
treatment options.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3">
<p id="P32">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baskar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeoh</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cancer and radiation therapy: Current advances and future
directions</article-title>
<source/>Int. J. Med. Sci
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>199</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22408567</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gromier</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic immunotherapy through tumor-specific translation and
cytotoxicity of poliovirus</article-title>
<source/>Discovery Medicine
          <year>2015</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dobrikova</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dobrikov</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walton</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gemberling</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic polio virotherapy of cancer</article-title>
<source/>Cancer
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>120</volume>
<fpage>3277</fpage>
<lpage>3286</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24939611</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McFadden</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic poxviruses</article-title>
<source/>Ann. Rev. Virol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>119</fpage>
<lpage>141</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25839047</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kou</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qiu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Intraoperative imaging-guided cancer surgery: From current
fluorescence molecular imaging methods to future multi-modality imaging
technology</article-title>
<source/>Theranostics
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>1072</fpage>
<lpage>1084</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25250092</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>David</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thorne</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thorne</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Targeted and armed oncolytic poxviruses: A novel
multi-mechanistic therapeutic class for cancer</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Cancer
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>64</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19104515</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dobrikova</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Poiley-Nelson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Recombinant oncolytic poliovirus eliminates glioma <italic>in
vivo</italic> without genetic adaptation to a pathogenic
phenotype</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Ther
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>1865</fpage>
<lpage>1872</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18766173</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Noone</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mariotto</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Simard</surname>
<given-names>EP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boscoe</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Annual report to the nation on the status of cancer,
1975–2010, featuring prevalence of comorbidity and impact on
survival among persons with lung, colorectal, breast, or prostate
cancer</article-title>
<source/>Cancer
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>120</volume>
<fpage>1290</fpage>
<lpage>1314</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24343171</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic treatment for cancer recommended for
approval</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Ther
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>1131</fpage>
<lpage>1131</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26122825</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Poliovirus Vaccine for Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM)
(PVS-RIPO)</article-title>
<source/><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> [Internet]
          <year>2000</year>
<publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>National Library of Medicine (US)</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goetz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gromeier</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Preparing an oncolytic poliovirus recombinant for clinical
application against glioblastoma multiforme</article-title>
<source/>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>197</fpage>
<lpage>203</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20299272</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goetz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dobrikova</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shveygert</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dobrikov</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gromeier</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic poliovirus against malignant glioma</article-title>
<source/>Future Virol
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>1045</fpage>
<lpage>1058</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984883</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldfarb</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brower</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwaitzberg</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Minimally invasive surgery and cancer: controversies part
1</article-title>
<source/>Surgical Endoscopy
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>304</fpage>
<lpage>334</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19572178</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Greig</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Talimogene laherparepvec: First global approval</article-title>
<source/>Drugs
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>147</fpage>
<lpage>154</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26620366</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gromeier</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dobrikova</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dobrikov</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bryant</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic poliovirus immunotherapy of
glioblastoma</article-title>
<source/>Neuro Oncol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>41</fpage>
<lpage>41</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hashiguchi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kasai</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fukuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ichimura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yasui</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Chemotherapy-induced neutropenia and febrile neutropenia in
patients with gynecologic malignancy</article-title>
<source/>Anti-Cancer Drugs
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>1054</fpage>
<lpage>1060</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26267078</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hogle</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Poliovirus cell entry: Common structural themes in viral cell
entry pathways</article-title>
<source/>Annu. Rev. Microbiol
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>677</fpage>
<lpage>702</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142481</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kesselheim</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Franklin</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Darrow</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Trends in utilization of FDA expedited drug development and
approval programs, 1987–2014: Cohort study</article-title>
<source/>British Med. J
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>351</volume>
<fpage>h4633</fpage>
<lpage>h4633</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kotla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gustin</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Proteolysis of MDA5 and IPS-1 is not required for inhibition of
the type I IFN response by poliovirus</article-title>
<source/>Virol. J
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>158</fpage>
<lpage>158</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26437794</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Larson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oronsky</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scicinski</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fanger</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stirn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Going viral: A review of replication-selective oncolytic
adenoviruses</article-title>
<source/>Oncotarget
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>19976</fpage>
<lpage>19989</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26280277</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Merrill</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bernhardt</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sampson</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wikstrand</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bigner</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Poliovirus receptor CD<sub>155</sub>-targeted oncolysis of
glioma</article-title>
<source/>NeuroOncology
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>208</fpage>
<lpage>217</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parato</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Senger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Forsyth</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Recent progress in the battle between oncolytic viruses and
tumours</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Cancer
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>965</fpage>
<lpage>976</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16294217</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rapoport</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Molasiotis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raftopoulos</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roila</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting</article-title>
<source/>BioMed Res. Int
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>2015</volume>
<fpage>457326</fpage>
<lpage>457327</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26425547</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reyes-Gibby</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>SCJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shete</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Informative gene network for chemotherapy-induced peripheral
neuropathy</article-title>
<source/>BioData Min
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>24</fpage>
<lpage>24</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26269716</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>DeSantis</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Virgo</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mariotto</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cancer treatment and survivorship statistics,
2012</article-title>
<source/>CA Cancer J. Clin
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>220</fpage>
<lpage>241</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22700443</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Southam</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Division of microbiology: Present status of oncolytic virus
studies</article-title>
<source/>Trans. N.Y. Acad. Sci
          <year>1960</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>657</fpage>
<lpage>673</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stubbe</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Valero</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Complementary strategies for the management of radiation therapy
side effects</article-title>
<source/>J. Adv. Practitioner Oncol
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>219</fpage>
<lpage>231</lpage>
<comment>PMID: 25032003</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sugerman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Chemotherapy</article-title>
<source/>JAMA
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>310</volume>
<fpage>218</fpage>
<lpage>218</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23839767</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sze</surname>
<given-names>DY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rose</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic virotherapy</article-title>
<source/>J. Vascular Intervent. Radiol
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1115</fpage>
<lpage>1122</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Toyoda</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wimmer</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cello</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic poliovirus therapy and immunization with
poliovirus-infected cell lysate induces potent antitumor immunity against
neuroblastoma <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title>
<source/>Int. J. Oncol
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>87</lpage>
<comment>PMID: 21109928</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21109928</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Toyoda</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mueller</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wimmer</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cello</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic treatment and cure of neuroblastoma by a novel
attenuated poliovirus in a novel poliovirus-susceptible animal
model</article-title>
<source/>Cancer Res
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>2857</fpage>
<lpage>2864</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17363609</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Workenhe</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mossman</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oncolytic virotherapy and immunogenic cancer cell death:
Sharpening the sword for improved cancer treatment
strategies</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Ther
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>251</fpage>
<lpage>256</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24048442</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>