<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Stem Cell Investig</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Stem Cell Investig</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCI</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Stem Cell Investigation</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2306-9759</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2313-0792</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>AME Publishing Company</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28447035</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5388678</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">sci-04-2017.02.11</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/sci.2017.02.11</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Novel therapeutic approaches: Rett syndrome and human induced pluripotent stem cell technology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gomathi</surname>
<given-names>Mohan</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Balachandar</surname>
<given-names>Vellingiri</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1">Human Molecular Genetics and Stem Cell Laboratory, Department of Human Genetics and Molecular Biology, Bharathiar University, Coimbatore-641 046, Tamil Nadu, <country>India</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="afn1">
<p><italic>Contributions:</italic> (I) Conception and design: M Gomathi; (II) Administrative support: V Balachandar; (III) Provision of study materials or patients: M Gomathi; (IV) Collection and assembly of data: M Gomathi; (V) Data analysis and interpretation: All authors; (VI) Manuscript writing: All authors; (VII) Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor1"><italic>Correspondence to:</italic> Vellingiri Balachandar, PhD. Group Leader and Assistant Professor, Human Molecular Cytogenetics and Stem Cell Laboratory, Department of Human Genetics and Molecular Biology, Bharathiar University, Coimbatore-641 046, Tamil Nadu, India. Email: <email xlink:href="geneticbala@yahoo.co.in">geneticbala@yahoo.co.in</email>; <email xlink:href="geneticbala@gmail.com">geneticbala@gmail.com</email>.</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p><italic>Conflicts of Interest:</italic> The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>02</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<elocation-id>20</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>26</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>21</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>2017 Stem Cell Investigation. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Stem Cell Investigation.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Recent advances in induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) technology target screening and discovering of therapeutic agents for the possible cure of human diseases. Human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSC) are the right kind of platform for testing potency of specific active compounds. Ayurveda, the Indian traditional system of medicine developed between 2,500 and 500 BC, is a science involving the intelligent formulations of herbs and minerals. It can serve as a “goldmine” for novel neuroprotective agents used for centuries to treat neurological disorders. This review discusses limitations in screening drugs for neurological disorders and the advantages offered by hiPSC integrated with Indian traditional system of medicine. We begin by describing the current state of hiPSC technology in research on Rett syndrome (RTT) followed by the current controversies in RTT research combined with the emergence of patient-specific hiPSC that indicate an urgent need for researchers to understand the etiology and drug mechanism. We conclude by offering recommendations to reinforce the screening of active compounds present in the ayurvedic medicines using the human induced pluripotent neural model system for research involving drug discovery for RTT. This integrative approach will fill the current knowledge gap in the traditional medicines and drug discovery.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<title>Keywords: </title>
<kwd>Human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSC)</kwd>
<kwd>Rett syndrome (RTT)</kwd>
<kwd>neurodevelopmental disorder</kwd>
<kwd>ayurvedic medicines</kwd>
<kwd>drug discovery</kwd>
<kwd>active compounds</kwd>
<kwd>Indian Traditional Ayurvedic System</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>