<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9500169</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">20475</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neurobiol Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neurobiol. Dis.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Neurobiology of disease</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0969-9961</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-953X</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26992888</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5409093</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2016.03.010</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS780843</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Rapamycin Prevents, but does not Reverse, Aberrant Migration in Pten Knockout Neurons</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Getz</surname>
<given-names>Stephanie A</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>DeSpenza</surname>
<given-names>Tyrone</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Meijie</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luikart</surname>
<given-names>Bryan W</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Department of Physiology and Neurobiology, Geisel School of Medicine at Dartmouth College Lebanon, New Hampshire, 03756, United States of America</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><bold>Submitting and Communicating Author:</bold> Prof. Bryan W. Luikart, Geisel School of Medicine at Dartmouth, Physiology and Neurobiology, 1 Medical Center Drive, Borwell 708E, Lebanon, 03756, USA, <email>Bryan.W.Luikart@Dartmouth.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p id="P32">
<bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold>
</p>
<p id="P33">The authors declare no competing financial interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>3</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>15</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<lpage>20</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.nbd.2016.03.010-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN) is a major negative regulator of the Akt/mammalian target of rapamycin (mTor) pathway. Mutations in <italic>PTEN</italic> have been found in a subset of individuals with autism and macrocephaly. Further, focal cortical dysplasia (FCD) has been observed in patients with <italic>PTEN</italic> mutations prompting us to examine the role of Pten in neuronal migration. The dentate gyrus of Pten<sup><italic>Flox/Flox</italic></sup> mice was injected with Cre- and non-Cre-expressing retroviral particles, which integrate into the dividing genome to birthdate cells. Control and Pten knockout (KO) cell position in the granule cell layer was quantified over time to reveal that Pten KO neurons exhibit an aberrant migratory phenotype beginning at 7.5 days-post retroviral injection (DPI). We then assessed whether rapamycin, a mTor inhibitor, could prevent or reverse aberrant migration of granule cells. The preventative group received daily intraperitoneal (IP) injections of rapamycin from 3–14 DPI, before discrepancies in cell position have been established, while the reversal group received rapamycin afterward, from 14–24 DPI. We found that rapamycin prevented and reversed somal hypertrophy. However, rapamycin prevented, but did not reverse aberrant migration in Pten KO cells. We also find that altered migration occurs through mTorC1 and not mTorC2 activity. Together, these findings suggest a temporal window by which rapamycin can treat aberrant migration, and may have implications for the use of rapamycin to treat <italic>PTEN</italic>-mutation associated disorders.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>