<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101461858</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">35583</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Autism Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Autism Res</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Autism research : official journal of the International Society for Autism Research</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1939-3792</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-3806</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27520745</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5426537</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aur.1681</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS72501</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prenatal Stress Exposure, Oxytocin Receptor Gene (<italic>OXTR</italic>) Methylation and Child Autistic Traits: The Moderating Role of <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 Genotype</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rijlaarsdam</surname>
<given-names>Jolien</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van IJzendoorn</surname>
<given-names>Marinus H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Verhulst</surname>
<given-names>Frank C</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jaddoe</surname>
<given-names>Vincent W. V.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Felix</surname>
<given-names>Janine F.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tiemeier</surname>
<given-names>Henning</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bakermans-Kranenburg</surname>
<given-names>Marian J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Centre for Child and Family Studies, Leiden University, Leiden, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>School of Pedagogical and Educational Sciences, Erasmus University Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry/ Psychology, Erasmus MC-University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Generation R Study Group, Erasmus MC-University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus MC-University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Pediatrics, Erasmus MC-University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Psychiatry, Erasmus MC-University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Marian J. Bakermans-Kranenburg, Centre for Child and Family Studies, Leiden University, PO Box 9555, 2300 RB Leiden, The Netherlands, <email>bakermans@fsw.leidenuniv.nl</email>, tel: +31 71 527 3798; fax: +31 71 527 3945</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN1">
<p id="P34">
<bold>Conflict of Interest</bold>
</p>
<p id="P35">Dr. Frank C. Verhulst is the contributing editor of the Achenbach System of Empirically Based Assessment, from which he receives remuneration. The other authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>25</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>13</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>430</fpage>
<lpage>438</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/aur.1681-->
<permissions>
<license>
<license-p>This is the peer reviewed version of the following article:
Rijlaarsdam, J., van IJzendoorn, M. H., Verhulst, F. C., Jaddoe, V. W. V.,
Felix, J. F., Tiemeier, H. and Bakermans-Kranenburg, M. J. (2017), Prenatal
stress exposure, oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) methylation, and child
autistic traits: The moderating role of OXTR rs53576 genotype. Autism
Research, 10: 430–438. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/aur.1681">10.1002/aur.1681</ext-link>, which has been published in final form at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/aur.1681/abstract">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/aur.1681/abstract</ext-link>.
This article may be used for non-commercial purposes in accordance with
Wiley Terms and Conditions for Self- Archiving.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Lay Abstract</title>
<p id="P1">The gene encoding the oxytocin receptor (<italic>OXTR</italic>), localized on chromosome 3p25, is considered a promising candidate for explaining genetic vulnerability to autistic traits. Although several lines of evidence implicate <italic>OXTR</italic> SNP rs53576 (G/A) variation in social behavior, findings have been inconsistent, possibly because DNA methylation after stress exposure was eliminated from consideration. This study investigated the main and interactive effects of <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 genotype, stress exposure, and <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation on child autistic traits. Prenatal maternal stress exposure, but not <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 genotype and <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation, showed a main effect on child autistic traits. For child autistic traits in general and social communication problems in particular, we observed a significant <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 genotype by <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation interaction. More specifically, <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation levels were positively associated with social problems for <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 G-allele homozygous children but not for A-allele carriers. These results highlight the importance of incorporating epi-allelic information and support the role of <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation in child autistic traits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Scientific Abstract</title>
<p id="P2">Findings of studies investigating <italic>OXTR</italic> SNP rs53576 (G-A) variation in social behavior have been inconsistent, possibly because DNA methylation after stress exposure was eliminated from consideration. Our goal was to examine <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 allele-specific sensitivity for neonatal <italic>OXTR</italic> DNA methylation in relation to (1) a prenatal maternal stress composite, and (2) child autistic traits. Prospective data from fetal life to age 6 years were collected in a total of 743 children participating in the Generation R Study. Prenatal maternal stress exposure was uniquely associated with child autistic traits but was unrelated to <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation across both <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 G-allele homozygous children and A-allele carriers. For child autistic traits in general and social communication problems in particular, we observed a significant <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 genotype by <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation interaction in the absence of main effects, suggesting that opposing effects cancelled each other out. Indeed, <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation levels were positively associated with social problems for <italic>OXTR</italic> rs53576 G-allele homozygous children but not for A-allele carriers. These results highlight the importance of incorporating epi-allelic information and support the role of <italic>OXTR</italic> methylation in child autistic traits.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>DNA methylation</kwd>
<kwd>oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR)</kwd>
<kwd>autistic traits</kwd>
<kwd>stress exposure</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>