<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ther Adv Infect Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ther Adv Infect Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TAI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptai</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Therapeutic Advances in Infectious Disease</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2049-9361</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2049-937X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28634536</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5467880</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2049936117690501</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2049936117690501</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Telavancin: a novel semisynthetic lipoglycopeptide agent to counter the challenge of resistant Gram-positive pathogens</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>Biswadeep</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2049936117690501"></xref>
<aff id="aff1-2049936117690501">Department of Pharmacology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS) Rishikesh, Rishikesh, India</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sarkar</surname>
<given-names>Chayna</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff2-2049936117690501">Department of Pharmacology &amp; Clinical Pharmacology, North Eastern Indira Gandhi Regional Institute of Health &amp; Medical Sciences (NEIGRIHMS) Shillong, Shillong, India</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>Debasmita</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff3-2049936117690501">Department of Computer Science &amp; Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, Manipal University Jaipur, Dehmi Kalan, Jaipur Ajmer Expressway, Rajasthan, India</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>Amit</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff4-2049936117690501">Department of Surgery, All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS) Rishikesh, Rishikesh, India</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kalra</surname>
<given-names>Arnav</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff5-2049936117690501">Department of Pharmacology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS) Rishikesh, Rishikesh, India</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sahni</surname>
<given-names>Shubham</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff6-2049936117690501">Department of Pharmacology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS) Rishikesh, Rishikesh, India</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2049936117690501">
<email>biswadeepdas@hotmail.com</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p><bold>Conflict of interest statement:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>08</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>49</fpage>
<lpage>73</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2017</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Telavancin (TD-6424), a semisynthetic lipoglycopeptide vancomycin-derivative, is a novel antimicrobial agent developed by Theravance for overcoming resistant Gram-positive bacterial infections, specifically methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA). The US Food and Drug Administration (USFDA) had approved telavancin in 2009 for the treatment of complicated skin and skin structure infections (cSSSIs) caused by Gram-positive bacteria, including MRSA (<italic>S. aureus, Streptococcus agalactiae, Streptococcus pyogenes, Streptococcus anginosus</italic> group, or <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic>). Telavancin has two proposed mechanisms of action. <italic>In vitro</italic>, telavancin has a rapid, concentration-dependent bactericidal effect, due to disruption of cell membrane integrity. Telavancin has demonstrable <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against aerobic and anaerobic Gram-positive bacteria. Telavancin and vancomycin have similar spectra of activity. Gram-negative bacteria are usually non-susceptible to telavancin. Telavancin has been successfully tested in various animal models of bacteremia, endocarditis, meningitis, and pneumonia. Phase II Telavancin versus Standard Therapy for Treatment of Complicated Skin and Soft-Tissue Infections due to Gram-Positive Bacteria (FAST 1 and FAST 2) and phase III [Assessment of Telavancin in Complicated Skin and Skin Structure Infections 1 (ATLAS 1 and ATLAS 2)] clinical trials have been conducted for evaluating telavancin’s efficacy and safety in cSSSIs. Phase III clinical trials have been carried out for evaluating telavancin’s safety and efficacy in nosocomial pneumonia [Assessment of Telavancin for Treatment of Hospital acquired Pneumonia 1 and 2 (ATTAIN 1 and ATTAIN 2)]. A phase II randomized, double-blind, clinical trial has been carried out for evaluating telavancin’s safety and efficacy in uncomplicated <italic>S. aureus</italic> bacteremia [Telavancin for Treatment of Uncomplicated <italic>S. aureus</italic> Bacteremia (ASSURE)]. Pacemaker lead–related infective endocarditis due to a vancomycin intermediate <italic>S. aureus</italic> (VISA) strain (non-daptomycin susceptible) was successfully treated with parenteral telavancin for 8 weeks. Telavancin extensively binds to serum albumin (~93%) and has a relatively small volume of distribution. Telavancin is not biotransformed by any cytochrome P<sub>450</sub> microsomal enzymes and excreted mainly in the urine. Though well-tolerated, worrisome adverse effects, including renal dysfunction and QTc prolongation are of potential concern. Given its extensive binding to plasma proteins, long half-life, and a long post-antibiotic effect, it represents a promising addition to the therapeutic armamentarium in combating infections caused by resistant Gram-positive pathogens, namely, MRSA.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>MRSA</kwd>
<kwd>second-generation lipoglycopeptide resistant Gram-positive infections</kwd>
<kwd>semisynthetic</kwd>
<kwd>Telavancin (TD-6424)</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>