<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NPJ Genom Med</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NPJ Genom Med</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>NPJ Genomic Medicine</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2056-7944</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28706735</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5505728</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pii">npjgenmed201631</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npjgenmed.2016.31</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The importance of copy number variation in congenital heart disease</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running">CNV in CHD</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Costain</surname>
<given-names>Gregory</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Silversides</surname>
<given-names>Candice K</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bassett</surname>
<given-names>Anne S</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Clinical Genetics Research Program, Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</institution>, Toronto, ON, <country>Canada</country></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Medical Genetics Residency Training Program, University of Toronto and Division of Clinical and Metabolic Genetics, The Hospital for Sick Children</institution>, Toronto, ON, <country>Canada</country></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>The Toronto Congenital Cardiac Centre for Adults, Division of Cardiology, University Health Network and Mount Sinai Hospital</institution>, Toronto, ON, <country>Canada</country></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Toronto General Research Institute and The Dalglish Family Hearts and Minds Clinic for 22q11.2 Deletion Syndrome, University Health Network</institution>, Toronto, ON, <country>Canada</country></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, University of Toronto, and Campbell Family Mental Health Research Institute, Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</institution>, Toronto, ON, <country>Canada</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>
(<email>anne.bassett@utoronto.ca</email>)</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>16031</fpage>
<lpage></lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>15</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>05</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>05</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--author-paid-->
<license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Congenital heart disease (CHD) is the most common class of major malformations in humans. The historical association with large chromosomal abnormalities foreshadowed the role of submicroscopic rare copy number variations (CNVs) as important genetic causes of CHD. Recent studies have provided robust evidence for these structural variants as genome-wide contributors to all forms of CHD, including CHD that appears isolated without extra-cardiac features. Overall, a CNV-related molecular diagnosis can be made in up to one in eight patients with CHD. These include <italic>de novo</italic> and inherited variants at established (chromosome 22q11.2), emerging (chromosome 1q21.1), and novel loci across the genome. Variable expression of rare CNVs provides support for the notion of a genetic spectrum of CHD that crosses traditional anatomic classification boundaries. Clinical genetic testing using genome-wide technologies (e.g., chromosomal microarray analysis) is increasingly employed in prenatal, paediatric and adult settings. CNV discoveries in CHD have translated to changes to clinical management, prognostication and genetic counselling. The convergence of findings at individual gene and at pathway levels is shedding light on the mechanisms that govern human cardiac morphogenesis. These clinical and research advances are helping to inform whole-genome sequencing, the next logical step in delineating the genetic architecture of CHD.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Genome-wide rare copy number variation (CNV) is now recognised as an important contributor to congenital heart disease (CHD). This review surveys recent advances in the field of structural genomics, with the goal of informing both the clinical translation of findings and the anticipated future wave of whole-genome sequencing (WGS) studies. Herein, CHD refers to major malformations of the heart or great vessels present at birth. Cardiomyopathies, vasculopathies and cardiac arrhythmias are excluded. The focus is on findings from large-scale genome-wide studies of submicroscopic germline CNV, and not on chromosomal abnormalities detectable on karyotype, case reports or small case series of individual CNVs, or deletion/duplication analyses of individual genes.</p>
<sec>
<title>Clinical description and epidemiology of CHD</title>
<p>CHD is the most common class of major congenital anomalies in humans, and a major source of morbidity and paediatric mortality around the world.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1 bib2 bib3">1–3</xref></sup> Most incidence estimates range from 4 to 10 in 1,000 live births.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1 bib2 bib3">1–3</xref></sup> Bicuspid aortic valve, isolated aneurysm of the atrial septum, and persistent left superior vena cava are usually excluded from these incidence figures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> Although most cardiac defects can be diagnosed prenatally by fetal echocardiography, many anomalies are not identified on routine prenatal ultrasound.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4 bib5 bib6 bib7">4–7</xref></sup> Prenatal diagnosis of severe CHD can improve outcomes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7 bib8 bib9">7–9</xref></sup> Signs and symptoms are related to the type and severity of the heart defect. Many, but not all, cardiac lesions are identified in childhood. Surgical repair creates a new cardiac phenotype with unique associated late sequelae. Despite advances in early detection and surgical repair, CHD remains the leading global cause of non-infectious neonatal death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref></sup> The vast majority of patients who survive this early period require lifelong specialised cardiac care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10 bib11 bib12 bib13">10–13</xref></sup></p>
<p>Beginning at 3 weeks of embryonic life, the heart is the first organ to start developing in the human embryo.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> An overview of the complex sequence of events that results in a well-formed heart at birth is beyond the scope of this review.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> Disruption of any developmental step can result in a cardiac malformation. Anatomical, functional and clinical categorisations exist for the myriad described cardiac lesions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Advances in imaging technology have led to improved diagnostic precision.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> Various constellations of multiple defects can be found together, and can result in more complex CHD, of which tetralogy of Fallot (TOF) is the most common form (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup> CHD may occur in apparent isolation, or in conjunction with other, extra-cardiac features (syndromic CHD). Overall, individuals with CHD are at increased risk for extra-cardiac congenital anomalies and for neurodevelopmental problems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>With advances in paediatric surgery, the prevalence of individuals living with CHD is increasing in many areas of the world.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup> Adults with CHD now outnumber affected children.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup> With increased longevity, there is more attention on long-term outcomes and causation. Evidence from family and twin studies supports a genetic aetiology for CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18 bib19 bib20 bib21">18–21</xref></sup> However, classic Mendelian inheritance patterns are usually not observed, reported recurrence risks are low, and there are low concordance rates of CHD within families.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18 bib19 bib20 bib21">18–21</xref></sup> Non-genetic factors, e.g., teratogens such as alcohol or infections like rubella, or other comorbidities like maternal type 1 diabetes mellitus, may have a role in increasing risk for CHD and may interact with genetic predisposition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> For these reasons CHD has long been considered an archetypal model for multifactorial inheritance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> Until recently, the main molecular genetic insights into the aetiology of CHD involved large chromosomal anomalies visible on karyotype.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Context: early studies of chromosomal imbalances in CHD</title>
<p>Major chromosomal anomalies including aneuploidies have been associated with CHD for over half a century.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref></sup> The major aneuploidies compatible with postnatal life are traditionally associated with certain types of CHD: Down syndrome/trisomy 21 (atrioventricular canal defect), Edward syndrome/trisomy 18 (ventricular septal defect or VSD, pulmonary stenosis), Patau syndrome/trisomy 13 (VSD, atrial septal defect, transposition of the great arteries or TGA), Turner syndrome/monosomy X (coarctation of the aorta, aortic stenosis, VSD), and Klinefelter syndrome/XXY (Ebstein anomaly, TOF).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref></sup> It is important to note however that a broad spectrum of CHD has been observed within each of these syndromes.</p>
<p>Although genome-wide, the resolution of karyotype is low, rarely identifying structural anomalies less than 5–10 Mb in size. Chromosomal abnormalities visible on karyotype often involve deletion or duplication of hundreds of genes, and expression of complex developmental phenotypes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup> Karyotype was thus not often helpful to identify individual genes important to cardiac morphogenesis. Over 20 years ago, a technological advance became clinically available that used targeted probe testing with fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridisation to provide a molecular diagnosis for selected microdeletion syndromes associated with CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref></sup> Testing required a high clinical index of suspicion and knowledge of the targeted syndrome to allow the specific probe to be ordered.</p>
<p>Fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridisation was instrumental in revealing the presence of submicroscopic structural anomalies associated with identifiable genetic syndromes, e.g., 7p11.23 and 22q11.2 deletions, respectively, for Williams–Beuren syndrome and 22q11.2 deletion syndrome (22q11.2DS), the latter formerly known as DiGeorge/velocardiofacial syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> Studies of these recurrent, usually <italic>de novo</italic>, 1.5–3 Mb sized CNVs have proven useful to identify individual genes (<italic>ELN</italic> at the 7p11.23 locus and <italic>TBX1</italic> and <italic>CRKL</italic> at the 22q11.2 locus) that are important in cardiac morphogenesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> Animal models with genetically engineered deletions and point mutations of selected genes have been instrumental in these studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28 bib29 bib30">28–30</xref></sup></p>
<p>These early findings have left the impression that most chromosomal anomalies associated with CHD: (i) arise as <italic>de novo</italic> mutations; (ii) usually result in multiple congenital extra-cardiac features making them readily identifiable in the newborn period; (iii) have a rather specific pattern of associated CHD per individual syndrome (e.g., supravalvular aortic stenosis in Williams–Beuren syndrome); and (iv) individually account for relatively few patients with CHD. It would take new molecular technologies to reveal otherwise.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Genome-wide CNV in health and disease</title>
<p>A breakthrough discovery in 2004 showed that structural genomic variants (CNVs) are, as a class, common in the general population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref></sup> These include both losses (deletions) and gains (duplications) with diverse potential mechanisms of action (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> CNVs are not inherently pathological. Within any individual’s genome, there are typically both myriad common (i.e., &gt;1–5% frequency in the general population), and one or more rare, CNVs. The mutation rate of structural rearrangements like CNVs is much higher than that of single base pair changes, and CNVs may disrupt none, one, or several genomic elements (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31 bib32 bib33">31–33</xref></sup> Some ‘recurrent’ CNVs are individually rare but arise with similar breakpoints in unrelated families because of an underlying genomic architecture that predisposes to CNV. CNVs that are common may act as neutral variants or sometimes as modifiers of disease susceptibility. Rare CNVs are far more likely than common CNVs to be associated with disease, especially developmental disorders like CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33 bib34 bib35 bib36">33–36</xref></sup> As for virtually all genetic variants, CNVs, including rare pathogenic CNVs, are usually associated with some degree of variable expression and/or incomplete penetrance. Increasing knowledge about CNV has revolutionized thinking about differences between individual human genomes and the genetic architecture of common complex (multifactorial) disorders like CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Genome-wide CNV in CHD</title>
<p>Over the past decade strong evidence has accumulated that genome-wide rare CNV represents a considerable source of the genetic variation that contributes to CHD susceptibility.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37 bib38 bib39 bib40 bib41 bib42 bib43 bib44 bib45 bib46 bib47 bib48 bib49 bib50 bib51 bib52 bib53 bib54 bib55 bib56">37–56</xref></sup> These findings include both known associations such as chromosome 22q11.2 deletions, and new discoveries across the genome. Studying CNV in CHD is contributing to our understanding of cardiac morphogenesis and related disorders,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> and to new knowledge that is relevant for clinical practice.</p>
<sec>
<title>Increased overall burden of rare CNVs</title>
<p>A consistent finding across multiple genome-wide studies is that there is an excess burden of rare CNVs in CHD compared with control populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38 bib39 bib40">38–40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42 bib43 bib44 bib45 bib46 bib47 bib48 bib49 bib50 bib51 bib52 bib53 bib54 bib55">42–55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup> Differences in the definition of rarity, size cut-offs, overlap of genes and/or coding sequence (exons), array platforms and the CNV calling algorithm(s) used, other technologies, exclusions (e.g., karyotypic anomalies, 22q11.2 deletions) and CHD sample ascertainment strategies, will all affect the proportions of individuals reported to have rare CNVs. The majority of patients studied were putatively non-syndromic. Most studies excluded 22q11.2 deletions and other diagnosable syndromes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). This may obscure the fact that a relatively large proportion of individuals with CHD have 22q11.2 deletions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">59</xref></sup> TOF is the best-studied cardiac lesion but all CHD adequately studied to date shows an excess burden of rare CNVs. Both gain and loss CNVs are involved, with certain loci recurring (see below), in addition to the 22q11.2 deletion. One attempt at a meta-analysis identified dozens of putatively associated loci.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref></sup> Other CNVs appear so rarely that recurrence has not yet been observed. Most studies have reported only CNVs involving autosomes; sex chromosome copy number findings may also be relevant to CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">60</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Increased burden of <italic>de novo</italic> CNVs</title>
<p>Restricting to rare CNVs that have arisen as <italic>de novo</italic> mutations shows similar excess burden findings in CHD, even after excluding 22q11.2 deletions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). Few studies employed direct control populations; however, the general population rate of <italic>de novo</italic> CNVs is well studied in other cohorts and typically quoted as &lt;2%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> One study involving patients with TGA reported a lower <italic>de novo</italic> mutation rate than for other cardiac lesions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref></sup> This would be consistent with offspring recurrence data for TGA that suggest fewer dominant-acting mutations for this CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref></sup> However, the numbers of patients studied to date is too small to draw firm conclusions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). The elevated <italic>de novo</italic> CNV mutation rate in other severe CHD may in part explain how it is maintained in the population, despite a strong negative selective pressure and before the advent of modern paediatric surgery. Although rare <italic>de novo</italic> mutations are of interest and often considered to be more highly penetrant, it is important to note that most CNVs, even rare CNVs known to be pathogenic, are inherited. Moreover, recurrent CNVs that arise <italic>de novo</italic> in some patients are inherited from parents without CHD in others (see below), consistent with variable expression and in some cases reduced penetrance.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>22q11.2 deletions and duplications</title>
<p>The role of 22q11.2 deletions in CHD was well delineated before the advent of chromosomal microarray analysis (CMA).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> Cumulative prevalence estimates of this recurrent 22q11.2 deletion include ~50% in interrupted aortic arch type B, ~33% in truncus arteriosus, ~15% in TOF and 5–10% in VSD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">59</xref></sup> Appreciation for other genome-wide rare recurrent and non-recurrent CNVs in CHD more generally has served to reinforce the importance of 22q11.2 deletions as the archetypal model for continued genetic discovery and clinical translation of findings. From a molecular genetic perspective, human and animal studies are shedding light on the specific determinants of cardiac expression (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box1">Box 1</xref>). From a clinical perspective, diagnosis is helpful and changes management, including genetic counselling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">62</xref></sup></p>
<p>General features of 22q11.2 deletions are proving to be generalisable to other CNVs associated with CHD. Although enriched for conotruncal and other anomalies, all types of CHD have been associated with 22q11.2 deletions. Severity ranges from non-viable (fetal and early pregnancy loss) to subclinical, e.g., spontaneously closing VSDs. Many patients do not have a CHD phenotype. If ascertainment is not through congenital cardiac clinics, the prevalence of readily detectable CHD may be as low as ~25–40%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">63</xref></sup> Although multi-system expression is the norm over the lifetime, readily detectable congenital anomalies may not be present.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> The CHD may appear ‘isolated’, especially prenatally or at birth, as neurodevelopmental and neuropsychiatric features may not become apparent for years or decades.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">62</xref></sup> Dysmorphic features are usually subtle, and absence of ‘typical’ facial features does not affect the likelihood of the diagnosis being present or the severity of the presentation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> Mortality is significantly increased,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> and surgical and perioperative complications in those with 22q11.2 deletions and conotruncal anomalies can be greater than other patients with the same CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">64</xref></sup> The deletion may be inherited or <italic>de novo</italic>. If inherited, the parent with the deletion will often not have CHD or, if present, the same CHD or other features as the affected proband.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> There is a high mutation rate in the population due to the local genomic architecture: flanking segmental duplications and resulting increased risk of non-allelic homologous recombination during meiosis. The reciprocal duplication can result in similar phenotypes, including CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">65</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>1q21.1 deletions and duplications</title>
<p>One of the first loci to be identified from genome-wide studies of CNV in CHD was the recurrent 1q21.1 CNV. Sometimes occurring as a deletion,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">66</xref></sup> but more commonly as a duplication, this is a highly replicated finding, especially in TOF where the prevalence appears to be just less than one in every 100 patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">68</xref></sup> As for all CNVs associated with CHD, the expression is variable, even within families, for both cardiac anomalies and other phenotypes, and is not necessarily correlated with the length of the CNV.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">69</xref></sup> 1q21.1 duplications are rare in control populations, e.g., in five out of 18,828 controls (0.027%) from three studies, where some controls were not screened for disease (reviewed in ref <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref>). Although it is uncertain if any single gene at this locus can be designated as truly causal, the most evidence points to the <italic>GJA5</italic> gene that encodes connexin 40,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">68</xref></sup> a cardiac gap junction protein expressed in the right ventricular outflow tract.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> Point mutations in <italic>GJA5</italic> can be associated with atrial fibrillation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>8p23.1 deletions overlapping GATA4</title>
<p>Before the first wave of genome-wide CNV studies, the 8p deletion syndrome and sequence mutations in <italic>GATA4</italic> were both reported to be associated with CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">72</xref></sup> Haploinsufficiency of <italic>GATA4</italic> is now one of the most frequent rare structural anomalies identified in genome-wide CNV studies of CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup> Unlike the typical chromosomal rearrangements at 1q21.1, 15q11.2 and 22q11.2 mediated by non-allelic homologous recombination, these 8p deletions are non-recurrent and of varying size. Haploinsufficiency of adjacent genomic elements like <italic>SOX7</italic> may shape the cardiac expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">73</xref></sup> Duplications at the 8p23.1 locus have also been reported in CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">60</xref></sup> The spectrum of cardiac lesions favours septal defects, including atrioventricular canal defects,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref></sup> but as for other loci there is significant cardiac phenotypic heterogeneity. <italic>GATA4</italic> encodes an essential cardiac transcription factor that works in concert with other key regulators of cardiac morphogenesis like <italic>NKX2-5</italic> and <italic>TBX5</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>15q11.2 deletions</title>
<p>The putative association of 15q11.2 deletions with CHD illustrates the complexity imbued by incomplete penetrance, non-cardiac phenotypic expression, and ascertainment. Proximal deletions in this complex region (breakpoints BP1-BP2) on chromosome 15 are risk factors of modest effect for neurodevelopmental and neuropsychiatric disorders.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74 bib75 bib76">74–76</xref></sup> A majority are inherited,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref></sup> typically from a parent with milder or no overt phenotypic consequences. With a nonspecific phenotype and prevalence in control populations of up to 1 in 400,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">75</xref></sup> 15q11.2 deletions are typically categorized as variants of uncertain significance (VUS).</p>
<p>Two early studies reported that individuals with this 15q11.2 deletion were moderately enriched in cohorts with diverse CHD, relative to control populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup> However, one study had an increased burden of extra-cardiac phenotypes in cases,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref></sup> and the other had a low prevalence in the controls used (one in 1,538).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup> Since then, 15q11.2 deletions have been identified infrequently in genome-wide CNV studies of CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> Case series of individuals with 15q11.2 deletions ascertained through clinical testing for developmental phenotypes or multiple congenital anomalies report variable rates of CHD,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74 bib75 bib76">74–76</xref></sup> influenced in part by screening with echocardiography.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref></sup> A notable proportion have had left-sided cardiac lesions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">75</xref></sup> but the observed spectrum of cardiac lesions is broad. Specific susceptibility element(s) within this region remain to be determined. The typical deletion encompasses four highly conserved, non-imprinted genes (<italic>CYFIP1</italic>, <italic>NIPA1</italic>, <italic>NIPA2</italic> and <italic>TUBGCP5</italic>) with as yet no independent link to cardiac morphogenesis. Additional rare variants are common in these individuals and may act independently or in concert with the 15q11.2 deletion to increase risk for CHD,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75 bib76 bib77">75–77</xref></sup> although in one case series there was similar prevalence of CHD in a smaller subgroup without secondary CNVs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">76</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Pathway analyses and gene families</title>
<p>Interpreting genome-wide CNVs is challenging, as individual variants are rare and often involve multiple genomic elements. Also, non-knockout mutation dosage changes in most genes are uncharacterized in both humans and model organisms. Several studies have applied pathway and gene enrichment analyses of varying degrees of sophistication to rare CNV datasets to identify gene sets important to cardiac development. Although most were limited in scope, there are significant results for not only functional gene sets that would be expected (vascular development/cardiac structure)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup> but also for more novel gene sets: WNT signalling,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup> ‘gene neighbours’ (with shared genetic or physical interactions) of <italic>GATA4</italic>/<italic>TBX5</italic>/<italic>NKX2-5</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> angiogenesis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup> semaphorin-plexin pathways,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup> ciliary proteome,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup> TGF-beta signalling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup> and neuron projection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup> The latter is notable because of the high rate of neurodevelopmental problems in patients with CHD, and similar findings from a large whole-exome sequencing study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref></sup> There is also overlap with arrhythmogenic genes initially implicated in electrical/functional as opposed to structural heart abnormalities (e.g., <italic>GJA5</italic> and <italic>CACNA1C</italic>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref></sup> CNV overlap of non-protein-coding genes like microRNAs is less well studied but may also implicate cardiac pathways.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">80</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Clinical genetic testing with CMA</title>
<p>Diagnosis of microdeletion and microduplication syndromes previously necessitated a high index of suspicion for classic clinical features that may or may not be present. CMA (also known as array comparative genomic hybridisation) is a clinical genetic test that allows for the identification of not only the individually rare CNVs underlying these established syndromes but also other emerging ‘genomic disorders’ across the genome. Initial consensus testing indications for CMA were multiple congenital anomalies and/or developmental delay/intellectual disability/autism spectrum disorder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> Various outcomes are possible with CMA (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box2">Box 2</xref>).</p>
<p>The clinical yield of CMA in CHD has been best described in the prenatal setting. Jansen <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> identified 13 publications that included 1,131 cases in their meta-analysis of array comparative genomic hybridisation studies in prenatally diagnosed CHD. The incremental yield (i.e., excluding aneuploidy and 22q11.2 deletions) of clinically relevant CNVs was 7.0%; 3.4% in ‘isolated’ CHD and 9.3% in syndromic CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> When including 22q11.2 deletions, the overall yield was 12% (about one in eight).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> An additional benefit of CMA was in the detection of atypical 22q11.2 deletions that are not detectable using standard probes in targeted fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridisation testing. VUS were identified in an additional 3.4% of CHD fetuses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> Thus for pre-test counselling, one might predict a 14% chance of uncovering an anomaly on CMA that is deemed clinically reportable: 4% 22q11.2 deletion, 7% other pathogenic CNV and 3% VUS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> One caveat is that pathogenic CNV included both those variants implicated in CHD, as well as ‘incidental’ findings relevant to neurodevelopment. The largest component study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">82</xref></sup> drove most of the significant findings in this meta-analysis. As more knowledge accumulates, original results of such genetic testing need to be re-annotated with respect to pathogenicity. Postnatal studies support a similarly high and increasing yield of pathogenic CNVs in both isolated and syndromic CHD cohorts,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">83</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">84</xref></sup> as well as a high rate of VUS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">85</xref></sup> As expected, the yield is consistently higher in individuals with syndromic CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">83</xref></sup></p>
<p>Indications for genome-wide testing are likely to expand. In practice, CMA is now often offered for apparently isolated forms of serious CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">84</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">85</xref></sup> Some have advocated for the universal postnatal use of CMA in isolated CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">86</xref></sup> In consanguineous families, single-nucleotide polymorphism arrays offer the added benefit of determining regions of loss of heterozygosity, which may then direct targeted sequencing of recessive genes implicated in cardiovascular development. The cost of testing and the current high rate of VUS are important disadvantages. Another major caveat is that most single gene disorders are not detectable with CMA. Patients, families and clinicians may mistakenly conclude on the basis of a normal CMA result that an identifiable genetic contribution to the CHD has been ruled out (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box2">Box 2</xref>). The application of CMA, while helpful for providing a molecular diagnosis for a significant minority of patients with CHD, is not a replacement for a comprehensive medical genetic evaluation.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Recurrence risk estimation and genetic counselling</title>
<p>Genetic counselling in CHD has traditionally relied upon empiric recurrence risk values,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">88</xref></sup> but rare CNVs can have a significant impact in specific cases. As in other domains, classic microdeletion syndromes like 22q11.2DS are the archetypal example of clinical applicability. Other genetically diagnosable subtypes of CHD promise similar possibilities with respect to changing standard recurrence risk prediction and genetic counselling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">88</xref></sup></p>
<p>Incorporating rare CNVs into risk prediction and counselling requires a nuanced approach. Careful phenotyping and genotyping of the parents is essential.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">87</xref></sup> A <italic>de novo</italic> CNV may be mistaken for the sole, causal variant in an individual with CHD. In one example, a subject with left-sided CHD and a <italic>de novo</italic> partial 1q21.1 duplication also inherited two rare CNVs overlapping candidate genes for CHD from a less severely affected father.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup>
<italic>De novo</italic> rare CNVs can seemingly have no, or subclinical deleterious effects. Parental germline mosaicism is also a consideration. In one recent study of rare CNV in CHD, the parents of two out of 20 affected probands with apparently <italic>de novo</italic> CNVs were ultimately found to have low level mosaicism in serum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup></p>
<p>Most rare CNVs are inherited. Some, such as 22q11.2 deletions, are recurrent and/or have been observed in unrelated individuals, while others are ultra-rare or unique to a particular family (private). Inheritance of a CNV from a purportedly unaffected parent can be falsely reassuring. As discussed above, variable expression of cardiac phenotypes is the norm. The effects of high but incompletely penetrant mutations on reproductive fitness in the parental generation are an important source of bias.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">89</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90">90</xref></sup> A parent may also have a subclinical cardiac phenotype (e.g., bicuspid aortic valve demonstrates familial recurrence with hypoplastic left heart syndrome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">91</xref></sup>) or a non-cardiac phenotype that may not be readily apparent. Alternatively, inheritance of any variant from an affected parent has an <italic>a priori</italic> likelihood of at least 50%. Co-segregation of a variant with CHD within a nuclear family (i.e., from affected parent to affected child) is thus suggestive but not specific. Two large-scale studies have considered multiplex nuclear families,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup> but none to date have adjudicated CNVs within the extended family context. Counselling always needs to emphasise the potential for considerable variability in the type and severity of CHD, and in any extra-cardiac manifestations.</p>
<p>Prognostication in paediatric probands and concerns about sibling recurrence were previously the primary impetus for clinical genetic testing and counselling. With improved childhood survival, there is growing interest in issues germane to adults with CHD,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10 bib11 bib12">10–12</xref></sup> including offspring recurrence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">88</xref></sup> Irrespective of informative molecular genetic findings, surveillance during pregnancy, including fetal echocardiography, is the standard of care for offspring of both women and men with CHD. In the setting of a putative susceptibility CNV in either parent, there may be opportunities for pre-implantation genetic diagnosis or prenatal genetic diagnosis (with chorionic villus sampling or amniocentesis). The above caveats about interpreting inherited variants are relevant in this situation. Whether genetic subtyping with respect to rare CNV could also inform general obstetrical management in women with CHD is a question that requires further study.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Clinical prognostication and prediction of extra-cardiac features</title>
<p>Rare CNVs are associated with a range of developmental disorders and major extra-cardiac phenotypes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">92</xref></sup> Available data suggest that ‘syndromal’ patients with TOF, including those with recognisable genetic syndromes, have worse surgical outcomes and worse 10-year actuarial survival.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib93">93</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94">94</xref></sup> Gaynor <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">95</xref></sup> showed that neurodevelopmental outcomes were also significantly worse in infants with CHD who had confirmed or suspected genetic syndromes. Notably, patient-specific factors were more important predictors of worse neurodevelopmental outcomes than intraoperative factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">95</xref></sup> There is a clinical impetus to better understand and predict phenotypic expression of rare CNVs across the lifespan, particularly as regards surgical and neurodevelopmental outcomes. In general, the larger and rarer the rearrangement the more easily observable the phenotypic effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> Given comparably sized rearrangements at the same locus, deletions usually have more severe phenotypic effects than duplications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> Last, extra-cardiac features can appear later in life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">92</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib96">96</xref></sup> For this reason, the ‘syndromic’ label is difficult to apply reliably and may be misleading, particularly in children and in the prenatal setting.</p>
<p>Two studies have explored the potential consequences of large rare CNVs on early outcomes, after excluding aneuploidies and 22q11.2 deletions. Carey and colleagues studied 223 patients with single-ventricle CHD and data on neurocognitive and growth outcomes at 14 months.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup> They identified putatively pathogenic rare genic CNVs &gt;300 kb in size in 14% (25 duplications and six deletions), including CNVs associated with genomic disorders in 13 patients. Comparing those with a deletion or duplication (CNV+) to those without such a CNV showed some subtle effects on growth associated with duplications, and worse neurocognitive outcomes on one of two measures in the small subgroup with deletions. Of note, worse neurodevelopmental outcomes are associated with large deletions in other populations without CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">97</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98">98</xref></sup> As anticipated, worse neurocognitive outcomes were associated with the genomic disorders associated with recurrent CNVs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup> Only three out of the 14 subjects examined in the CNV+ group had dysmorphic features or significant extra-cardiac phenotypes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup> Recently, Kim <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">54</xref></sup> reported that the presence of a rare genic CNV &gt;300 kb in size was also independently associated with decreased transplant-free survival in a separate cohort of 422 children with non-syndromic CHD.</p>
<p>With increasing survival into adulthood, genetic factors that may inform longevity and reproduction are clinically, as well as scientifically, relevant. Late cardiac complications result in significant morbidity and mortality; however, not all patients develop adverse late outcomes (cardiac or extra-cardiac).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10 bib11 bib12">10–12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99">99</xref></sup> Adults with 22q11.2DS, with and without CHD, have been studied.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">89</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib100">100</xref></sup> One study of reproductive fitness in adults with TOF and without 22q11.2DS showed that syndromal subjects were more likely to be childless, but failed to identify any association with the rare CNV profile.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref></sup> A smaller adult cohort with TGA, ascertained and studied in a similar manner, showed comparable results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref></sup> A majority of deaths in adults with CHD are a consequence of cardiovascular complications, including heart failure, arrhythmias and sudden death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10 bib11 bib12">10–12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99">99</xref></sup> Whether rare CNV burden is also associated with later clinical outcomes is unknown.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Insights into human cardiac development, and implications for discovery-based science</title>
<p>Several genetic mechanisms and many genes are involved in increasing susceptibility to CHD. Microarray technology for genome-wide CNV detection has greatly accelerated the pace of discovery of new candidate genes and pathways. Ongoing research to delineate copy number variable regions in the genome and measure their frequencies in the general population, at ever-higher resolutions, is key to being able to interpret results from disease populations. Efforts to catalogue CNV loci associated with CHD are valuable (see, e.g., the meta-analysis by Thorsson <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref></sup>), but any such list requires regular updating and revision.</p>
<p>CNVs can narrow critical regions for CHD, including those previously implicated by large karyotypically-visible anomalies. Hundreds to thousands of protein-coding genes are expressed in the human heart or great vessels at some point in early development. The complex interplay of multiple proteins and regulatory elements may lead to relative weak spots susceptible to disruption by mutations, yet this susceptibility is balanced by the innate redundancy of these systems. Disruption of normal cardiac morphogenesis requires overcoming the robustness of genetic networks that have been fine-tuned through evolution. By virtue of their size and mutational frequency, CNVs can simultaneously disrupt multiple genes and/or regulatory elements within an individual (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>), and this could be why CNV is so important to CHD causation. In addition to the examples provided above, studies involving the 1p36 deletion syndrome nicely illustrate this concept, as well as the associated challenges in ascribing causality to specific genes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib101 bib102 bib103 bib104 bib105">101–105</xref></sup> Only a minority of rare CNVs however will result in complex multi-system developmental phenotypes and/or <italic>in utero</italic> or early neonatal mortality.</p>
<p>The considerable variability in the type and severity of CHD associated with individual recurrent CNVs provides further support for, and new insights into, the genetically and functionally interdependent pathways that govern cardiogenesis. There appears to be significant shared underlying genetic susceptibility to lesions considered anatomically discrete, akin to the genetically related spectrum of seemingly disparate neurodevelopmental disorders.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">92</xref></sup> Combining clinically distinct CHD (e.g., multiple conotruncal defects) can increase power for rare variant identification and analyses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> Common and rare genetic modifiers of expression remain to be discovered (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box1">Box 1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Future considerations</title>
<p>Individually rare CNVs—gains and losses, inherited and <italic>de novo</italic>—are collectively important genetic factors contributing to abnormal heart and great vessel development in humans. All rare variants sufficiently studied to date are characterised by some degree of variable cardiac and extra-cardiac expression. Many also display reduced penetrance. Estimating these parameters is challenging, and can be confounded by ascertainment bias and reproductive fitness effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">89</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90">90</xref></sup> The individual rarity of non-recurrent CNVs has meant that there is often insufficient evidence (be it epidemiology, cell biology or model organism-based) to conclude causality. Large human sample sizes including the wealth of data generated from clinical use of CMA, high-throughput model organism screening,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib106">106</xref></sup> and targeted mutagenesis using CRISPR/Cas9 technology will all help in this endeavour.</p>
<p>Epistatic interactions are not well studied in human CHD. Our ability to provide increasingly personalised counselling will be determined by our understanding of modifiers of expression. Elegant experiments in mice with heterozygous <italic>Nkx2-5</italic> mutations demonstrate the layers of complexity that we can expect to encounter even in individuals with pathogenic single-gene mutations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib107">107</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib108">108</xref></sup> For CNV, genome-wide molecular studies in cohorts with 22q11.2 deletions provide the template for studying other recurrent variants (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box1">Box 1</xref>). For example, an immediate next step for many CNVs would be to carefully define the breakpoints and study the intact allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). The success of this approach is best illustrated by distal 1q21.1 deletions causing TAR syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib109">109</xref></sup></p>
<p>In our experience, the primary hope of many families and clinicians is that prenatal or early postnatal genetic, e.g., CMA, testing will help in predicting neurodevelopmental outcomes. This has not been the focus of most studies reviewed herein. However, research on CNV in CHD has been occurring in parallel with studies of developmental delay/intellectual disability, autism spectrum disorder and schizophrenia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33 bib34 bib35 bib36">33–36</xref></sup> Our understanding of genome-wide CNV, in terms of both general mechanisms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>) and specific loci, has been heavily influenced by neurodevelopmental disorders. A component of neurocognitive outcomes in individuals with CHD is genetically determined, and this can be dissected using the same approaches as studies of developmental disorders more generally. The expectation is that the frequency of VUS will decrease and the helpfulness of pathogenic CNV diagnoses will improve as more data accrue. The escalating uptake of methods that facilitate prenatal detection of CNV, including non-invasive prenatal testing that now permits screening for selected recurrent microdeletions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib110">110</xref></sup> will further stoke demands for reliable prognostication and genetic counselling.</p>
<p>There is an impetus to consider in a similar fashion to CNV and structural variation the contribution of rare sequence-based changes to the genetic architecture of CHD. New genetic technologies have proved useful in advancing our understanding of CHD aetiopathogenesis, and increasing clinical diagnostic yield. Recently, whole-exome sequencing has begun to facilitate novel gene discovery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib111">111</xref></sup> In the two largest whole-exome sequencing study to date, Zaidi <italic>et al.</italic> and Homsy <italic>et al.</italic> demonstrated enrichment of <italic>de novo</italic> point mutations in individuals with severe CHD and identified multiple new candidate genes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib111">111</xref></sup> Interpretation of rare sequence variants will be informed by genes and pathways identified through rare CNV. WGS is the next logical step in this progression. The ability to comprehensively assess sequence and structural changes in coding and noncoding sequence genome-wide within an individual with CHD will undoubtedly identify new mechanisms that govern human cardiac morphogenesis. WGS offers the promise of improved resolution with respect to structural variation compared with CMA. The path forward involves the application of WGS on a large-scale. This will need to be married with careful phenotyping, family studies, and other hallmarks of excellence in genetic discovery study design. Personal WGS as a single universal genetic test in CHD that is cost-effective and of broadly applicable clinical utility is a highly anticipated but future consideration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib112">112</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>ASB holds the Canada Research Chair in Schizophrenia Genetics and Genomic Disorders, and the Dalglish Chair in 22q11.2 Deletion Syndrome. This work was supported by the University of Toronto McLaughlin Centre and Canadian Institutes of Health Research (MOP 97800). The authors thank Gladys Wong and Sean Bekeschus for assistance with manuscript preparation.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="bib1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hoffman, J. I. &amp; Kaplan, S. <article-title>The incidence of congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1890</fpage>–1900 (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12084585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van der Linde, D. et al. <article-title>Birth prevalence of congenital heart disease worldwide: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>2241</fpage>–2247 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22078432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van der Bom, T. et al. <article-title>The changing epidemiology of congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Cardiol.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>–60 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21045784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhang, Y. F., Zeng, X. L., Zhao, E. F. &amp; Lu, H. W. <article-title>Diagnostic value of fetal echocardiography for congenital heart disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/>Medicine (Baltimore)
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>e1759</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26496297</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Friedberg, M. K. et al. <article-title>Prenatal detection of congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>J. Pediatr.
<volume>155</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>–31, 31.e1 (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19394031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bahtiyar, M. O. &amp; Copel, J. A. <article-title>Screening for congenital heart disease during anatomical survey ultrasonography</article-title>. <source/>Obstet. Gynecol. Clin. North Am.
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>–223 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26002162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Donofrio, M. T. et al. <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of fetal cardiac disease: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>2183</fpage>–2242 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24763516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Holland, B. J., Myers, J. A. &amp; Woods, C. R. Jr. <article-title>Prenatal diagnosis of critical congenital heart disease reduces risk of death from cardiovascular compromise prior to planned neonatal cardiac surgery: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/>Ultrasound Obstet. Gynecol.
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>631</fpage>–638 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25904437</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Khoshnood, B. et al. <article-title>Trends in prenatal diagnosis, pregnancy termination, and perinatal mortality of newborns with congenital heart disease in France, 1983–2000: a population-based evaluation</article-title>. <source/>Pediatrics
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>–101 (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15629987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Silversides, C. K. et al. <article-title>Canadian Cardiovascular Society 2009 Consensus Conference on the management of adults with congenital heart disease: shunt lesions</article-title>. <source/>Can. J. Cardiol.
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>e70</fpage>–e79 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20352137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Silversides, C. K. et al. <article-title>Canadian Cardiovascular Society 2009 Consensus Conference on the management of adults with congenital heart disease: outflow tract obstruction, coarctation of the aorta, tetralogy of Fallot, Ebstein anomaly and Marfan’s syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Can. J. Cardiol.
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>e80</fpage>–e97 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20352138</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Silversides, C. K. et al. <article-title>Canadian Cardiovascular Society 2009 Consensus Conference on the management of adults with congenital heart disease: complex congenital cardiac lesions</article-title>. <source/>Can. J. Cardiol.
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>e98</fpage>–117 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20352139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bhatt, A. B. et al. <article-title>Congenital heart disease in the older adult: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>1884</fpage>–1931 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25896865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Munoz-Chapuli, R. &amp; Perez-Pomares, J. M. <article-title>Cardiogenesis: an embryological perspective</article-title>. <source/>J. Cardiovasc. Transl. Res.
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>–48 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20560033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Egbe, A., Uppu, S., Lee, S., Ho, D. &amp; Srivastava, S. <article-title>Prevalence of associated extracardiac malformations in the congenital heart disease population</article-title>. <source/>Pediatr. Cardiol.
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1239</fpage>–1245 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24823885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marino, B. S. et al. <article-title>Neurodevelopmental outcomes in children with congenital heart disease: evaluation and management: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>1143</fpage>–1172 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22851541</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marelli, A. J., Mackie, A. S., Ionescu-Ittu, R., Rahme, E. &amp; Pilote, L. <article-title>Congenital heart disease in the general population: changing prevalence and age distribution</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>163</fpage>–172 (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17210844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Oyen, N. et al. <article-title>Recurrence of congenital heart defects in families</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>–301 (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597048</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chin-Yee, N. J., Costain, G., Swaby, J. A., Silversides, C. K. &amp; Bassett, A. S. <article-title>Reproductive fitness and genetic transmission of tetralogy of Fallot in the molecular age</article-title>. <source/>Circ. Cardiovasc. Genet.
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>–109 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24563425</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pierpont, M. E. et al. <article-title>Genetic basis for congenital heart defects: current knowledge: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association Congenital Cardiac Defects Committee, Council on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young: endorsed by the American Academy of Pediatrics</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>3015</fpage>–3038 (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17519398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib21">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gill, H. K., Splitt, M., Sharland, G. K. &amp; Simpson, J. M. <article-title>Patterns of recurrence of congenital heart disease: an analysis of 6,640 consecutive pregnancies evaluated by detailed fetal echocardiography</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>923</fpage>–929 (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib22">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jenkins, K. J. et al. <article-title>Noninherited risk factors and congenital cardiovascular defects: current knowledge: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association Council on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young: endorsed by the American Academy of Pediatrics</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>2995</fpage>–3014 (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17519397</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib23">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Patel, S. S. &amp; Burns, T. L. <article-title>Nongenetic risk factors and congenital heart defects</article-title>. <source/>Pediatr. Cardiol.
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1535</fpage>–1555 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23963188</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nora, J. J. <article-title>Multifactorial inheritance hypothesis for the etiology of congenital heart diseases. The genetic-environmental interaction</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>604</fpage>–617 (<year>1968</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4876982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib25">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Edwards, J. J. &amp; Gelb, B. D. <article-title>Genetics of congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Curr. Opin. Cardiol.
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>–241 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26872209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib26">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wimalasundera, R. C. &amp; Gardiner, H. M. <article-title>Congenital heart disease and aneuploidy</article-title>. <source/>Prenat. Diagn.
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1116</fpage>–1122 (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15614848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib27">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van Karnebeek, C. D. &amp; Hennekam, R. C. <article-title>Associations between chromosomal anomalies and congenital heart defects: a database search</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>–166 (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10323742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib28">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pober, B. R. <article-title>Williams-Beuren syndrome</article-title>. <source/>N. Engl. J. Med.
<volume>362</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>–252 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib29">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McDonald-McGinn, D. M. et al. <article-title>22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Dis. Prim.
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>15071</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27189754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib30">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Scambler, P. J. <article-title>22q11 deletion syndrome: a role for TBX1 in pharyngeal and cardiovascular development</article-title>. <source/>Pediatr. Cardiol.
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>378</fpage>–390 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20054531</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib31">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Iafrate, A. J. et al. <article-title>Detection of large-scale variation in the human genome</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>949</fpage>–951 (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15286789</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib32">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sebat, J. et al. <article-title>Large-scale copy number polymorphism in the human genome</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>305</volume>, <fpage>525</fpage>–528 (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15273396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib33">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lee, C. &amp; Scherer, S. W. <article-title>The clinical context of copy number variation in the human genome</article-title>. <source/>Expert Rev. Mol. Med.
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e8</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20211047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib34">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cooper, G. M. et al. <article-title>A copy number variation morbidity map of developmental delay</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>838</fpage>–846 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21841781</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib35">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Miller, D. T. et al. <article-title>Consensus statement: chromosomal microarray is a first-tier clinical diagnostic test for individuals with developmental disabilities or congenital anomalies</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>749</fpage>–764 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20466091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib36">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costain, G. et al. <article-title>Pathogenic rare copy number variants in community-based schizophrenia suggest a potential role for clinical microarrays</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>4485</fpage>–4501 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23813976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib37">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Thienpont, B. et al. <article-title>Submicroscopic chromosomal imbalances detected by array-CGH are a frequent cause of congenital heart defects in selected patients</article-title>. <source/>Eur. Heart J.
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>2778</fpage>–2784 (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17384091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib38">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Silversides, C. K. et al. <article-title>Rare copy number variations in adults with tetralogy of Fallot implicate novel risk gene pathways</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e1002843</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22912587</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib39">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Soemedi, R. et al. <article-title>Contribution of global rare copy-number variants to the risk of sporadic congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>91</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>–501 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22939634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib40">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hitz, M. P. et al. <article-title>Rare copy number variants contribute to congenital left-sided heart disease</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e1002903</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22969434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib41">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lalani, S. R. et al. <article-title>Rare DNA copy number variants in cardiovascular malformations with extracardiac abnormalities</article-title>. <source/>Eur. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>–181 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22929023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib42">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Xie, L. et al. <article-title>Rare <italic>de novo</italic> copy number variants in patients with congenital pulmonary atresia</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e96471</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24826987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib43">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhao, W. et al. <article-title>High-resolution analysis of copy number variants in adults with simple-to-moderate congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>161A</volume>, <fpage>3087</fpage>–3094 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24115576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib44">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">White, P. S. et al. <article-title>Analysis of chromosomal structural variation in patients with congenital left-sided cardiac lesions</article-title>. <source/>Birth Defects Res. A Clin. Mol. Teratol.
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>951</fpage>–964 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25066379</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib45">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Greenway, S. C. et al. <article-title><italic>De novo</italic> copy number variants identify new genes and loci in isolated sporadic tetralogy of Fallot</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>931</fpage>–935 (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib46">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Priest, J. R. et al. <article-title>Rare copy number variants in isolated sporadic and syndromic atrioventricular septal defects</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>158A</volume>, <fpage>1279</fpage>–1284 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22529060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib47">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Warburton, D. et al. <article-title>The contribution of <italic>de novo</italic> and rare inherited copy number changes to congenital heart disease in an unselected sample of children with conotruncal defects or hypoplastic left heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Genet.
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>–27 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23979609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib48">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fakhro, K. A. et al. <article-title>Rare copy number variations in congenital heart disease patients identify unique genes in left-right patterning</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>2915</fpage>–2920 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282601</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib49">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Goldmuntz, E. et al. <article-title>Microdeletions and microduplications in patients with congenital heart disease and multiple congenital anomalies</article-title>. <source/>Congenit. Heart Dis.
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>592</fpage>–602 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22010865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib50">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tomita-Mitchell, A. et al. <article-title>Human gene copy number spectra analysis in congenital heart malformations</article-title>. <source/>Physiol. Genomics
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>518</fpage>–541 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22318994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib51">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Breckpot, J. et al. <article-title>Challenges of interpreting copy number variation in syndromic and non-syndromic congenital heart defects</article-title>. <source/>Cytogenet. Genome Res.
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>–259 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21921585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib52">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Thorsson, T. et al. <article-title>Chromosomal imbalances in patients with congenital cardiac defects: a meta-analysis reveals novel potential critical regions involved in heart development</article-title>. <source/>Congenit. Heart Dis.
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>–208 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24720490</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib53">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costain, G. et al. <article-title>Genome-wide rare copy number variations contribute to genetic risk for transposition of the great arteries</article-title>. <source/>Int. J. Cardiol.
<volume>204</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>–121 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26655555</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib54">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kim, D. S. et al. <article-title>Burden of potentially pathologic copy number variants is higher in children with isolated congenital heart disease and significantly impairs covariate-adjusted transplant-free survival</article-title>. <source/>J. Thorac. Cardiovasc. Surg.
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>1147</fpage>–1151.e4 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26704054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib55">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sanchez-Castro, M. et al. <article-title>Search for rare copy-number variants in congenital heart defects identifies novel candidate genes and a potential role for FOXC1 in patients with coarctation of the aorta</article-title>. <source/>Circ. Cardiovasc. Genet.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>–94 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26643481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib56">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">An, Y. et al. <article-title>Genome-wide copy number variant analysis for congenital ventricular septal defects in Chinese Han population</article-title>. <source/>BMC Med. Genomics
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26742958</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib57">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Glessner, J. T. et al. <article-title>Increased frequency of <italic>de novo</italic> copy number variants in congenital heart disease by integrative analysis of single nucleotide polymorphism array and exome sequence data</article-title>. <source/>Circ. Res.
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>884</fpage>–896 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25205790</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib58">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carey, A. S. et al. <article-title>Effect of copy number variants on outcomes for infants with single ventricle heart defects</article-title>. <source/>Circ. Cardiovasc. Genet.
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>444</fpage>–451 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24021551</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib59">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Peyvandi, S. et al. <article-title>22q11.2 deletions in patients with conotruncal defects: data from 1,610 consecutive cases</article-title>. <source/>Pediatr. Cardiol.
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1687</fpage>–1694 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23604262</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib60">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Osoegawa, K. et al. <article-title>Identification of novel candidate gene loci and increased sex chromosome aneuploidy among infants with conotruncal heart defects</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>164A</volume>, <fpage>397</fpage>–406 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24127225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib61">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fung, W. L. et al. <article-title>Practical guidelines for managing adults with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Genet. Med.
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>599</fpage>–609 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25569435</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib62">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bassett, A. S. et al. <article-title>Practical guidelines for managing patients with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J. Pediat.
<volume>159</volume>, <fpage>332</fpage>–339 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21570089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib63">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bassett, A. S. et al. <article-title>Clinical features of 78 adults with 22q11 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>138</volume>, <fpage>307</fpage>–313 (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16208694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib64">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">O’Byrne, M. L. et al. <article-title>22q11.2 Deletion syndrome is associated with increased perioperative events and more complicated postoperative course in infants undergoing infant operative correction of truncus arteriosus communis or interrupted aortic arch</article-title>. <source/>J. Thorac. Cardiovasc. Surg.
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>1597</fpage>–1605 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24629220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib65">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Portnoi, M. F. <article-title>Microduplication 22q11.2: a new chromosomal syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Eur. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>–93 (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19254783</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib66">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Christiansen, J. et al. <article-title>Chromosome 1q21.1 contiguous gene deletion is associated with congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Circ. Res.
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>1429</fpage>–1435 (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15117819</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib67">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dolcetti, A. et al. <article-title>1q21.1 Microduplication expression in adults</article-title>. <source/>Genet. Med.
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>282</fpage>–289 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23018752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib68">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Soemedi, R. et al. <article-title>Phenotype-specific effect of chromosome 1q21.1 rearrangements and GJA5 duplications in 2436 congenital heart disease patients and 6760 controls</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1513</fpage>–1520 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22199024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib69">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Verhagen, J. M. et al. <article-title>Phenotypic variability associated with a large recurrent 1q21.1 microduplication in a three-generation family</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Syndromol.
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>–76 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26279651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib70">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chaldoupi, S. M., Loh, P., Hauer, R. N., de Bakker, J. M. &amp; van Rijen, H. V. <article-title>The role of connexin40 in atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source/>Cardiovasc. Res.
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>–23 (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19535379</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib71">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Garg, V. et al. <article-title>GATA4 mutations cause human congenital heart defects and reveal an interaction with TBX5</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>424</volume>, <fpage>443</fpage>–447 (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12845333</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib72">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pehlivan, T. et al. <article-title>GATA4 haploinsufficiency in patients with interstitial deletion of chromosome region 8p23.1 and congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>–206 (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10096597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib73">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wat, J. J. &amp; Wat, M. J. <article-title>Sox7 in vascular development: review, insights and potential mechanisms</article-title>. <source/>Int. J. Dev. Biol.
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–8 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24860989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib74">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vanlerberghe, C. et al. <article-title>15q11.2 microdeletion (BP1-BP2) and developmental delay, behaviour issues, epilepsy and congenital heart disease: a series of 52 patients</article-title>. <source/>Eur. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>140</fpage>–147 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25596525</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib75">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cafferkey, M., Ahn, J. W., Flinter, F. &amp; Ogilvie, C. <article-title>Phenotypic features in patients with 15q11.2(BP1-BP2) deletion: further delineation of an emerging syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>164A</volume>, <fpage>1916</fpage>–1922 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24715682</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib76">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hashemi, B. et al. <article-title>Deletion of 15q11.2(BP1-BP2) region: Further evidence for lack of phenotypic specificity in a pediatric population</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>167A</volume>, <fpage>2098</fpage>–2102 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25946043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib77">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costain, G., Roche, S. L., Scherer, S. W., Silversides, C. K. &amp; Bassett, A. S. <article-title>Rare copy number variations in an adult with transposition of the great arteries emphasize the importance of updated genetic assessments in syndromic congenital cardiac disease</article-title>. <source/>Int. J. Cardiol.
<volume>203</volume>, <fpage>516</fpage>–518 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26551885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib78">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Homsy, J. et al. <article-title><italic>De novo</italic> mutations in congenital heart disease with neurodevelopmental and other congenital anomalies</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>350</volume>, <fpage>1262</fpage>–1266 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26785492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib79">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Merico, D. et al. <article-title>MicroRNA dysregulation, gene networks, and risk for schizophrenia in 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Front. Neurol.
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25484875</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib80">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Xing, H. J. et al. <article-title>Identification of microRNAs present in congenital heart disease associated copy number variants</article-title>. <source/>Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci.
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>2114</fpage>–2120 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23884835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib81">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jansen, F. A. et al. <article-title>Array comparative genomic hybridization and fetal congenital heart defects: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/>Ultrasound Obstet. Gynecol.
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>–35 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25319878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib82">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shaffer, L. G. et al. <article-title>Experience with microarray-based comparative genomic hybridization for prenatal diagnosis in over 5000 pregnancies</article-title>. <source/>Prenat. Diagn.
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>976</fpage>–985 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22865506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib83">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Geng, J. et al. <article-title>Chromosome microarray testing for patients with congenital heart defects reveals novel disease causing loci and high diagnostic yield</article-title>. <source/>BMC Genomics
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1127</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516202</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib84">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Connor, J. A. et al. <article-title>Genetic testing practices in infants with congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Congenit. Heart Dis.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>–167 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23782710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib85">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Buckley, J. R., Kavarana, M. N., Chowdhury, S. M. &amp; Scheurer, M. A. <article-title>Current practice and utility of chromosome microarray analysis in infants undergoing cardiac surgery</article-title>. <source/>Congenit. Heart Dis.
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>E131</fpage>–E138 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25494910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib86">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Helm, B. M. &amp; Freeze, S. L. <article-title>Genetic evaluation and use of chromosome microarray in patients with isolated heart defects: benefits and challenges of a new model in cardiovascular care</article-title>. <source/>Front. Cardiovasc. Med.
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27379245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib87">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chaix, M. A., Andelfinger, G. &amp; Khairy, P. <article-title>Genetic testing in congenital heart disease: a clinical approach</article-title>. <source/>World J. Cardiol.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>180</fpage>–191 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26981213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib88">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van Engelen, K. et al. <article-title>The value of the clinical geneticist caring for adults with congenital heart disease: diagnostic yield and patients’ perspective</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>161A</volume>, <fpage>1628</fpage>–1637 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23696448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib89">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costain, G., Chow, E. W., Silversides, C. K. &amp; Bassett, A. S. <article-title>Sex differences in reproductive fitness contribute to preferential maternal transmission of 22q11.2 deletions</article-title>. <source/>J. Med. Genet.
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>819</fpage>–824 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22051516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib90">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costain, G. <article-title>Parental expression is overvalued in the interpretation of rare inherited variants</article-title>. <source/>Eur. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>–7 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24755951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib91">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hinton, R. B. Jr. et al. <article-title>Hypoplastic left heart syndrome is heritable</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1590</fpage>–1595 (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17936159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib92">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bassett, A. S., Scherer, S. W. &amp; Brzustowicz, L. M. <article-title>Copy number variations in schizophrenia: critical review and new perspectives on concepts of genetics and disease</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Psychiatry
<volume>167</volume>, <fpage>899</fpage>–914 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib93">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Michielon, G. et al. <article-title>Genetic syndromes and outcome after surgical correction of tetralogy of Fallot</article-title>. <source/>Ann. Thorac. Surg.
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>968</fpage>–975 (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16488703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib94">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anaclerio, S. et al. <article-title>Conotruncal heart defects: impact of genetic syndromes on immediate operative mortality</article-title>. <source/>Ital. Heart J.
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>624</fpage>–628 (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15554034</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib95">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gaynor, J. W. et al. <article-title>Patient characteristics are important determinants of neurodevelopmental outcome at one year of age after neonatal and infant cardiac surgery</article-title>. <source/>J. Thorac. Cardiovasc. Surg.
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>1344</fpage>–1353, 1353.e1–3 (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib96">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costain, G. et al. <article-title>13q13.1-q13.2 deletion in tetralogy of Fallot: clinical report and a literature review</article-title>. <source/>Int. J. Cardiol.
<volume>146</volume>, <fpage>134</fpage>–139 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20598760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib97">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Girirajan, S. et al. <article-title>Refinement and discovery of new hotspots of copy-number variation associated with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>–237 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23375656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib98">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stefansson, H. et al. <article-title>CNVs conferring risk of autism or schizophrenia affect cognition in controls</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>505</volume>, <fpage>361</fpage>–366 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24352232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib99">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Preuss, C. &amp; Andelfinger, G. <article-title>Genetics of heart failure in congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Can. J. Cardiol.
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>803</fpage>–810 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23706783</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib100">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bassett, A. S. et al. <article-title>Premature death in adults with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J. Med. Genet.
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>–330 (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19246480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib101">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Arndt, A. K. et al. <article-title>Fine mapping of the 1p36 deletion syndrome identifies mutation of PRDM16 as a cause of cardiomyopathy</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–77 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib102">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">de Leeuw, N. &amp; Houge, G. <article-title>Loss of PRDM16 is unlikely to cause cardiomyopathy in 1p36 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>–154 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24387995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib103">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Arndt, A. K., Macrae, C. A. &amp; Klaassen, S. <article-title>Reponse to De Leeuw and Houge</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>154</fpage>–155 (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24387996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib104">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jordan, V. K., Zaveri, H. P. &amp; Scott, D. A. <article-title>1p36 deletion syndrome: an update</article-title>. <source/>Appl. Clin. Genet.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>–200 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26345236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib105">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fregeau, B. et al. <article-title><italic>De novo</italic> mutations of RERE cause a genetic syndrome with features that overlap those associated with proximal 1p36 deletions</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>963</fpage>–970 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27087320</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib106">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Li, Y. et al. <article-title>Global genetic analysis in mice unveils central role for cilia in congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>521</volume>, <fpage>520</fpage>–524 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25807483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib107">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Winston, J. B. et al. <article-title>Heterogeneity of genetic modifiers ensures normal cardiac development</article-title>. <source/>Circulation
<volume>121</volume>, <fpage>1313</fpage>–1321 (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20212279</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib108">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Winston, J. B. et al. <article-title>Complex trait analysis of ventricular septal defects caused by Nkx2-5 mutation</article-title>. <source/>Circ. Cardiovasc. Genet.
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>–300 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22534315</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib109">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Albers, C. A. et al. <article-title>Compound inheritance of a low-frequency regulatory SNP and a rare null mutation in exon-junction complex subunit RBM8A causes TAR syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>–439, S1-2 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib110">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Benn, P. <article-title>Expanding non-invasive prenatal testing beyond chromosomes 21, 18, 13, X and Y</article-title>. <source/>Clin. Genet10.1111/cge.12818 (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib111">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zaidi, S. et al. <article-title><italic>De novo</italic> mutations in histone-modifying genes in congenital heart disease</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>498</volume>, <fpage>220</fpage>–223 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23665959</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib112">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stavropoulos, D. J. et al. <article-title>Whole-genome sequencing expands diagnostic utility and improves clinical management in paediatric medicine</article-title>. <source/>NPJ Gen. Med.
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>15012</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib113">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mlynarski, E. E. et al. <article-title>Copy-number variation of the glucose transporter Gene SLC2A3 and congenital heart defects in the 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>96</volume>, <fpage>753</fpage>–764 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25892112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib114">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Racedo, S. E. et al. <article-title>Mouse and human CRKL is dosage sensitive for cardiac outflow tract formation</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>96</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>–244 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25658046</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib115">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chapnik, E., Sasson, V., Blelloch, R. &amp; Hornstein, E. <article-title>Dgcr8 controls neural crest cells survival in cardiovascular development</article-title>. <source/>Dev. Biol.
<volume>362</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>–56 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22138056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib116">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Guo, T. et al. <article-title>Genotype and cardiovascular phenotype correlations with TBX1 in 1,022 Velo-Cardio-Facial/DiGeorge/22q11.2 Deletion Syndrome patients</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mutat.
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1278</fpage>–1289 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21796729</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib117">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Swaby, J. A. et al. <article-title>Complex congenital heart disease in unaffected relatives of adults with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Cardiol.
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>466</fpage>–471 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21257016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib118">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Digilio, M. C. et al. <article-title>Familial recurrence of nonsyndromic congenital heart defects in first degree relatives of patients with deletion 22q11.2</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>134 A</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>–164 (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib119">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mlynarski, E. E. et al. <article-title>Rare copy number variants and congenital heart defects in the 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Genet.
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>–285 (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26742502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib120">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Guo, T. et al. <article-title>Histone modifier genes alter conotruncal heart phenotypes in 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>869</fpage>–877 (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26608785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib121">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kearney, H. M. et al. <article-title>American College of Medical Genetics standards and guidelines for interpretation and reporting of postnatal constitutional copy number variants</article-title>. <source/>Genet. Med.
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>680</fpage>–685 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21681106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="fig1">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Spectrum of human CHD. CHD is an umbrella term for a range of malformations of the heart and great vessels (aorta and pulmonary arteries). There exist multiple clinically and anatomically discrete lesions, of differing incidence and severity. See text and associated references for details. (<bold>a</bold>) Labelled diagram of the structurally normal human heart. (<bold>b</bold>) Examples of some congenital cardiac lesions, based on anatomy. For a full list of congenital cardiac defects, consult a congenital cardiology textbook. Multiple congenital defects may be present within an individual. (<bold>c</bold>) Labelled diagram of one specific form of CHD: tetralogy of Fallot (TOF).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="npjgenmed201631-f1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Examples of CNV and associated disease mechanisms. (<bold>a</bold>) Normal diploid status and two examples of CNV (a simple deletion and a tandem duplication). Not pictured are the diverse other forms of CNV, including non-contiguous insertions, higher-order copy number changes (multi-allelic CNV), and more complex rearrangements. CNVs may involve no, one or multiple genomic elements. (<bold>b</bold>) Selected mechanisms underlying disease effects of copy number losses (deletions). A gene is indicated by a contiguous monochromatic set of rectangles, and a regulatory element (e.g., promoter) by an oval. The definition of ‘gene’ extends beyond protein-coding genes to potentially include noncoding elements like microRNAs and long noncoding RNAs. Of note, duplications can effect change through increased copy number of a dosage sensitive gene (not pictured) or via the mechanisms depicted for deletions (e.g., via disruption at a breakpoint or partial intragenic duplication). Inspired by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> in ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">92</xref> and Figure 2 in ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="npjgenmed201631-f2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Prevalence of 1q21.1 duplications in cohorts with TOF. Box size is proportional to study size: <italic>n</italic>=33,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup>
<italic>n</italic>=510,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup>
<italic>n</italic>=948,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">68</xref></sup>
<italic>n</italic>=433,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup>
<italic>n</italic>=81,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref></sup>
<italic>n</italic>=68<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> and <italic>n</italic>=57.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref></sup> The blue diamond represents the combined prevalence of 1q21.1 duplications in a total of 2130 subjects with TOF, and the diamond width corresponds to 95% confidence interval bounds. In contrast, 1q21.1 duplications are rare in control populations (see text).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="npjgenmed201631-f3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"></graphic>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="tbl1">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Case–control studies of genome-wide rare CNV burden in CHD<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></title>
</caption>
<table border="1" frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
</colgroup>
<thead valign="bottom">
<tr>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Study</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Cases (n)</italic>
</th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>CHD type</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Controls (n)</italic>
</th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Significant case–control CNV burden findings</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>22q11.2 deletions excluded or absent</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">100</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Various<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">65</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Increased proportion of subjects with rare CNVs &gt;100 kb in size (39.0 vs 21.5%)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">Yes<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Costain <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">101<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn4">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">TGA</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">415<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn5">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Increased proportion of subjects with rare CNVs &gt;500 kb in size (10.1 vs 4.6%)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Carey <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">223</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Single ventricle</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">270</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Increased proportion of subjects with rare genic CNVs &gt;300 kb in size (13.9 vs 4.4%)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Fakhro <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">262</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">HTX</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">991</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Increased proportion of subjects with rare genic CNVs (14.5 vs 7.4%)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Kim <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">54</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">422</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Various<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">500</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Increased proportion of subjects with rare genic CNVs &gt;300 kb in size (12.1 vs 5.0%)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Silversides <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">433<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn4">d</xref></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">TOF</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">416<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn5">e</xref></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Increased proportion of subjects with rare CNVs &gt;500 kb in size (9.1 vs 5.1%)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn6">f</xref></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Soemedi <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">2,256</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Various<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">841</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Increased proportion of subjects with rare genic loss CNVs (7.8 vs 4.4%)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">Yes</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t1-tfoot1">
<p>Abbreviations: ASD, atrial septal defect; CHD, congenital heart disease; CNVs, copy number variations; HLHS, hypoplastic left heart syndrome; HTX, heterotaxy; PDA, patent ductus arteriosus; TGA, transposition of the great arteries; TOF, tetralogy of Fallot; VSD, ventricular septal defect.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t1-fn1">
<label>a</label>
<p>Minimum <italic>n</italic>=100 case subjects. Glessner <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> reported an increased burden of <italic>de novo</italic> CNVs in CHD cases relative to controls, but multiple numerical inconsistencies in their report resulted in its exclusion from this table.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t1-fn2">
<label>b</label>
<p>Zhao <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref></sup>: ASD (<italic>n</italic>=58), VSD (<italic>n</italic>=22), PDA (<italic>n</italic>=15), TOF (<italic>n</italic>=2), Ebstein anomaly (<italic>n</italic>=2), and tricuspid incompetence (<italic>n</italic>=1); Kim <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">54</xref></sup>: HLHS (<italic>n</italic>=130), TOF (<italic>n</italic>=64), TGA (<italic>n</italic>=34), VSD (<italic>n</italic>=40), VSD/coA (<italic>n</italic>=19), single ventricle (<italic>n</italic>=30) and other (<italic>n</italic>=105); Soemedi <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup>: the four largest of the 29 categories were TOF (<italic>n</italic>=808), ASD (<italic>n</italic>=293), TGA (<italic>n</italic>=165) and VSD (<italic>n</italic>=163).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t1-fn3">
<label>c</label>
<p>Included one atypical 22q11.2 deletion overlapping <italic>CRKL</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t1-fn4">
<label>d</label>
<p>Only subjects of European ancestry were considered in burden analyses.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t1-fn5">
<label>e</label>
<p>All rare CNVs in cases and controls were adjudicated for rarity by comparing to those in additional population-based controls: <italic>n</italic>=2357,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup>
<italic>n</italic>=10 113.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
<fn id="t1-fn6">
<label>f</label>
<p>Also within-TOF finding of more exonic losses in the syndromic subgroup.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="tbl2">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Studies of genome-wide <italic>de novo</italic> CNV rate in CHD (22q11.2 deletions excluded)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t2-fn1">a</xref></title>
</caption>
<table border="1" frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="center"/>
</colgroup>
<thead valign="bottom">
<tr>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Study</italic>
</th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Recruitment site(s)</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Case trios (n)</italic>
</th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>CHD type</italic>
</th>
<th align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">
<italic>Array type(s)</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" charoff="50" colspan="2" valign="top">
<italic>De novo rate per subject</italic>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t2-fn2">b</xref>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Hitz <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Canada (QC)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">53</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Left-sided</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Affymetrix Human Genome-Wide SNP Array 6.0 (Santa Clara, CA, USA)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">6/53</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">11.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Xie <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref></sup></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">South Central China</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">82</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">PA</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Illumina 660W-Quad &amp; Omni1-Quad BeadChips (San Diego, CA, USA)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">12/78</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">15.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Greenway <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">USA (Boston), Brazil</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">114</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">TOF</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Affymetrix Human Genome-Wide SNP Array 6.0</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">9/112</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">8.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Warburton <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">USA (NY)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">223</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">CNT, HLHS</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">NimbleGen CGH HD2 (Madison, WI, USA)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">20/213</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">9.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Soemedi <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">UK, Germany, Belgium, Australia</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">283</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">TOF</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Illumina 660W-Quad</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">13/283</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">4.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Sanchez-Castro <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref></sup></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">France</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">316</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">CoA</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Agilent 2*400K (Santa Clara, CA, USA, custom-designed)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">3/76</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">3.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">TOF</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">5/81</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">6.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">TGA</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top"> </td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">0/159</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">0.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Glessner <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">USA (various)</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">538</td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Various<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t2-fn3">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" charoff="50" valign="top">Illumina Omni-1.0 and 2.5M<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t2-fn4">d</xref></td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">47/534</td>
<td align="center" charoff="50" valign="top">8.8%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t2-tfoot1">
<p>Abbreviations: CHD, congenital heart disease; CNT, conotruncal anomalies; CNVs, copy number variations; CoA, coarctation of the aorta; HLHS, hypoplastic left heart syndrome; HTX, heterotaxy; PA, pulmonary atresia; TGA, transposition of the great arteries; TOF, tetralogy of Fallot; VSD, ventricular septal defect.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t2-fn1">
<label>a</label>
<p>Minimum <italic>n</italic>=50 trios.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t2-fn2">
<label>b</label>
<p>Proportion of unrelated case subjects with at least one <italic>de novo</italic> CNV, after excluding individuals with 22q11.2 deletions.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t2-fn3">
<label>c</label>
<p>Left-ventricular outflow lesions&gt;CNT&gt;&gt;heterotaxy&gt;other (exact numbers cannot be determined from data provided).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="t2-fn4">
<label>d</label>
<p>Also employed whole-exome sequencing for characterisation of CNV.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<boxed-text id="box1">
<caption>
<title>Genetic studies of 22q11.2 deletion syndrome (22q11.2DS) as a guide for understanding variable expression</title>
</caption>
<p>The 22q11.2 deletion alone cannot account for the variable expression of the congenital cardiac phenotype in 22q11.2DS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> Efforts are underway to dissect the layered genetic architecture that gives rise to this variability. Progress to date offers a blueprint for studying pathways from CNV genotype to CHD phenotype more generally.</p>
<p><italic> Within the 22q11.2 region:</italic>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>• Length of the deletion and specific breakpoints<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>There is little to no discernible association of severity of the phenotype, including the CHD, with the length of the deletion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib113">113</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Haploinsufficiency of multiple genes within the region appears to be important, including <italic>TBX1</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup>
<italic>CRKL</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib114">114</xref></sup> and <italic>DGCR8</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib115">115</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Sequence variation in <italic>TBX1</italic> on the intact 22q11.2 allele does not have a major role in cardiac expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib116">116</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>• Animal models of the full deletion and of haploinsufficiency of specific deleted genes<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Haploinsufficiency of multiple genes within the region appears to be important, including <italic>TBX1</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup>
<italic>CRKL</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib114">114</xref></sup> and <italic>DGCR8</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib115">115</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Sequence variation in <italic>TBX1</italic> on the intact 22q11.2 allele does not have a major role in cardiac expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib116">116</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>• Variation on the intact allele<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Sequence variation in <italic>TBX1</italic> on the intact 22q11.2 allele does not have a major role in cardiac expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib116">116</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
</p>
<p><italic>Outside the 22q11.2 region (genome-wide):</italic>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>• Family studies<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Family history data support a heritable susceptibility to CHD in families of probands with <italic>de novo</italic> 22q11.2 deletions and CHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib117">117</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib118">118</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A common duplication of <italic>SLC2A3</italic> was significantly enriched in individuals with 22q11.2 deletions and CHD, implicating this CNV as a possible genetic modifier in a small proportion of subjects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib113">113</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Preliminary data suggest that rare CNVs outside the 22q11.2 region may overlap genes that modify risk for CHD in a small proportion of subjects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib119">119</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Whole-exome sequencing implicated rare mutations in histone modification genes as possibly influencing risk for CHD in the presence of the 22q11.2 deletion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib120">120</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>• Common genome-wide variation<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A common duplication of <italic>SLC2A3</italic> was significantly enriched in individuals with 22q11.2 deletions and CHD, implicating this CNV as a possible genetic modifier in a small proportion of subjects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib113">113</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Preliminary data suggest that rare CNVs outside the 22q11.2 region may overlap genes that modify risk for CHD in a small proportion of subjects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib119">119</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Whole-exome sequencing implicated rare mutations in histone modification genes as possibly influencing risk for CHD in the presence of the 22q11.2 deletion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib120">120</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>• Additional rare CNV<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Preliminary data suggest that rare CNVs outside the 22q11.2 region may overlap genes that modify risk for CHD in a small proportion of subjects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib119">119</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Whole-exome sequencing implicated rare mutations in histone modification genes as possibly influencing risk for CHD in the presence of the 22q11.2 deletion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib120">120</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>• Additional rare sequence mutations<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Whole-exome sequencing implicated rare mutations in histone modification genes as possibly influencing risk for CHD in the presence of the 22q11.2 deletion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib120">120</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
</p>
</boxed-text>
<boxed-text id="box2">
<caption>
<title>Outcomes of clinical genetic testing with CMA</title>
</caption>
<p>There are four general outcomes of CMA: (1) no abnormality (normal array); (2) pathogenic variant; (3) VUS; and, rarely, (4) secondary or incidental finding. Categories 2–4 may co-occur. Many laboratories follow the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics (ACMG) guidelines for interpretation and reporting of postnatal constitutional CNVs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib121">121</xref></sup>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p><italic>Normal array:</italic> In the case of a normal array, the cause of the individual’s CHD remains unexplained. Counselling about a negative result includes the fact that this is the likeliest outcome. This normal result does not preclude the likelihood that other genetic testing may be clinically available now or in the future that could help to resolve the aetiology of the CHD. CMA will not detect sequence mutations, or chromosomal imbalances below a certain resolution.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Example: A normal array in a patient with truncus arteriosus and a loss-of-function mutation in <italic>NKX2-5</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Pathogenic variant:</italic> Discovery of a pathogenic CNV that is a known risk factor for CHD will prompt a recommendation for a referral to medical genetics and/or a sub specialty clinic for further specific assessment and counselling. Parental testing where possible is usually recommended. In some cases, parental studies will uncover the same CNV or perhaps a balanced chromosome rearrangement that confers a significant recurrence risk for having other children with a pathogenic CNV.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Example: A typical 1q21.1 duplication in a patient with TOF.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref></sup></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>VUS:</italic> VUS are those CNVs that are not yet reliably characterised as either benign or pathogenic. Subcategories exist: ‘VUS; likely pathogenic’, ‘VUS; likely benign’ and ‘VUS (no sub-classification)’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib121">121</xref></sup> Genetic assessment and counselling may be recommended about what is known now, and/or in the future should new information arise. VUS, especially those deemed ‘likely pathogenic’, are often a source of future pathogenic variants.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Example: A duplication overlapping <italic>CACNA1C</italic> and a typical 15q11.2 deletion in a patient with TGA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref></sup></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Secondary finding:</italic> There is the possibility of finding a variant associated with a genetic disorder not believed to be related to the primary reason for referral. In these rare instances, the genetic disorder may be associated with an adult onset condition.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Example: Haploinsufficiency of the familial breast and ovarian cancer gene <italic>BRCA2</italic> in a patient with TOF.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib96">96</xref></sup></p></list-item></list></p>
</boxed-text>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>