<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8804207</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">1862</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Schizophr Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Schizophr. Res.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Schizophrenia research</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0920-9964</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1573-2509</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28094170</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5507209</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2016.12.012</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS874815</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Common developmental genome deprogramming in schizophrenia – role of Integrative Nuclear FGFR1 Signaling (INFS)</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Narla</surname>
<given-names>S. T.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Y-W.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Benson</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sarder</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brennand</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stachowiak</surname>
<given-names>E.K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stachowiak</surname>
<given-names>M.K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Pathology and Anatomical Sciences, State University of New York at Buffalo, Buffalo, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Western New York Stem Cell Culture and Analysis Center, State University of New York at Buffalo, Buffalo, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, Departments of Psychiatry and Neuroscience, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Correspondence should be addressed to Michal K. Stachowiak Department of Pathology and Anatomical Sciences, SUNY, 3435 Main Street, 206A Farber Hall, Buffalo, N.Y. 14214, <email>mks4@buffalo.edu</email> tel. (716) 829 3540</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p><bold>Competing Financial Interests:</bold> authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>13</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>13</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>185</volume>
<fpage>17</fpage>
<lpage>32</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.schres.2016.12.012-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">The watershed-hypothesis of schizophrenia asserts that over 200 different mutations dysregulate distinct pathways that converge on an unspecified common mechanism(s) that controls disease ontogeny. Consistent with this hypothesis, our RNA-sequencing of neuron committed cells (NCCs) differentiated from established iPSCs of 4 schizophrenia patients and 4 control subjects uncovered a dysregulated transcriptome of 1349 mRNAs common to all patients. Data reveal global dysregulation of developmental genome, deconstruction of coordinated mRNA, and mRNA networks, and the formation of aberrant, new coordinated mRNA networks indicating a concerted action of the responsible factor(s). Sequencing of miRNA transcriptomes demonstrated an overexpression of 16 miRNAs and deconstruction of coordinated miRNA–mRNA networks in schizophrenia NCCs. ChiPseq revealed that the nuclear (n) form of FGFR1, a pan-ontogenic regulator, is overexpressed in schizophrenia NCCs and overtargets dysregulated mRNA and miRNA genes. The nFGFR1 targeted 54% of all human gene promoters and 84.4% of schizophrenia dysregulated genes. The upregulated genes reside within major developmental pathways that control neurogenesis and neuron formation, whereas downregulated genes are involved in oligodendrogenesis. Our results indicate (i) an early (preneuronal) genomic etiology of schizophrenia, (ii) dysregulated genes and new coordinated gene networks are common to unrelated cases of schizophrenia, (iii) gene dysregulations are accompanied by increased nFGFR1-genome interactions, and (iv) modeling of increased nFGFR1 by an overexpression of a nFGFR1 lead to up or downregulation of selected genes as observed in schizophrenia NCCs. Together our results designate nFGFR1 signaling as a potential common dysregulated mechanism in investigated patients and potential therapeutic target in schizophrenia.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Schizophrenia</kwd>
<kwd>developmental hypothesis</kwd>
<kwd>genome regulation</kwd>
<kwd>miRNA Fibroblast Growth Factor Receptor 1</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>