<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28819289</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5561180</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9103</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-09103-6</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>ESCRT-III Membrane Trafficking Misregulation Contributes To Fragile X Syndrome Synaptic Defects</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2357-5707</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Vita</surname>
<given-names>Dominic J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>Kendal</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>kendal.broadie@vanderbilt.edu</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2264 7217</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.152326.1</institution-id><institution></institution><institution>Vanderbilt University, Department of Biological Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Nashville, Tennessee 37235 USA </aff>
<aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2264 7217</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.152326.1</institution-id><institution></institution><institution>Vanderbilt University, Kennedy Center for Research on Human Development, </institution></institution-wrap>Nashville, Tennessee 37235 USA </aff>
<aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2264 7217</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.152326.1</institution-id><institution></institution><institution>Vanderbilt University, Vanderbilt Brain Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Nashville, Tennessee 37235 USA </aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>17</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>17</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<elocation-id>8683</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>16</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>19</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement>
<license license-type="OpenAccess">
<license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="Par1">The leading cause of heritable intellectual disability (ID) and autism spectrum disorders (ASD), Fragile X syndrome (FXS), is caused by loss of the mRNA-binding translational suppressor Fragile X Mental Retardation Protein (FMRP). In the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS disease model, we found FMRP binds <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA (human Chmp4) to repress Shrub expression, causing overexpression during the disease state early-use critical period. The FXS hallmark is synaptic overelaboration causing circuit hyperconnectivity. Testing innervation of a central brain learning/memory center, we found FMRP loss and Shrub overexpression similarly increase connectivity. The ESCRT-III core protein Shrub has a central role in endosome-to-multivesicular body membrane trafficking, with synaptic requirements resembling FMRP. Consistently, we found FMRP loss and Shrub overexpression similarly elevate endosomes and result in the arrested accumulation of enlarged intraluminal vesicles within synaptic boutons. Importantly, genetic correction of Shrub levels in the FXS model prevents synaptic membrane trafficking defects and strongly restores innervation. These results reveal a new molecular mechanism underpinning the FXS disease state.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
<meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="Par2">During normal brain maturation, neurons extend excess axonal and dendritic processes in search of appropriate synaptic partners. Superfluous synapses are later selectively eliminated, with less active connections pruned away and more active connections strengthened and stabilized into maturity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Such activity-dependent (A-D) synapse remodeling occurs predominantly during early-use critical periods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. This synaptic refinement is necessary to establish proper neural circuit architecture, optimize function and tune behavioral output. Defects in this mechanism are linked to intellectual disability (ID) and autism spectrum disorder (ASD), including the most common inherited form of Fragile X syndrome (FXS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Most FXS cases arise from trinucleotide repeat expansion in the 5′ UTR of the <italic>fragile x mental retardation 1</italic> (<italic>fmr1</italic>) gene, leading to hypermethylation and transcriptional silencing of the Fragile X Mental Retardation Protein (FMRP) gene product<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. FMRP functions as a selective mRNA-binding protein, predominantly acting to suppress translation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Both FXS patients and animal disease models lacking FMRP exhibit an increased number of overelaborated, immature synapses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Identifying the molecular translation mechanisms resulting in these connectivity defects is of central importance in combating the disease condition.</p>
<p id="Par3">The <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS model has proven invaluable for identifying molecular pathways underpinning synaptic impairments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Conserved phenotypes include synaptic overgrowth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, loss of A-D synaptic refinement during critical periods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, and severe learning/memory deficits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Importantly, impairments are fully rescued through transgenic introduction of human FMRP, proving evolutionarily conserved function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. To discover new FMRP targets, we performed a developmental proteomics screen for brain protein changes in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Our most exciting hit was the <underline>E</underline>ndosomal <underline>S</underline>orting <underline>C</underline>omplex <underline>R</underline>equired for <underline>T</underline>ransport III (ESCRT-III) core protein Shrub (yeast Snf7/Vps32, human CHMP4)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Importantly, recent <italic>Drosophila</italic> studies have shown key roles for the ESCRT pathway in neural mechanisms highly reminiscent of the FXS disease condition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. In particular, <italic>shrub</italic> mutant neurons display process pruning impairments resulting in an excessive number of branched termini<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, a hallmark phenotype characteristic of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Taken together, these studies suggest a probable link between misregulation of the ESCRT-III core protein Shrub and neural circuit synaptic refinement defects in the FXS disease state.</p>
<p id="Par4">The ESCRT pathway was defined for its role in endosome-to-multivesicular body (MVB) membrane trafficking<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. It consists of four protein complexes (ESCRT-0,I,II,III) and the associated AAA-ATPase Vps4, together with numerous auxiliary proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. The ESCRT-III core protein Shrub drives reverse-topology membrane abscission, budding of membrane away from the cytoplasm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Shrub monomers polymerize head-to-tail, creating spiral, helical arrays on membranes causing inward curvature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Importantly, unlike the other ESCRTs, ESCRT-III subunits exist as auto-inhibited monomers in the cytosol until recruited to membranes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. As a result of sequential recruitment, relative protein stoichiometry is absolutely pivotal for proper ESCRT-III function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Too much or too little of ESCRT-III components results in similar impaired function and membrane trafficking aberrations, often reported as increased, enlarged endocytic organelles due to blocked endosomal maturation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. ESCRT-III also regulates plasma membrane remodeling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> and synaptic connectivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. These extensive studies suggest a link between misregulation of ESCRT-III core protein Shrub mediated membrane trafficking and synaptic refinement defects in the FXS condition.</p>
<p id="Par5">In the current study, we test the hypothesis that FMRP negatively regulates ESCRT-III Shrub to control both synaptic membrane trafficking and neural circuit connectivity. Using RNA immunoprecipitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> and brain Western blot assays<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, we find FMRP binds <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA to negatively regulate Shrub protein levels during a defined early-use critical period immediately following eclosion. Since FMRP functions in an activity sensor mechanism to mediate the A-D translation of mRNA targets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, we use optogenetics to reveal that Shrub expression is positively upregulated by neural activity dependent on FMRP. Using well-defined olfactory projection neuron (PN) innervation of the central brain mushroom body (MB) learning/memory center<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, we find that Shrub gain-of-function (GOF) closely phenocopies FMRP loss-of-function (LOF) synaptic errors with a combination of confocal and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) studies. We further find accumulated endocytic organelles with arrested membrane trafficking intermediates in both Shrub GOF and FMRP LOF synapses, consistent with previous reports of ESCRT-III defects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Finally, we strongly mitigate FMRP LOF membrane trafficking and synaptic connectivity defects through reducing Shrub levels in the FXS disease model. Together, these results link ESCRT-III membrane trafficking impairments at the synapse to synaptic connectivity defects as a new causative mechanism in the FXS disease state.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="Sec3">
<title>FMRP binds shrub mRNA to negatively regulate expression during the A-D critical period</title>
<p id="Par6">Based on a developmental brain proteomics screen in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS disease model, we identified a transient change in Shrub protein levels during the early-use critical period<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. To test this candidate, we performed brain Western blots from staged animals during a defined window (0–3 hours post-eclosion; 3PE), established as the peak for FMRP-/activity-dependent refinement of the MB learning/memory center in the central brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Using well-characterized antibodies for Shrub<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> and dFMRP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, we find brain Shrub levels to be consistently increased in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutants compared to <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> genetic background controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1A</xref>). In quantified comparisons normalized to α-tubulin controls, Shrub levels are elevated ~45% in the FXS disease model brain compared to matched controls (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1B</xref>). To test the specificity of FMRP regulation on Shrub, we expressed wildtype FMRP in neurons under control of the <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4 driver in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null background (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1C</xref>). This FMRP rescue reduces Shrub protein to levels indistinguishable from controls. In quantified comparisons normalized to α-tubulin controls, Shrub levels are the same as transgenic driver alone controls (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1D</xref>). These results demonstrate a role for FMRP in limiting Shrub expression in neurons specifically during the early-use critical period.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>FMRP negatively regulates brain Shrub levels during the A–D critical period. (<bold>A</bold>) Brain Western blot comparing <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> background control to <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup> null mutant at 0–3 hr post eclosion (3PE). Proteins probed indicated on left, molecular weights on right. (<bold>B</bold>) Dot plots of the normalized Shrub data points, with mean ± SEM. (<bold>C</bold>) Brain Western blot comparing driver control (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+) to UAS-dFMRP rescue (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+; UAS-<italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>9557–3</italic></sup>, <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>
<italic>/dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) at 3PE. Proteins probed indicated on left, molecular weights on right. (<bold>D</bold>) Dot plots of normalized Shrub data points, with mean ± SEM. (<bold>E</bold>) RNA immunoprecipitation (RIP) comparing <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> control to <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup> null. RNAs probed indicated on left, molecular weights on right. (<bold>F</bold>) Optogenetic control of Shrub in <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/UAS-ChR2(H134R)-mCherry control animals (left) and <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/UAS-ChR2(H134R)-mCherry; <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup> mutants (right) reared on EtOH vehicle (not stimulated) or ATR (stimulated) food. Animals were illuminated with 5 Hz blue light for 2 hr, with brains tested by anti-Shrub Western blot. Dot plots of normalized Shrub data points, with mean ± SEM. Statistics done with two tailed unpaired t-tests, indicated as **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 and N.S. <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e684" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig1_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p id="Par7">FMRP is an mRNA-binding protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, typically exerting regulatory suppression of translation via interaction with select targets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. To test if FMRP directly interacts with <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA, we employed RNA immunoprecipitation (RIP) to assay FMRP-RNA binding in <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> controls compared to <italic>dfmr1</italic> nulls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1E</xref>). In these assays, antibodies conjugated to magnetic beads immunoprecipitate bound mRNAs, which are reverse transcribed and probed using target-specific primers. Brain lysates prepared from newly eclosed animals (3PE) were incubated with specific anti-FMRP antibodies to test for <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA binding (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1E</xref>). As controls, we used a characterized <italic>futsch/map1b</italic> mRNA target of FMRP (positive control) and <italic>α</italic>-<italic>tubulin</italic> mRNA which does not bind FMRP (negative control)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. FMRP bound mRNAs were first purified with trizole and then reverse transcribed with RT-PCR. In <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> controls, there is strong enrichment for <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA bound to FMRP in the immunoprecipitation (IP) lanes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1E</xref>). In contrast, <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutants lacking FMRP show no detectable <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA binding. These results are mirrored with the <italic>futsch</italic> mRNA positive control, but there is no enrichment for the <italic>α</italic>-<italic>tubulin</italic> mRNA negative control (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1E</xref>). These findings demonstrate FMRP directly interacts with <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA in the brain to suppress Shrub protein translation.</p>
<p id="Par8">FMRP functions in an activity sensor mechanism to mediate activity-dependent (A-D) changes in protein expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Upon neural stimulation, FMRP is dephosphorylated leading to release of bound, repressed mRNA targets and driving A-D translational upregulation, including its own transcript<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. To test the hypothesis of A-D Shrub elevation during the early-use window identified above, we used optogenetic manipulation to elevate neural activity (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1F</xref>). Staged animals expressing light-activated channelrhodopsin (UAS-ChR2(H134R)-mCherry) driven with <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4 were raised on food containing either 1) the essential cofactor all-trans retinal (ATR; experimental) or 2) ethanol vehicle only (EtOH; controls). Both sets of animals were then exposed to 5 Hz blue light pulses for the 2 hours immediately following eclosion. As above, brains were then dissected and probed with anti-Shrub and -dFMRP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1F</xref>). Compared to vehicle controls (EtOH), stimulated animals reared on ATR show a &gt;50% increase in brain Shrub levels (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1F</xref>, left). There is also a slight but significant increase in FMRP levels (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutants, there is no change in brain Shrub levels with optogenetic stimulation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1F</xref>, right), indicating that FMRP is absolutely required to regulate Shrub expression in an A-D mechanism during the early-use critical period.</p>
<p id="Par9">As the next step, we proceeded to test the contribution of elevated Shrub expression to the primary synaptic connectivity hallmark phenotypes characterizing the FXS disease state. In subsequent studies, Shrub is over-expressed in target neurons to generate a gain-of-function (GOF) condition mimicking the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null phenotype (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1A,B</xref>). Brain Western blots at 3PE show UAS-<italic>shrub</italic> driven by <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4 elevates Shrub protein levels in neurons compared to the transgenic control (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+), with no change in dFMRP protein levels (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1A</xref>). Quantified measurements show a significant increase in brain Shrub levels, comparable to the elevation characterizing the FXS disease model (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1B</xref>). To correct elevated Shrub levels, we use a <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup> null heterozygous (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/+) loss-of-function (LOF) condition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Brain Western blots show this mutant in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> background (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dfmr1</italic>) significantly reduces brain Shrub levels compared to <italic>dfmr1</italic> alone (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1C,D</xref>). Importantly, introducing <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/+ into animals lacking FMRP (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dfmr1</italic>.) completely restores normal brain Shrub levels (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1E</xref>). Quantified measurements show no significant difference in brain Shrub levels in the rescued mutant animals compared to genetic background controls (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1F</xref>). These Shrub manipulations will be compared to the FXS disease model in all subsequent experiments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec4">
<title>Shrub GOF phenocopies FMRP LOF synaptic overelaboration</title>
<p id="Par10">FMRP-deficient neurons display overelaborated synaptic connectivity in FXS patients and animal models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. To test the role of Shrub elevation on this hallmark phenotype, we assayed well-characterized olfactory projection neuron (PN) innervation of the central brain mushroom body (MB) calyx learning and memory center<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. We recently demonstrated PNs manifest FMRP- and activity-dependent critical period connectivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Using a new, highly-restricted Gal4 (Nrv3-Gal4)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> to drive a membrane marker (UAS-mCD8-GFP) in a small PN subset, MB calyx innervation was cross-compared between <italic>dfmr1</italic> nulls and Shrub over-expression (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>) in targeted neurons (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). In transgenic controls (Nrv3-Gal4/+), there is a consistent pattern of MB calyx microglomeruli innervation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2A</xref>, left). In sharp contrast, both <italic>dfmr1</italic> LOF (middle) and targeted <italic>shrub</italic> GOF (right) cause increased PN innervation, with similar overelaborated and overextended MB calyx areas (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2A</xref>). In quantified comparisons, <italic>dfmr1</italic> (1.55 ± 0.17, <italic>n</italic> = 22 hemispheres, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (1.7 ± 0.17, <italic>n</italic> = 28, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) have significantly increased PN innervation areas normalized to control (1.0 ± 0.06, <italic>n</italic> = 26), but no significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05) with each other (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2B</xref>, left). Individual PN synaptic boutons also show similarly enlarged areas in both <italic>dfmr1</italic> (9.17 ± 0.43 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 61 boutons, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (9.84 ± 0.38 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 70, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) compared to controls (6.45 ± 0.43 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 47). Once again, PN-targeted <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> phenocopies the FXS disease model (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2B</xref>, middle). Importantly, MB calyx area is indistinguishable between genotypes, showing mutant defects map specifically to increased PN innervation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2B</xref>, right).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF similarly increase projection neuron innervation. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative confocal images of central brain mushroom body calyx in transgenic control (UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4/+), the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant (UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4, <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>/<italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) and <italic>shrub</italic> over-expression (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>) GOF line (UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4/UAS-Shrub). PN axons (green) in calyx (Brp labeled, magenta) at 3PE. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of mushroom body calyx innervation area (left), single projection neuron bouton area (middle) and total calyx area (right) in dot plots showing all data points with mean ± SEM indicated for all three genotypes. (<bold>C</bold>) Sholl analysis of PN innervation of the mushroom body calyx based on centered 2 μm concentric rings. (<bold>D</bold>) Quantification of innervation area per ring for the above three genotypes. Red dotted line indicates maximum control innervation. Statistics done with one way ANOVA with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test post hoc indicated as <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05 (N.S.), *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ****<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1116" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig2_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p id="Par11">In examining innervation patterns, it is apparent that <italic>dfmr1</italic> null and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> PNs extend into MB calyx regions not innervated in controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2A</xref>). Similar connectivity defects have been reported previously in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS disease model, for example in central brain circadian clock neurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. To test the role of Shrub elevation on this <italic>dfmr1</italic> phenotype, we did Sholl analyses on the spatial extent of MB calyx innervation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2C</xref>). A series of 2 μm concentric rings centered on the calyx centroid was superimposed on each Nrv3-Gal4 &gt; UAS-mCD8-GFP image, with GFP-positive areas from each ring quantified (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2C</xref>). Compared to transgenic controls (Nrv3-Gal4/+), both <italic>dfmr1</italic> and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> exhibit similar striking expansion of innervation areas, which reach far further from the MB calyx centroid (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2D</xref>). In controls, innervation area peaks around 30 μm<sup>2</sup> at 8 μm from the MB center (dotted red line). In contrast, both <italic>dfmr1</italic> null and PN-targeted <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> exhibit similar higher levels of innervation (40–50 μm<sup>2</sup>) for further distances from the calyx centroid (8–12 μm; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2D</xref>). Innervation areas surpassed controls in <italic>dfmr1</italic> LOF and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> GOF in all rings between 6 and 16 μm, with the largest differences at 8 μm (<italic>dfmr1</italic>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), 10 μm (<italic>dfmr1</italic>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), 12 μm (<italic>dfmr1</italic>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and 14 μm (<italic>dfmr1</italic>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Importantly, there is no significant difference between <italic>dfmr1</italic> and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> in any ring (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2D</xref>). Taken together, these results show PN-targeted <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> phenocopies FXS model overelaboration of MB calyx innervation, including increased area, enlarged synaptic boutons and expanded spatial ramification. These results suggest elevated Shrub levels drive FXS synaptic connectivity errors. Since the mechanistic consequences of Shrub GOF are unknown, we next examined Shrub function in PN synaptic terminals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec5">
<title>Shrub GOF phenocopies FMRP LOF synaptic membrane trafficking defects</title>
<p id="Par12">The ESCRT-III core component Shrub (yeast Snf7/Vps32, human CHMP4) has conserved functions in the membrane trafficking<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Disruptions in this mechanism result in aberrant, enlarged endocytic organelles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> with associated neurological defects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Importantly, Shrub LOF and GOF similarly disrupt membrane trafficking<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, suggesting Shrub elevation in the FXS disease state could impair membrane trafficking to cause synaptic connectivity defects. The small GTPase Rab5 is commonly used to label endosomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, and often presents as aberrant, enlarged punctae in <italic>shrub</italic> mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3A</xref>). We used this marker to test how <italic>dfmr1</italic> LOF and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> GOF might affect endosomes in PN synaptic terminals. During normal membrane trafficking, internalized vesicles fuse into endosomes that are subsequently acted upon by ESCRTs to form a multivesicular body (MVB; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3A</xref>, top); however, ESCRT defects result in impaired maturation (bottom). We hypothesized Shrub GOF and FMRP LOF similarly disrupt progression through this pathway to cause an increase in enlarged Rab5-positive endosomes. To test this hypothesis, dissected brains from newly-eclosed animals (3PE) with GFP-marked PNs (Nrv3-Gal4 &gt; UAS-mCD8-GFP) were labeled for Rab5 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3B</xref>). Single optic slices (&lt;0.5 μm) of PN synaptic boutons were assayed for endosomes. Compared to transgenic controls (Nrv3-Gal4/+), both <italic>dfmr1</italic> nulls and PN-targeted <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> show a striking increase in Rab5-positive endosome number in PN boutons within the calyx (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3B</xref>). This suggests a similar endocytic membrane trafficking defect.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF similarly increase PN synaptic endosomes. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic of ESCRT trafficking of Rab5-positive endosomes. <underline>Top</underline>: Normally functioning ESCRT in which endocytosis leads to endosomes and subsequent multivesicular body (MVB) formation. <underline>Bottom</underline>: Defective ESCRT in which trafficking is arrested leading to Rab5-positive enlarged endosomes. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative confocal images of single PN synaptic boutons (green) labeled with anti-Rab5 (magenta) comparing the transgenic control (<underline>top</underline>: UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4/+), <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant (<underline>middle</underline>: UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4, <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>/<italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (<underline>bottom</underline>: UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4/UAS-Shrub). The right column shows heat maps of Rab5 labeling, with the range indicated below. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification dot plots showing data points with mean ± SEM of the above three genotypes displaying Rab5 puncta per synaptic bouton area. (<bold>D</bold>) Quantification of the bouton frequency with 0 or ≥1 Rab5-positive punctae. Statistics done with one way ANOVA with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test post hoc indicated as N.S. <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 and ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1431" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig3_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p id="Par13">Using the Rab5 endosomal marker in quantified comparisons, both <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutants (0.1 ± 0.03 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 23 boutons, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and PN-targeted <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> GOF (0.04 ± 0.01 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 29, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) show highly significant increases in the number of endosomes per synaptic bouton area compared to controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3C</xref>). Importantly, FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF show no significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05), and are indistinguishable from each other (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3C</xref>). A number of studies report an increase in Rab5-positive endosomal size resulting from ESCRT defects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. It should be noted that Rab5-positive endosomes in control PN boutons are typically too small to be resolved with light microscopy, and only become readily detectable when aberrantly enlarged in <italic>dfmr1</italic> LOF and <italic>shrub</italic> GOF conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3B</xref>). Comparing the frequency of detectable Rab5-positive synaptic endosomes across genotypes, &lt;5% of control synaptic boutons contain any measurable endosomes, whereas &gt;50% of both <italic>dfmr1</italic> null and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> boutons have large endosomes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3D</xref>). These findings suggest that small, dynamic endosomes predominate in control boutons, but that more aberrantly enlarged endosomes characterize both <italic>dfmr1</italic> LOF and <italic>shrub</italic> GOF boutons (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3D</xref>), consistent with a local membrane trafficking defect within the synapse. However, these synaptic organelles are at the edge of light microscopy resolution, particularly in control brains, so we next turned to transmission electron microscopy for a more detailed examination of PN synapse structure and membrane trafficking changes due to Shrub elevation in the FXS disease state.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec6">
<title>Shrub GOF phenocopies FMRP LOF synaptic ultrastructural deficits</title>
<p id="Par14">Our lab and others have characterized ultrastructure abnormalities in FMRP-deficient synaptic boutons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>, albeit never with a focus on PN innervation of the MB calyx. To determine whether increased Shrub levels might affect synaptic ultrastructure in the FXS disease state, we used transmission electron microscopy (TEM) to compare <italic>dfmr1</italic> null and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> PN synaptic boutons (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>). The MB calyx (CA) is located in the posteriodorsal brain region, revealed in light microscopy by dense labeling of the presynaptic marker bruchpilot (purple), with PN axons (green) entering through the inner antennocerebral tract (iACT; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4A</xref>). PN synaptic boutons are easily identified as the largest varicosities (arrows) in the calyx. For TEM studies, acutely dissected brains (3PE) embedded in epoxy resin were oriented with the microtome sectional plane progressing from dorsal to ventral (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4A</xref>, rhombus). Electron micrographs reveal the MB calyx as an oval, fan-shaped nucleus 40–50 μm in cross-sectional diameter (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4B</xref>; pseudo-colored purple), encapsulated on three sides by Kenyon cell (KC) somata (blue). Just anterior to the MB calyx, the iATC is an easily identifiable TEM landmark with longitudinal projections bending into the base of the MB calyx (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4B</xref>; pseudo-colored green). PN synaptic boutons can be seen extending off the iACT into the calyx (green varicosities). Comparing the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant to matched control, there are no detectable differences in the gross MB calyx architecture, including iATC placement, KC cell bodies and calyx size (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4B</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF similarly alter PN synaptic ultrastructure. (<bold>A</bold>) Confocal image stack of the mushroom body calyx showing sectioning strategy; white arrows (PN boutons), rhombus (sectional plane) and red arrow (sectional direction). PNs are labeled with UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4/+ (green) in the MB calyx (magenta). Abbreviations: inner antennocerebral tract (iACT), calyx (CA), dorsal (D) and ventral (V). (<bold>B</bold>) Low magnification (1450X) transmission electron micrographs of <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> genetic background control (left) and <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup> null mutant (right) during 3PE. Both images are pseudo-colored as in (<bold>A</bold>): iACT axons and PN boutons (green), calyx (magenta), and Kenyon cells (KC, blue). (<bold>C</bold>) Representative PN synaptic bouton electron micrographs comparing transgenic control (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+), <italic>dfmr1</italic> null (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) and <italic>shrub</italic> over-expression (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>) GOF (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+; UAS-Shrub/+). The dotted red lines depict the PN bouton borders; active zone t-bars are shown by yellow arrows, synaptic vesicles pools (SV), mitochondria (M), Kenyon cell (KC). (<bold>D</bold>) Dot plot showing PN bouton area quantification for the above three genotypes, with mean ± SEM. Statistics done with one way ANOVA with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test post hoc indicated as N.S. <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 and ****<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1641" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig4_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p id="Par15">Comparison of low magnification TEM images of <italic>dfmr1</italic> nulls and controls shows a striking difference in PN boutons in the MB calyx (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4B</xref>). In controls, synaptic boutons are difficult to discriminate at low magnification, whereas <italic>dfmr1</italic> mutants display obvious, enlarged boutons, consistent with published FXS reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. To test whether Shrub GOF has similar effects, we examined <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> PN boutons in parallel at high magnification (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4C</xref>). Synaptic boutons were defined as large varicosities (red dotted line) completely surrounded by the smaller Kenyon cell (KC) dendritic profiles to form the MB calyx microglomeruli. PN boutons in controls and both mutant conditions contain stereotypical synaptic architecture, including clearly defined synaptic vesicle (SV) pools, multiple mitochondria (M) and active zones with electron-dense t-bars (yellow arrows). There are no apparent differences in any of these parameters (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4C</xref>). However, control boutons are much smaller compared to both <italic>dfmr1</italic> LOF nulls and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> GOF animals (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4C</xref>). Quantitative analyses show <italic>dfmr1</italic> null (14.49 ± 0.59 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 61 boutons, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (15.51 ± 0.62 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 65, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) boutons both exhibit significantly increased areas compared to controls (11.21 ± 0.07 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 39; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4D</xref>). Importantly, there is no significant difference between <italic>dfmr1</italic> and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05), with both showing an indistinguishable synaptic bouton enlargement (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4C,D</xref>). These results are consistent with increased Shrub levels driving FXS synaptic ultrastructure errors, and suggest membrane trafficking impairment within the synaptic termini as the causative mechanism.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec7">
<title>Shrub GOF phenocopies FMRP LOF synaptic membrane trafficking errors</title>
<p id="Par16">To more precisely investigate defects in synaptic membrane trafficking, TEM was next used to analyze ultrastructural changes in PN synaptic bouton organelles. We hypothesized that FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF would cause enlarged, trafficking-arrested endosomes, consistent with Shrub requirements in other contexts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. For TEM, we defined endosomes as vacuole organelles with a single membrane and 0.01 μm<sup>2</sup> minimum area. Such synaptic organelles are present in all genotypes analyzed (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5A</xref>; pseudo-colored purple and insets), with control boutons displaying a low density that never exceeds 0.25 μm<sup>2</sup> in area (top). In stark contrast, <italic>dfmr1</italic> null and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> boutons both present increased numbers of these organelles, with greatly inflated areas (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5A</xref>; middle and bottom). Quantification reveals significantly increased numbers per bouton in <italic>dfmr1</italic> null (0.19 ± 0.02, <italic>n</italic> = 61 boutons, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (0.25 ± 0.02, <italic>n</italic> = 65, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) compared to controls (0.12 ± 0.02, <italic>n</italic> = 40; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5B</xref>). Importantly, there is no significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05) between FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF boutons (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5B</xref>). In the size of these compartments, there is highly significantly increased areas in both <italic>dfmr1</italic> (0.07 ± 0.008 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 156 endosomes, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (0.05 ± 0.007 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 237, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) compared to controls (0.02 ± 0.004 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 46; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5C</xref>). Once again, there is no significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05) between FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF boutons (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5C</xref>). These results are consistent with an ESCRT-III defect and suggest elevated Shrub in the FXS disease state disrupts endocytic membrane trafficking within synaptic terminals.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF similarly increase PN synaptic endosomic vacuoles. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative electron micrographs of projection neuron synaptic boutons in the MB calyx comparing transgenic control (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+), <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) and <italic>shrub</italic> over-expression (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>) GOF (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+; UAS-Shrub/+). Typical endosomic vacuole examples are pseudo-colored (magenta), with insets showing enlarged organelle (red box in main image). Dot plot quantification of endosomes per bouton area (<bold>B</bold>) and endosome area (<bold>C</bold>) for all three genotypes, comparing mean ± SEM. Statistics done with one way ANOVA with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test post hoc indicated as N.S. <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and ****<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1914" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig5_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p id="Par17">During multivesicular body (MVB) formation, Shrub spiraled filaments drive membrane budding away from the cytosol, leading to formation of an intraluminal vesicle (ILV; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6A</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Shrub GOF can disrupt this process by overwhelming membrane trafficking with run-away filament formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, due to an imbalance of ESCRT-III subunit stoichiometry. We hypothesized Shrub GOF would impair ILV formation, resulting in big luminal vesicles (BLV; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6A</xref>). Consistently, just such arrested trafficking organelles characterize both <italic>dfmr1</italic> null and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> synaptic boutons (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6B</xref>). These aberrant compartments occur in the mutants only, and are not found in control boutons. In controls, ILVs are small, highly regular in size and never exceed 0.008 μm<sup>2</sup> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6B</xref>, top), whereas <italic>dfmr1</italic> and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> BLVs are larger, display a greater variation in size and can be 10X larger at nearly 0.08 μm<sup>2</sup> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6B</xref>; middle and bottom). In quantified comparisons, BLV areas in <italic>dfmr1</italic> null (0.019 ± 0.007 μm<sup>2</sup>; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> (0.02 ± 0.007 μm<sup>2</sup>; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) PN boutons are both significantly larger than ILV areas in controls (0.007 ± 0.001 μm<sup>2</sup>; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6C</xref>). Importantly, BLVs are indistinguishable between FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6B,C</xref>). These results suggest elevated Shrub levels in the FXS disease state impair ILV formation and arrest membrane trafficking in synaptic boutons. The phenocopy of FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF defects is compelling, but to test causation we next corrected Shrub levels in the FXS condition and then assayed synaptic and membrane trafficking defects.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF similarly arrest ILV formation in synaptic boutons. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic depicting how increased Shrub levels impact ILV formation. <underline>Top</underline>: Proper Shrub levels form spiral protein filaments (blue) that are capped by Vps24 (red octagon) leading to small interluminal vesicle (ILV) formation within MVBs. <underline>Bottom</underline>: Excessive Shrub levels result in unrestrained filaments (blue), not correctly capped, leading to big luminal vesicle (BLV) formation. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative electron micrographs comparing ILV organelles in transgenic controls (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+) to enlarged BLV organelles characterizing both the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) and <italic>shrub</italic> over-expression (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup>) GPF (<italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+; UAS-Shrub/+). (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification dot plot of luminal vesicle areas in all three genotypes, showing mean ± SEM. Statistics done with one way ANOVA with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test post hoc indicated as N.S. <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e2077" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig6_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec8">
<title>Correcting Shrub levels in the FXS disease model mitigates synaptic errors</title>
<p id="Par18">The above results show FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF similarly cause overelaborated PN synaptic innervation of the central brain MB learning/memory center (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>), as well as defective endosomal membrane trafficking within PN synaptic boutons (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig6">6</xref>). We therefore hypothesized that FMRP-dependent Shrub suppression controls synaptic membrane trafficking to limit synaptic connectivity, with Shrub elevation due to FMRP loss causing the synaptic hyper-connectivity errors characterizing the FXS disease state. This hypothesis predicts that reducing Shrub levels towards normal in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant background should alleviate both FXS membrane trafficking defects and synaptic connectivity impairments. To test this hypothesis, we introduced a heterozygous <italic>shrub</italic> null allele (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>+)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> into <italic>dfmr1</italic> homozygous null animals. As previously, PNs plasma membranes were labeled with GFP (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>UAS-mCD8-GFP; <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>, Nrv3-Gal4<italic>/dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) to assay phenotypes specifically within PN synaptic terminals. Under the same conditions, we compared the corrected <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>+ heterozygous condition to both the genetic background (positive control) and FXS disease model (negative control). Representative confocal light microscopy images and quantified results for PN synaptic connectivity are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7</xref>, and similar TEM data for synaptic membrane trafficking are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig8">8</xref>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Shrub correction in <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutants restores PN innervation of MB calyx. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative confocal images of PN innervation of the MB calyx comparing transgenic control (UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4/+), <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant (UAS-mCD8::GFP/+; Nrv3-Gal4, <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>/<italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup> null heterozygote (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/+) in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> homozygous null background (UAS-mCD8::GFP/<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>; Nrv3-Gal4, <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>/<italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>). PN (green) in the calyx, with anti-FMRP labeled (magenta). (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification dot plot of MB innervation area showing mean ± SEM in the above three genotypes. Statistics done with one way ANOVA with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test post hoc indicated as N.S. <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and ****<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e2250" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig7_HTML"></graphic></fig>
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Shrub correction in <italic>dfmr1</italic> prevents PN synaptic bouton ultrastructure defects. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative electron micrographs comparing synaptic PN ultrastructure between the transgenic control (Nrv3-Gal4/+), <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant (Nrv3-Gal4, <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>/<italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup> null heterozygote (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/+) in <italic>dfmr1</italic> homozygous null background (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/+; Nrv3-Gal4, <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>/<italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>). Dotted red lines depict PN synaptic bouton borders and red arrows indicate endosomic vacuoles, pseudo-colored (magenta). Quantification as dot plot for (<bold>B</bold>) bouton area and (<bold>C</bold>) endosome number per bouton area for the above genotypes. Statistics done with one way ANOVA with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test post hoc indicated as N.S. <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ****<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e2346" xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_Fig8_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p id="Par19">We first assayed PN innervation, again employing Nrv3-Gal4 &gt; UAS-mCD8-GFP labeling immediately post-eclosion (3PE; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7A</xref>). Consistent with above results, transgenic controls (Nrv3-Gal4/+) display stereotyped innervation of the MB calyx, remaining constricted to a small subset of the total calycle region (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7A</xref>, top), and <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutants exhibit obviously increased PN elaboration with spatially expanded innervation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7A</xref>, middle). Consistent with our hypothesis, removing a single copy of <italic>shrub</italic> in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutant background (<italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>+; <italic>dfmr1/dfmr1</italic>) is sufficient to strongly ameliorate the excessive PN innervation characterizing the FXS model (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7A</xref>, bottom). FMRP labeling in both <italic>dfmr1</italic> alone and with <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>+ confirms the complete loss of FMRP in both genotypes compared to the control (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7A</xref>, middle column). With Shrub correction, PN innervation of MB calyx is more restricted in both area and spatial domain, more closely resembling the controls than <italic>dfmr1</italic> nulls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7A</xref>). Consistent with these observations, removal of one copy of <italic>shrub</italic> in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> null background significantly reduces the PN innervation area within the MB calyx (1.3 ± 0.1; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) compared to <italic>dfmr1</italic> alone (1.6 ± 0.1; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 vs. control), as normalized to control (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7B</xref>). Importantly, no significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05) remains between <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>+; <italic>dfmr1/dfmr1</italic> and controls (1.0 ± 0.03; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7B</xref>). These results clearly demonstrate that increased Shrub levels strongly contribute to FXS synaptic connectivity errors. We next wanted to test roles of FMRP-dependent Shrub elevation in synaptic ultrastructure and membrane trafficking defects.</p>
<p id="Par20">We assayed PN synaptic boutons using TEM immediately post-eclosion (3PE; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig8">8A</xref>). Consistent with above results, transgenic control (Nrv3-Gal4/+) boutons are much smaller than <italic>dfmr1</italic> null boutons (left vs. middle). In contrast, Shrub correction reduces the bouton size (right). In quantitative comparisons, removing a single copy of <italic>shrub</italic> significantly reduces bouton area (12.48 ± 0.65 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 62 boutons, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) relative to <italic>dfmr1</italic> nulls (15.99 ± 0.76 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 76; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig8">8B</xref>). Importantly, no significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05) remains between <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>+; <italic>dfmr1/dfmr1</italic> and controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig8">8B</xref>). Finally, we tested whether correcting Shrub in the <italic>dfmr1</italic> background affects endocytic membrane trafficking at the synapse. Consistent with above results, control boutons contain low numbers of small endosomes, whereas boutons lacking FMRP show more, larger organelles (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig8">8A</xref>, left and middle; pseudo-colored). Consistent with our hypothesis, correcting Shrub levels reduces the number of these compartments (right). When organelles per synaptic bouton area is quantified, both the controls (0.08 ± 0.01 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 72 boutons, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>
<italic>/</italic>+; <italic>dfmr1/dfmr1</italic> (0.08 ± 0.0.1 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 62, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) are significantly reduced compared to <italic>dfmr1</italic> alone (0.16 ± 0.02 μm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 76; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig8">8C</xref>). The control and Shrub correction conditions are identical, with no differences persisting (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig8">8C</xref>). These results indicate the endocytic membrane trafficking errors in <italic>dfmr1</italic> null LOF synaptic boutons result from increased levels of Shrub. Collectively, the above findings strongly indicate that loss of FMRP-dependent Shrub regulation resulting in over-expression heavily impairs synaptic membrane trafficking to drive the synaptic hyper connectivity errors characterizing the FXS disease state.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="Par21">Using a brain developmental proteomics screen in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS model, we set out to find molecular players underlying synaptic connectivity errors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. Here, we pursued a top candidate, the ESCRT-III protein Shrub (yeast Snf7, human CHMP4), a key component in select membrane trafficking mechanisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. FMRP binds target transcripts to repress protein translation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, and we show here that FMRP binds <italic>shrub</italic> mRNA to limit Shrub protein levels specifically during the early-use critical period. This time window of initial sensory input closely following eclosion is delineated by peak FMRP expression levels and a transient requirement for FMRP in activity-dependent refinement mechanisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. FMRP mediates activity-dependent synaptic connectivity changes as an activity sensor regulating translation downstream of sensory input<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. This FMRP function relies on phosphorylation, with sensory input activity driving dephosphorylation to remove translational inhibition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, and a FMRP phosphomimetic restoring protein levels and correcting synaptic connectivity errors in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Using transient optogenetic stimulation immediately following eclosion, we show here that Shrub expression in neurons is acutely upregulated in an FMRP-dependent mechanism by activity during the early-use critical period, suggesting FMRP exerts translational repression of Shrub in this activity-dependent mechanism.</p>
<p id="Par22">FMRP function in regulating synaptic connectivity is well established, with null mutants displaying increased complexity of both pre- and postsynaptic compartments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. We show here that FMRP similarly limits olfactory projection neuron (PN) innervation of the mushroom body (MB) calyx, a key input into a central brain learning and memory center<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. Consistently, the ESCRT pathway also controls synaptic connectivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Specifically, the ESCRT-III core component Shrub has critical roles shaping the architecture of <italic>Drosophila</italic> peripheral and central neurons. Loss-of-function (LOF) <italic>shrub</italic> mutations cause dendritic arbor overelaboration highly reminiscent of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS disease model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Critically, gain-of-function (GOF) in <italic>shrub</italic> homologs mimics LOF defects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, predicting that <italic>shrub</italic> GOF in the FXS state should have similar consequences. Consistently, we show here that PN-targeted <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> closely phenocopies <italic>dfmr1</italic> null defects of over-elaborated and over-extended innervation within the MB calyx. This parallel extends down to the level of individual PN synaptic boutons, which are similarly enlarged in both FMRP LOF and Shub GOF conditions, closely resembling the synaptic expansion characterizing other FXS model circuits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. These findings link Shrub function driving membrane trafficking to synaptic remodeling defects, strongly suggesting that elevated Shrub levels could be contributing to FXS connectivity errors.</p>
<p id="Par23">Membrane from the cell surface of developing neurons is in a state of constant flux via endocytic budding and exocytic fusion, which requires tightly-regulated trafficking through the endomembrane organelle system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. The proper balance of membrane addition and retrieval is therefore essential for the surface remodeling that occurs during synaptic connectivity changes. For example, regulated endocytosis is required for dendritic arbor development of <italic>Drosophila</italic> sensory neurons, where endocytic membrane trafficking precedes synaptic reorganization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. Interfering with this membrane retrieval mechanism either through 1) blocking endocytosis (e.g. dynamin mutants) or 2) perturbing endosomic maturation (e.g. ESCRT pathway mutants) causes improper circuit wiring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Together with connectivity errors, the common membrane trafficking phenotype observed is the presence of irregular endocytic organelle compartments, visualized with endosomal markers such as Rab5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Specifically, mutations in ESCRT machinery such as Shrub result in the accumulation of enlarged endosomal organelles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. We show here that consistent endomembrane trafficking defects with accumulated, greatly enlarged Rab5-positive endosomes occur in both <italic>dfmr1</italic> null LOF and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> GOF synaptic boutons. These arrested endosomes are rarely observed in controls, suggesting that synaptic membrane trafficking errors due to Shrub over-expression characterize the FXS disease state.</p>
<p id="Par24">Our synaptic ultrastructure studies consistently reveal accumulation of enlarged vacuoles in PN boutons, which are presumed to be arrested endosomes. Enlarged endosomes arise from impaired membrane trafficking flux, causing endosomes to swell as membrane accumulates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. These findings suggest a bottleneck in synaptic membrane trafficking as a result of increased Shrub levels in the FXS condition, leading to an accumulation of arrested intermediates. We hypothesize this trafficking defect contributes to PN synapse errors in the FXS disease state. Indeed, <italic>Drosophila</italic> PN axons exhibit endosome clustering and fusion prior to MVB formation, with disruptions in this membrane traffic causing phenotypes similar to those reported here<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Our results support the conclusion that membrane trafficking is abnormal in the FXS disease state due to heightened Shrub levels. Although our results point to a endocytic membrane trafficking defect as causative, a study of ESCRT functions in synaptic remodeling suggest that while endosomal defects occur in all ESCRT pathway mutants, they may not be sufficient to explain synaptic errors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. This work revealed a second ESCRT module of Shrub acting locally at the plasma membrane to directly induce neural process fragmentation. We see no evidence of this mechanism in the MB calyx, but it is possible that this direct plasma membrane impairment contributes to synaptic defects in the FXS disease state.</p>
<p id="Par25">In this study we focus attention on early adult brain PNs to demonstrate FMRP-mediated Shrub regulation modulates critical period synaptic connectivity. However, FMRP and Shrub act in other neuron types (e.g. sensory and motor neurons) and during various developmental periods (e.g. embryo and larva)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. Thus, FMRP may regulate Shrub in multiple neuronal classes at different times. To date, no other published work links FMRP and Shrub. However, a recent study demonstrates FMRP regulates synaptic pruning of MB neurons (downstream of PNs) during metamorphosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>, a process where Shrub has a pivotal role<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Likewise, the well-studied neuromuscular junction (NMJ) model synapse shows A-D modulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>, with established roles for FMRP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and Shrub<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> modulating connectivity during embryonic and larval development. These examples suggest possible overlaps in developing neurons, but what about mature neurons? Following the critical period when synaptic connectivity is refined, FMRP expression markedly decreases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, and some mature neurons do not display the overelaborated architecture characterizing <italic>dfmr1</italic> null mutants during development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. This implies a restricted role for FMRP at maturity, although Shrub is required for membrane traffic throughout life. Indeed, our results indicate a transient FMRP regulation of Shrub translation during critical period development. Thus, FMRP-Shrub interactions may be restricted to neuronal development stages.</p>
<p id="Par26">Previous investigations linking membrane trafficking defects to synaptic connectivity errors focus on LOF mutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, yet our findings show similar phenotypes from Shrub GOF. This duality may be explained by ESCRT-III subunit stoichiometry in assembled function. Unlike other ESCRTs, ESCRT-III components exist as auto-inhibited monomers that assemble sequentially on the membrane upon activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, with the relative abundance of ESCRT-III subunits paramount to membrane trafficking functions. Indeed, yeast studies demonstrate that increased levels of the Shrub homolog Snf7 strongly hamper ESCRT-III function, resulting in endosomal trafficking defects similar to LOF mutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. The rationale is that Shrub/Snf7 continues to form protein filaments unless capped by Vps24, a critical checkpoint step that allows membrane trafficking to proceed forward<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. When Shrub/Snf7 is in stoichiometric excess, capping does not occur properly and filaments fail to stop polymerizing, resulting in impaired membrane trafficking. We show here that aberrantly enlarged intraluminal vesicle organelles (BLV compartments) occur only in FMRP LOF and Shrub GOF synaptic boutons, consistent with unrestrained Shrub filament formation at trafficking endosomes. Given arrested BLV compartments characterize both <italic>dfmr1</italic> null and <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>OE</italic></sup> boutons, we propose a membrane trafficking impairment underlies synaptic connectivity defects in the FXS disease state.</p>
<p id="Par27">Our work suggests a cell-autonomous role for FMRP in suppressing Shrub translation to regulate synaptic refinement within the neuron. However, we do not preclude the possibility of intercellular signaling and, indeed, FMRP is well known to regulate intercellular signaling in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Moreover, ESCRT-III membrane trafficking is also well known to regulate the presentation of cell surface proteins involved in intercellular signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. In this context, glia are known to sculpt connectivity during development, with glial phagocytosis synaptic pruning conserved from insects to mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. A recent <italic>Drosophila</italic> study demonstrated that FMRP loss causes reduced glial phagocytosis during metamorphic neuronal pruning<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. It is possible that a similar mechanism occurs during the later, activity-dependent refinement. This mechanism could involve two steps; 1) Shrub-dependent, cell-autonomous synapse marking, and 2) consequent pruning via glial engulfment. Studies suggest Shrub-dependent processes act upstream of glial synapse elimination, and may be required for glial activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Although beyond the scope of the current study, it is interesting to speculate that elevated Shrub levels in the FXS condition could disrupt cell-autonomous synapse tagging, preventing glial engulfment. Future studies will probe connections between Shrub membrane trafficking and glia in the FXS disease state.</p>
<p id="Par28">We demonstrate here that lack of FMRP-mediated Shrub regulation strongly contributes to FXS synaptic defects. However, we note that Shrub is only a piece of the puzzle. FMRP regulates many neural transcripts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>, although the scope of this regulation remains indeterminate, and a number of these targets are established to play roles in synaptic connectivity. Validated targets like Microtubule Associated Protein 1B (<italic>Drosophila</italic> Futsch) control the cytoskeleton during synaptic outgrowth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, while others such as matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) modulate <italic>trans</italic>-synaptic signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Whether these targets act in the same, parallel or distinct pathways in the FXS context is entirely unknown. However, it is interesting to envision a coupled mechanism in which they work together to manifest disease impairments. For example, extracellular MMPs could control information relay at synapses via surface receptors that are impacted by Shrub-mediated membrane trafficking supported by cytoskeletal changes regulated by Futsch. Sculpting synapses could thereby require appropriate extracellular, membrane and cytoskeletal remodeling in a linked cascade. This linkage could potentially explain why manipulating individual FMRP targets can rescue FXS synaptic connectivity phenotypes. Investigations involving modulating multiple targets in combination in the disease model background will be required to dissect the complex interactions between FMRP targets.</p>
<p id="Par29">This study reveals for the first time a link between ESCRT-III membrane trafficking and FXS synaptic connectivity defects. Correcting Shrub levels prevents synaptic membrane trafficking defects and mitigates synaptic connectivity errors. Our results suggest FMRP directly negatively regulates Shrub translation to control Shrub-dependent synaptic membrane traffic driving synaptic refinement. ESCRT-III has been similarly implicated in other neurological disorders. For example, mutations in the human ESCRT-III component CHMP2B are linked to frontotemporal dementia (FTD), with defects in endocytic membrane trafficking similar to those reported here<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. However, FTD causes neurodegeneration, seemingly at the opposite end of the neurological spectrum from synaptic overgrowth. However, our study and others have focused on neurodevelopment, while FTD occurs in aging neurons. This raises the interesting possibility that disrupting the same membrane trafficking pathway could lead to opposite effects depending on age, underscoring the importance of developmental timing in studying neurological disorders. Future studies are required to dissect how Shrub-dependent membrane trafficking errors underlie synaptic connectivity defects in the FXS disease state. However, our current results clearly implicate increased Shrub levels in innervation abnormalities in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> FXS model brain learning and memory center, promising novel avenues for FXS therapeutic intervention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec10" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="Sec11">
<title>Drosophila genetics</title>
<p id="Par30">Stocks were reared on standard cornmeal/agar/molasses food at 25 °C on a 12 h light:dark cycle. All lines were generated with standard genetic crosses schemes with the following starter stocks: (1) <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> genetic background control, 2) <italic>dfmr1</italic>
<sup><italic>50M</italic></sup>/TM6TbGFP null allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, 3) UAS-9557–3 <italic>dfmr1</italic> transgene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, 4) <italic>shrub</italic>
<sup><italic>4</italic></sup>/Cyo null allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, 5) UAS-<italic>shrub</italic> transgene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, 6) <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/Cyo pan-neuronal driver (Bloomington stock # 8765), 7) Nrv3-Gal4 selective projection neuron driver (Janelia FlyLight Collection R54F05)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, 8) UAS-ChR2(H134R)-mCherry channelrhodopsin transgene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, and 9) UAS-mCD8-GFP membrane marker<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. <italic>w</italic>
<sup>1118</sup> was used as genetic background control. Transgenic controls used were <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4/+ and Nrv3-Gal4/+. All genotypes were run in parallel for each experimental replicate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec12">
<title>Western blots</title>
<p id="Par31">The brains of staged animals were dissected on ice in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) containing 1X Roche complete EDTA free protease inhibitor (Roche 04 693 123 001) and immediately snap-frozen on dry ice. Samples were homogenized in lysate buffer containing 1X LDS (NuPAGE LDS Sample Buffer 4X Life Technologies NP0007), 1X ΣPI, 1X PMSF and 1.3% BME in ddH<sub>2</sub>0, and then incubated at 4 °C for 30 mins with rotation. Lysates were spun down at 16000 g for 10 mins at 4 °C, and supernatant was then heated for 10 mins at 70 °C followed by a 10 min 16000 g centrifugation. Lysate from 4 brains was loaded into 4–12% Bis-Tris gels with MES running buffer, and run for 10 mins at 100 V followed by a shift to 150 V until the dye ran off. Samples were transferred to nitrocellulose membranes overnight (O/N) at 4 °C using 1X NuPAGE transfer buffer (novex NP0006-1), supplemented with 20% methanol (MeOH). Membranes were rinsed with ddH<sub>2</sub>0 and then blocked in 5% powdered milk in Tris buffered saline (TBS: 150 mM NaCL, 5 Mm KCl, 25 mM Tris) for 2 h at room temperature (RT) with rotation. Membranes were incubated in primary antibody diluted in 5% powdered milk in TBS with 0.1% Tween-20 (TBS-T) O/N at 4 °C with rotation. Blots were then washed 6 × 5 mins in 5% powdered milk in TBS-T at RT with rotation followed by a 2 h incubation with secondary antibody diluted in wash buffer. Membranes were washed as above then imaged using a Li-Cor Odyssey machine. Protein bands were analyzed using Image Studio software normalized to loading controls, then presented as percent of control. Primary antibodies used were: rabbit anti-Shrub (1:10000), a gift from Fen Biao Gao<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, mouse anti-dFMRP (1:3000) (Sigma F4554) and mouse anti-α-tubulin (1:5000) (DHSB 12G10). Secondary antibodies used were: Alexaflour 680 goat anti-rabbit and -mouse (1:10000).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec13">
<title>RNA immunoprecipitation</title>
<p id="Par32">RNA immunoprecipitation (RIP) was done as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, with minor changes. Staged animals were decapitated and the heads snap-frozen on dry ice in nuclease free tubes. 100 heads per genotype were homogenized with a pestle in 600 µl lysis buffer (20 mM hepes, 100 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM EDTA, 0.05% Triton X, 5% glycerol, 1X SigmaFast Protease inhibitor, 120 U/ml RNAse inhibitor). The lysate was incubated for 30 mins at 4 °C with rotation, and then spun at 12,000 g for 10 mins at 4 °C. The supernatant was transferred to prechilled tubes containing non-conjugated DynaBeads (Invitrogen 10003D), and allowed to preclear for 30 mins at 4 °C with rotation. DynaBeads were conjugated to monoclonal mouse anti-dFMRP (Sigma F4554) according to the manufacturer’s protocol, and precleared lysate (200 µl) was added to the antibody-bead slurry (80 µl) O/N at 4 °C with rotation. The beads were then separated from supernatant and washed 3X with 500 µl fresh lysis buffer vortexing with 500 µl TRIzole (ambion 15596026). Chloroform (100 µl) was added and samples were vortexed for 30 sesc and then incubated for 2 mins. Samples were then centrifuged at 16000 g for 10 mins at 4 °C. The upper aqueous layer was transferred to prechilled tubes, and glycogen (1 µl) then 2-propanol (250 µl) added and incubated for 10 mins at RT with rotation. Samples were then spun at 16000 g for 10 mins at 4 °C, the supernatant removed and the pellet washed 3X with 75% EtOH (500 µl), followed by centrifugation at 16000 g for 10 mins at 4 °C. EtOH was then removed and pellets air-dried for 10 mins. ddH<sub>2</sub>0 (20 µl) was added and mRNA reverse transcribed with a SuperScript Vilo kit (Invitrogen 11754-050) according to manufacturer’s protocol. cDNA was amplified with HotSart Taq (New England BioLabs M0495S) using a touchdown PCR protocol. Amplified cDNA was separated on a 0.8% agarose gel and visualized with SyberSafe DNA stain (Invitrogen S33102). Gels were run at 150 V for 1 h. PCR primers used: <italic>shrub</italic> forward primer GTTTCTTCGGGAAGATGTTCGG, <italic>shrub</italic> reverse primer CTGATGGGCTCTCTTGAGGG, <italic>futsch/map1b</italic> forward primer CAGTTTCACCCGCCACCG, <italic>futsch/map1b</italic> reverse primer GCACGTTGCTGTTGTTTAGGC, <italic>α</italic>-<italic>tubulin</italic> forward primer CTGTGGTCGATGAGGTCCG <italic>α</italic>-<italic>tubulin</italic> reverse primer GCGTAGGTCACCAGAGGG.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec14">
<title>Optogenetic stimulation</title>
<p id="Par33">Optogenetic experiments were performed as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Briefly, staged animals expressing channelrhodopsin (UAS-ChR2(H134R)-mCherry) under the <italic>elav</italic>-Gal4 pan-neuronal driver were fed from hatching on standard food supplemented with either 10 μl EtOH vehicle (in 10 ml volume; control) or with 10 μM all-trans retinol (ATR), an essential cofactor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Immediately following eclosion, animals were placed in 30 mm petri dishes with pleated Whatman paper saturated with vehicle control or ATR in a 20% sucrose solution. Sealed petri dishes were placed in a LED exposure chamber with two Luxeon Rebel Endor Star 3 × 15-Watt LED arrays (470 nm blue light, LED Supply). At 15 V, the LED arrays generate ~100 μW/cm<sup>2</sup> at a working distance of 2 cm. Animals were exposed to 5 Hz pulses of blue light for 2 h and subsequently processed for Western blotting as described above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec15">
<title>Immunocytochemistry imaging</title>
<p id="Par34">Staged animal brains were labeled and imaged as previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, with slight variation. Briefly, brains were dissected in cold PBS and immediately fixed using 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) + 4% sucrose + Triton-X in PBS (PBST) for 30 mins at RT with rotation. Samples were then rinsed 3X with PBS and blocked for 2 h in 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) + 0.5% normal goat serum (NGS) or without NGS if depending on secondary used in PBST at RT with rotation. Samples were incubated in primary antibody at 4 °C O/N with rotation, washed 3 × 20 mins in PBST at RT with rotation, and then incubated with secondary antibody for 4 h at RT with rotation. Antibodies were diluted in 0.2% BSA with or without 0.1% NGS depending on secondary in PBST. Primary antibodies used were: rabbit anti-GFP (1:2000) (Abcam 290), FitC conjugated goat anti-GFP (1:500) (Abcam 6662), rat anti-mCD8 (1:100) (eBioscience), mouse anti-Brp (1:100) (DHSB nc82), rabbit anti-Shrub (1:1000)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, and rabbit anti-Rab5 (1:200), a gift from Fengwei Yu<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Secondary antibodies used were: AlexaFluor 568 goat anti-mouse, AlexaFluor 488 goat anti-rabbit and -rat, AlexaFluor 488 donkey anti-rat and -goat, and AlexaFluor 568 donkey anti-rabbit (all 1:250). Labeled brains were mounted in Flouromount (EMS 17984-25) with posterior up. Images were acquired on a Zeiss LSM 510 Meta confocal microscope using Plan Neofluar 40X oil immersion objectives with a numerical aperture of 1.3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec16">
<title>Electron microscopy</title>
<p id="Par35">Electron microscopy was done as previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, with slight variations. Dissected brains from staged animals were immediately fixed in 2.5% gluteraldehyde (GTA) in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate (SC) buffer (pH 7.4) O/N at 4 °C. Samples were then washed 3 × 20 mins with 0.1 M SC buffer at RT followed by a final wash in 0.1 M SC buffer O/N at 4 °C. Samples were fixed with 1% osmium tetroxide in 0.1 M SC buffer in glass tubes for 1 hr at RT, and then washed 3 × 20 mins with 0.1 m SC buffer. Samples were treated with 2% uranyl acetate (UA) in ddH<sub>2</sub>0 for 2 hr at RT covered, followed by 3 × 20 min washes in ddH<sub>2</sub>0. Samples were then placed through an EtOH dehydration series (30, 50, 70 90, 95, 2 × 100%) for 10 min each at RT. Propylene oxide (PO) was used as a transitional solvent: 50/50 EtOH/PO, 2 × 100 PO for 10 min each, 75/50 PO/Epon-812 resin for 30 mins, 50/50 PO/Epon-812 for 1 hr, and 50/50 PO/Epon-812 O/N at RT. Fresh Epon-812 was then allowed to infiltrate tissue for 2 hr, 4 hr and O/N at RT. Flat block molds were half filled with Embed-812 resin and heated at 60 °C for 4 hr or until resin reached a tacky consistency. Samples were placed in blocks oriented anterior up and dorsal forward. Blocks were filled with resin and polymerized for 48 hr at 60 °C. Thick sections (500 nm) were made using a Leica Ultracut UCT microtome until the dorsal most region of the brain was reached. Thick sections were continued for another 40 μm. Thin sections (65 nm) were then taken and collected on formvar-coated slotted grids (Electron Microscopy Sciences) at 10 sections per grid. PN boutons were chosen at random from within each MB calyx. Only 1 section per grid was imaged, with at least 5 grids (~3 μm) between each grid examined. Images were acquired using a Philips CM10 transmission electron microscopy at 80 kV.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec17">
<title>Analysis statistics</title>
<p id="Par36">All measurements were done using ImageJ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. For area measurements (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2B,C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig7">7</xref>) images were processed with the despeckle tool and threshold signals then selected using the wand tool in ImageJ. Rab5 studies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>) were performed on single optical slices, with boutons selected at random and outlined with the free hand tool in ImageJ. All genotypes were run in parallel at the same time and under the same conditions for each replicate. All statistical analysis was performed using Prism (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). Data from two group comparisons were analyzed with a two-tailed unpaired t-test. Data from three or more comparisons were analyzed with one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with the Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunn’s multiple comparison test, comparing each mean to every other column. In figures, significant levels are shown as p &gt; 0.05 (not significant; N.S.), *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001 and ****p &lt; 0.0001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec18">
<title>Data availability</title>
<p id="Par37">All datasets generated and analyzed for the current study are available upon reasonable request from the corresponding author.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
<sec id="Sec19">
<p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2017_9103_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplemental Figure S1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p>
<bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-09103-6
</p>
</fn>
<fn>
<p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>We thank the <italic>Drosophila</italic> Bloomington Stock Center for supplying essential lines. We are particularly grateful to Fen-Biao Gao for providing us with key stocks and antibody for Shrub, and Fengwei Yu for kindly giving us the Rab5 antibody. We would like to acknowledge the Broadie lab for constant support in developing this work, and particularly Mary Lynn Dear, Caleb Doll and Tyler Kennedy for critical input on this manuscript. This work was entirely funded by the National Institutes of Health R01 MH084989 to K.B.</p>
</ack>
<notes notes-type="author-contribution">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p>D.J.V. performed all experiments and data analyses. K.B. designed and directed experiments. K.B. and D.J.V. jointly developed concepts and co-wrote the manuscript.</p>
</notes>
<notes notes-type="COI-statement">
<sec id="FPar1">
<title>Competing Interests</title>
<p id="Par38">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
</sec>
</notes>
<ref-list id="Bib1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CR1">
<label>1.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wiesel</surname>
<given-names>TN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hubel</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Effects of visual deprivation on morphology and physiology of cells in the cat’s lateral geniculate body</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurophysiol.
          <year>1963</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>978</fpage>
<lpage>993</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14084170</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR2">
<label>2.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Doll, C. A. &amp; Broadie, K. Impaired activity-dependent neural circuit assembly and refinement in autism spectrum disorder genetic models. <italic>Front</italic>. <italic>Cell</italic>. <italic>Neurosci</italic>. <bold>8</bold> (2014).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR3">
<label>3.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bagni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenough</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>From mRNP trafficking to spine dysmorphogenesis: the roots of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>376</fpage>
<lpage>387</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn1667</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15861180</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR4">
<label>4.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Doll</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent FMRP requirements in development of the neural circuitry of learning and memory</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Camb. Engl.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>142</volume>
<fpage>1346</fpage>
<lpage>1356</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR5">
<label>5.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gatto</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Temporal requirements of the fragile x mental retardation protein in modulating circadian clock circuit synaptic architecture</article-title>
<source/>Front. Neural Circuits
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/neuro.04.008.2009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19738924</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR6">
<label>6.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Variation of the CGG repeat at the fragile X site results in genetic instability: resolution of the Sherman paradox</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>1991</year>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>1047</fpage>
<lpage>1058</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(91)90283-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1760838</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR7">
<label>7.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Verkerk</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of a gene (FMR-1) containing a CGG repeat coincident with a breakpoint cluster region exhibiting length variation in fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>1991</year>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>905</fpage>
<lpage>914</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(91)90397-H</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1710175</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR8">
<label>8.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gatto</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>GABAergic circuit dysfunction in the Drosophila Fragile X syndrome model</article-title>
<source/>Neurobiol. Dis.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>142</fpage>
<lpage>159</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2014.01.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24423648</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR9">
<label>9.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reeve</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The Drosophila fragile X mental retardation protein controls actin dynamics by directly regulating profilin in the brain</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Biol. CB
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>1156</fpage>
<lpage>1163</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.05.050</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15964283</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR10">
<label>10.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tessier</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Drosophila fragile X mental retardation protein developmentally regulates activity-dependent axon pruning</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Camb. Engl.
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>1547</fpage>
<lpage>1557</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR11">
<label>11.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>YQ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Drosophila fragile X-related gene regulates the MAP1B homolog Futsch to control synaptic structure and function</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>591</fpage>
<lpage>603</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00589-X</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11733059</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR12">
<label>12.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Comery</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Abnormal dendritic spines in fragile X knockout mice: maturation and pruning deficits</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
          <year>1997</year>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>5401</fpage>
<lpage>5404</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.10.5401</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144249</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR13">
<label>13.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hinton</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wisniewski</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rudelli</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Analysis of neocortex in three males with the fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Med. Genet.
          <year>1991</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>289</fpage>
<lpage>294</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.1320410306</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1724112</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR14">
<label>14.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bolduc</surname>
<given-names>FV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tully</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Excess protein synthesis in Drosophila Fragile X mutants impairs long-term memory</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1143</fpage>
<lpage>1145</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2175</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18776892</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR15">
<label>15.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coffee</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> neuronal function of the fragile X mental retardation protein is regulated by phosphorylation</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>900</fpage>
<lpage>915</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddr527</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080836</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR16">
<label>16.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rushton</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fragile X mental retardation protein regulates trans-synaptic signaling in Drosophila</article-title>
<source/>Dis. Model. Mech.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>1400</fpage>
<lpage>1413</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.012229</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24046358</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR17">
<label>17.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>YQ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Woodruff</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The Drosophila fragile X gene negatively regulates neuronal elaboration and synaptic differentiation</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Biol. CB
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>1863</fpage>
<lpage>1870</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2004.09.085</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15498496</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR18">
<label>18.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dockendorff</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jongens</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dreyfuss</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of dFMR1, a Drosophila melanogaster homolog of the fragile X mental retardation protein</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Cell. Biol.
          <year>2000</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>8536</fpage>
<lpage>8547</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.20.22.8536-8547.2000</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11046149</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR19">
<label>19.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pharmacological reversal of synaptic plasticity deficits in the mouse model of Fragile X syndrome by group II mGluR antagonist or lithium treatment</article-title>
<source/>Brain Res.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>1380</volume>
<fpage>106</fpage>
<lpage>119</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2010.11.032</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21078304</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR20">
<label>20.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Franco, L. M., Okray, Z., Linneweber, G. A., Hassan, B. A. &amp; Yaksi, E. Reduced Lateral Inhibition Impairs Olfactory Computations and Behaviors in a Drosophila Model of Fragile X Syndrome. <italic>Curr</italic>. <italic>Biol</italic>. doi:10.1016/j.cub.2017.02.065.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR21">
<label>21.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tessier, C. R. &amp; Broadie, K. Molecular and Genetic Analysis of the Drosophila Model of Fragile X Syndrome. in <italic>Modeling Fragile X Syndrome</italic> (ed. Denman, R. B.) 119–156, doi:10.1007/978-3-642-21649-7_7 (Springer Berlin Heidelberg, 2012).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR22">
<label>22.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Babst</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katzmann</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Estepa-Sabal</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meerloo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emr</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Escrt-III: An endosome-associated heterooligomeric protein complex required for mvb sorting</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Cell
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>271</fpage>
<lpage>282</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1534-5807(02)00220-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12194857</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR23">
<label>23.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Katoh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The ALG-2-interacting Protein Alix Associates with CHMP4b, a Human Homologue of Yeast Snf7 That Is Involved in Multivesicular Body Sorting</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>278</volume>
<fpage>39104</fpage>
<lpage>39113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M301604200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12860994</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR24">
<label>24.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brenman</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jan</surname>
<given-names>YN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>F-B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The coiled-coil protein shrub controls neuronal morphogenesis in Drosophila</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Biol. CB
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>1006</fpage>
<lpage>1011</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2006.03.067</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713958</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR25">
<label>25.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Christ</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raiborg</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wenzel</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campsteijn</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stenmark</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cellular Functions and Molecular Mechanisms of the ESCRT Membrane-Scission Machinery</article-title>
<source/>Trends Biochem. Sci.
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>42</fpage>
<lpage>56</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2016.08.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27669649</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR26">
<label>26.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Issman-Zecharya</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schuldiner</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The PI3K class III complex promotes axon pruning by downregulating a Ptc-derived signal via endosome-lysosomal degradation</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Cell
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>461</fpage>
<lpage>473</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2014.10.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25458013</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR27">
<label>27.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Loncle</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Agromayor</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martin-Serrano</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>An ESCRT module is required for neuron pruning</article-title>
<source/>Sci. Rep.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep08461</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25676218</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR28">
<label>28.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Endocytic pathways downregulate the L1-type cell adhesion molecule neuroglian to promote dendrite pruning in Drosophila</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Cell
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>463</fpage>
<lpage>478</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2014.06.014</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25158855</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR29">
<label>29.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Siller</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neural circuit architecture defects in a Drosophila model of Fragile X syndrome are alleviated by minocycline treatment and genetic removal of matrix metalloproteinase</article-title>
<source/>Dis. Model. Mech.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>673</fpage>
<lpage>685</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.008045</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21669931</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR30">
<label>30.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Babst</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A protein’s final ESCRT</article-title>
<source/>Traffic Cph. Den.
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>2</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0854.2004.00246.x</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR31">
<label>31.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Babst</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katzmann</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wendland</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emr</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Endosome-associated complex, ESCRT-II, recruits transport machinery for protein sorting at the multivesicular body</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Cell
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>289</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1534-5807(02)00219-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12194858</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR32">
<label>32.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Katzmann</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Babst</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emr</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ubiquitin-dependent sorting into the multivesicular body pathway requires the function of a conserved endosomal protein sorting complex, ESCRT-I</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>106</volume>
<fpage>145</fpage>
<lpage>155</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00434-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11511343</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR33">
<label>33.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hurley</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ESCRTs are everywhere</article-title>
<source/>EMBO J.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>2398</fpage>
<lpage>2407</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201592484</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26311197</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR34">
<label>34.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schöneberg, J., Lee, I.-H., Iwasa, J. H. &amp; Hurley, J. H. Reverse-topology membrane scission by the ESCRT proteins. <italic>Nat</italic>. <italic>Rev</italic>. <italic>Mol</italic>. <italic>Cell Biol</italic>. advance online publication (2016).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR35">
<label>35.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chiaruttini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Relaxation of Loaded ESCRT-III Spiral Springs Drives Membrane Deformation</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>163</volume>
<fpage>866</fpage>
<lpage>879</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.10.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26522593</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR36">
<label>36.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">McMillan, B. J. <italic>et al</italic>. Electrostatic Interactions between Elongated Monomers Drive Filamentation of Drosophila Shrub, a Metazoan ESCRT-III Protein. <italic>Cell Rep</italic>., doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2016.06.093.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR37">
<label>37.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Q-T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural analysis and modeling reveals new mechanisms governing ESCRT-III spiral filament assembly</article-title>
<source/>J Cell Biol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>206</volume>
<fpage>763</fpage>
<lpage>777</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201403108</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25202029</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR38">
<label>38.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tang, S. <italic>et al</italic>. Structural basis for activation, assembly and membrane binding of ESCRT-III Snf7 filaments. <italic>eLife</italic><bold>4</bold> (2015).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR39">
<label>39.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bajorek</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis for ESCRT-III protein autoinhibition</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>754</fpage>
<lpage>762</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.1621</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525971</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR40">
<label>40.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saksena</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wahlman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Teis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emr</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Functional Reconstitution of ESCRT-III Assembly and Disassembly</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>136</volume>
<fpage>97</fpage>
<lpage>109</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.11.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19135892</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR41">
<label>41.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Teis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saksena</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emr</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ordered assembly of the ESCRT-III complex on endosomes is required to sequester cargo during MVB formation</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Cell
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>578</fpage>
<lpage>589</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2008.08.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854142</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR42">
<label>42.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aoyama</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Loss- and gain-of-function analyses of vacuolar protein sorting 2 in Notch signaling of Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>
<source/>Genes Genet. Syst.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>57</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1266/ggs.88.45</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23676709</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR43">
<label>43.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arlt</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Perz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ungermann</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>An Overexpression Screen in Saccharomyces cerevisiae Identifies Novel Genes that Affect Endocytic Protein Trafficking</article-title>
<source/>Traffic
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>1592</fpage>
<lpage>1603</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0854.2011.01252.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21777356</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR44">
<label>44.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scheffer</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanism of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-triggered ESCRT assembly and regulation of cell membrane repair</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms6646</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534348</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR45">
<label>45.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cvetkovska</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hibbert</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emran</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Overexpression of Down syndrome cell adhesion molecule impairs precise synaptic targeting</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>677</fpage>
<lpage>682</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3396</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23666178</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR46">
<label>46.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jefferis</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marin</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stocker</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Target neuron prespecification in the olfactory map of Drosophila</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>414</volume>
<fpage>204</fpage>
<lpage>208</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35102574</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719930</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR47">
<label>47.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development of the Drosophila mushroom bodies: sequential generation of three distinct types of neurons from a neuroblast</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Camb. Engl.
          <year>1999</year>
<volume>126</volume>
<fpage>4065</fpage>
<lpage>4076</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR48">
<label>48.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J-A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beigneux</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>F-B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ESCRT-III dysfunction causes autophagosome accumulation and neurodegeneration</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Biol. CB
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>1561</fpage>
<lpage>1567</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2007.07.029</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17683935</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR49">
<label>49.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morawa</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lgd regulates the activity of the BMP/Dpp signalling pathway during Drosophila oogenesis</article-title>
<source/>Development
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>142</volume>
<fpage>1325</fpage>
<lpage>1335</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.112961</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25804739</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR50">
<label>50.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Troost</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grawe</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martinez-Arias</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activation of Notch in lgd mutant cells requires the fusion of late endosomes with the lysosome</article-title>
<source/>J Cell Sci
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>126</volume>
<fpage>645</fpage>
<lpage>656</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.116590</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23178945</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR51">
<label>51.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hori</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kirchhausen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Artavanis-Tsakonas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Synergy between the ESCRT-III complex and Deltex defines a ligand-independent Notch signal</article-title>
<source/>J. Cell Biol.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>195</volume>
<fpage>1005</fpage>
<lpage>1015</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201104146</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22162134</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR52">
<label>52.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Troost</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jaeckel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ohlenhard</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The tumour suppressor Lethal (2) giant discs is required for the function of the ESCRT-III component Shrub/CHMP4</article-title>
<source/>J Cell Sci
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>125</volume>
<fpage>763</fpage>
<lpage>776</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.097261</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22389409</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR53">
<label>53.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Purified recombinant Fmrp exhibits selective RNA binding as an intrinsic property of the fragile X mental retardation protein</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <year>1998</year>
<volume>273</volume>
<fpage>15521</fpage>
<lpage>15527</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.25.15521</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9624140</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR54">
<label>54.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Darnell</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fragile X mental retardation protein targets G quartet mRNAs important for neuronal function</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>489</fpage>
<lpage>499</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00566-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719189</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR55">
<label>55.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zang</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Mouse Model of the Human Fragile X Syndrome I304N Mutation</article-title>
<source/>PLOS Genet
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000758</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20011099</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR56">
<label>56.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Darnell</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>FMRP stalls ribosomal translocation on mRNAs linked to synaptic function and autism</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>146</volume>
<fpage>247</fpage>
<lpage>261</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.06.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21784246</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR57">
<label>57.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Narayanan</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>FMRP Phosphorylation Reveals an Immediate-Early Signaling Pathway Triggered by Group I mGluR and Mediated by PP2A</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>14349</fpage>
<lpage>14357</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2969-07.2007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18160642</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR58">
<label>58.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gatto</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fragile X mental retardation protein is required for programmed cell death and clearance of developmentally-transient peptidergic neurons</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Biol.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>356</volume>
<fpage>291</fpage>
<lpage>307</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2011.05.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21596027</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR59">
<label>59.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Doll</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neuron class-specific requirements for Fragile X Mental Retardation Protein in critical period development of calcium signaling in learning and memory circuitry</article-title>
<source/>Neurobiol. Dis.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>76</fpage>
<lpage>87</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2016.02.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26851502</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR60">
<label>60.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jenett</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A GAL4-driver line resource for Drosophila neurobiology</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>991</fpage>
<lpage>1001</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2012.09.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063364</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR61">
<label>61.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Woodruff</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Broadie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanistic relationships between Drosophila fragile X mental retardation protein and metabotropic glutamate receptor A signaling</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Cell. Neurosci.
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>747</fpage>
<lpage>760</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2008.01.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18280750</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR62">
<label>62.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scharkowski</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frotscher</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lutz</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Korte</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Michaelsen-Preusse</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered Connectivity and Synapse Maturation of the Hippocampal Mossy Fiber Pathway in a Mouse Model of the Fragile X Syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Cereb. Cortex N. Y. N 1991
          <year>2017</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR63">
<label>63.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Loerwald</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huber</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gibson</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Postsynaptic FMRP promotes the pruning of cell-to-cell connections among pyramidal neurons in the L5A neocortical network</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>3413</fpage>
<lpage>3418</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2921-13.2014</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR64">
<label>64.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jefferis</surname>
<given-names>GSXE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marin</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Watts</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development of neuronal connectivity in Drosophila antennal lobes and mushroom bodies</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>80</fpage>
<lpage>86</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-4388(02)00293-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861168</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR65">
<label>65.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Winkle</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gupton</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Membrane Trafficking in Neuronal Development: Ins and Outs of Neural Connectivity</article-title>
<source/>Int. Rev. Cell Mol. Biol.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>322</volume>
<fpage>247</fpage>
<lpage>280</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.ircmb.2015.10.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26940520</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR66">
<label>66.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kanamori</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yoshino</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yasunaga</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dairyo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Local endocytosis triggers dendritic thinning and pruning in Drosophila sensory neurons</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms7515</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25761586</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR67">
<label>67.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sakuma</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Drosophila Strip serves as a platform for early endosome organization during axon elongation</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms6180</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25312435</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR68">
<label>68.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Control of dendritic development by the Drosophila fragile X-related gene involves the small GTPase Rac1</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Camb. Engl.
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>130</volume>
<fpage>5543</fpage>
<lpage>5552</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR69">
<label>69.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Drosophila model of Fragile X syndrome exhibits defects in phagocytosis by innate immune cells</article-title>
<source/>J. Cell Biol.
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>216</volume>
<fpage>595</fpage>
<lpage>605</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201607093</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28223318</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR70">
<label>70.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vonhoff</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keshishian</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title><italic>In Vivo</italic> Calcium Signaling during Synaptic Refinement at the Drosophila Neuromuscular Junction</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci.
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>5511</fpage>
<lpage>5526</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2922-16.2017</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR71">
<label>71.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>W-S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Astrocytes mediate synapse elimination through MEGF10 and MERTK pathways</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>504</volume>
<fpage>394</fpage>
<lpage>400</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12776</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24270812</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR72">
<label>72.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Paolicelli</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic Pruning by Microglia Is Necessary for Normal Brain Development</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>333</volume>
<fpage>1456</fpage>
<lpage>1458</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1202529</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21778362</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR73">
<label>73.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tasdemir-Yilmaz</surname>
<given-names>OE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Astrocytes engage unique molecular programs to engulf pruned neuronal debris from distinct subsets of neurons</article-title>
<source/>Genes Dev.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>20</fpage>
<lpage>33</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.229518.113</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24361692</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR74">
<label>74.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Deficient neuron-microglia signaling results in impaired functional brain connectivity and social behavior</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>400</fpage>
<lpage>406</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3641</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487234</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR75">
<label>75.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rasband</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eliceiri</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Methods
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>671</fpage>
<lpage>675</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2089</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>