<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8806785</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4226</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Glia</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Glia</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Glia</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0894-1491</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1098-1136</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26469940</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5580048</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.22925</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS898577</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mutation of Ataxia–Telangiectasia Mutated is Associated with Dysfunctional Glutathione Homeostasis in Cerebellar Astroglia</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>Andrew</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bushman</surname>
<given-names>Jared</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Munger</surname>
<given-names>Joshua</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Noble</surname>
<given-names>Mark</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pröoschel</surname>
<given-names>Christoph</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mayer-Pröoschel</surname>
<given-names>Margot</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Biomedical Genetics, University of Rochester, Rochester, New York, 14642</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, University of Rochester, Rochester, New York, 14642</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>School of Pharmacy Health Sciences Center, University of Wyoming, Laramie, Wyoming, 82071</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics, University of Rochester, Rochester, New York, 14642</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Address correspondence to: Margot Mayer-Pröoschel; University of Rochester, Department of Biomedical Genetics, 601 Elwood Avenue, Box 633, Rochester, NY 14642. <email>Margot_Mayer-proschel@urmc.rochester.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="equal" id="FN2">
<p>Andrew Campbell and Jared Bushman contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>10</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>15</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>64</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>227</fpage>
<lpage>239</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/glia.22925-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Astroglial dysfunction plays an important role in neurodegenerative diseases otherwise attributed to neuronal loss of function. Here we focus on the role of astroglia in ataxia–telangiectasia (A–T), a disease caused by mutations in the ataxia–telangiectasia mutated (<italic>ATM</italic>) gene. A hallmark of A–T pathology is progressive loss of cerebellar neurons, but the mechanisms that impact neuronal survival are unclear. We now provide a possible mechanism by which A–T astroglia affect the survival of cerebellar neurons. As astroglial functions are difficult to study in an <italic>in vivo</italic> setting, particularly in the cerebellum where these cells are intertwined with the far more numerous neurons, we conducted <italic>in vitro</italic> coculture experiments that allow for the generation and pharmacological manipulation of purified cell populations. Our analyses revealed that cerebellar astroglia isolated from Atm mutant mice show decreased expression of the cystine/glutamate exchanger subunit xCT, glutathione (GSH) reductase, and glutathione-S-transferase. We also found decreased levels of intercellular and secreted GSH in A–T astroglia. Metabolic labeling of L-cystine, the major precursor for GSH, revealed that a key component of the defect in A–T astroglia is an impaired ability to import this rate-limiting precursor for the production of GSH. This impairment resulted in suboptimal extracellular GSH supply, which in turn impaired survival of cerebellar neurons. We show that by circumventing the xCT-dependent import of L-cystine through addition of <italic>N</italic>-acetyl-L-cysteine (NAC) as an alternative cysteine source, we were able to restore GSH levels in A–T mutant astroglia providing a possible future avenue for targeted therapeutic intervention.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>ataxia–telangiectasia</kwd>
<kwd>astroglia</kwd>
<kwd>xCT</kwd>
<kwd>glutathione</kwd>
<kwd>neuronal survival</kwd>
<kwd>cerebellum</kwd>
<kwd>ataxia–telangiectasia mutated</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>