<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8800478</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">1990</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Brain Behav Immun</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Brain Behav. Immun.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Brain, behavior, and immunity</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0889-1591</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1090-2139</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27519153</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5611850</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2016.08.005</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS906606</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Maternal high fat diet exposure is associated with increased hepcidin levels, decreased myelination, and neurobehavioral changes in male offspring</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Graf</surname>
<given-names>Amanda E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lallier</surname>
<given-names>Scott W.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Waidyaratne</surname>
<given-names>Gavisha</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>Michael D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tipple</surname>
<given-names>Trent E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hester</surname>
<given-names>Mark E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trask</surname>
<given-names>Aaron J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>Lynette K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>a</label>Centers for Perinatal Research, The Research Institute at Nationwide Children’s Hospital, United States</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>b</label>Department of Pediatrics, The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH, United States</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>c</label>Cardiovascular Research, The Research Institute at Nationwide Children’s Hospital, Columbus, OH, United States</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>d</label>Division of Neonatology, Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, United States</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author at:. Center for Perinatal Research, The Research Institute at Nationwide Children’s Hospital, 575 Children’s Cross Road, Columbus, OH 43215, United States. <email>Lynette.Rogers@Nationwidechildrens.org</email> (L.K. Rogers)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>
<bold>Conflict of interest statement</bold>
</p>
<p>There are no conflicts of interest, financial or otherwise, to disclose by the authors.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>19</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>09</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>25</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>369</fpage>
<lpage>378</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.bbi.2016.08.005-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Maternal obesity induces chronic inflammatory responses that impact the fetus/neonate during the perinatal period. Inflammation, iron regulation, and myelination are closely interconnected and disruptions in these processes may have deleterious effects on neurodevelopment. Hepcidin levels are increased in response to inflammation causing subsequent decreases in ferroportin and available iron needed for myelination. Our current studies were designed to test the hypotheses that: 1) maternal high fat diet (HFD) prior to and during pregnancy is sufficient to induce inflammation and alter iron regulation in the brain of the offspring, and 2) HFD exposure is associated with altered myelination and neurobehavioral deficits in the offspring. Our data revealed modest increases in inflammatory cytokines in the serum of dams fed HFD prior to pregnancy compared to dams fed a control diet (CD). Early increases in IL-5 and decreases in IL-10 were observed in serum at PN7 while IL-5 remained elevated at PN21 in the HFDexposed pups. At PN0, most cytokine levels in whole brain homogenates were higher in the pups born to HFD-fed dams but were not different or were lower than in pups born to CD-fed dams at PN21. Conversely, the inflammation mediated transcription factor Nurr77 remained elevated at PN21. At birth, brain hepcidin, ferroportin, and <sc>l</sc>-ferritin levels were elevated in pups born to HFD-fed dams compared to pups born to CD-fed dams. Hepcidin levels remained elevated at PN7 and PN21 while ferroportin and <sc>l</sc>-ferritin levels were lower at PN7 and were not different at PN21. Decreases in myelination in the medial cortex were observed in male but not in female pups born to maternal HFD-fed dams at PN21. These structural changes correlated with changes in behavior (novel object recognition) in at 4 months in males only. Our data indicate that maternal obesity (HFD) results in disruption of iron regulation in the brains of the offspring with structural and neurobehavioral deficits in males.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Maternal obesity</kwd>
<kwd>High fat diet</kwd>
<kwd>Inflammation</kwd>
<kwd>Hepcidin</kwd>
<kwd>Neurodevelopment</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>