<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8411723</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">3864</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genet Epidemiol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genet. Epidemiol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Genetic epidemiology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0741-0395</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1098-2272</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28726280</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5643247</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gepi.22060</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS903627</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An efficient study design to test parent-of-origin effects in family trios</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Xiaobo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Gao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Rui</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Biostatistics and Epidemiology, Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Neurosurgery, School of Medicine, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1"><bold>Correspondence</bold>. Rui Feng, Department of Biostatistics and Epidemiology, Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, 209 Blockley Hall, 423 Guardian Drive, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA. <email>ruifeng@mail.med.upenn.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>11</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>20</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>587</fpage>
<lpage>598</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/gepi.22060-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Increasing evidence has shown that genes may cause prenatal, neonatal, and pediatric diseases depending on their parental origins. Statistical models that incorporate parent-of-origin effects (POEs) can improve the power of detecting disease-associated genes and help explain the missing heritability of diseases. In many studies, children have been sequenced for genome-wide association testing. But it may become unaffordable to sequence their parents and evaluate POEs. Motivated by the reality, we proposed a budget-friendly study design of sequencing children and only genotyping their parents through single nucleotide polymorphism array. We developed a powerful likelihood-based method, which takes into account both sequence reads and linkage disequilibrium to infer the parental origins of children’s alleles and estimate their POEs on the outcome. We evaluated the performance of our proposed method and compared it with an existing method using only genotypes, through extensive simulations. Our method showed higher power than the genotype-based method. When either the mean read depth or the pair-end length was reasonably large, our method achieved ideal power. When single parents’ genotypes were unavailable or parental genotypes at the testing locus were not typed, both methods lost power compared with when complete data were available; but the power loss from our method was smaller than the genotype-based method. We also extended our method to accommodate mixed genotype, low-, and high-coverage sequence data from children and their parents. At presence of sequence errors, low-coverage parental sequence data may lead to lower power than parental genotype data.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>family study design</kwd>
<kwd>haplotype</kwd>
<kwd>imprinting</kwd>
<kwd>next generation sequence</kwd>
<kwd>pediatric disease</kwd>
<kwd>statistical method</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>