<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9607835</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">20545</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Molecular psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1359-4184</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1476-5578</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27725662</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5687809</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2016.157</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS918730</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Developmental plasticity shapes synaptic phenotypes of autism-associated neuroligin-3 mutations in the calyx of Held</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Seigneur</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gokce</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Südhof</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, CA, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, CA, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Developmental Neurobiology, St Jude Children's Research Hospital, Memphis, TN, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: Dr B Zhang, Department of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, Stanford University School of Medicine, Lorry Lokey SIM1 Building 07-535 265 Campus Drive, Room G1015, Stanford, CA 94305, USA. <email>zbo@stanford.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p><bold>Conflict of Interest</bold>: The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>9</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>15</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>1483</fpage>
<lpage>1491</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/mp.2016.157-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Neuroligins are postsynaptic cell-adhesion molecules that bind to presynaptic neurexins. Mutations in neuroligin-3 predispose to autism, but how such mutations affect synaptic function remains incompletely understood. Here we systematically examined the effect of three autism-associated mutations, the neuroligin-3 knockout, the R451C knockin, and the R704C knockin, on synaptic transmission in the calyx of Held, a central synapse ideally suited for high-resolution analyses of synaptic transmission. Surprisingly, germline knockout of neuroligin-3 did not alter synaptic transmission, whereas the neuroligin-3 R451C and R704C knockins decreased and increased, respectively, synaptic transmission. These puzzling results prompted us to ask whether neuroligin-3 mutant phenotypes may be reshaped by developmental plasticity. Indeed, conditional knockout of neuroligin-3 during late development produced a marked synaptic phenotype, whereas conditional knockout of neuroligin-3 during early development caused no detectable effect, mimicking the germline knockout. In canvassing potentially redundant candidate genes, we identified developmentally early expression of another synaptic neurexin ligand, cerebellin-1. Strikingly, developmentally early conditional knockout of cerebellin-1 only modestly impaired synaptic transmission, whereas in contrast to the individual single knockouts, developmentally early conditional double knockout of both cerebellin-1 and neuroligin-3 severely decreased synaptic transmission. Our data suggest an unanticipated mechanism of developmental compensation whereby cerebellin-1 and neuroligin-3 functionally occlude each other during development of calyx synapses. Thus, although acute manipulations more likely reveal basic gene functions, developmental plasticity can be a major factor in shaping the overall phenotypes of genetic neuropsychiatric disorders.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>