<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101235742</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32212</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Med. Genet. B Neuropsychiatr. Genet.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>American journal of medical genetics. Part B, Neuropsychiatric genetics : the official publication of the International Society of Psychiatric Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4841</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-485X</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28512748</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5690554</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.32535</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS852332</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Genetic Influences on ADHD Symptom Dimensions: Examination of <italic>A Priori</italic> Candidates, Gene-based Tests, Genome-wide Variation, and SNP Heritability</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bidwell</surname>
<given-names>L. Cinnamon</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>Joshua C.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weafer</surname>
<given-names>Jessica</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Palmer</surname>
<given-names>Abraham</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Wit</surname>
<given-names>Harriet</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>MacKillop</surname>
<given-names>James</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Institute of Cognitive Science, University of Colorado at Boulder, Boulder, CO 80309, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Psychology, University of Georgia Athens, GA 30602, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Psychiatry and Human Behavior, Brown University, Providence, RI 02912</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Neuroscience, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL 60637, USA</aff>
<aff id="A5">
<label>5</label>Department of Psychiatry, University of California, San Diego, San Diego, CA 92093, USA</aff>
<aff id="A6">
<label>6</label>Institute for Genomic Medicine, University of California San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92103, USA</aff>
<aff id="A7">
<label>7</label>Peter Boris Centre for Addictions Research, McMaster University/St. Joseph’s Healthcare Hamilton, Hamilton, ON L8P 3R2, Canada</aff>
<aff id="A8">
<label>8</label>Homewood Research Institute, Homewood Health Centre, Guelph, ON N1E 4J3 Canada</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="equal" id="FN1">
<label>*</label>
<p>Dr. Bidwell and Mr. Gray contributed equally to this manuscript.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p><underline>Disclosures:</underline> The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>16</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>174</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>458</fpage>
<lpage>466</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/ajmg.b.32535-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Although the heritability of ADHD is estimated to be high, identifying specific genetic markers remains challenging. Most studies to date have examined the genetic basis of ADHD by employing dichotomous diagnostic phenotypes, but, as ADHD symptoms tend to be phenotypically dimensional, an alternative and potentially informative approach is to examine continuous indices of inattention and hyperactivity-impulsivity symptoms. The current study aimed to identify genetic effects on dimensionally-focused adult ADHD-related phenotypes in 990 individuals of European ancestry with intentionally low levels of substance misuse to avoid confounding. The study used four complementary approaches: 1) analysis of <italic>a priori</italic> candidate loci identified in prior meta-analytic work; 2) gene-based analysis; 3) hypothesis-free genome-wide association testing; and 4) single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) heritability via genomic-relatedness-matrix restricted maximum likelihood analysis (GREML). The GREML analysis included a bivariate model to test whether the ADHD symptom dimensions index the same genetic liability. The results revealed significant differential associations between two <italic>a priori</italic> loci and ADHD phenotypes, rs6296 in <italic>HTR1B</italic> with inattention and rs3746544 in <italic>SNAP-25</italic> with hyperactivity-impulsivity. No significant gene-based or genome-wide associations were detected, but SNP heritability revealed that a large portion of genetic variance was accounted for by common SNPs (44%, 55%, and 59% for inattention, hyperactivity-impulsivity, and total ADHD, respectively) and substantial shared genetic variance across inattention and hyperactivity-impulsivity (86%). These findings reveal both unique and common patterns of genetic influences across dimensional ADHD-related phenotypes. More broadly, these findings reveal the value in using multiple methods to understand the genetic etiology of ADHD.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>ADHD</kwd>
<kwd>Inattention</kwd>
<kwd>Hyperactivity</kwd>
<kwd>Impulsivity</kwd>
<kwd>Genetics</kwd>
<kwd>Heritability</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>