<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">JAMA Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>JAMA Psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2168-622X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2168-6238</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28746715</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5710474</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.1986</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">yoi170050</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group specific-use="electronic" subj-group-type="category">
<subject>Research</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group specific-use="print" subj-group-type="domain">
<subject>Research</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Investigation</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="online-first">
<subject>Online First</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Identification of Genetic Loci Jointly Influencing Schizophrenia Risk and the Cognitive Traits of Verbal-Numerical Reasoning, Reaction Time, and General Cognitive Function</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Genetic Loci Influencing Schizophrenia Risk and Cognitive Traits</alt-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Genetic Loci Influencing Schizophrenia Risk and Cognitive Traits</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Smeland</surname>
<given-names>Olav B.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frei</surname>
<given-names>Oleksandr</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kauppi</surname>
<given-names>Karolina</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>W. David</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Wen</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Yunpeng</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krull</surname>
<given-names>Florian</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bettella</surname>
<given-names>Francesco</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eriksen</surname>
<given-names>Jon A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Witoelar</surname>
<given-names>Aree</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>Gail</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>Chun C.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff9">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>Wesley K.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff11">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>Max</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff12">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lencz</surname>
<given-names>Todd</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff13">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff14">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff15">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Chi-Hua</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ueland</surname>
<given-names>Torill</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff16">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jönsson</surname>
<given-names>Erik G.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff17">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Djurovic</surname>
<given-names>Srdjan</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff18">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff19">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deary</surname>
<given-names>Ian J.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dale</surname>
<given-names>Anders M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff20">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Andreassen</surname>
<given-names>Ole A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="yoi170050aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<on-behalf-of>for the NeuroCHARGE (Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology) Cognitive Working Group</on-behalf-of>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="yoi170050aff1"><label>1</label>Norwegian Centre for Mental Disorders Research, KG Jebsen Centre for Psychosis Research, Institute of Clinical Medicine, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff2"><label>2</label>Norwegian Centre for Mental Disorders Research, Division of Mental Health and Addiction, Oslo University Hospital, Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Neuroscience, University of California San Diego, La Jolla</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Radiology, University of California San Diego, La Jolla</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff5"><label>5</label>Center for Multimodal Imaging and Genetics, University of California San Diego, La Jolla</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Radiation Sciences, Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff7"><label>7</label>Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff9"><label>9</label>Department of Cognitive Science, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff10"><label>10</label>Department of Family Medicine and Public Health, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff11"><label>11</label>Institute of Biological Psychiatry, Roskilde, Denmark</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff12"><label>12</label>Institute of Mental Health, Singapore</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff13"><label>13</label>Division of Psychiatry Research, Zucker Hillside Hospital, Glen Oaks, New York</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff14"><label>14</label>Center for Psychiatric Neuroscience, Feinstein Institute for Medical Research, Manhasset, New York</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff15"><label>15</label>Department of Psychiatry, Hofstra Northwell School of Medicine, Hempstead, New York</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff16"><label>16</label>Department of Psychology, University of Oslo, Olso, Norway</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff17"><label>17</label>Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Centre for Psychiatric Research, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff18"><label>18</label>Department of Medical Genetics, Oslo University Hospital, Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff19"><label>19</label>NORMENT, KG Jebsen Centre for Psychosis Research, Department of Clinical Science, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway</aff>
<aff id="yoi170050aff20"><label>20</label>Department of Psychiatry, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla</aff>
<author-notes>
<title>Article Information</title>
<p content-type="byline-footnote" specific-use="print"><bold>Group Information:</bold> The NeuroCHARGE Cognitive Working Group members are listed at the end of this article.</p>
<corresp id="yoi170050cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Olav B. Smeland, MD, PhD, Division of Mental Health and Addiction, Oslo University Hospital, Kirkeveien 166, 0424 Oslo, Norway (<email xlink:href="o.b.smeland@medisin.uio.no">o.b.smeland@medisin.uio.no</email>).</corresp>
<p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> May 30, 2017.</p>
<p><bold>Correction:</bold> This article was corrected on August 16, 2017, for a typographical error in the Abstract.</p>
<p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published Online:</bold> July 26, 2017. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.1986</uri></p>
<p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Drs Smeland and Frei had full access to all the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
<p><italic>Study concept and design:</italic> Smeland, Kauppi, Dale, Andreassen.</p>
<p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p>
<p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Smeland.</p>
<p><italic>Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p>
<p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Smeland, Frei, Kauppi, Li, Wang, Krull, Eriksen, Witoelar, Fan, Thompson, Lencz, Dale.</p>
<p><italic>Obtained funding:</italic> Smeland, Wang, Thompson, Chen, Deary, Dale, Andreassen.</p>
<p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Li, Wang, Bettella, Lencz, Ueland, Djurovic, Deary, Dale, Andreassen.</p>
<p><italic>Study supervision:</italic> Smeland, Deary, Dale, Andreassen.</p>
<p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Andreassen reported receiving a speaker’s honorarium from Lundbeck. No other disclosures were reported.</p>
<p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was supported by grants R01GM104400, NS057198, and EB00790 from the <funding-source rid="sp1">National Institutes of Health</funding-source>; grant R01MH100351 from the <funding-source rid="sp2">National Institute of Mental Health</funding-source>; grant U24DA041123 from the <funding-source rid="sp3">National Institutes of Health</funding-source>, <funding-source rid="sp4">National Institute on Drug Abuse</funding-source>, and <funding-source rid="sp5">National Cancer Institute</funding-source>; grants 229129, 213837, 248778, 223273, and 249711 from the <funding-source rid="sp6">Research Council of Norway</funding-source>; grants 2016-064, 2017-004, and 2017-112 from the <funding-source rid="sp7">South-East Norway Regional Health Authority</funding-source>; grant SKGJ-2011-36 from <funding-source rid="sp8">KG Jebsen Stiftelsen</funding-source>; grant MR/K026992/1 from the UK <funding-source rid="sp9">Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council</funding-source> and <funding-source rid="sp10">Medical Research Council</funding-source>; and the <funding-source rid="sp11">Research Council of Norway</funding-source> through a FRIPRO Mobility Grant, contract No. 251134 (Dr. Wang). The FRIPRO Mobility grant scheme (FRICON) is co-funded by the <funding-source rid="sp12">European Union’s Seventh Framework Programme</funding-source> for research, technological development and demonstration under Marie Curie grant agreement No. 608695.</p>
<p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funding sources had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
<p content-type="study-group-members-end"><bold>Group Information:</bold> The NeuroCHARGE Cognitive Working Group was part of the collaboration responsible for this work. Its members are Gail Davies, PhD (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK; Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Nicola Armstrong, PhD (School of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Sydney, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Joshua C. Bis, PhD (Cardiovascular Health Research Unit, Department of Medicine, University of Washington, Seattle); Jan Bressler, PhD (Human Genetics Center, School of Public Health, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston); Vincent Chouraki, MD, PhD (Inserm-UMR744, Institut Pasteur de Lille, Unité d'Epidémiologie et de Santé Publique, Lille, France; Department of Neurology, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA); Sudheer Giddaluru, PhD (K.G. Jebsen Centre for Psychosis Research and the Norwegian Centre for Mental Disorders Research [NORMENT], Department of Clinical Science, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway; Dr Einar Martens Research Group for Biological Psychiatry, Center for Medical Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway); Edith Hofer, PhD (Department of Neurology, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria; Institute for Medical Informatics, Statistics and Documentation, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria); Carla A. Ibrahim-Verbaas, MD, PhD (Department of Neurology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Genetic Epidemiology Unit, Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands); Mirna Kirin, PhD (Centre for Population Health Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Jari Lahti, PhD (Institute of Behavioural Sciences, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland; Folkhälsan Research Centre, Helsinki, Finland); Sven J. van der Lee, MD (Genetic Epidemiology Unit, Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands); Stephanie Le Hellard, PhD (K.G. Jebsen Centre for Psychosis Research and the Norwegian Centre for Mental Disorders Research [NORMENT], Department of Clinical Science, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway; Dr Einar Martens Research Group for Biological Psychiatry, Center for Medical Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway); Tian Liu, PhD (Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany; Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics, Berlin, Germany); Riccardo E. Marioni, PhD (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK; Medical Genetics Section, University of Edinburgh Centre for Genomic and Experimental Medicine, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, UK; Queensland Brain Institute, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD, Australia); Christopher Oldmeadow, PhD (Hunter Medical Research Institute and Faculty of Health, University of Newcastle, Newcastle, NSW, Australia); Iris Postmus, PhD (Department of Gerontology and Geriatrics, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands); Albert V. Smith, PhD (Icelandic Heart Association, Kopavogur, Iceland; Faculty of Medicine, University of Iceland, Reykjavik, Iceland); Jennifer A. Smith, PhD (Department of Epidemiology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor); Anbupalam Thalamuthu, PhD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Russell Thomson, PhD (Menzies Research Institute, Hobart, Tasmania); Veronique Vitart, PhD (MRC Human Genetics Unit, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Jing Wang, PhD (Framingham Heart Study, Framingham, MA; Department of Biostatistics, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA); Lei Yu, PhD (Rush Alzheimer’s Disease Center, Rush University Medical Center, Chicago, IL); Lina Zgaga, PhD (Department of Public Health and Primary Care, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland; Andrija Stampar School of Public Health, Medical School, University of Zagreb, Zagreb, Croatia); Wei Zhao, PhD (Department of Epidemiology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor); Ruth Boxall, MSc (Medical Genetics Section, University of Edinburgh Centre for Genomic and Experimental Medicine, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, UK); Sarah E. Harris, PhD (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK; Medical Genetics Section, University of Edinburgh Centre for Genomic and Experimental Medicine, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, UK); W. David Hill, PhD (Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); David C. Liewald, BSc (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Michelle Luciano, PhD (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK; Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Hieab H. Adams, MSc (Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands); David Ames, MD (National Ageing Research Institute, Royal Melbourne Hospital, Melbourne, VIC, Australia; Academic Unit for Psychiatry of Old Age, St George’s Hospital, University of Melbourne, Kew, Australia); Najaf Amin, PhD (Genetic Epidemiology Unit, Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands); Philippe Amouyel, MD, PhD (Inserm-UMR744, Institut Pasteur de Lille, Unité d'Epidémiologie et de Santé Publique, Lille, France); Amelia A. Assareh, PhD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Rhoda Au, PhD (Department of Neurology, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA; Framingham Heart Study, Framingham, MA); James T. Becker, PhD (Department of Neurology, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA; Department of Psychiatry, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA; Department of Psychology, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA); Alexa Beiser, PhD (Department of Neurology, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA; Framingham Heart Study, Framingham, MA; Department of Biostatistics, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA); Claudine Berr, MD, PhD (Inserm, U106, Montpellier, France; Université Montpellier I, Montpellier, France); Lars Bertram, MD (Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics, Berlin, Germany; Faculty of Medicine, School of Public Health, Imperial College, London, UK); Eric Boerwinkle, PhD (Human Genetics Center, School of Public Health, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston; Brown Foundation Institute of Molecular Medicine for the Prevention of Human Diseases, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston; Human Genome Sequencing Center, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX); Brendan M. Buckley, PhD (Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, University College Cork, Cork, Ireland); Harry Campbell, MD (Centre for Population Health Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Janie Corley, PhD (Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Philip L. De Jager, MD, PhD (Program in Translational NeuroPsychiatric Genomics, Department of Neurology, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Boston, MA; Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA; Program in Medical and Population Genetics, Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA); Carole Dufouil, PhD (Inserm U708, Neuroepidemiology, Paris, France; Inserm U897, Université Bordeaux Segalen, Bordeaux, France); Johan G. Eriksson, MD, PhD (Folkhälsan Research Centre, Helsinki, Finland; National Institute for Health and Welfare, Helsinki, Finland; Department of General Practice and Primary Health Care, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland; Unit of General Practice, Helsinki University Central Hospital, Helsinki, Finland); Thomas Espeseth, PhD (K.G. Jebsen Centre for Psychosis Research, Norwegian Centre For Mental Disorders Research [NORMENT], Division of Mental Health and Addiction, Oslo University Hospital and Institute of Clinical Medicine, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway; Department of Psychology, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway); Jessica D. Faul, PhD (Survey Research Center, Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor); Ian Ford, PhD (Robertson Center for Biostatistics, Glasgow, UK); Generation Scotland (Generation Scotland, University of Edinburgh Centre for Genomic and Experimental Medicine, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, UK); Rebecca F. Gottesman, MD, PhD (Department of Neurology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD); Michael E. Griswold, PhD (Center of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, University of Mississippi Medical Center, Jackson); Vilmunder Gudnason, MD, PhD (Icelandic Heart Association, Kopavogur, Iceland; Faculty of Medicine, University of Iceland, Reykjavik, Iceland); Tamara B. Harris, MD (Intramural Research Program National Institutes on Aging, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD); Gerardo Heiss, MD, PhD (Department of Epidemiology, University of North Carolina Gillings School of Global Public Health, Chapel Hill); Albert Hofman, MD, PhD (Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands); Elizabeth G. Holliday, PhD (Hunter Medical Research Institute and Faculty of Health, University of Newcastle, Newcastle, NSW, Australia); Jennifer Huffman, PhD (MRC Human Genetics Unit, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Sharon L. R. Kardia, PhD (Department of Epidemiology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor); Nicole Kochan, PhD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Neuropsychiatric Institute, Prince of Wales Hospital, Sydney, NSW, Australia); David S. Knopman, MD (Department of Neurology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN); John B. Kwok, PhD (Neuroscience Research Australia, Randwick, NSW, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Jean-Charles Lambert, PhD (Inserm-UMR744, Institut Pasteur de Lille, Unité d'Epidémiologie et de Santé Publique, Lille, France); Teresa Lee, PhD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Neuropsychiatric Institute, Prince of Wales Hospital, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Guo Li, MS (Cardiovascular Health Research Unit, Department of Medicine, University of Washington, Seattle); Shu-Chen Li, PhD (Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany; Technische Universität Dresden, Dresden, Germany); Marisa Loitfelder, PhD (Department of Neurology, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria); Oscar L. Lopez, MD (Department of Neurology, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA); Astri J. Lundervold, PhD (Department of Biological and Medical Psychology, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway; Kavli Research Centre for Aging and Dementia, Haraldsplass Deaconess Hospital, Bergen, Norway; K.G. Jebsen Centre for Research on Neuropsychiatric Disorders, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway); Anders Lundqvist, PhD (Umeå Center for Functional Brain Imaging [UFBI], Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden); Karen A. Mather, PhD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Saira S. Mirza, MD (Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands); Lars Nyberg, PhD (Umeå Center for Functional Brain Imaging [UFBI], Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden; Department of Radiation Sciences, Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden; Department of Integrative Medical Biology, Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden); Ben A. Oostra, PhD (Genetic Epidemiology Unit, Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands); Aarno Palotie, MD, PhD (Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Cambridge, UK; Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland [FIMM], University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland; Department of Medical Genetics, University of Helsinki and University Central Hospital, Helsinki, Finland); Goran Papenberg, PhD (Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany; Karolinska Institutet, Aging Research Center, Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden); Allison Pattie, BSc (Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Katja Petrovic, MSc (Department of Neurology, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria); Ozren Polasek, MD, PhD (Faculty of Medicine, Department of Public Health, University of Split, Split, Croatia); Bruce M. Psaty, MD, PhD (Cardiovascular Health Research Unit, Department of Medicine, University of Washington, Seattle; Deparment of Epidemiology, University of Washington, Seattle; Deparment of Health Services, University of Washington, Seattle; Group Health Research Unit, Group Health Cooperative, Seattle, WA); Paul Redmond, MSc (Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Simone Reppermund, PhD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Jerome I. Rotter, MD (Institute for Translational Genomics and Population Sciences, Los Angeles BioMedical Research Institute, Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, Los Angeles, CA; Division of Genetic Outcomes, Department of Pediatrics, Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, Los Angeles, CA); Helena Schmidt, MD, PhD (Department of Neurology, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria; Centre for Molecular Medicine, Institute of Molecular Biology and Biochemistry, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria); Maaike Schuur, PhD (Department of Neurology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Genetic Epidemiology Unit, Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands); Peter W. Schofield, MD (School of Medicine and Public Health, University of Newcastle, Newcastle, NSW, Australia); Rodney J. Scott, PhD (Hunter Medical Research Institute and Faculty of Health, University of Newcastle, Newcastle, NSW, Australia); Vidar M. Steen, PhD (K.G. Jebsen Centre for Psychosis Research and the Norwegian Centre for Mental Disorders Research [NORMENT], Department of Clinical Science, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway; Dr Einar Martens Research Group for Biological Psychiatry, Center for Medical Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway); David J. Stott, MD, PhD (Institute of Cardiovascular and Medical Sciences, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK); John C. van Swieten, MD, PhD (Department of Neurology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands); Kent D. Taylor, PhD (Institute for Translational Genomics and Population Sciences, Los Angeles BioMedical Research Institute, Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, Los Angeles, CA; Department of Pediatrics, Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, Los Angeles, CA); Julian Trollor, MD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Department of Developmental Disability Neuropsychiatry, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Stella Trompet, PhD (Department of Gerontology and Geriatrics, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, the Netherlands; Department of Cardiology, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, the Netherlands); Andre G. Uitterlinden, PhD (Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands; Department of Internal Medicine, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands); Galit Weinstein, PhD (Department of Neurology, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA; Framingham Heart Study, Framingham, MA); Elisabeth Widen, MD, PhD (Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland [FIMM], University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland); Beverly G. Windham, MD (Division of Geriatrics, Department of Medicine, University of Mississippi Medical Center, Jackson); J. W. Jukema, MD, PhD (Department of Cardiology, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, the Netherlands; Durrer Center for Cardiogenetic Research, Amsterdam, the Netherlands; Interuniversity Cardiology Institute of the Netherlands, Utrecht, the Netherlands); Alan F. Wright, PhD (MRC Human Genetics Unit, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Margaret J. Wright, PhD (Neuroimaging Genetics Group, QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute, Brisbane, QLD, Australia); Qiong Yang, PhD (Framingham Heart Study, Framingham, MA; Department of Biostatistics, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA); Helene Amieva, PhD (Inserm U897, Université Bordeaux Segalen, Bordeaux, France); John R. Attia, PhD (Hunter Medical Research Institute and Faculty of Health, University of Newcastle, Newcastle, NSW, Australia); David A. Bennett, MD (Rush Alzheimer's Disease Center, Rush University Medical Center, Chicago, IL); Henry Brodaty, MD, DSc (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Dementia Collaborative Research Centre, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Anton J. M. de Craen, PhD (Department of Gerontology and Geriatrics, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands); Caroline Hayward, PhD (MRC Human Genetics Unit, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); M. Arfan Ikram, MD, PhD (Department of Neurology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands; Department of Radiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands); Ulman Lindenberger, PhD (Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany); Lars-Goran Nilsson, PhD (ARC, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm and UFBI, Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden); David J. Porteous, PhD (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK; Medical Genetics Section, University of Edinburgh Centre for Genomic and Experimental Medicine, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, UK; Generation Scotland, University of Edinburgh Centre for Genomic and Experimental Medicine, Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, UK); Katri Räikkönen, PhD (Institute of Behavioural Sciences, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland); Ivar Reinvang, PhD (Department of Psychology, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway); Igor Rudan, MD, PhD (Centre for Population Health Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Perminder S. Sachdev, MD, PhD (Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Neuropsychiatric Institute, Prince of Wales Hospital, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Reinhold Schmidt, MD (Department of Neurology, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria); Peter R. Schofield, PhD (Neuroscience Research Australia, Sydney, NSW, Australia; Faculty of Medicine, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia); Velandai Srikanth, PhD (Menzies Research Institute, Hobart, Tasmania; Stroke and Ageing Research, Medicine, Southern Clinical School, Monash University, Melbourne, VIC, Australi); John M. Starr, PhD (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK; Alzheimer Scotland Dementia Research Centre, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Stephen T. Turner, MD (Division of Nephrology and Hypertension, Department of Internal Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN); David R. Weir, PhD (Survey Research Center, Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor); James F. Wilson, DPhil (Centre for Population Health Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK); Cornelia M. van Duijn, PhD (Genetic Epidemiology Unit, Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands; Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Ageing, Leiden, the Netherlands); Lenore J. Launer, PhD (Intramural Research Program National Institutes on Aging, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD); Annette L. Fitzpatrick, PhD (Deparment of Epidemiology, University of Washington, Seattle; Department of Global Health, University of Washington, Seattle); Sudha Seshadri, MD (Department of Neurology, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA; Framingham Heart Study, Framingham, MA); Thomas H. Mosley Jr, PhD (Division of Geriatrics, Department of Medicine, University of Mississippi Medical Center, Jackson); and Ian J. Deary, PhD (Centre for Cognitive Ageing and Cognitive Epidemiology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK; Department of Psychology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK).</p>
<p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> We thank all study participants and the researchers involved in the Schizophrenia Working Group of the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.med.unc.edu/pgc">http://www.med.unc.edu/pgc</ext-link>), Psychiatric Genomics Consortium, Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology, the Cognitive Genomics Consortium, and the UK Biobank for their contributions.</p>
</author-notes>
<pub-date iso-8601-date="2017-07-26T10:00" pub-type="epreprint">
<day>26</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date iso-8601-date="2017-10-04T10:00" pub-type="epub">
<day>4</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ecorrected">
<day>16</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>4</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 12 months and
						0 days and was based on the <pub-date
						pub-type="epub"/>. -->
<volume>74</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>1065</fpage>
<lpage>1075</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>10</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="final">
<day>26</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>30</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright 2017 American Medical Association. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamapsychiatry-74-1065.pdf">jamapsychiatry-74-1065.pdf</self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="roundpoint" xlink:href="http://app.jamanetwork.com/?doi=10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.1986"></self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?doi=10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.1986"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-1">
<title>Importance</title>
<p>Schizophrenia is associated with widespread cognitive impairments. Although cognitive deficits are one of the factors most strongly associated with functional outcome in schizophrenia, current treatment strategies largely fail to ameliorate these impairments. To develop more efficient treatment strategies in patients with schizophrenia, a better understanding of the pathogenesis of these cognitive deficits is needed. Accumulating evidence indicates that genetic risk of schizophrenia may contribute to cognitive dysfunction.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-2">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>To identify genomic regions jointly influencing schizophrenia and the cognitive domains of reaction time and verbal-numerical reasoning, as well as general cognitive function, a phenotype that captures the shared variation in performance across cognitive domains.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-3">
<title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title>
<p>Combining data from genome-wide association studies from multiple phenotypes using conditional false discovery rate analysis provides increased power to discover genetic variants and could elucidate shared molecular genetic mechanisms. Data from the following genome-wide association studies, published from July 24, 2014, to January 17, 2017, were combined: schizophrenia in the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium cohort (n = 79 757 [cases, 34 486; controls, 45 271]); verbal-numerical reasoning (n = 36 035) and reaction time (n = 111 483) in the UK Biobank cohort; and general cognitive function in CHARGE (Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology) (n = 53 949) and COGENT (Cognitive Genomics Consortium) (n = 27 888). </p>
</sec>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-4">
<title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title>
<p>Genetic loci identified by conditional false discovery rate analysis. Brain messenger RNA expression and brain expression quantitative trait locus functionality were determined.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-5">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Among the participants in the genome-wide association studies, 21 loci jointly influencing schizophrenia and cognitive traits were identified: 2 loci shared between schizophrenia and verbal-numerical reasoning, 6 loci shared between schizophrenia and reaction time, and 14 loci shared between schizophrenia and general cognitive function. One locus was shared between schizophrenia and 2 cognitive traits and represented the strongest shared signal detected (nearest gene <italic>TCF20</italic>; chromosome 22q13.2), and was shared between schizophrenia (<italic>z</italic> score, 5.01; <italic>P</italic> = 5.53 × 10<sup>−7</sup>), general cognitive function (<italic>z</italic> score, –4.43; <italic>P</italic> = 9.42 × 10<sup>−6</sup>), and verbal-numerical reasoning (<italic>z</italic> score, –5.43; <italic>P</italic> = 5.64 × 10<sup>−8</sup>). For 18 loci, schizophrenia risk alleles were associated with poorer cognitive performance. The implicated genes are expressed in the developmental and adult human brain. Replicable expression quantitative trait locus functionality was identified for 4 loci in the adult human brain.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-6">
<title>Conclusions and Relevance</title>
<p>The discovered loci improve the understanding of the common genetic basis underlying schizophrenia and cognitive function, suggesting novel molecular genetic mechanisms.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>This analysis of genome-wide association studies identifies genomic regions jointly influencing schizophrenia and the cognitive domains of reaction time and verbal-numerical reasoning, as well as general cognitive function.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="key-points">
<title>Key Points</title>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-7">
<title>Question</title>
<p>What genetic loci jointly influence schizophrenia and cognitive function?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-8">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>In this analysis of genome-wide association studies on schizophrenia and cognitive traits in more than 250 000 participants, 21 genomic regions were found to be shared between schizophrenia and cognitive traits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ab-yoi170050-9">
<title>Meaning</title>
<p>The findings provide new insights into the common genetic basis underlying schizophrenia and cognitive function, suggesting novel molecular genetic mechanisms.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp1">National Institutes of Health</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp2">National Institute of Mental Health</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp3">National Institutes of Health</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp4">National Institute on Drug Abuse</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp5">National Cancer Institute</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp6">Research Council of Norway</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp7">South-East Norway Regional Health Authority</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp8">KG Jebsen Stiftelsen</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp9">Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp10">Medical Research Council</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp11">Research Council of Norway</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source id="sp12">European Union’s Seventh Framework Programme</funding-source>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>