<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101497281</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">35714</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Adv Protein Chem Struct Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Adv Protein Chem Struct Biol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Advances in protein chemistry and structural biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1876-1623</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1876-1631</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28427564</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5753773</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.apcsb.2017.01.005</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS914282</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Inflammation in epileptic encephalopathies</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shandra</surname>
<given-names>Oleksii</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moshé</surname>
<given-names>Solomon L.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Galanopoulou</surname>
<given-names>Aristea S.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Saul R. Korey Department of Neurology, Laboratory of Developmental Epilepsy, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, New York, U.S.A</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Dominick P. Purpura Department of Neuroscience, Montefiore/Einstein Epilepsy Center, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, New York, U.S.A</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Pediatrics, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, New York, U.S.A</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Aristea S. Galanopoulou MD PhD, 1410 Pelham Parkway South, Kennedy Center Rm 306, Bronx NY 10461, USA, Tel: 718-430-3791, Fax: 718-430-8899, <email>aristea.galanopoulou@einstein.yu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>19</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>28</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>28</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>59</fpage>
<lpage>84</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/bs.apcsb.2017.01.005-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">West syndrome (WS) is an infantile epileptic encephalopathy (EE) that manifests with infantile spasms, hypsarrhythmia (in ~60% of infants) and poor neurodevelopmental outcomes. The etiologies of WS can be structural-metabolic pathologies (~60%), genetic (12–15%) or of unknown origin. The current treatment options include hormonal treatment [adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) and high dose steroids], the GABA aminotransferase inhibitor vigabatrin, while ketogenic diet can be given as add-on treatment in refractory IS. There is a need to identify new therapeutic targets and more effective treatments for WS.</p>
<p id="P2">Theories about the role of inflammatory pathways in the pathogenesis and treatment of WS have emerged, being supported by both clinical and preclinical data from animal models of WS. Ongoing advances in genetics have revealed numerous genes involved in the pathogenesis of WS, including genes directly or indirectly involved in inflammation. Inflammatory pathways also interact with other signaling pathways implicated in WS, such as the neuroendocrine pathway. Furthermore, seizures may also activate pro-inflammatory pathways raising the possibility that inflammation can be a consequence of seizures and epileptogenic processes. With this targeted review we plan to discuss the evidence pro and against the following key questions. Does activation of inflammatory pathways in the brain cause epilepsy in WS and does it contribute to the associated comorbidities and progression? Can activation of certain inflammatory pathways be a compensatory or protective event? Are there interactions between inflammation and the neuroendocrine system that contribute to the pathogenesis of West syndrome? Does activation of brain inflammatory signaling pathways contribute to the transition of WS to Lennox-Gastaut syndrome? Are there any lead candidates or unexplored targets for future therapy development for WS targeting inflammation?</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>West syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>cognition</kwd>
<kwd>inflammation</kwd>
<kwd>neuroinflammation</kwd>
<kwd>Epilepsy</kwd>
<kwd>mTOR</kwd>
<kwd>multiple-hit model</kwd>
<kwd>Lennox Gastaut syndrome</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>