<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8200709</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2827</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Mol Neurobiol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell. Mol. Neurobiol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Cellular and molecular neurobiology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0272-4340</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1573-6830</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28687876</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5756687</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10571-017-0514-0</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS891267</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Chromosome 21-encoded microRNAS (mRNAs) – impact on Down's syndrome and trisomy-21 linked disease</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alexandrov</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Percy</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lukiw</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Russian Academy of Medical Sciences, Moscow 113152, Russian Federation</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Physiology, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Toronto, Canada</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Surrey Place Centre, Toronto, Canada</aff>
<aff id="A5">
<label>5</label>LSU Neuroscience Center, Louisiana State University Health Science Center, New Orleans LA 70112, USA</aff>
<aff id="A6">
<label>6</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Louisiana State University Health Science Center, New Orleans LA 70112, USA</aff>
<aff id="A7">
<label>7</label>Department of Neurology, Louisiana State University Health Science Center, New Orleans LA 70112, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Corresponding author: Walter J. Lukiw, BS, MS, PhD, LSU Neuroscience Center, Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center, 2020 Gravier Street, Suite 904, New Orleans LA 70112-2272 USA, <email>wlukiw@lsuhsc.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>8</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>07</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>769</fpage>
<lpage>774</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1007/s10571-017-0514-0-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Down's syndrome (DS; also known as trisomy 21; T21) is caused by a triplication of all or part of human chromosome 21 (chr21). DS is the most common genetic cause of intellectual disability attributable to a naturally-occurring imbalance in gene dosage. DS incurs huge medical, healthcare and socioeconomic costs and there are as yet no effective treatments for this incapacitating human neurogenetic disorder. There is a remarkable <italic>wide variability</italic> in the <italic>‘phenotypic spectrum’</italic> associated with DS, the progression of symptoms and the age of DS onset fluctuate, and there are further variabilities of the biophysical nature of the chr21 duplication. Besides the cognitive disruptions and dementia in DS patients other serious health problems such as atherosclerosis, altered lipogenesis, Alzheimer's disease (AD), amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS; Lou Gehrig's disease), autoimmune disease, various cancers including lymphoma, leukemia, glioma and glioblastoma, status epilepticus, congenital heart disease, hypotonia, manic depression, prostate cancer, Usher syndrome, motor disorders, Hirschsprung disease, and various physical anomalies such as early aging occur at elevated frequencies, and all are part of the Down syndrome <italic>‘phenotypic spectrum’</italic>. This communication will review the genetic link between these fore-mentioned diseases and a small group of just 5 stress-associated microRNAs (miRNAs) - that include let-7c, miRNA-99a, miRNA125b, miRNA-155 and miRNA-802 – encoded and clustered on the long arm of human chr21 and spanning the chr21q21.1-chr21q21.3 region.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>42 amino acid amyloid-beta (Aβ42) peptide</kwd>
<kwd>Alzheimer's disease (AD)</kwd>
<kwd>Down's Syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>microRNA (miRNA)</kwd>
<kwd>small non-coding RNAs (sncRNAs)</kwd>
<kwd>systemic inflammation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>