<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8211617</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6714</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Prog. Neuropsychopharmacol. Biol. Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Progress in neuro-psychopharmacology &amp; biological psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0278-5846</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1878-4216</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28803923</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5809232</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pnpbp.2017.08.004</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS904489</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Stress Induced Neural Reorganization: A Conceptual Framework Linking Depression and Alzheimer’s Disease</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gliebus</surname>
<given-names>Gediminas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Van Bockstaele</surname>
<given-names>Elisabeth J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Pharmacology and Physiology, College of Medicine, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA 19102</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Neurology, Drexel Neuroscience Institute, Philadelphia, PA 19107</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Corresponding Author: Jennifer Ross, Department of Pharmacology and Physiology, College of Medicine, Drexel University, 245 S. 15th Street, Philadelphia, PA 19102, Voice: (908) 770-7802, <email>jar485@drexel.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>16</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>136</fpage>
<lpage>151</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.pnpbp.2017.08.004-->
<abstract>
<p id="P2">Chronic stress is a risk factor for a number of physiological disorders including cardiovascular disease, obesity and gastrointestinal disorders, as well as psychiatric and neurodegenerative disorders. There are a number of underlying molecular and cellular mechanisms altered in the course of chronic stress, which may increase the vulnerability of individuals to develop psychiatric disorders such as depression, and neurodegenerative disorders such as Alzheimer’s Disease (AD). This is evident in the influence of stress on large-scale brain networks, including the resting state Default Mode Network (DMN), the effects of stress on neuronal circuitry and architecture, and the cellular and molecular adaptations to stress, which may render individuals with stress related psychiatric disorders more vulnerable to neurodegenerative disease later in life. These alterations include decreased negative feedback inhibition of the hypothalamic pituitary axis (HPA) axis, decreased dendritic arborization and spine density in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and hippocampus, and the release of proinflammatory cytokines, which may suppress neurogenesis and promote neuronal cell death. Each of these factors are thought to play a role in stress-related psychiatric disease as well as AD, and have been observed in clinical and post-mortem studies of individuals with depression and AD. The goal of the current review is to summarize clinical and preclinical evidence supporting a role for chronic stress as a putative link between neuropsychiatric and neurodegenerative disease. Moreover, we provide a rationale for the importance of taking a medical history of stress-related psychiatric diseases into consideration during clinical trial design, as they may play an important role in the etiology of AD in stratified patient populations.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>stress</kwd>
<kwd>amyloid</kwd>
<kwd>norepinephrine</kwd>
<kwd>dopamine-β-hydroxylase</kwd>
<kwd>depression</kwd>
<kwd>adrenergic receptors</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>