<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="case-report" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Adv Biomed Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Adv Biomed Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ABR</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Advanced Biomedical Research</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2277-9175</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29456978</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5812087</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ABR-7-7</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2277-9175.223740</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Case of Tyrosinemia Type III with Status Epilepticus and Mental Retardation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Najafi</surname>
<given-names>Reza</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mostofizadeh</surname>
<given-names>Neda</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hashemipour</surname>
<given-names>Mahin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<italic>From the Department of Pediatric Endocrinology and Metabolism, Ilam University of Medical Sciences, Ilam, Iran</italic>
</aff>
<aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<italic>Endocrine and Metabolism Research Center, University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran</italic>
</aff>
<aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<italic>Department of Pediatric Endocrinology, Endocrine and Metabolism Research Center, Isfahan, Iran</italic>
</aff>
<aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<italic>Child Growth and Development Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran</italic>
</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">
<italic><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Neda Mostofizadeh, Endocrine and Metabolism Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran. E-mail: <email xlink:href="nmostofizadeh@yahoo.com">nmostofizadeh@yahoo.com</email></italic>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>22</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<elocation-id>7</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<month>2</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2018 Advanced Biomedical Research</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Tyrosinemia type III is an autosomal recessive disorder caused by the deficiency of 4- hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase (4-HPPD). It is characterized by elevated levels of blood tyrosine and massive excretion of its derivatives into the urine. Clinical findings of tyrosinemia type III include neurological symptoms and mental retardation. Only a few patients presenting with this disease have been described, and the clinical phenotype remains variable and unclear. We present a case, who was admitted to the hospital at the age of 4 months for recurrent seizures. Two months later, she was admitted again with status epilepticus. Laboratory data showed increased level of tyrosine in the blood. She was treated with a diet low in tyrosine and phenylalanine and anamix formula that leading to catch-up growth and improvement of her symptoms. Plasma tyrosine level dropped to normal values. In any child who presents with the neurologic symptom, some rare diagnosis like tyrosinemia type III should be considered.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>
<italic>Mental retardation</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>
<italic>status epilepticus</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>
<italic>tyrosinemia type III</italic>
</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Tyrosinemia type III is a rare disorder. Only a few patients have been described. Tyrosine is a precursor of dopamine, norepinephrine, epinephrine, melanin, and thyroxine.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] This autosomal recessive disease is caused by the deficiency of 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>] that is mainly expressed in neurons, neutrophils, kidney, and liver cells.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>] It catalyzes the reaction of 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvic acid to homogentisic acid [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>].[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>]</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Tyrosine metabolism pathway</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="ABR-7-7-g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>The disease is characterized by increased level of blood tyrosine and massive excretion of its derivatives into the urine.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>] Excessive NO release can also participate in neuronal damage.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] Age of presentation is from 1 to 17 months.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] The clinical phenotype remains variable and unclear.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>]</p>
<p>Neurological symptoms include developmental delay, behavioral disturbance, seizures, microcephaly, ataxia, tremor, hypotonia, absent deep tendon reflexes,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>] here, we present a case of tyrosinemia type III with status epilepticus.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1-2">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>This patient was a 21-month-old girl, who was born at term with birth weight 2250 g and head circumference 33 cm following a pregnancy with polyhydramnios. The patient had no perinatal problem. She was the second child of No consanguineous parents. The first sibling was a 4-year-old boy who is healthy and normally developed. She was admitted to Pediatric Emergency Department at 4 months of age for recurrent seizure. Two months later she was admitted again with status epilepticus. Her seizure controlled with antiepileptic drugs. We did not find any reason for status epilepticus in routine lab tests, cerebrospinal fluid analysis; brain computed tomography scan, brain magnetic resonance imaging, and blood gas analysis. All of them were normal.</p>
<p>Metabolic investigations showed increased level of tyrosine in the blood (737 μmol/l and 915 μmol/l) in 2 consecutive time, (normal range 88–204 μmol/l). The levels of 4-hydroxyphenyl lactic acid (1710 mmol/mol creatinine with normal &lt;5.3) and 4-hydroxyphenyl pyruvic acid (2184 mmol/mol creatinine with normal &lt;4.9) in the urine were elevated, without marked elevation of succinylacetone. Kidney and liver functions were normal. Clinical findings and biological abnormalities were suggestive of tyrosinemia type III and were treated with a diet low in tyrosine, phenylalanine, and anamix formula plus ascorbic acid supplementation (50 mg/day in two doses) that leading to catch-up growth and improvement of her symptoms. Plasma tyrosine level dropped to normal values. Now her mental status is mildly delayed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1-3" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>To our knowledge, only a few patients presenting with this disease have been described in the literature, and none of them presented with status epilepticus.</p>
<p>Most of the reported patients have had neurological symptoms after the neonatal period while others detected by neonatal screening have been asymptomatic. Like our patient all have had normal liver and renal function and none has skin or eye abnormalities.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>]</p>
<p>The most common long-term complication is intellectual impairment, found in 75% of patients. In 2008, a patient with tyrosinemia type III was described with autism and mental retardation.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>] Mild hypertyrosinemia may be offered as typical clinical features of the disease.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>]</p>
<p>Asymptomatic infants with 4-HPPD deficiency have been identified by neonatal screening for hypertyrosinemia.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] Our patient presented with seizure and status epilepticus, and neurological abnormalities. Similar to our patient Endo <italic>et al</italic>. reported a patient with seizure, mental retardation, and neurological abnormalities. In another study, Cerone <italic>et al</italic>. reported a patient with intermittent ataxia.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]</p>
<p>The high tyrosine concentration in an otherwise normal amino acid profile has been found in patients presenting with neurological symptoms.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>]</p>
<p>The diagnosis is suspected in children with sustained moderate increases in plasma levels of tyrosine (typically 350–700 μmole/L on a normal diet) and massive excretion of its derivatives, 4-hydroxyphenyl pyruvic acid, 4-hydroxyphenyl lactic, and 4-hydroxyphenyl acetic acid into in urine.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] One of the important factors for definitive diagnosis is genetic study or assay the activity of a 4-HPPD enzyme in liver biopsy.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] That is what we could not do it and can be a limitation of our study.</p>
<p>In 2001 on a review of 13 patients, five were detected by neonatal screening, two of which were free of any symptoms, with a normal development at 13 months, and 5.4 years, respectively, following a low tyrosine and phenylalanine diet; the three other patients showed mild intellectual impairment. Eight out of 13 patients were diagnosed after the neonatal period because of neurologic signs, that one of them showing a normal development at the age of 17 years,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>] in contrast to our patient that the first neurological signs were started at 4 months of age. Clinical and biochemical findings in patients with a 4-HPPD deficiency in previous and present studies illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Clinical and biochemical findings in patients with 4-HPPD deficiency</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="ABR-7-7-g002"></graphic>
</table-wrap>
<p>In favor of our patient long-term treatment with a tyrosine-restricted diet led to control of seizure disorder.</p>
<p>In the last reported cases, improvement of signs, symptoms, and psychomotor function were observed with a restricted diet.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>] However, D’Eufemia <italic>et al</italic>. reported that their patient showed normal psychomotor development and no clinical signs in spite of a normal diet.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>]</p>
<p>In our patient, mild mental retardation remained, similar to the reported case by Heylen <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>] Their patient's language skills and autistic behavior improved by using a tyrosine-restricted diet while no changes were made in the mental retardation.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>]</p>
<p>The effects of therapeutic interventions by using a low-protein diet are still unknown, and it is not yet clear whether lowering plasma tyrosine levels is able to alter the natural history of the disease in spite of this fact that it is recommended to treat these patients with a tyrosine- and phenylalanine-restricted diet.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>]</p>
<p>As treatment with 2-(2-nitro-4-trifluoromethylbenzoyl)-1,3-ciclohexanedione (NTBC) in patients with tyrosinemia type I shifts the metabolic block from fumarylacetoacetate hydrolase to p-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase or from tyrosinemia type I to tyrosinemia type III, treatment with NTBC must be supplemented by dietary treatment with a phenylalanine- and tyrosine-reduced diet, which is the rational approach to treatment in tyrosinemias type II and III.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>] NTBC do not approve for the treatment of tyrosinemia type III, for this reason, we did not apply it in our patient.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>]</p>
<sec id="sec2-1">
<title>Declaration of patient consent</title>
<p>The authors certify that they have obtained all appropriate patient consent forms. In the form the patient(s) has/have given his/her/their consent for his/her/their images and other clinical information to be reported in the journal. The patients understand that their names and initials will not be published and due efforts will be made to conceal their identity, but anonymity cannot be guaranteed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-2">
<title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
<p>Nil.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-3" sec-type="COI-statement">
<title>Conflicts of interest</title>
<p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="ref1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rezvani</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kliegman</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Behrman</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Genson</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stanton</surname>
<given-names>BF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tyrosinemia</article-title>
<source/>Nelson Textbook of Pediatric
          <year>2011</year>
<edition>19th ed</edition>
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>D’Eufemia</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Finocchiaro</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Celli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raccio</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Properzi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zicari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Increased nitric oxide release by neutrophils of a patient with tyrosinemia type III</article-title>
<source/>Biomed Pharmacother
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>359</fpage>
<lpage>61</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18657947</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cerone</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holme</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schiaffino</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caruso</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maritano</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Romano</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tyrosinemia type III: Diagnosis and ten-year follow-up</article-title>
<source/>Acta Paediatr
          <year>1997</year>
<volume>86</volume>
<fpage>1013</fpage>
<lpage>5</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9343288</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The genetic tyrosinemias</article-title>
<source/>Am J Med Genet C Semin Med Genet
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>142C</volume>
<fpage>121</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16602095</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heylen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scherer</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marie</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nassogne</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tyrosinemia Type III detected via neonatal screening: Management and outcome</article-title>
<source/>Mol Genet Metab
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>605</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23036342</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lindstedt</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holme</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lock</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hjalmarson</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strandvik</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Treatment of hereditary tyrosinaemia type I by inhibition of 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase</article-title>
<source/>Lancet
          <year>1992</year>
<volume>340</volume>
<fpage>813</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1383656</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tanaka</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mitsubuchi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Animal models of tyrosinemia</article-title>
<source/>J Nutr
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>1556S</fpage>
<lpage>60</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17513424</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kitano</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Uehara</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nagata</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Matsuda</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shinka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Four-hydroxyphenylpyruvic acid oxidase deficiency with normal fumarylacetoacetase: A new variant form of hereditary hypertyrosinemia</article-title>
<source/>Pediatr Res
          <year>1983</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>92</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6828337</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Awata</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Matsuda</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of the human 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvic acid dioxygenase gene (HPD)</article-title>
<source/>Genomics
          <year>1994</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>534</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7851880</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giardini</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cantani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kennaway</surname>
<given-names>NG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>D’Eufemia</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Chronic tyrosinemia associated with 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase deficiency with acute intermittent ataxia and without visceral and bone involvement</article-title>
<source/>Pediatr Res
          <year>1983</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>25</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6132360</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ellaway</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holme</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Standing</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Preece</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ploechl</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Outcome of tyrosinaemia type III</article-title>
<source/>J Inherit Metab Dis
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>824</fpage>
<lpage>32</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11916315</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holme</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Blau</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Duran</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blaskovics</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gibson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Disorders of tyrosine degradation</article-title>
<source/>Physician's Guide to the Laboratory Diagnosis of Metabolic Diseases
          <year>1996</year>
<edition>2nd ed</edition>
<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tahiroglu</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mungan</surname>
<given-names>NÖ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Firat</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Avci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autism symptoms related to tyrosinaemia type III: A case report</article-title>
<source/>Turk J Endocrinol Metab
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>55</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoffmann</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engelmann</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Hoffmann</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zschocke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nyhan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Liver disease</article-title>
<source/>Inherited Metabolic Diseases, A Clinical Approach
          <year>2010</year>
<publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Preece</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rylance</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacDonald</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>RGF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A new case of tyrosinemia type I11 detected by neonatal screening</article-title>
<source/>J Inher Metab Dis
          <year>1996</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>Suppl 1</issue>
<fpage>32</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>