<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="case-report" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Open Access Macedonian Journal of Medical Sciences</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1857-9655</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Republic of Macedonia</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>ID Design 2012/DOOEL Skopje</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29483987</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5816321</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OAMJMS-6-71</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3889/oamjms.2018.004</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Neurofibromatosis Type 1 with Massive Ventricular Polyposis: First Report in the Medical Literature</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tchernev</surname>
<given-names>Georgi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chokoeva</surname>
<given-names>Anastasiya Atanasova</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wollina</surname>
<given-names>Uwe</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lotti</surname>
<given-names>Torello</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maximov</surname>
<given-names>Georgi Konstantinov</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lozev</surname>
<given-names>Ilia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<italic>”Onkoderma”- Policlinic for Dermatology and Dermatologic Surgery, Sofia, Bulgaria</italic>
</aff>
<aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<italic>Medical Institute of Ministry of Interior (MVR-Sofia), Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Dermatologic Surgery, General Skobelev 26, 1606 Sofia, Bulgaria</italic>
</aff>
<aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<italic>Städtisches Klinikum Dresden, Department of Dermatology and Allergology, 01067 Dresden, Germany</italic>
</aff>
<aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<italic>Universitario di Ruolo, Dipartimento di Scienze Dermatologiche, Università degli Studi di Firenze, Facoltà di Medicina e Chirurgia - Chair of Dermatology, University of Rome, Rome, Italy</italic>
</aff>
<aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<italic>Medical Institute of Ministry of Interior, Department of General, Vascular and Abdominal Surgery, General Skobelev 79, 1606 Sofia, Bulgaria</italic>
</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Georgi Tchernev. Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Dermatologic Surgery, Medical Institute of Ministry of Interior (MVR-Sofia), General Skobelev 79, 1606 Sofia, Bulgaria; Onkoderma - Policlinic for Dermatology, Venereology and Dermatologic Surgery, General Skobelev 26, 1606, Sofia, Bulgaria. E-mail: <email xlink:href="georgi_tchernev@yahoo.de">georgi_tchernev@yahoo.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<day>25</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>01</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>71</fpage>
<lpage>73</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>02</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>10</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>20</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2018 Georgi Tchernev, Anastasiya Atanasova Chokoeva, Uwe Wollina, Torello Lotti, Georgi Konstantinov Maximov, Ilia Lozev.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/CC BY-NC/4.0">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC 4.0).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="st1">
<title>BACKGROUND::</title>
<p>Neurofibromatosis type 1 (<italic>NF1</italic>) is a multisystemic disorder with genetic background, characterised by specific cutaneous findings, skeletal dysplasias, and growth of both benign and malignant nervous system tumours. <italic>NF1</italic> is caused by mutations in the <italic>NF1</italic> gene, situated in chromosome 17q11.2, with an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance and clinical manifestation of neurofibromas, malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumour, optic and non-optic nerve gliomas, congenital heart disease, cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease and orthopaedic disorders. The incidence of gastrointestinal manifestations of <italic>NF1</italic> is relatively low, compared to neurological disorders, presenting approximately in 5 to 25% of the patient, but later in life.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="st2">
<title>CASE REPORT::</title>
<p>We present a patient with <italic>NF1</italic>, ventricular polyposis and attentional disorders with cognitive phenotype, while both of her daughters also present with cutaneous manifestations of <italic>NF1</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="st3">
<title>CONCLUSION::</title>
<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first reported case of <italic>NF1</italic> with ventricular polyposis as a gastrointestinal manifestation in the mother and <italic>NF1</italic> with no signs of inner organ involvement in both of her daughters.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>NF1</kwd>
<kwd>surgical removal</kwd>
<kwd>polyposis ventriculi</kwd>
<kwd>neurofibromas</kwd>
<kwd>Billroth II</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) is a multisystemic disorder with genetic background, characterised by specific cutaneous findings, skeletal dysplasias, and growth of both benign and malignant nervous system tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>]. NF1 is caused by mutations in the NF1 gene, situated in chromosome 17q11.2, which provides instructions for making a protein called neurofibromin, produced in many cells, including nerve cells and specialised cells surrounding nerves (oligodendrocytes and Schwann cells) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]. Neurofibromin acts as a tumour suppressor, and therefore, mutations in the NF1 gene lead to the production of a nonfunctional version of neurofibromin, incapable to regulate cell growth and division [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>].</p>
<p>The clinical signs and symptoms vary widely among affected people, usually beginning in early childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>]. One of the most typical manifestations represents the so-called café-au-lait spots wich can be single or multiple, gradually increasing in size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>]. Tumors like neurofibromas can arise along nerves throughout the body [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>].</p>
<p>Clinical diagnosis of NF1 requires the presence of at least 2 of the following 7 criteria: 1) Six or more café-au-lait spots or hyperpigmented macules =5 mm in diameter in prepubertal children and 15 mm postpubertal; 2) Axillary or inguinal freckles (&gt;2 freckles); 3) Two or more typical neurofibromas or one plexiform neurofibroma; 4) Optic nerve glioma; 5) Two or more iris hamartomas (Lisch nodules); 6) Sphenoid dysplasia or typical long-bone abnormalities such as pseudarthrosis; 7) First-degree relative (mother, father, sister, brother) with NF1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1-2">
<title>Case report</title>
<p>A 78-year old female patient presented with complaints of malaise, and weakness. Attentional disorders with cognitive phenotype, depressive and suicide attentions (from 1985), spondyloarthritis, sub compensatory ocular peripheral syndrome, lumbar osteochondrosis, right-sided lumbosacral radicular syndrome, vertebral syndrome and gonarthrosis on the right (from 2003) were reported from the medical history as comorbidities with long-standing duration. Ulcus callosum gastric was also reported as accompanied disease and polyposis ventriculi, treated with resection ventriculi (Billroth II) in 2004. The patient had been hospitalised in 2007 with pain in the epigastrium and abdomen. Abdominal ultrasonography had established well circumscribed, heterogeneous solid tumour formation, measuring 4 cm, in the pylori-antral part of the stomach, resembling cholelithiasis, polyp or a mesenchymal tumour. Further fibro gastroscopy had revealed three polyps, one measuring 15/10 mm, and the others 2/3 cm, with ulcerated surface and wide basis. The diagnosis of hyperplasiogenic polyposis ventriculi was made, based on the fibro gastroscopic findings and histological examination. The polyps had been removed on a later stage.</p>
<p>Clinical examination revealed multiple nodular and tumour-like formations, measuring from 1 to 5 cm, disseminated on the whole body and extremities, with a smooth surface and regular borders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). The same clinical findings were observed in patient’s daughters, both of them with long-standing duration and progressive behaviour for dissemination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b,c,d,e</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>1a,b – Clinical manifestation of a 78-year-old female patient with NF 1 and ventricular polyposis; 1c,d,e,f – Clinical manifestation of NF1 in both patient’s daughters</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="OAMJMS-6-71-g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>The conducted paraclinical blood tests revealed the decreased level of erythrocytes (3.18 10^12/l), haemoglobin (65.0 g/l), hematocrit (0.21 l/l) and increased plated cells count (562.0 10^9/l). Abdominal ultrasonography did not reveal any abnormalities in structure or function of the inner organs. Irigoscopy established hypotonic and hypokinetic dyskinesia of colon ascendens. Fibrogastroscopy findings were indicative of chronic active gastritis.</p>
<p>The diagnosis of massive ventricular polyposis, associated with neurofibromatosis type I, affecting the patients and her daughters was made. All of the patients did not undergo genetic examination.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1-3" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Neurofibromatoses refer to 3 genetically inherited disorders, which are clinically and genetically distinct diseases, including NF1, neurofibromatosis type 2 and Schwannomatosis.</p>
<p>NF1 also known as Von Recklinghausen’s disease or peripheral neurofibromatosis, is the most common form of neurofibromatosis represents up to 90% of the cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]. It has an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance, with one mutated copy of the NF1 gene in each cell, which is inherited from an affected parent in about half of the cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]. Sporadic new mutations are responsible for the other half of the cases, with no family history of the disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>]. In contrast to most of the autosomal dominant conditions, two copies of the NF1 gene must be altered to trigger tumour formation in neurofibromatosis type 1, as the mutation in the second copy of the NF1 gene occurs during a person’s lifetime in cells surrounding nerves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>]. It is not clear enough how mutations in the NF1 gene lead to the other features of neurofibromatosis type 1, such as café-au-lait spots and learning disabilities or autism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>]. On the other hand, it is established that children and adolescents with NF1 are at increased risk for wide-ranging behavioural, developmental, and cognitive impairments, all decreasing quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>].</p>
<p>Furthermore, an interesting research by Jonas RK. et al (2017) observed significantly reduced neural activity across multiple brain regions involved in higher-order semantic processing and motivation in patients with NF1 relative to controls and atypical age-associated changes in neural activity in patients with NF1, such that during risk-taking, neural activity tended to decrease with age in controls, whereas it tended to increase with age in patients with NF1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>]. The more commonly encountered manifestations of NF 1 include plexiform neurofibromas, malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumour (MPNST), optic and non-optic nerve gliomas, congenital heart disease, cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease, and orthopaedic disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]. Other signs and symptoms may include high blood pressure, bone abnormalities, lisch nodules, learning disabilities and attention deficit, hyperactivity disorder; autism spectrum disorder, larger than average head size, short stature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>]. The incidence of gastrointestinal manifestations of NF 1 is relatively low, compared to neurological disorders, presenting approximately in 5 to 25% of the patient, but later in life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]. Gastrointestinal symptoms include visceral neurogenic tumours, gastrointestinal stromal tumour and neuroendocrine tumours and clinical signs could include abdominal pain, dyspepsia, vomiting, anaemia, melena, hematemesis, hematochezia, intussusception, volvulus, small bowel obstruction, fever and abdominal mass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>].</p>
<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first reported case of NF1 in a three-member family, with different clinical manifestation and associated symptoms, including ventricular polyposis in the mother and no signs of inner organ involvement in her daughters.</p>
<p>Although there is no general cure for NF1, surgery can be used to remove tumours that cause pain or a loss of function, press on vital structures, obstruct vision, or grow rapidly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>]. Annual examinations and screening are mandatory, as the patient’s morbidity is a result of the associated complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supported-by">
<p><bold>Funding:</bold> This research did not receive any financial support</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><bold>Competing Interests:</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="ref1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ferner</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neurofibromatosis 1</article-title>
<source/>Eur J Hum Genet
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>131</fpage>
<lpage>8</lpage>
<comment>https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.ejhg.5201676 PMid:16957683</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16957683</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maharjan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lady with wings:a case report of giant neurofibromatosis type I</article-title>
<source/>Medicine (Baltimore)
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>96</volume>
<issue>29</issue>
<fpage>e7523</fpage>
<comment>https://doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000007523 PMid:28723766 PMCid:PMC5521906</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28723766</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Case of a Patient with Neurofibromatosis Type I Presenting with Abdominal Pain</article-title>
<source/>Ann Acad Med Singapore
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>45</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>524</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<comment>PMid:27922148</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27922148</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wiener</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Battles</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bedoya</surname>
<given-names>SZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baldwin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Widemann</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pao</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identifying Symptoms of Distress in Youth Living with Neurofibromatosis Type 1 (NF1)</article-title>
<source/>J Genet Couns
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<comment>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10897-017-0128-1</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jonas</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roh</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Montojo</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pacheco</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosser</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bearden</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Risky Decision Making in Neurofibromatosis Type 1:An Exploratory Study</article-title>
<source/>Biol Psychiatry Cogn Neurosci Neuroimaging
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>170</fpage>
<lpage>179</lpage>
<comment>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpsc.2016.12.003 PMid:28736755</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28736755</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>