<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">7605818</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">1921</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Brain Res Bull</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Brain Res. Bull.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Brain research bulletin</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0361-9230</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-2747</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29137928</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5835406</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainresbull.2017.11.007</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS921707</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>CaMKIIα expression in a mouse model of NMDAR hypofunction schizophrenia: putative roles for IGF-1R and TLR4</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ogundele</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Comparative Biomedical Sciences, Louisiana State University School of Veterinary Medicine, Baton Rouge, Louisiana</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Co-Corresponding Authors: Olalekan M. Ogundele (<email>ogundele@lsu.edu</email>). Charles C. Lee (<email>cclee@lsu.edu</email>)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> The author states that the present manuscript presents no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>25</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>53</fpage>
<lpage>70</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.brainresbull.2017.11.007-->
<abstract>
<p id="P2">Schizophrenia (SCZ) is a neuropsychiatric disorder that is linked to social behavioral deficits and other negative symptoms associated with hippocampal synaptic dysfunction. Synaptic mechanism of schizophrenia is characterized by loss of hippocampal N-Methyl-D-Aspartate Receptor (NMDAR) activity (NMDAR hypofunction) and dendritic spines. Previous studies show that genetic deletion of hippocampal synaptic regulatory calcium-calmodulin dependent kinase II alpha (CaMKIIα) cause synaptic and behavioral defects associated with schizophrenia in mice. Although CaMKIIα is involved in modulation of NMDAR activity, it is equally linked to inflammatory and neurotropin signaling in neurons. Based on these propositions, we speculate that non-neurotransmitter upstream receptors associated with neurotropic and inflammatory signaling activities of CaMKIIα may alter its synaptic function. Besides, how these receptors (i.e. inflammatory and neurotropic receptors) alter CaMKIIα function (phosphorylation) relative to hippocampal NMDAR activity in schizophrenia is poorly understood. Here, we examined the relationship between toll-like receptor (TLR4; inflammatory), insulin-like growth factor receptor 1 (IGF-1R; neurotropic) and CaMKIIα expression in the hippocampus of behaviorally deficient schizophrenic mice after we induced schizophrenia through NMDAR inhibition.</p>
<p id="P3">Schizophrenia was induced in WT (C57BL/6) mice through intraperitoneal administration of 30mg/Kg ketamine (NMDAR antagonist) for 5 days (WT/SCZ). Five days after the last ketamine treatment, wild type schizophrenic mice show deficiencies in sociability and social novelty behavior. Furthermore, there was a significant decrease in hippocampal CaMKIIα (p&lt;0.001) and IGF-1R (p&lt;0.001) expression when assessed through immunoblotting and confocal immunofluorescence microscopy. Additionally, WT schizophrenic mice show an increased percentage of phosphorylated CaMKIIα in addition to upregulated TLR4 signaling (TLR4, NF-κB, and MAPK/ErK) in the hippocampus. To ascertain the functional link between TLR4, IGF-1R and CaMKIIα relative to NMDAR hypofunction in schizophrenia, we created hippocampal-specific TLR4 knockdown mouse using AAV-driven Cre-lox technique (TLR4 KD). Subsequently, we inhibited NMDAR function in TLR4 KD mice in an attempt to induce schizophrenia (TLR4 KD SCZ). Interestingly, IGF-1R and CaMKIIα expressions were preserved in the TLR4 KD hippocampus after attenuation of NMDAR function. Furthermore, TLR4 KD SCZ mice showed no prominent defects in sociability and social novelty behavior when compared with the control (WT).</p>
<p id="P4">Our results show that a sustained IGF-1R expression may preserve the synaptic activity of CaMKIIα while TLR4 signaling ablates hippocampal CaMKIIα expression in NMDAR hypofunction schizophrenia. Together, we infer that IGF-1R depletion and increased TLR4 signaling are non-neurotransmitter pro-schizophrenic cues that can reduce synaptic CaMKIIα activity in a pharmacologic mouse model of schizophrenia.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Schizophrenia</kwd>
<kwd>NMDAR</kwd>
<kwd>IGF-1R</kwd>
<kwd>CaMKIIα</kwd>
<kwd>MAPK/ErK</kwd>
<kwd>TLR4</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>