<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9319162</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2572</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Opin Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Curr. Opin. Neurol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Current opinion in neurology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1350-7540</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1473-6551</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29493556</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5846342</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WCO.0000000000000537</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS943980</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Behavioral and Neuroanatomical Approaches in Models of Neurodevelopmental Disorders: Opportunities for Translation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Silverman</surname>
<given-names>Jill L</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ellegood</surname>
<given-names>Jacob</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>University of California, Davis, MIND Institute, School of Medicine, Sacramento, CA, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Mouse Imaging Centre, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Canada</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence should be addressed to: Jill L Silverman, Ph.D., MIND Institute and Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of California Davis School of Medicine, 4625 2nd Avenue, Sacramento, CA 95817, <email>jsilverman@ucdavis.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p id="P24">
<bold>Conflicts of Interest</bold>
</p>
<p id="P25">None</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>16</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>126</fpage>
<lpage>133</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1097/WCO.0000000000000537-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Purpose of review</title>
<p id="P1">This review highlights the invaluable contribution of <italic>in vivo</italic> rodent models in dissecting the underlying neurobiology for numerous neurodevelopmental disorders. Currently, models are routinely generated with precision genomics and characterized for research on neurodevelopmental disorders. In order to impact translation, outcome measures that are translationally relevant are essential. This review emphasizes the importance of applicable, accurate neurobehavioral and anatomical analyses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Recent findings</title>
<p id="P2">Numerous well-validated assays for testing alterations across behavioral domains with sensitivity and throughput have become important tools for studying the effects of genetic mutations on neurodevelopment. Recent work has highlighted relationships and links between behavioral outcomes and various anatomical metrics from neuroimaging via magnetic resonance. These readouts are biological markers and outcome measures for translational research and will be have important roles for genetic or pharmacologic intervention strategies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Summary</title>
<p id="P3">Combinatorial approaches that leverage translationally relevant behavior and neuroanatomy can be used to develop a platform for assessment of cutting edge preclinical models. Reliable, robust behavioral phenotypes in preclinical model systems, with clustering of brain pathology will lead to well-informed, precise biochemical mechanistic hypotheses. Ultimately, these steadfast workhorse techniques will accelerate the progress of developing and testing targeted treatments for multiple neurodevelopmental disorders.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Mouse models</kwd>
<kwd>behavior</kwd>
<kwd>autism</kwd>
<kwd>brain</kwd>
<kwd>development</kwd>
<kwd>genetics</kwd>
<kwd>neurodevelopmental disorder</kwd>
<kwd>translation</kwd>
<kwd>anatomy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>