<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biol. Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Biological Psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0006-3223</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-2402</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29100628</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5855319</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0006-3223(17)32008-5</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.09.020</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Developmental Changes Within the Genetic Architecture of Social Communication Behavior: A Multivariate Study of Genetic Variance in Unrelated Individuals</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>St Pourcain</surname>
<given-names>Beate</given-names>
</name>
<email>Beate.StPourcain@mpi.nl</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">∗</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eaves</surname>
<given-names>Lindon J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">e</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ring</surname>
<given-names>Susan M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>Simon E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Medland</surname>
<given-names>Sarah</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">f</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>David M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">g</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>George</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">d</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Language and Genetics Department, Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour, Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Medical Research Council Integrative Epidemiology Unit, University of Bristol, Bristol, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>School of Social and Community Medicine, University of Bristol, Bristol, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Human and Molecular Genetics, Institute for Psychiatric and Behavioral Genetics, Commonwealth University School of Medicine, Richmond, Virginia</aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Psychiatric Genetics, QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute, Queensland, Australia</aff>
<aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>University of Queensland Diamantina Institute, Translational Research Institute, University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Address correspondence to Beate St. Pourcain, Ph.D., Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics, Wundtlaan 1, Nijmegen 6525 XD, The Netherlands.Max Planck Institute for PsycholinguisticsWundtlaan 1Nijmegen 6525 XDThe Netherlands <email>Beate.StPourcain@mpi.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub">.-->
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>01</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>83</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>598</fpage>
<lpage>606</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>17</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>1</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>17</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2017 Society of Biological Psychiatry. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Society of Biological Psychiatry</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="abs0010">
<sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Recent analyses of trait-disorder overlap suggest that psychiatric dimensions may relate to distinct sets of genes that exert maximum influence during different periods of development. This includes analyses of social communication difficulties that share, depending on their developmental stage, stronger genetic links with either autism spectrum disorder or schizophrenia. We developed a multivariate analysis framework in unrelated individuals to model directly the developmental profile of genetic influences contributing to complex traits, such as social communication difficulties, during an approximately 10-year period spanning childhood and adolescence.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Longitudinally assessed quantitative social communication problems (<italic>N</italic> ≤ 5551) were studied in participants from a United Kingdom birth cohort (Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children; age range, 8–17 years). Using standardized measures, genetic architectures were investigated with novel multivariate genetic-relationship-matrix structural equation models incorporating whole-genome genotyping information. Analogous to twin research, genetic-relationship-matrix structural equation models included Cholesky decomposition, common pathway, and independent pathway models.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>A two-factor Cholesky decomposition model described the data best. One genetic factor was common to Social Communication Disorder Checklist measures across development; the other accounted for independent variation at 11 years and later, consistent with distinct developmental profiles in trait-disorder overlap. Importantly, genetic factors operating at 8 years explained only approximately 50% of genetic variation at 17 years.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Using latent factor models, we identified developmental changes in the genetic architecture of social communication difficulties that enhance the understanding of autism spectrum disorder– and schizophrenia-related dimensions. More generally, genetic-relationship-matrix structural equation models present a framework for modeling shared genetic etiologies between phenotypes and can provide prior information with respect to patterns and continuity of trait-disorder overlap.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>ALSPAC</kwd>
<kwd>Genetic relationship matrix</kwd>
<kwd>Genetic-relationship matrix structural equation modeling</kwd>
<kwd>Genetic variance decomposition</kwd>
<kwd>Longitudinal analysis</kwd>
<kwd>Structural equation modeling</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p id="p0240">
<boxed-text id="b0010">
<p id="p0235">SEE COMMENTARY ON PAGE 544</p>
</boxed-text>
</p>
<p id="p0010">The extent to which genetic etiologies are shared between traits and disorders naturally depends on the genetic composition of the two phenotypes. While psychiatric disorders are diagnostic entities defined by clinical criteria, including the age of onset, human behavior changes continously during development. This includes developmental alterations in complex genetic trait architectures as reported for cognitive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">(1)</xref> as well as social communication–related characteristics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">(2)</xref>.</p>
<p id="p0015">Difficulties in socially engaging and communicating with others, as observed in the general population, are heritable (twin-h<sup>2</sup> = 0.74) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">(3)</xref>, and a considerable proportion of the underlying genetic variation can be tagged by single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) heritability (SNP-h<sup>2</sup> ≤ 0.45) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">(2)</xref>. For both social communication and social interaction problems, multivariate twin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref> and bivariate genetic-relationship-matrix residual maximum likelihood (GREML) studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">(6)</xref> reported evidence for a degree of genetic stability but also change during childhood and adolescence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref> that may affect genetic similarities with other traits.</p>
<p id="p0020">Studying the genetic overlap between psychatric illness and social communication difficulties across multiple developmental stages, different developmental profiles for childhood-onset versus adult-onset psychiatric disorders have been identified <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">(9)</xref>. The genetic overlap with clinical autism spectrum disorder, a complex, highly heritable early-onset neurodevelopmental condition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">(10)</xref>, was strongest for social communication difficulties during childhood but declined with progressing age of the trait. By contrast, the genetic correlation with clinical schizophrenia, an adult-onset psychiatric illness with a typical first-time diagnosis between 16 and 30 years of age <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">(10)</xref>, was highest for social communication problems during later adolescence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">(9)</xref>. Thus, the risk of developing these contrasting psychiatric conditions might be related to distinct sets of genes, both of which affect social communication skills but exert their maximum influence during different periods of development.</p>
<p id="p0025">Discontinuity in trait-disorder overlap may, however, also result because of attrition-related artifacts, such as decreasing power or inherent sample bias <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">(11)</xref>. As knowledge about developmental changes in complex genetic trait architectures is still scarce, development-related variations in trait-disorder overlap are often dismissed. The aim of this study is to provide insight into the developmental profile of genetic factors influencing complex traits, such as social communication difficulties during childhood and adolescence, using a longitudinal analysis framework. Building on our previous work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, we investigate here two extreme hypotheses, as follows: 1) whether the genetic variance/covariance structure of social communication difficulties during childhood and adolescence is consistent with multiple independent genetic influences, suggesting developmental changes in the genes responsible for interindividual variation over time, or 2) whether, alternatively, there is evidence for a shared single genetic factor, irrespective of age.</p>
<p id="p0030">To study the developmental profile of genetic factors in unrelated individuals, we implemented multivariate genetic-relationship-matrix structural equation models (GSEMs). These models use genome-wide genetic relationship matrices (GRMs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">(12)</xref>, calculated from hundreds of thousands of SNPs across the genome, to estimate the total amount of phenotypic variance and covariance tagged by common genetic variants, similar to GREML <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>. GREML and related approaches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref> have reshaped the research of complex genetic trait architectures beyond twin designs by exploiting the availability of genome-wide genetic data in cohorts of unrelated individuals. Genetic correlations are, however, typically estimated by these methods by studying two phenotypes only. Using a structural equation modeling (SEM) framework <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">(17)</xref>, as widely applied within twin research <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>, we now extend this bivariate approach by flexibly modeling complex latent genetic factor structures within a multivariate context. In this article, we use multivariate GSEMs to model longitudinal data on social communication difficulties across childhood and adolescence in the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children (ALSPAC), a phenotypically rich longitudinal population-based birth cohort from the United Kingdom <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">(18)</xref>.</p>
<sec id="sec1">
<title>Methods and Materials</title>
<sec id="sec1.1">
<title>Participants and Measures</title>
<p id="p0035">All analyses were carried out using children’s data from ALSPAC, a United Kingdom population-based longitudinal pregnancy-ascertained birth cohort (estimated birth dates 1991–1992) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">(18)</xref>. The study website contains details of all the data that are available through a fully searchable data dictionary (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0010" xlink:href="http://www.bris.ac.uk/alspac/researchers/data-access/data-dictionary/">http://www.bris.ac.uk/alspac/researchers/data-access/data-dictionary/</ext-link>). Ethical approval was obtained from the ALSPAC Law and Ethics Committee (IRB00003312) and the local research ethics committees. Written informed consent was obtained from a parent or individual with parental responsibility, and assent (and for older children consent) was obtained from the child participants.</p>
<sec id="sec1.1.1">
<title>Phenotype Information</title>
<p id="p0040">Social communication difficulties during childhood and adolescence were collected with the 12-item mother-reported Social Communication Disorder Checklist (SCDC) (score range, 0–24; age range, 3–18 years) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">(3)</xref>. The SCDC is a brief screening instrument of social reciprocity and verbal and nonverbal communication (e.g., “Not aware of other people’s feelings”), which has high reliability and internal consistency and good validity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">(3)</xref>, with higher scores reflecting more social communication deficits. Quantitative SCDC scores in ALSPAC children and adolescents were measured at 8, 11, 14, and 17 years of age, and information on phenotypic and genotypic data was available for 4174 to 5551 children (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S1</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0045">Descriptive analyses of SCDC scores were performed with R version 3.2.4 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria). The distribution of SCDC scores was positively skewed and predominantly leptokurtic (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S1</xref>). Each score was adjusted for sex, age, and the two most significant ancestry-informative principal components (see below) using ordinary least squares regression. Residuals were subsequently transformed to perfect normality using rank-based inverse normal transformation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">(19)</xref>, as previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">(9)</xref>, to allow for comparisons across different algorithms (see below). There were moderate phenotypic correlations between repeatedly assessed SCDC scores using both untransformed and transformed data (SCDC, Spearman’s rho, 0.39–0.57; Pearson’s <italic>r</italic>, 0.38–0.61) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S2</xref>) as previously shown <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">(9)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1.1.2">
<title>Genome-wide Genotype Information</title>
<p id="p0050">ALSPAC children were genotyped using the Illumina HumanHap550 quad chip genotyping platforms (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Methods</xref>). After quality control, 8237 children and 477,482 directly genotyped SNPs were kept within the study.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1.2">
<title>Genetic-Relationship-Matrix Structural Equation Models</title>
<p id="p0055">Multivariate SEM techniques were used to assess the relative importance of genetic and residual influences to variation in longitudinal SCDC scores during child and adolescent development. Similar to GREML <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">(12)</xref>, GSEMs use the genetic similarity between unrelated individuals to partition the expected phenotypic variance/covariance matrix into genetic and residual components. More generally, however, the statistical framework of GSEM is analogous to twin analysis methodologies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref> but uses GRMs, instead of twin correlations, to estimate genetic variance/covariance structures using full information maximum likelihood (FIML). Thus, genetic and environmental influences are modeled in the GSEM framework as latent factors contributing to interindividual covariation in phenotypic measures. The advantage of our approach is that multivariate SEM methodology has been widely established within twin research <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref> and allows for flexible modeling of complex genetic factor structures. Conversely, GREML, as implemented in the Genome-wide Complex Trait Analysis (GCTA) software package, is currently restricted to bivariate situations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">(6)</xref>. While multivariate GSEMs can be fit with SEM software such as OpenMx <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">(20)</xref> using both mxGREML and FIML algorithms, these models are currently computationally expensive (see Results). We therefore implemented GSEMs within R (version 3.2.4) (for details see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Methods</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0060">In short, GSEMs describe the phenotypic covariance structure using one or more additive genetic factors A that capture genetic variance, tagged by common genotyped SNPs, as well as one or more residual factors E that capture residual variance, containing untagged genetic variation and unique environmental influences (including measurement error). As SEM methodology has its origins in the method of path analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">(21)</xref>, path diagrams are useful in visualizing the relationship among observed and latent variables (represented as squares and circles, respectively). In these diagrams, single-headed arrows (factor loadings or paths) denote causal relationships between measures, whereas double-headed arrows define correlations.</p>
<p id="p0065">In our formulation, additive genetic variances (GSEM-Var<sub>g</sub>) and genetic covariances are modeled as the product of additive genetic factor loadings and genetic factor variances (the latter being standardized to unit variance). For example, using multivariate GSEM, a saturated model can be fit to the data through a decomposition of both the genetic variance and the residual variance into as many latent factors as there are observed variables (Cholesky decomposition model) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Methods</xref>). Estimated genetic variances and covariances can then be used to estimate genetic correlations (GSEM-r<sub>g</sub>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">(22)</xref>, i.e., the extent to which two phenotypes share common genetic factors (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Methods</xref>). We used the Cholesky decomposition model as a saturated and baseline model (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplement</xref>). Besides Cholesky decomposition models, multivariate GSEMs also permit the fitting of models with smaller numbers of latent genetic and residual factors, defined according to theory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">(23)</xref>.</p>
<p id="p0070">Multivariate GSEMs of longitudinally assessed SCDC scores were fitted in two stages. In the first stage (I), we specified a priori three standard multivariate AE models, analogous to twin research: a Cholesky decomposition model (saturated model), an independent pathway model, and a common pathway model.<list id="olist0010" list-type="simple"><list-item id="o0010"><label>1.</label><p id="p0075">The Cholesky decomposition model, as described above, is a fully parameterized descriptive model without any restrictions on the structure of latent genetic and residual influences (20 free parameters) and involves multiple independent genetic influences sharing genetic etiologies across development.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>2.</label><p id="p0080">The independent pathway model, in its simplest form, specifies a single common genetic factor and a single common residual factor, in addition to age-specific genetic and residual influences (16 free parameters).</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>3.</label><p id="p0085">The common pathway model, in its simplest form, parameterizes a single latent factor, influenced by both genetic and residual sources of variance, in addition to age-specific genetic and residual influences, and is the most constrained model (14 free parameters). The model constrains the variance of the latent factor to one (i.e., the sum of squared genetic and residual factor loadings). Although the likelihood of this model can be estimated, the resulting Hessian is not invertible owing to singularity problems. For these reasons, the model constraint was relaxed within this work.</p></list-item></list></p>
<p id="p0090">Both the independent pathway model and the common pathway model are consistent with a shared single genetic factor across development and are nested submodels of the full Cholesky decomposition model. The goodness of fit of GSEMs to empirical data was assessed using likelihood ratio test (LRT), the Akaike information criterion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">(24)</xref>, and the Bayesian information criterion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">(25)</xref> (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Methods</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0095">In the second stage (II), we adopted a data-driven approach and investigated the pattern of genetic factor loadings for the best-fitting model from stage I in detail. The smallest genetic factor loadings were successively dropped from the model, and the overall fit of the model was compared with the best-fitting a priori defined GSEM (or an adapted form) using LRTs. The statistical significance of factor loadings was assessed using a Wald test (two-sided test). Standard errors for genetic and residual variances and covariances and genetic correlations were derived from the variance-covariance matrix of the estimated factor loadings using the delta method. Standard errors for factor loadings were estimated by GSEMs. For rank-transformed measures with unit variance, such as the SCDC scores in this study, genetic variances are equivalent to SNP-h<sup>2</sup> estimates. However, path coefficients for multivariate GSEMs were restandardized to enhance the interpretability.</p>
<p id="p0100">GRMs were estimated using the GCTA software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">(12)</xref> and based on directly genotyped SNPs. All GSEMs were fitted to data from participants with nonmissing information to simplify the estimation algorithm. All R scripts are available via the R gsem package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0015" xlink:href="https://gitlab.gwdg.de/beate.stpourcain/gsem">https://gitlab.gwdg.de/beate.stpourcain/gsem</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplement</xref>). For the purpose of benchmark comparisons with univariate GCTA, we also fitted univariate GSEMs, where genetic variances were estimated as a single variance component.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1.3">
<title>Genetic-Relationship-Matrix Residual Maximum Likelihood</title>
<p id="p0105">The GCTA software package can be used to estimate the proportion of phenotypic variation that is jointly explained by SNPs on a genotyping chip using GREML (AE model) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">(13)</xref>. Likewise, bivariate GREML <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">(6)</xref> allows estimating genetic covariances and genetic correlations between two phenotypes. An advantage of this method is that genetic correlations between two phenotypes can be estimated even when these phenotypes are not measured in the same individuals.</p>
<p id="p0110">Univariate and bivariate GREML were carried out as part of sensitivity and simulation analyses. For comparison with GSEMs, GRMs were derived from directly genotyped SNPs but excluded individuals with a pairwise relationship &gt; 0.025, as recommended <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">(13)</xref>. All analyses were conducted with GCTA software version 1.25.2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">(12)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1.4">
<title>OpenMx SEM Models</title>
<p id="p0115">OpenMx SEM models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">(20)</xref>, as implemented in the OpenMx software (versions 2.5 and 2.7; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0020" xlink:href="http://openmx.psyc.virginia.edu/">http://openmx.psyc.virginia.edu/</ext-link>), were fitted using FIML and mxGREML and included a full Cholesky decomposition of both genetic and residual variances (AE model; see above). Bivariate OpenMx SEM analyses were conducted as part of a simulation analysis. Genetic variances, genetic covariances, and genetic correlations were derived as described for GSEM above. All analyses were conducted on high-performance clusters at the University of Bristol and the Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1.5">
<title>Data Simulation</title>
<p id="p0120">To evaluate the accuracy of multivariate GSEMs, we carried out data simulations (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Methods</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec1.6">
<title>Attrition Analysis</title>
<p id="p0125">SCDC attrition scores were generated to investigate potential sources of bias. Analyses included sample-specific estimates of genetic correlations among SCDC attrition scores and between SCDC scores and subsequent sample dropout (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Methods</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec2.1">
<title>Accuracy of Multivariate GSEM</title>
<p id="p0130">We simulated a bivariate trait (<italic>N</italic> = 5000) with two standardized measures (10 replicates) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Figure S1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S3</xref>) and confirmed the accuracy of multivariate GSEMs through comparison with GCTA and OpenMx software. All methods provided accurate estimates, with respect to genetic and residual variances and covariances as well as genetic and residual factor loadings (GSEMs and OpenMx SEM models only), with comparable root mean squared error, mean absolute deviation, and little bias (bias<sup>2</sup> &lt; 10<sup>−3</sup> for all methods) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S3</xref>). Computationally, multivariate OpenMx SEM models were, however, more expensive (≤ 78 GB RAM FIML version 2.5; ≤ 2694 minutes mxGREML/FIML version 2.7) than multivariate GSEMs (≤ 13 GB RAM, ≤ 301 minutes) per single bivariate replicate analysis. A comparison of computing resources is shown in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S4</xref>. There was also little difference between estimated OpenMx versus GSEM parameters when analyzing a trivariate simulated trait with three standardized measures, as part of a benchmark test (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Figure S1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S5</xref>). Trivariate replicate analyses using OpenMx were not considered within this study owing to computational constraints.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.2">
<title>Univariate Analyses</title>
<p id="p0135">Using univariate GSEMs, common genetic variants explained a large proportion of phenotypic variation in SCDC scores during childhood as well as during later adolescence (age 8, Var<sub>g</sub> [SE] = 0.25 [0.061], <italic>p</italic> = 3.4 × 10<sup>−5</sup>; age 11, Var<sub>g</sub> [SE] = 0.22 [0.061], <italic>p</italic> = 2.9 × 10<sup>−4</sup>; age 17, Var<sub>g</sub> [SE] = 0.47 [0.086], <italic>p</italic> = 4.4 × 10<sup>−8</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S6</xref>) but not during early adolescence (age 14, Var<sub>g</sub> [SE] = 0.086 [0.064], <italic>p</italic> = .18), as previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">(2)</xref>. Univariate GCTA (GREML) yielded nearly identical results (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S7</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Genetic variance (Var<sub>g</sub>) of Social Communication Disorder Checklist (SCDC) scores during development. Var<sub>g</sub> for SCDC scores across development as estimated using a univariate model (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S6</xref>) (<italic>N</italic> ≥ 4174) and the full Cholesky decomposition model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>, model 1, and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S8</xref>) (<italic>N</italic> = 3295). Genetic factors A<sub>3</sub> and A<sub>4</sub> of the Cholesky decomposition model are not shown, as their estimated Var<sub>g</sub> was negligible (&lt; 0.01). All reported Var<sub>g</sub> estimates are equivalent to SNP-h<sup>2</sup> estimates. Gray lines indicate 1 SE in total Var<sub>g</sub> for each SCDC measure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.3">
<title>Multivariate Analyses</title>
<p id="p0140">We first examined the profile of genetic factors contributing to variation in SCDC scores during development (13,180 observations; 3295 participants) using three a priori defined multivariate GSEMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–C</xref>). Based on all three fit indices, LRT, Akaike information criterion, and Bayesian information criterion, the best-fitting a priori defined model was the full Cholesky decomposition model (model 1) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). Neither a single factor independent pathway model nor a single factor common pathway model could sufficiently capture the underlying variance/covariance structure of the data. As the full Cholesky decomposition model is also the baseline model, however, the model identification progressed with the identification of meaningful GSEMs through data-driven model modifications. Consistent with near zero factor loadings for the latent genetic factors A<sub>3</sub> and A<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S8</xref>), a two-genetic-factor Cholesky model was studied (model 4) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>) that provided a near-identical fit to the data (Δχ<sup>2</sup><sub>3</sub> &lt; 0.01, <italic>p</italic> = 1) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). This model parameterized one genetic factor arising at 8 years of age and a second independent genetic factor explaining novel genetic influences arising at 11 years of age, each contributing to phenotypic variation during later development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). Using LRTs, the model fitting progressed (model 5) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S8</xref>) until all genetic factor loadings reached <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 without a significant drop in the log-likelihood (Δχ<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub> &lt; 0.01, <italic>p</italic> = 1, with respect to model 4).<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Path diagrams of a priori defined multivariate genetic-relationship-matrix structural equation models and data-driven model modifications. <bold>(A)</bold> Full Cholesky decomposition model. <bold>(B)</bold> Independent pathway model. <bold>(C)</bold> Common pathway model. <bold>(D)</bold> Two-genetic-factor Cholesky model (data-driven model modification). Observed phenotypic measures are represented by squares, and latent factors are represented by circles. Single-headed arrows (paths) define causal relationships between variables. Note that the variance of latent variables is constrained to unit variance; this is omitted from the diagrams to improve clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"></graphic></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Path diagram of the full Cholesky decomposition model for Social and Communication Disorders Checklist scores <bold>(A)</bold> and its reduced form <bold>(B)</bold>. The full Cholesky decomposition model <bold>(A)</bold> and its most parsimonious reduced form <bold>(B)</bold> are described in detail in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> (model 1 and 5, respectively). Corresponding to the phenotypic measures P<sub>1</sub> (8 years), P<sub>2</sub> (11 years), P<sub>3</sub> (14 years), and P<sub>4</sub> (17 years), the latent genetic factors with factor loadings (a) are A<sub>1</sub> (8 years), A<sub>2</sub> (11 years), A<sub>3</sub> (14 years), and A<sub>4</sub> (17 years), and the latent residual factors with factor loadings (e) are E<sub>1</sub> (8 years), E<sub>2</sub> (11 years), E<sub>3</sub> (14 years), and E<sub>4</sub> (17 years). All path coefficients are standardized. There were 3295 participants with repeated scores across all ages. Note that the variance of latent variables is constrained to unit variance; this is omitted from the diagrams to improve clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"></graphic></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Multivariate GSEMs of SCDC Scores</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Model</th><th>Path Diagram</th><th>−2LL</th><th>k</th><th>Δχ<sup>2</sup> to Model 1</th><th>Δ<italic>df</italic> to Model 1</th><th><italic>p</italic></th><th>AIC</th><th>BIC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A Priori Defined Multivariate GSEMs</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td> 1. Full Cholesky decomposition model—saturated model</td><td><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref></td><td align="char">7900.97</td><td align="char">20</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td align="char">7940.97</td><td align="char">8062.97</td></tr><tr><td> 2. Independent pathway model</td><td><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref></td><td align="char">7914.51</td><td align="char">16</td><td align="char">13.55</td><td align="char">4</td><td>.0089</td><td align="char">7946.51</td><td align="char">8044.12</td></tr><tr><td> 3. Common pathway model</td><td><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref></td><td align="char">8082.7</td><td align="char">14</td><td align="char">181.73</td><td align="char">6</td><td align="char">&lt; 10<sup>−15</sup></td><td align="char">8110.70</td><td align="char">8196.10</td></tr><tr><td>Data-Driven Model Modification</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td> 4. Two-genetic-factor Cholesky model</td><td><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref></td><td align="char">7900.96</td><td align="char">17</td><td align="char">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="char">3</td><td>1</td><td align="char">7934.96</td><td align="char">8038.67</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th></th><th>Path Diagram</th><th>−2LL</th><th>k</th><th>Δχ<sup>2</sup> to Model 4</th><th>Δ<italic>df</italic> to Model 4</th><th><italic>p</italic></th><th>AIC</th><th>BIC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Best-Fitting Model</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td> 5. Two-genetic-factor Cholesky model (excluding nonsignificant paths)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tbl1fna">a</xref></td><td><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref></td><td align="char">7900.96</td><td align="char">15</td><td align="char">&lt; 0.01</td><td align="char">2</td><td align="char">1</td><td align="char">7930.96</td><td align="char">8022.47</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0015"><p>The GSEMs were assessed with likelihood ratio tests, the AIC and the BIC. Following the investigation of a priori defined GSEM, the model fitting progressed until all genetic factor loadings reached <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 without a significant drop in the log-likelihood. Path diagrams are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>. There were 3295 participants with SCDC scores across all ages.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0020"><p>AIC, Akaike information criterion; BIC, Bayesian information criterion; GSEM, goodness-of-fit of genetic-relationship-matrix structural equation model; k, number of parameters; LL, log-likelihood; SCDC, Social and Communication Disorders Checklist.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0010">The best-fitting model.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p id="p0145">The identified model included one common genetic factor A<sub>1</sub> accounting for shared phenotypic variation throughout development as well as a second genetic factor A<sub>2</sub> influencing SCDC scores at 11 years and especially at 17 years of age (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> shows the full Cholesky decomposition model (model 1) and its best-fitting reduced form (model 5) with their standardized path coefficients (factor loadings ≥ 0.32 explain &gt; 10% of the phenotypic variance).</p>
<p id="p0150">Overall, the estimates of genetic variance, as predicted by GSEMs (model 1 and 5) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S9</xref>), were consistent with univariate GSEM estimates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>), although the latter were based on larger sample numbers (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S6</xref>). The pattern of genetic factor loadings suggested, however, a dynamic change in the variance composition of the trait during development such that only approximately 50% of the genetic variance at 17 years of age was accounted for by genetic variation at 8 years of age (e.g., age 17, ratio Var<sub>g</sub> [A<sub>1</sub>] to Var<sub>g</sub> [A<sub>1</sub>+A2]; model 1, 0.53% [SE = 0.18]; model 5, 0.53% [SE = 0.12]) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0155">The predicted bivariate genetic correlations by multivariate GSEMs (model 1 and 5) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S9</xref>) were overall similar to bivariate GCTA (GREML) estimates, although the latter were based on larger numbers of observations (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S10</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Figure S3</xref>). Restricting analyses to the same sets of individuals, both bivariate GSEMs and bivariate GCTA (GREML) provided near-identical estimates (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S10</xref>), although these analyses were less powerful. Thus, small differences in genetic correlations patterns, as estimated by multivariate GSEMs versus bivariate GCTA (GREML), are likely to be due to minor differences in sample numbers.</p>
<p id="p0160">Furthermore, there was little evidence that genetic influences between SCDC scores and subsequent SCDC sample dropout are shared in ALSPAC (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S11</xref>). Nominal evidence for a genetic correlation was observed between SCDC scores at 8 years of age and dropout at 14 years of age only (genetic correlation = 0.39 [SE = 0.19], <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>one-tailed</italic></sub> = .02). Nonetheless, SCDC attrition scores were genetically correlated across all SCDC measures in ALSPAC (<italic>p</italic><sub><italic>one-tailed</italic></sub> &lt; 10<sup>−3</sup>) (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="appsec1">Supplemental Table S12</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="p0165">Using multivariate SEM in combination with common variant-based genetic correlation matrices, we investigated the developmental structure of genetic factors contributing to social communication difficulties during childhood and adolescence. We showed that the genetic architecture of this population-based complex trait changes continuously during development and is consistent with multiple genetic influences operating at different stages during development. Thus, our study provides evidence against the hypothesis that social communication behavior during development is a genetically homogeneous phenotype.</p>
<p id="p0170">The best-fitting model, specifying two distinct genetic factors, suggested that the genetic origins of child and adolescent social communication behavior lie in middle and late childhood. The first genetic factor, parameterized to account for all genetic influences at 8 years of age, explained a considerable proportion of phenotypic variance throughout development (&gt; 20%) with the exclusion of SCDC scores at 14 years of age that have negligible SNP-h<sup>2</sup> estimates. This is consistent with recent reports of low SNP-h<sup>2</sup> for autistic symptoms at the beginning of adolescence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">(1)</xref> and might be related to pubertal adjustments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">(2)</xref>.</p>
<p id="p0175">The second genetic factor, parameterized to be independent of the first one and to capture novel genetic influences arising at 11 years of age, explained predominantly phenotypic variation at 17 years of age (approximately 19%). Thus, the model predicted changes in the composition of the genetic variance during development, and only approximately 50% of the genetic variation at 17 years of age was accounted for by genetic variation at 8 years of age. Within defined developmental stages, however, such as stages spanning midchildhood to very early adolescence (e.g., 8–11 years), we found evidence for strong genetic correlations across measures. These results are consistent with recent longitudinal twin research that reported moderate to high genetic stability for autistic traits, including communication impairments, between midchildhood and early adolescence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">(7)</xref>, but only moderate genetic stability between behavior in childhood versus emerging adulthood <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">(8)</xref>. The identified genetic factor structure using GSEMs therefore reflects both a degree of genetic stability and a genetic change in social communication behavior during development, depending on the size of the developmental window.</p>
<p id="p0180">The identification of two distinct genetic factors, especially during later adolescence, suggests that SCDC scores at 8 or 11 years of age are, in terms of average composition, different from SCDC scores at 17 years of age. Developmental changes in the genetic architecture of social communication traits are consistent with biological maturation processes during childhood and adolescence. For example, synaptic pruning in the cerebral cortex is a signature late maturational process for generating a diversity of neuronal connections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">(26)</xref>, which occurs during puberty and extends into early adult life <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">(27)</xref>. In parallel, there are changes in adolescent social cognitive development, especially with respect to emotional perspective taking, resistance to peer influence, and changes in social behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">(28)</xref>. Given the identified genetic factor structure, it could be speculated whether multiple concepts of social reciprocity and verbal and nonverbal communication may coexist, especially at 17 years of age, and whether changes in genetic factor contributions may continue into early adulthood. Thus, even for psychological instruments with high reliability, internal consistency, and good discriminant validity, such as the SCDC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">(3)</xref>, the nature of the captured continuous phenotype may vary across developmental periods spanning approximately 10 years. This underlines the need for behavioral genetic studies across the life span.</p>
<p id="p0185">An important implication that flows from the observation of developmental variations in the genetic trait architecture is that measures assessed at different developmental stages may reveal different patterns of trait-disorder overlap, as previously shown for clinical autism spectrum disorder and schizophrenia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">(9)</xref>. Moreover, the identification of a two-genetic-factor model is also consistent with recent reports of little genetic overlap between autism spectrum disorder and schizophrenia-related dimensions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">(29)</xref>, especially with respect to social communication symptoms. Structural models capturing developmental changes in the genetic architecture of complex phenotypes can therefore be leveraged to obtain prior information concerning the stability of trait-disorder overlap and consequently the extent to which development-specific genetic trait factors are shared among different psychiatric dimensions. Our findings therefore have specific relevance for the study of functional dimensions of human behavior spanning the continuum from normal to abnormal and across development, consistent with the framework of Research Domain Criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">(30)</xref>.</p>
<p id="p0190">Finally, our study proves that structural models of genetic influences in unrelated individuals, as captured by GRMs, are computationally feasible within a longitudinal context. Beyond the scope of bivariate GCTA (GREML), multivariate GSEMs allow for the modeling of complex latent genetic factor structures across different stages of development, in particular, their genetic variance composition, and can reveal developmental origins of genetic variation that are otherwise hidden. It is furthermore possible to envisage that the concept of GSEM can be extended to investigate multivariate models of cross-disorder overlap and other complex phenomena, such as reciprocal causation. Note that also novel OpenMx FIML and mxGREML algorithms are currently being developed.</p>
<p id="p0195">A limitation of our study is the analysis of nonmissing data across all repeatedly assessed measures. Thus, weaker genetic links, spanning wider age gaps, may not have been sufficiently captured as a consequence of lower power, although genetic correlations predicted by multivariate GSEM and bivariate GCTA(GREML) were overall similar. In addition, cohort studies can be affected by attrition bias <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">(11)</xref>. We identified, however, little evidence for a specific genetic link between variation in SCDC scores and subsequent sample dropout, although attrition scores across all assessed SCDC measures were genetically correlated. This is consistent with studies reporting an association between study nonparticipation, including SCDC dropout, and polygenic risk for schizophrenia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref>, regardless of when phenotypes were sampled during development. In addition, we exclusively studied rank-transformed phenotypes to ensure multivariate normality and comparability across different estimation algorithms, and we therefore cannot exclude transformation-related biases. However, genetic overlap with psychiatric conditions provided some evidence for the content validity of the analyzed trait <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">(9)</xref>. Also, maternal characteristics may have contributed to phenotypic and, to a lesser extent, genetic correlations. However, the impact of these effects is likely to be small, given the identified developmental changes in genetic variances and covariances for SCDC scores during development. Finally, a Cholesky decomposition of a variance/covariance matrix may not always result in fitting statistics that follow the expected χ<sup>2</sup> distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">(31)</xref>. Model comparisons using real and simulated data, however, provided little evidence for systematic differences between GCTA(GREML), GSEM, and OpenMx SEMs. Thus, despite potential limitations, our study demonstrates that structural models of longitudinally assessed behavioral traits can provide information on developmental changes in genetic trait architectures as tagged by common SNPs.</p>
<sec id="sec3.1">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="p0200">The genetic architecture of social communication difficulties, as tagged by common genetic variation, changes with age and involves multiple genetic factors operating at different developmental stages during a 10-year period spanning childhood and adolescence. The identification of distinct genetic trait factors is consistent with different profiles of trait-disorder overlap and underlines the importance of investigating genetic trait variances within a multivariate context.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list id="cebib0010">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bib1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation id="sref1" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trzaskowski</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Visscher</surname>
<given-names>P.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Plomin</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DNA evidence for strong genetic stability and increasing heritability of intelligence from age 7 to 12</article-title>
<source/>Mol Psychiatry
          <volume>19</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>380</fpage>
<lpage>384</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23358157</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation id="sref2" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>St Pourcain</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Skuse</surname>
<given-names>D.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mandy</surname>
<given-names>W.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hakonarson</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Timpson</surname>
<given-names>N.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Variability in the common genetic architecture of social-communication spectrum phenotypes during childhood and adolescence</article-title>
<source/>Mol Autism
          <volume>5</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>18</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24564958</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation id="sref3" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Skuse</surname>
<given-names>D.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mandy</surname>
<given-names>W.P.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scourfield</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Measuring autistic traits: Heritability, reliability and validity of the Social and Communication Disorders Checklist</article-title>
<source/>Br J Psychiatry
          <volume>187</volume>
<year>2005</year>
<fpage>568</fpage>
<lpage>572</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16319410</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation id="sref4" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Neale</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maes</surname>
<given-names>H.H.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Methodology for Genetic Studies of Twins and Families</chapter-title>
<year>2004</year>
<publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation id="sref5" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>N.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eaves</surname>
<given-names>L.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The genetical analysis of covariance structure</article-title>
<source/>Heredity
          <volume>38</volume>
<year>1977</year>
<fpage>79</fpage>
<lpage>95</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">268313</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation id="sref6" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goddard</surname>
<given-names>M.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Visscher</surname>
<given-names>P.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wray</surname>
<given-names>N.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Estimation of pleiotropy between complex diseases using single-nucleotide polymorphism-derived genomic relationships and restricted maximum likelihood</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <volume>28</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>2540</fpage>
<lpage>2542</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22843982</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation id="sref7" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmboe</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rijsdijk</surname>
<given-names>F.V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hallett</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Happé</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Plomin</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ronald</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Strong genetic influences on the stability of autistic traits in childhood</article-title>
<source/>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry
          <volume>53</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>221</fpage>
<lpage>230</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24472256</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation id="sref8" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gillberg</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lichtenstein</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lundström</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Etiological influences on the stability of autistic traits from childhood to early adulthood: Evidence from a twin study</article-title>
<source/>Mol Autism
          <volume>8</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28316769</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation id="sref9" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>St Pourcain</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>E.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anttila</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>B.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maller</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Golding</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ASD and schizophrenia show distinct developmental profiles in common genetic overlap with population-based social-communication difficulties</article-title>
<source/>Mol Psychiatry
          <volume>23</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>263</fpage>
<lpage>270</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28044064</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation id="sref10" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</chapter-title>
<edition>4th ed.</edition>
<year>1994</year>
<publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation id="sref11" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tilling</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hubbard</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stergiakouli</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thapar</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Association of genetic risk for schizophrenia with nonparticipation over time in a population-based cohort study</article-title>
<source/>Am J Epidemiol
          <volume>183</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>1149</fpage>
<lpage>1158</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27188935</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation id="sref12" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goddard</surname>
<given-names>M.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Visscher</surname>
<given-names>P.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>GCTA: A tool for genome-wide complex trait analysis</article-title>
<source/>Am J Hum Genet
          <volume>88</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>76</fpage>
<lpage>82</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167468</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation id="sref13" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benyamin</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McEvoy</surname>
<given-names>B.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gordon</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Henders</surname>
<given-names>A.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nyholt</surname>
<given-names>D.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Common SNPs explain a large proportion of the heritability for human height</article-title>
<source/>Nat Genet
          <volume>42</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>565</fpage>
<lpage>569</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562875</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation id="sref14" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bulik-Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>B.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Loh</surname>
<given-names>P.-R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Finucane</surname>
<given-names>H.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ripke</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schizophrenia Working Group of the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium</surname>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>LD score regression distinguishes confounding from polygenicity in genome-wide association studies</article-title>
<source/>Nat Genet
          <volume>47</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>291</fpage>
<lpage>295</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25642630</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation id="sref15" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Loh</surname>
<given-names>P.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bulik-Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>B.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vilhjálmsson</surname>
<given-names>B.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Finucane</surname>
<given-names>H.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salem</surname>
<given-names>R.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Efficient Bayesian mixed-model analysis increases association power in large cohorts</article-title>
<source/>Nat Genet
          <volume>47</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>284</fpage>
<lpage>290</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25642633</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation id="sref16" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Speed</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hemani</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>M.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balding</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Improved heritability estimation from genome-wide SNPs</article-title>
<source/>Am J Hum Genet
          <volume>91</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>1011</fpage>
<lpage>1021</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23217325</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation id="sref17" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bollen</surname>
<given-names>K.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Structural Equations with Latent Variables</chapter-title>
<year>1989</year>
<publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation id="sref18" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boyd</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Golding</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Macleod</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lawlor</surname>
<given-names>D.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fraser</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cohort profile: The “children of the 90s”—the index offspring of the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children</article-title>
<source/>Int J Epidemiol
          <volume>42</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>111</fpage>
<lpage>127</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22507743</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation id="sref19" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>R.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>DeHoff</surname>
<given-names>K.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Amos</surname>
<given-names>C.I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Normalizing a large number of quantitative traits using empirical normal quantile transformation</article-title>
<source/>BMC Proc
          <volume>1</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>S156</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18466501</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation id="sref20" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boker</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Neale</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maes</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilde</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spiegel</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brick</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>OpenMx: An open source extended structural equation modeling framework</article-title>
<source/>Psychometrika
          <volume>76</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>306</fpage>
<lpage>317</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23258944</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation id="sref21" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Correlation and causation</article-title>
<source/>J Agric Res
          <volume>20</volume>
<year>1921</year>
<fpage>557</fpage>
<lpage>585</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation id="sref22" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Falconer</surname>
<given-names>D.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mackay</surname>
<given-names>T.F.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Introduction to Quantitative Genetics</chapter-title>
<edition>4th ed.</edition>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Essex, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation id="sref23" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>MacCallum</surname>
<given-names>R.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roznowski</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Necowitz</surname>
<given-names>L.B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Model modifications in covariance structure analysis: The problem of capitalization on chance</article-title>
<source/>Psychol Bull
          <volume>111</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>490</fpage>
<lpage>504</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16250105</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation id="sref24" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Akaike</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Factor analysis and AIC</article-title>
<source/>Psychometrika
          <volume>52</volume>
<year>1987</year>
<fpage>317</fpage>
<lpage>332</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation id="sref25" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schwarz</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Estimating the dimension of a model</article-title>
<source/>Ann Stat
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>1978</year>
<fpage>461</fpage>
<lpage>464</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation id="sref26" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Selemon</surname>
<given-names>L.D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A role for synaptic plasticity in the adolescent development of executive function</article-title>
<source/>Transl Psychiatry
          <volume>3</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>e238</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23462989</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib27">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation id="sref27" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Petanjek</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Judaš</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Šimić</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rašin</surname>
<given-names>M.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Uylings</surname>
<given-names>H.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rakic</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kostovic</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Extraordinary neoteny of synaptic spines in the human prefrontal cortex. Proc Nat</article-title>
<source/>Acad Sci U S A
          <volume>108</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>13281</fpage>
<lpage>13286</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib28">
<label>28</label>
<element-citation id="sref28" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burnett</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blakemore</surname>
<given-names>S.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The development of adolescent social cognition</article-title>
<source/>Ann N Y Acad Sci
          <volume>1167</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>56</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19580552</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib29">
<label>29</label>
<element-citation id="sref29" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>E.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Happé</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bolton</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ronald</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A longitudinal twin study of the association between childhood autistic traits and psychotic experiences in adolescence</article-title>
<source/>Mol Autism
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>44</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26199714</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib30">
<label>30</label>
<element-citation id="sref30" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cuthbert</surname>
<given-names>B.N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Insel</surname>
<given-names>T.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Toward the future of psychiatric diagnosis: The seven pillars of RDoC</article-title>
<source/>BMC Med
          <volume>11</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>126</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23672542</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib31">
<label>31</label>
<element-citation id="sref31" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carey</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cholesky problems</article-title>
<source/>Behav Genet
          <volume>35</volume>
<year>2005</year>
<fpage>653</fpage>
<lpage>665</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16184491</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<p id="p0225">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
<caption>
<title>Supplemental Material</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
<ack id="ack0010">
<title>Acknowledgments and Disclosures</title>
<p>This work was supported by the United Kingdom Medical Research Council and Wellcome Trust (Grant No. 102215/2/13/2) and the University of Bristol, which provide core support for the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children (ALSPAC); Autism Speaks (Grant No. 7132), which provided support for autistic-trait related analyses in ALSPAC (to BSP); and the Max Planck Society (to BSP and SEF). The ALSPAC genome-wide association study data were generated by Sample Logistics and Genotyping Facilities at the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute and Laboratory Corporation of America using financial support from 23andMe.</p>
<p>This publication is the work of the authors, and they will serve as guarantors for the contents of this article.</p>
<p>We thank all the families who took part in this study; the midwives for their help in recruiting the families; and the whole ALSPAC team, which includes interviewers, computer and laboratory technicians, clerical workers, research scientists, volunteers, managers, receptionists, and nurses. We thank Robert Kirkpatrick for helpful discussions on structural equation models and support with the OpenMx code. We thank Gregory Carey for his contribution and many helpful discussions as part of the initial work on bivariate maternal effects Genome-wide Complex Trait Analysis models carried out together with LJE, DME, and BSP. We thank Callum Wright and Tobias van Valkenhoef for their help with the high-performance computing systems.</p>
<p>The authors report no biomedical financial interests or potential conflict of interests.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supplementary-material" id="appsec2">
<p id="p0230">Supplementary material cited in this article is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0025" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.09.020">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.09.020</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>