<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">7905589</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6173</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neurotoxicology</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neurotoxicology</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Neurotoxicology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0161-813X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1872-9711</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29079486</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5857223</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuro.2017.10.004</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS917345</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Exposure to Fine and Ultrafine Particulate Matter during Gestation Alters Postnatal Oligodendrocyte Maturation, Proliferation Capacity, and Myelination</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klocke</surname>
<given-names>Carolyn</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>Joshua L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sobolewski</surname>
<given-names>Marissa</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blum</surname>
<given-names>Jason L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zelikoff</surname>
<given-names>Judith T.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cory-Slechta</surname>
<given-names>Deborah A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Environmental Medicine, University of Rochester School of Medicine, Rochester, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Environmental Medicine, New York University School of Medicine, Tuxedo, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1"><bold>Corresponding Author</bold>: Carolyn Klocke, Department of Environmental Medicine, Box EHSC, 601 Elmwood Avenue, University of Rochester School of Medicine, Rochester, NY 14642; phone: 585-273-4590, <email>carolyn_klocke@urmc.rochester.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>21</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>24</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>196</fpage>
<lpage>206</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.neuro.2017.10.004-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Accumulating studies indicate that the brain is a direct target of air pollution exposure during the fetal period. We have previously demonstrated that exposure to <underline>c</underline>oncentrated <underline>a</underline>mbient <underline>p</underline>article<underline>s</underline> (CAPs) during gestation produces ventriculomegaly, periventricular hypermyelination, and enlargement of the corpus callosum (CC) during postnatal development in mice. This study aimed to further characterize the cellular basis of the observed hypermyelination and determine if this outcome, among other effects, persisted as the brain matured. Analysis of CC-1<sup>+</sup> mature oligodendrocytes in the CC at postnatal days (PNDs) 11–15 suggest a premature maturational shift in number and proportion of total cells in prenatally CAPs-exposed males and females, with no overall change in total CC cellularity. The overall number of Olig2<sup>+</sup> lineage cells in the CC was not affected in either sex at the same postnatal timepoint. Assessment of myelin status at early brain maturity (PNDs 57–61) revealed persistent hypermyelination in CAPs-exposed animals of both sexes. In addition, ventriculomegaly was persistent in CAPs-treated females, with possible amelioration of ventriculomegaly in CAPs-exposed males. When oligodendrocyte precursor cell (OPC) pool status was analyzed at PNDs 57–61, there were significant CAPs-induced alterations in cycling Ki67<sup>+</sup>/Olig2<sup>+</sup> cell number and proportion of total cells in the female CC. Total CC cellularity was slightly elevated in CAPs-exposed males at PNDs 57–61. Overall, these data support a growing body of evidence that demonstrate the vulnerability of the developing brain to environmental insults such as ambient particulate matter. The sensitivity of oligodendrocytes and myelin, in particular, to such an insult warrants further investigation into the mechanistic underpinnings of OPC and myelin disruption by constituent air pollutants.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>air pollution</kwd>
<kwd>particulate matter</kwd>
<kwd>myelin</kwd>
<kwd>oligodendrocyte</kwd>
<kwd>oligodendrocyte progenitor cell</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>