<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0370712</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">3660</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Exp Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Exp. Neurol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Experimental neurology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0014-4886</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1090-2430</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29337147</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5864555</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.expneurol.2018.01.005</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS941228</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>NEURONAL <italic>PTEN</italic> DELETION IN ADULT CORTICAL NEURONS TRIGGERS PROGRESSIVE GROWTH OF CELL BODIES, DENDRITES, AND AXONS</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gallent</surname>
<given-names>Erin A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Steward</surname>
<given-names>Oswald</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Reeve-Irvine Research Center, University of California, Irvine</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Anatomy and Neurobiology, University of California, Irvine</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Neurobiology and Behavior, University of California, Irvine</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Department of Neurosurgery, University of California, Irvine</aff>
<aff id="A5">
<label>5</label>School of Medicine, University of California, Irvine</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Corresponding Author: Oswald Steward, Ph.D., Reeve-Irvine Research Center, 837 Health Sciences Dr., University of California Irvine School of Medicine, Irvine, CA 92697, <email>osteward@uci.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>Conflict of Interest: OS is one of the co-founders of the company “Axonis”, which holds options on patents relating to PTEN deletion and axon regeneration.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>8</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>303</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<lpage>28</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.expneurol.2018.01.005-->
<abstract>
<p id="P2">Deletion of the phosphatase and tensin (<italic>PTEN</italic>) gene in neonatal mice leads to enlargement of the cell bodies of cortical motoneurons (CMNs) in adulthood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Gutilla et al., 2016</xref>). Here, we assessed whether <italic>PTEN</italic> deletion in adult mice would trigger growth of mature neurons. <italic>PTEN</italic> was deleted by injecting AAV-Cre into the sensorimotor cortex of adult transgenic mice with a lox-P flanked exon 5 of the <italic>PTEN</italic> gene and Cre-dependent reporter gene tdTomato. PTEN-deleted CMN’s identified by tdT expression and retrograde labeling with fluorogold (FG) were significantly enlarged four months following <italic>PTEN</italic> deletion, and continued to increase in size through the latest time intervals examined (12–15 months post-deletion). Sholl analyses of tdT-positive pyramidal neurons revealed increases in dendritic branches at 6 months following adult <italic>PTEN</italic> deletion, and greater increases at 12 months. 12 months after adult <italic>PTEN</italic> deletion, axons in the medullary pyramids were significantly larger and G-ratios were higher. Mice with PTEN deletion exhibited no overt neurological symptoms and no seizures. Assessment of motor function on the Rotorod and cylinder test revealed slight impairment of coordination with unilateral deletion; however, mice with bilateral <italic>PTEN</italic> deletion in the motor cortex performed better than controls on the rotarod at 8 and 10 months post-deletion. Our findings demonstrate that robust neuronal growth can be induced in fully mature cortical neurons long after the developmental period has ended and that this continuous growth occurs without obvious functional impairments.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Aging</kwd>
<kwd>motor cortex</kwd>
<kwd>cortical pyramidal neurons</kwd>
<kwd>
<italic>PTEN</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>mTOR</kwd>
<kwd>animal</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>