<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101250006</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32839</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Discov Med</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Discov Med</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Discovery medicine</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1539-6509</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1944-7930</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29373810</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5893311</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS941407</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Long-term T Cell Responses in the Brain After an Ischemic Stroke</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Selvaraj</surname>
<given-names>Uma Maheswari</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>M.Tech.</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stowe</surname>
<given-names>Ann M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Department of Neurology and Neurotherapeutics, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, 6000 Harry Hines Blvd., Dallas, TX 75390, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Corresponding Author: Ann M. Stowe, Ph.D. (<email>Ann.Stowe@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>
<bold>Disclosure</bold>
</p>
<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>2</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>134</issue>
<fpage>323</fpage>
<lpage>333</lpage>
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Stroke, which occurs during a loss of blood flow to the brain, is a global disease that accounts for 10% of yearly mortality. But stroke is also a leading cause of long-term adult disability, with recovery continuing for months to years after initial stroke onset. This long-term functional recovery from stroke encompasses changes in neuronal structure and function, and occurs throughout the post-stroke brain. Much less understood is whether the adaptive immune cells that infiltrated the brain during acute post-stroke neuroinflammation remain long-term, and if their presence supports or hinders functional recovery. Studies show that T cell subsets and their derived cytokines exhibit diverse protective and detrimental effects in the immediate acute phase following stroke. Interestingly, T cells are also important in regulating physiological behavior, which hints at a potential role in functional recovery after stroke. Moreover, T cell egress into the post-stroke brain might actually peak weeks after stroke onset, suggesting a long-term role for the adaptive immune system in the injured CNS. However, the significance of T cells in the long-term functional and behavioral recovery and repair phase of stroke remains largely unexplored. We summarize here recent work in delineating the beneficial and detrimental effects of T cells after a stroke, including antigen-specific and non-specific effects of T cells in the post-stroke recovery phase. We also highlight the role of T cells in other CNS diseases that may suggest mechanisms for future study of these adaptive immune cells in the ischemic brain.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>