<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Psychiatry Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Psychiatry Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Psychiatry &amp; Neuroscience : JPN</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1180-4882</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1488-2434</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Joule Inc.</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29688876</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5915241</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/jpn.170094</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">43-3-201</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Paper</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>CCNP Young Investigator Award</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Neuroanatomical phenotypes in mental illness: identifying convergent and divergent cortical phenotypes across autism, ADHD and schizophrenia</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>Min Tae M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>BSc</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Raznahan</surname>
<given-names>Armin</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shaw</surname>
<given-names>Philip</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>BM BCh, PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gogtay</surname>
<given-names>Nitin</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lerch</surname>
<given-names>Jason P.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chakravarty</surname>
<given-names>M. Mallar</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="af1-43-3-201">From the Schulich School of Medicine and Dentistry, Western University, London, Ont., Canada (Park); the Cerebral Imaging Centre, Douglas Mental Health University Institute, Montreal, Que., Canada (Park, Chakravarty); the Child Psychiatry Branch, National Institute of Mental Health, Bethesda, MD, USA (Raznahan); the Section on Neurobehavioral Clinical Research, Social and Behavioral Research Branch, National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD, USA (Shaw); the Intramural Program of the National Institute of Mental Health, Bethesda, MD, USA (Shaw); the Program in Neuroscience and Mental Health, Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ont., Canada (Lerch); and the Departments of Psychiatry and Biomedical Engineering, McGill University, Montreal, Que., Canada (Chakravarty).</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="c1-43-3-201">Correspondence to: M.T. Park, Douglas Mental Health University Institute, 6875 LaSalle Blvd, Montreal, Que., Canada H4H 1R3; <email>mtpark89@gmail.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn1-43-3-201">
<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>06</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>201</fpage>
<lpage>212</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>09</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>20</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2018 Joule Inc. or its licensors</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>There is evidence suggesting neuropsychiatric disorders share genomic, cognitive and clinical features. Here, we ask if autism-spectrum disorders (ASD), attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and schizophrenia share neuroanatomical variations.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>First, we used measures of cortical anatomy to estimate spatial overlap of neuroanatomical variation using univariate methods. Next, we developed a novel methodology to determine whether cortical deficits specifically target or are “enriched” within functional resting-state networks.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>We found cortical anomalies were preferentially enriched across functional networks rather than clustering spatially. Specifically, cortical thickness showed significant enrichment between patients with ASD and those with ADHD in the default mode network, between patients with ASD and those with schizophrenia in the frontoparietal and limbic networks, and between patients with ADHD and those with schizophrenia in the ventral attention network. Networks enriched in cortical thickness anomalies were also strongly represented in functional MRI results (Neurosynth; <italic>r</italic> = 0.64, <italic>p</italic> = 0.032).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>We did not account for variable symptom dimensions and severity in patient populations, and our cross-sectional design prevented longitudinal analyses of developmental trajectories.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>These findings suggest that common deficits across neuropsychiatric disorders cannot simply be characterized as arising out of local changes in cortical grey matter, but rather as entities of both local and systemic alterations targeting brain networks.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>