<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">2985190R</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">5004</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neurochem</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Neurochem.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of neurochemistry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-3042</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1471-4159</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29168882</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5924590</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jnc.14255</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS940840</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fibroblast Growth Factor 2 Regulates Activity and Gene Expression of Human Postmitotic Excitatory Neurons</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>Shweta</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>M-Redmond</surname>
<given-names>Tanya</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meng</surname>
<given-names>Fan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tidball</surname>
<given-names>Andrew</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Akil</surname>
<given-names>Huda</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>Stanley</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parent</surname>
<given-names>Jack M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Uhler</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">‡</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>*</label>Molecular and Behavioral Neuroscience Institute, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>†</label>Department of Neurology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>‡</label>Department of Biological Chemistry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Address correspondence and reprint requests to Dr. Michael Uhler, Molecular and Behavioral Research Institute, University of Michigan, 109 Zina Pitcher Pl., Ann Arbor, MI, 48109-2200</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>
<bold>Conflict of interest disclosure</bold>
</p>
<p>All authors declare no actual or potential conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>8</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>27</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>145</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>188</fpage>
<lpage>203</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1111/jnc.14255-->
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="P1">Many neuropsychiatric disorders are thought to result from subtle changes in neural circuit formation. We used human embryonic stem cells (hESCs) and induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs) to model mature, postmitotic excitatory neurons and examine effects of FGF2. FGF2 gene expression is known to be altered in brain regions of major depressive disorder (MDD) patients and FGF2 has anti-depressive effects in animal models of depression. We generated stable inducible neurons (siNeurons) conditionally expressing human neurogenin 2 (NEUROG2) to generate a homogenous population of post-mitotic excitatory neurons and study the functional as well as the transcriptional effects of FGF2. Upon induction of NEUROG2 with doxycycline, the vast majority of cells are post-mitotic, and the gene expression profile recapitulates that of excitatory neurons within 6 days. Using hES cell lines that inducibly express NEUROG2 as well as GCaMP6f, we were able to characterize spontaneous calcium activity in these neurons and show that calcium transients increase in the presence of FGF2. The FGF2-responsive genes were determined by RNA-Seq. FGF2-regulated genes previously identified in non-neuronal cell types were upregulated (EGR1, ETV4, SPRY4, and DUSP6) as a result of chronic FGF2 treatment of siNeurons. Novel neuron specific genes were also identified that may mediate FGF2-dependent increases in synaptic efficacy including NRXN3, SYT2, and GALR1. Since several of these genes have been implicated in MDD previously, these results will provide the basis for more mechanistic studies of the role of FGF2 in MDD.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="Abs2">
<title>Graphical Abstract</title>
<p id="P2">Alterations in Fibroblast Growth Factor (FGF) signaling have been implicated in Major Depressive Disorder (MDD). In this article, human stem cells are differentiated into glutamatergic neurons. FGF2 treatment of these neurons increases activity as determined using calcium imaging. RNAseq studies implicate a number of genes in this regulation of neuronal activity by FGF2 including SYT2, NRXN3 and GALR1.</p>
<p id="P3">
<graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="nihms940840u1.jpg"></graphic></p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>FGF2</kwd>
<kwd>stem cells</kwd>
<kwd>Neurogenin-2</kwd>
<kwd>glutamatergic</kwd>
<kwd>neuronal</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>