<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9207852</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2142</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Aust Crit Care</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Aust Crit Care</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Australian critical care : official journal of the Confederation of Australian Critical Care Nurses</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1036-7314</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29567042</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5936660</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aucc.2017.12.091</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS938483</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Face and Content Validity of Variables Associated with the Difficult-to-Sedate Child in the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit: A Survey of Pediatric Critical Care Clinicians</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lebet</surname>
<given-names>Ruth M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, RN</degrees>
<aff id="A1">University of Pennsylvania School of Nursing, 418 Curie Boulevard - #423B, Philadelphia, PA 19104-4217 USA</aff>
<!--<email>lebet@nursing.upenn.edu</email>-->
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asaro</surname>
<given-names>Lisa A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MS</degrees>
<role>Biostatistician</role>
<aff id="A2">Department of Cardiology, Boston Children’s Hospital, 300 Longwood Avenue, Boston, MA 02115 USA</aff>
<!--<email>lisa.asaro@cardio.chboston.org</email>-->
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zuppa</surname>
<given-names>Athena F.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, MSCE</degrees>
<role>Associate Professor</role>
<aff id="A3">Anesthesiology and Critical Care, Director, Center for Clinical Pharmacology, Associate Director, Pediatric Critical Care Fellowship Program, The Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, 34<sup>th</sup> &amp; Civic Center Boulevard, Suite 9329, The Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA 19104 USA</aff>
<!--<email>ZUPPA@email.chop.edu</email>-->
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Curley</surname>
<given-names>Martha A.Q.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN, PhD, FAAN</degrees>
<role>Ellen and Robert Kapito Professor in Nursing Science</role>
<aff id="A4">School of Nursing, Anesthesia and Critical Care Medicine, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, 418 Curie Boulevard - #425, Philadelphia, PA 19104-4217 USA</aff>
<!--<email>curley@nursing.upenn.edu</email>-->
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Corresponding author: Ruth Lebet, PhD, RN; University of Pennsylvania School of Nursing; 418 Curie Boulevard - #423B; Philadelphia, PA 19104-4217; <email>lebet@nursing.upenn.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>31</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>19</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>167</fpage>
<lpage>173</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.aucc.2017.12.091-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Background</title>
<p id="P1">Clinicians recognize that some critically ill children are difficult-to-sedate. It may be possible to identify this clinical phenotype for sedation response using statistical modeling techniques adopted from machine learning. This requires identification of a finite number of variables to include in the statistical model.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Objective</title>
<p id="P2">To establish face and content validity for 17 candidate variables identified in the international literature as characteristic of the difficult-to-sedate child phenotype.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P3">Pediatric critical care clinicians rated the relevance of 17 variables characterizing the difficult-to-sedate child using a four-point scale ranging from not (1) to highly relevant (4). Face and content validity of these variables were assessed by calculating a mean score for each item and computing an item-level content validity index. Items with a mean score &gt;1 were rated as having adequate face validity. An item-level content validity index ≥0.70 indicated good to excellent content validity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Setting and Participants</title>
<p id="P4">Web-based survey emailed to members of the Pediatric Acute Lung Injury &amp; Sepsis Investigators Network or the Society of Critical Care Medicine Pediatric Sedation Study Group.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P5">Of 411 possible respondents, 121 useable surveys were returned for a response rate of 29%. All items had a mean score &gt;1, indicating adequate face validity. Ten of 17 items scored an item-level content validity index ≥0.70. The highest scoring items were requiring three or more sedation classes simultaneously, daily modal sedation score indicating agitation, sedation score indicating agitation for 2 consecutive hours, receiving sedatives at a dose &gt;90th percentile of the usual starting dose and receiving intermittent paralytic doses for sedation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P6">Computation of an item-level content validity index validated variables to include in statistical modeling of the difficult-to-sedate phenotype. The results indicate consensus among pediatric critical care clinicians that the majority of candidate variables identified through literature review are characteristic of the difficult-to-sedate child.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>child</kwd>
<kwd>infant</kwd>
<kwd>intensive care</kwd>
<kwd>critical care</kwd>
<kwd>sedation</kwd>
<kwd>surveys</kwd>
<kwd>questionnaires</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>