<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0375361</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4604</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Child Psychol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Child Psychol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of child psychology and psychiatry, and allied disciplines</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9630</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1469-7610</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27861851</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5993542</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpp.12650</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS894541</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Infant social attention: an endophenotype of ASD-related traits?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>Emily J.H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Venema</surname>
<given-names>Kaitlin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Earl</surname>
<given-names>Rachel K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lowy</surname>
<given-names>Rachel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>Sara J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Centre for Brain and Cognitive Development, Birkbeck, University of London, London, UK</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Center on Human Development and Disability, University of Washington, Seattle, WA</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of School Psychology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, WA</aff>
<aff id="A5">
<label>5</label>Center for Child Health, Behavior &amp; Development, Seattle Children’s Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1"><bold>Correspondence</bold>: Emily J. H. Jones, Centre for Brain and Cognitive Development, Birkbeck, University of London, Malet Street, London WC1E 7HX, UK; <email>ubejon01@mail.bbk.ac.uk</email>; Sara J. Webb, Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of Washington, Box 357920, Seattle, WA 98195, USA; <email>sjwebb@uw.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>Conflict of interest statement: No conflicts declared.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN4">
<p>The authors declare that they have no potential or competing conflicts of interests with relation to this report.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>16</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>08</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>08</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>58</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>270</fpage>
<lpage>281</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1111/jcpp.12650-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Background</title>
<p id="P1">As a neurodevelopmental disorder, symptoms of ASD likely emerge from a complex interaction between preexisting genetic vulnerabilities and the child’s environment. One way to understand causal paths to ASD is to identify dimensional ASD-related traits that vary in the general population and that predispose individuals with other risk factors toward ASD. Moving beyond behavioral traits to explore underlying neurocognitive processes may further constrain the underlying genetics. Endophenotypes are quantitative, heritable, trait-related differences that are generally assessed with laboratory-based methods, can be identified in the general population, and may be more closely tied to particular causal chains that have a more restricted set of genetic roots. The most fruitful endophenotypes may be those observed in infancy, prior to the emergence of behavioral symptoms that they are hypothesized to cause. Social motivation is an ASD-related trait that is highly heritable. In this study, we investigate whether infant endophenotypes of social attention relate to familial risk for lower social motivation in the general population.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P2">We examined whether infant social attention (measured using habituation, EEG power, and event-related potential tasks previously used in infants/toddlers with ASD) varies quantitatively with parental social motivation in 117 six-month-old and 106 twelve-month-old typically developing infants assessed cross-sectionally. To assess heritable aspects of social motivation, primary caregiver biological parents completed two self-report measures of social avoidance and discomfort that have shown high heritability in previous work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">Parents with higher social discomfort and avoidance had infants who showed shorter looks to faces but not objects; reduced theta power during naturalistic social attention; and smaller P400 responses to faces versus objects.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P4">Early reductions in social attention are continuously related to lower parental social motivation. Alterations in social attention may be infant endophenotypes of social motivation traits related to ASD.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Autism spectrum disorders</kwd>
<kwd>infancy</kwd>
<kwd>endophenotype</kwd>
<kwd>social attention</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>