<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29950608</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6021387</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">28090</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-28090-w</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Maternal Vitamin D Prevents Abnormal Dopaminergic Development and Function in a Mouse Model of Prenatal Immune Activation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luan</surname>
<given-names>Wei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hammond</surname>
<given-names>Luke Alexander</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vuillermot</surname>
<given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7244-0345</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>Urs</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>Darryl Walter</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>eyles@uq.edu.au</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9320 7537</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1003.2</institution-id><institution>Queensland Brain Institute, </institution><institution>The University of Queensland, </institution></institution-wrap>Brisbane, QLD Australia </aff>
<aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000419368729</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.21729.3f</institution-id><institution>Zuckerman Mind Brain Behavior Institute, </institution><institution>Columbia University, </institution></institution-wrap>New York, New York USA </aff>
<aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2156 2780</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5801.c</institution-id><institution>Physiology and Behavior Laboratory, </institution><institution>ETH Zurich, </institution></institution-wrap>Schwerzenbach, Switzerland </aff>
<aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0650</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7400.3</institution-id><institution>Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, </institution><institution>University of Zurich-Vetsuisse, </institution></institution-wrap>Zurich, Switzerland </aff>
<aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0650</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7400.3</institution-id><institution>Neuroscience Centre Zurich, </institution><institution>University of Zurich and ETH Zurich, </institution></institution-wrap>Zurich, Switzerland </aff>
<aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0624 0996</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466965.e</institution-id><institution>Queensland Centre for Mental Health Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Brisbane, QLD Australia </aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>27</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>27</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<elocation-id>9741</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>8</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>13</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement>
<license license-type="OpenAccess">
<license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="Par1">Dysfunction in dopamine (DA) systems is a prominent feature in schizophrenia patients and may result from the abnormal development of mesencephalic (mes)DA systems. Maternal immune activation (MIA) and developmental vitamin D (DVD)-deficiency both induce schizophrenia-relevant dopaminergic abnormalities in adult offspring. In this study, we investigated whether maternal administration of the vitamin D hormone (1,25OHD, VIT<sub>D</sub>) could prevent MIA-induced abnormalities in DA-related behaviors and mesDA development. We administrated the viral mimetic polyriboinosinic-polyribocytidylic (poly (I:C)) simultaneously with 1,25OHD and/or their vehicles, to pregnant mouse dams at gestational day 9. Maternal treatment with VIT<sub>D</sub> prevented MIA-induced hypersensitivity to acute DA stimulation induced by amphetamine, whereas it failed to block prepulse inhibition deficiency in MIA-exposed offspring. MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> both reduced fetal mesDA progenitor (Lmx1a + Sox2+) cells, while VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment increased the number of mature (Nurr1 + TH+) mesDA neurons. Single-cell quantification of protein expression showed that VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment increased the expression of Lmx1a, Nurr1 and TH in individual mesDA cells and restored normal mesDA positioning. Our data demonstrate that VIT<sub>D</sub> prevents abnormal dopaminergic phenotypes in MIA offspring possibly via its early neuroprotective actions on fetal mesDA neurons. Maternal supplementation with the dietary form of vitamin D, cholecalciferol may become a valuable strategy for the prevention of MIA-induced neurodevelopmental abnormalities.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000925</institution-id>
<institution>Department of Health | National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>APP 1057883</award-id>
<award-id>APP 1057883</award-id>
<award-id>APP 1057883</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name>
<surname>Luan</surname>
<given-names>Wei</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>Urs</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>Darryl Walter</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001711</institution-id>
<institution>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur F&amp;amp;#x00F6;rderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung (Swiss National Science Foundation)</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>310030_169544</award-id>
<award-id>310030_169544</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name>
<surname>Vuillermot</surname>
<given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>Urs</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
<meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="Par2">Today schizophrenia is conceptualized as a polygenetic disorder possibly triggered by diverse environmental factors. Epidemiological studies implicate a growing number of pre- and perinatal environmental risk factors, including fetal hypoxia, obstetric complications, maternal infection and/or immune activation (MIA), and certain nutritional deficiencies such as developmental vitamin D (DVD)-deficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. These factors combine to affect the normal trajectory of brain development in ways that remain opaque.</p>
<p id="Par3">Dopamine dysregulation has long been proposed as an important pathophysiological feature of schizophrenia. Molecular imaging studies suggest that neurochemical abnormalities of presynaptic dopamine (DA) uptake and/or release may be core to the psychotic component in most schizophrenic patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. We have proposed that early alterations in the trajectory of developing DA neurons may represent a first step in the journey towards the dopaminergic changes observed in schizophrenia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par4">Animal models of MIA and DVD-deficiency provide support for this hypothesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Not only do these models capture DA-related behavioral and cognitive deficits relevant to schizophrenia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, but also they suggest that dopaminergic alterations originate in early fetal development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. DA neurons are born very early around 5 weeks post conception (1<sup>st</sup> trimester) in the human embryonic mesencephalon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, which is roughly equivalent to gestational day (GD) 9.5 in mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. MIA on GD 9 affects the genesis of mesencephalic dopamine (mesDA) neurons and affects the expression of genes crucial for their establishment, including sonic hedgehog (SHH) and fibroblast growth factor 8 (FGF8)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. MIA also changes the fetal expression of nuclear receptor related 1 protein (Nurr1), which is essential for mesDA differentiation and maintenance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. In DVD-deficient rat fetuses, the ratio of DA neurons between the two major mesDA neuronal subgroups (the substantia nigra pars compacta (SNc) and ventral tegmental area (VTA)), are altered<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. DVD-deficiency in rats also reduces the expression of Nurr1 and tyrosine hydroxylase (TH), the rate-limiting enzyme in DA synthesis in mesDAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. MIA and DVD-deficiency in rodents also lead to altered DA metabolisms in neonatal brains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par5">MIA is also a risk factor for other psychiatric conditions most noticeably autism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Using a MIA model that is based on maternal treatment with the viral mimetic polyriboinosinic-polyribocytidylic (poly (I:C)), we have recently shown that when the active vitamin D hormone (1,25OHD) (here on referred to as VIT<sub>D</sub>) is administered to MIA-exposed dams simultaneously with poly(I:C), it prevents certain MIA-induced behavioral deficits in associative learning, stereotyped digging and social interaction in juvenile offspring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Such behavioural disruptions are consistent but not exclusive to autism-related phenotypes. In the present study, we investigated whether administration of VIT<sub>D</sub> to MIA-exposed dams also prevents DA-related behavioral alterations in MIA offspring. We further explored the effects of VIT<sub>D</sub> and MIA on the expression of factors involved in early mesDA neuron maturation. To this aim, we established an automated image analysis method for the identification and measurement of individual mesDA cells. This method allowed us to assess the acute effects of MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments on mesDA neurogenesis and maturation at the single-cell level. GD11 was chosen to examine post-MIA effects at this time point, which allowed us to assess both active mesDA neurogenesis and the early stages of mesDA neuron maturation. We show that although MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> both reduced mesDA progenitor numbers, VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment increased mature mesDA neuron number and increased the expression of key mesDA differentiation factors. Therefore, one plausible neuroprotective action of VIT<sub>D</sub> may be its pro-differentiating role in mesDA neurogenesis in the MIA-exposed fetuses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="Sec3">
<title>Animals</title>
<p id="Par6">Female and male breeder C57BL6/N mice were obtained from Charles River Laboratories (Sulzfeld, Germany) at the age of 12–14 weeks. They were kept in regular open cage systems (Macrolon Type-III, Turnhout, Belgium) and had had a libitum access to water and standard rodent chow (Kliba 3430, Kaiseraugst, Switzerland) that contained 1000IU cholecalciferol/kg. Breeding began after 2 weeks of acclimatization to the animal holding rooms. Animals were housed and tested under a reversed light–dark cycle (lights on from 19h00 to 07h00). All procedures described in the present study had been approved by the Cantonal Veterinarian’s Office of Zurich, and all efforts were made to minimize the number of animals used and their suffering.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec4">
<title>Experimental groups</title>
<p id="Par7">The active hormonal form of VIT<sub>D</sub> (1α, 25-dihydroxy vitamin D3 = 1,25OHD; solid powder, Calbiochem, EMD Millipore, Cat No 679101-50UG, Switzerland) was prepared as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Sterile corn oil (Sigma–Aldrich, Switzerland) was used as vehicle (VEH). Poly(I:C) (potassium salt; Sigma–Aldrich, Switzerland) was prepared using sterile, pyrogen-free 0.9% NaCl (saline), and injected as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Saline (CON) was used as the vehicle for poly (I:C).</p>
<p id="Par8">C57BL6/N female mice were subjected to a timed-mating procedure as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Pregnant dams on GD 9 were first injected subcutaneously with VIT<sub>D</sub> (400 ng/kg/2 ml) or vehicle (VEH), and then immediately injected intravenously with either poly(I:C) (POL, 5 mg/kg; calculated based on the pure form) or saline solution (CON) at a volume of 5 ml/kg as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Thus, the experiment consisted of 4 groups: CON-VEH, CON-VIT<sub>D</sub>, POL-VEH, POL-VIT<sub>D</sub>. VIT<sub>D</sub> dose was chosen based on pilot studies that showed no effects on AMPH-mediated locomotion or PPI (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec5">
<title>Behavioral Studies</title>
<p id="Par9">Weaned offspring were housed in same-sex groups of 3–4 animals per cage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Behavioral testing was conducted at 10 weeks of age. To minimize possible confounds arising from litter effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, only 1 male offspring per litter was randomly selected. Hence, the number of offspring in each experimental group was equal to the number of treated dams. The group sizes were as follows: <italic>N</italic>(CON-VEH) = 11, <italic>N</italic>(CON-VIT<sub>D</sub>) = 8, <italic>N</italic>(POL-VEH) = 11, and <italic>N</italic>(POL-VIT<sub>D</sub>) = 8. All offspring were first subjected to prepulse inhibition (PPI), followed by amphetamine (AMPH) locomotion two to three days later. All behavioral tests were performed in the dark phase of the light-dark cycle.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec6">
<title>Prepulse Inhibition of the Acoustic Startle Reflex</title>
<p id="Par10">PPI was conducted using startle chambers (San Diego Instruments, California, USA) as described previously (for details see suppl methods)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. PPI was indexed by percentage inhibition of the startle response obtained in pulse-alone trials by the following expression: 100% × (1 − [mean reactivity on prepulse-plus- pulse trials/mean reactivity on pulse-alone trials]). In addition, the animals’ reactivity to pulse-alone trials (i.e., startle reactivity) and prepulse-alone trials (i.e., prepulse-induced reactivity) were also measured and analyzed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec7">
<title>Spontaneous and Amphetamine-induced Locomotor Activity</title>
<p id="Par11">Testing conditions, lighting and amphetamine dose were all as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Briefly, the animals were first acclimatized to the open field for 20 min and were then injected with sterile 0.9% saline and immediately returned to the same arenas for another 20 min. Subsequently, the animals were injected intraperitoneally (i.p.) with D-amphetamine sulfate (=AMPH; Sigma-Aldrich, Switzerland) at dose of 2.5 mg/kg (5 ml/kg) and monitored for a period of 60 min.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec8">
<title>Fetal Tissue Collection and Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p id="Par12">A second cohort of pregnant dams were prepared and assigned to poly(I:C), VIT<sub>D</sub>, or appropriate vehicle on GD 9 as described above. The number of dams assigned to each treatment group was <italic>N</italic>(CON-VEH) = 5, <italic>N</italic>(CON-VIT<sub>D</sub>) = 4, <italic>N</italic>(POL-VEH) = 5, and <italic>N</italic>(POL-VIT<sub>D</sub>) = 7. Two fetuses per dam were randomly collected (see below), so that the number of fetus in each group was <italic>n</italic>(CON-VEH) = 10, <italic>n</italic>(CON-VIT<sub>D</sub>) = 8, <italic>N</italic>(POL-VEH) = 10, and <italic>N</italic>(POL-VIT<sub>D</sub>) = 14.</p>
<p id="Par13">Fetal mesDA development was assessed at GD11 for the following reasons. First, at this age, the four major mesDA subpopulations we wished to assess (see below) are all present<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Second, by GD 11 the elevation in maternal inflammatory cytokines and chemokines induced by MIA has returned to baseline levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, thus removing any active cytokine-mediated cellular effects. Third, the half-life of 1,25OHD is 4–6 hours<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Therefore, it is likely the active agent would have been eliminated after 48 hrs.</p>
<p id="Par14">To collect the fetuses, dams were decapitated without prior anesthesia. The uterus was exposed and collected fetuses were immersion-fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde overnight. Fixed brains were soaked in 30% sucrose solution prior to embedding (Tissue-Tek, Emgrid, Australia). The mesencephalon cryosections were obtained in a one in three series. Sections were immunohistochemically processed simultaneously to eliminate variability. One series was processed for Sox2/Lmx1a, and a second series for Nurr1/TH. Primary antibodies were: rabbit anti-Sox2 (1:200, Millipore Chemicon, Australia), goat anti-Lmx1a (1:100, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, USA), sheep anti-TH (1:100, Novus Biologicals, USA), and rabbit anti-Nurr1 (1:500, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, USA). Fluorophore-conjugated secondary antibodies were diluted 1:1000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Australia). Nuclei were stained using 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, 1:1000, Sigma-Aldrich, Australia).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec9">
<title>Image acquisition and quantitative immunochemistry</title>
<p id="Par15">Immunostaining was assessed using a confocal microscope (Tie, Nikon Inc.) equipped with a Spectral Applied Research’s Diskovery spinning disk module with an inverted spinning disk. Images were captured and stitched using NIS software (Nikon Inc.). Images were acquired using 60x oil N.A. 1.4 objective (CFI Apo Lamda/W.D. 0.14 mm), providing a pixel size 0.092 × 0.092 µm<sup>2</sup>. Four mesDA subpopulations were assessed: mesDA progenitors (Lmx1a+Sox2+), post-mitotic (Lmx1a+Sox2−) mesDA neurons, immature (Nurr1+TH−) mesDA neurons, and mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDA neurons. Briefly, images were background-corrected using ImageJ software and were then analyzed using CellProfiler software (Broad Institute, Massachusetts, USA). This allowed us to quantify cell number, mediolateral/dorsoventral positions, individual protein expression (mean gray value per cell), and nuclear morphological parameters (for image processing and quantitative immunochemistry details see Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec10">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p id="Par16">All data were analyzed using parametric analysis of variance (ANOVA). Percent PPI was analyzed using a 2 × 2 × 3 × 3 (POL treatment × VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment × pulse level × prepulse level) ANOVA. In the AMPH sensitivity test, the total distance moved was expressed as a function of 5-min bins and was analyzed by 2 × 2 × 4 (POL treatment × VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment × 5-min bins) repeated-measure ANOVAs for the initial habituation and saline-treatment phases, and by 2 × 2 × 12 (POL treatment × VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment × 5-min bins) repeated-measure ANOVA for the subsequent AMPH treatment phase. The quantitative immunochemistry data were analyzed using a 2 × 2 (POL treatment × VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment) ANOVA using a repeated-measure design (repeated for section intervals). The distribution data were analyzed using a 2 × 2 (POL treatment × VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment) ANOVA using a repeated-measure design (repeated for bins). Following these initial ANOVAs, restricted ANOVAs or Dunnett’s Multiple Comparison Tests were conducted whenever appropriate. Statistical significance was set at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec11" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="Sec12">
<title>Effect of maternal VITD treatment on MIA-induced behaviors</title>
<p id="Par17">Consistent with previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, MIA impaired PPI in adult offspring (main overall effect of MIA: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub> = 4.63, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1A</xref>). The MIA-induced effect on PPI was driven primarily by a marked reduction the 110 dB<sub>A</sub> pulse condition (main effect of MIA treatment at the 110 dB<sub>A</sub> condition: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub> = 13.19, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), but not in the 100 or 120 dB<sub>A</sub> conditions (100 dB<sub>A</sub>: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub> = 0.67, <italic>p</italic> = 0.42; 120 dB<sub>A</sub>: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub> = 3.04, <italic>p</italic> = 0.09). Maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment did not prevent MIA-induced PPI impairments (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1A</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The effects of single and combined MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> on prepulse inhibition and amphetamine sensitivity in adult offspring. (<bold>A</bold>) Prepulse inhibition (PPI) of the acoustic startle reflex was used to investigate sensorimotor gating in adult offspring. %PPI is shown for three startling amplitudes (100, 110 and 120 dB<sub>A</sub>, which are noted as P-100, P-110 and P-120, respectively) and prepulse intensities (71, 77 and 83 dB<sub>A</sub>, corresponding to +6, +12 and +18 dB<sub>A</sub> above background white noise). Poly(I:C) exposure impaired P-110dB<sub>A</sub> PPI. The bar plots represent the mean %PPI for all prepulse and pulse levels. All values were medians ±SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, reflecting the significant main effect of MIA on mean % PPI; <sup>***</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, reflecting the significant main effect of MIA in the P-110 condition. (<bold>B</bold>) The line plot shows total distance travelled in an open field per bin (=5 min) during initial habituation and subsequent saline administration periods, followed by the amphetamine (AMPH; 2.5 mg/kg, i.p.) administration phase. <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, reflecting the significant difference between POL-VEH and CON-VEH offspring (AMPH bins 1–9); <sup>+</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, reflecting the significant difference between POL-VEH and POL-Vit<sub>D</sub> offspring (AMPH bins 11 and 12). All values were means ± SEM.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e782" xlink:href="41598_2018_28090_Fig1_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par18">In contrast, maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment prevented the emergence of AMPH hypersensitivity in offspring exposed to MIA. In line with previous findings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, AMPH-induced locomotor activity was increased in MIA offspring (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1B</xref>). This effect of MIA was blocked when pregnant dams were co-treated with VIT<sub>D</sub>, leading to a significant three-way interaction between POL treatment, VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment, and bins (<italic>F</italic><sub>(11,34)</sub> = 1.83, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Subsequent post-hoc group comparisons at each individual 5-min bin confirmed a significant increase in POL-VEH mediated locomotion relative to CON-VEH offspring (all p &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1B</xref>), and between POL-VEH and POL-Vit<sub>D</sub> offspring at bin 11 and 12 (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1B</xref>). Neither MIA nor maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment affected locomotor activity in the initial habituation and saline treatment phases of the test (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1B</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec13">
<title>MIA and VITD treatments both reduce mesDA progenitor number</title>
<p id="Par19">At GD11, mesDA progenitors are still proliferating<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Here we examined mesDA progenitors co-expressing the mesDA specification factor Lmx1a and the neural stem cell transcription factor Sox2 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2A–D and A’–D’</xref>). Sox2 is absent in post-mitotic Lmx1a + mesDAs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2C–D and C’–D’</xref>). There was a significant interaction between MIA and maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment on the number of mesDA progenitors (Lmx1a+Sox2 +) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 5.19, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2E</xref>). Post hoc comparisons revealed that mesDA progenitors were significantly reduced in MIA-treated fetuses (POL-VEH) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 6.68, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), VIT<sub>D</sub>-treated fetuses (CON-VIT<sub>D</sub>) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 8.12, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and MIA-VIT<sub>D</sub> co-treated fetuses (POL-VIT<sub>D</sub>) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 4.51, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) relative to controls (CON-VEH). Hence, MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> both reduced mesDA progenitor numbers in GD11 fetuses.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The effects of single and combined MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> on early mesencephalic dopamine (mesDA) cell number. (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) Fate mapping of developing mesDA cells in a medial coronal mesencephalic (MES) sections at gestational day (GD) 11. Markers are the nuclear dye DAPI (blue, A), mesDA specification factor Lmx1a (green, B), neuronal progenitor maker Sox2 (red, C), and a channel-merged image (<bold>D</bold>). (A’–D’) Higher magnification images of the dashed outlined boxes representing the floor plate (FP) from (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) accordingly. Lmx1a specifically marked mesDA cells in the FP dorsoventrally from ventricular zone (VZ), intermediate zone (IZ) to mantle zone (MZ). MesDA progenitors (Lmx1a+Sox2+) were primarily located in the proliferative VZ, in contrast, post-mitotic (Lmx1a+Sox2−) mesDAs were mostly located in IZ and MZ. (<bold>E</bold>) The cell number of these two mesDA subpopulations were counted using CellProfiler software at 60 µm intervals along the anterior-posterior (A–P) axis. The numbers of mesDA progenitors (Lmx1a+Sox2+) were reduced by all treatments relative to the control (CON-VEH) (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05). (<bold>F</bold>) Post-mitotic (Lmx1a+Sox2−) mesDA number was not altered by any treatment. (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>J</bold>) Fate mapping of post-mitotic mesDA subgroups that are characterized by Nurr1 and TH in medial coronal MES sections at GD11. Markers are the nuclear dye DAPI (blue, <bold>G</bold>), Nurr1 (magenta, H), TH (green, I), and a channel-merged image (J). (G’–J’) Higher magnification images of the dashed outlined boxes representing FP from (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>J</bold>) accordingly. Immature Nurr1+ mesDAs were primarily located in the IZ and MZ. Mature (Nurr1+ TH+) mesDAs were primarily located in MZ. (<bold>K</bold>) There were no significant differences of immature mesDA number among treatment groups (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05). (<bold>L</bold>) VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment itself increased mature (Nurr1+ TH+) mesDA number compared to its vehicle (VEH) (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment itself (CON-VIT<sub>D</sub>) particularly increased mature mesDA number in the posterior MES compared to control (CON-VEH) (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05). All values were means ± SEM. <sup>*</sup>P &lt; 0.05. n.s., represents not statistically significant. Scale bars: 100 µm (A–D and G–J); 50 µm (A’–D’ and G’–J’).</p></caption><graphic id="d29e992" xlink:href="41598_2018_28090_Fig2_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec14">
<title>Maternal VITD treatment increases the number of mature mesDAs</title>
<p id="Par20">Consistent with previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, immature (Nurr1+TH−) cells were found in the IZ, whereas mature (Nurr1+TH+) cells were largely restricted to the MZ (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2G–J and G’-J’</xref>). MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> had no effect on the number of immature mesDAs (<italic>p</italic>’s &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2K</xref>). However, there was a significant main effect of maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment on mature mesDAs (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,40)</sub> = 5.574, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2L</xref>). Significant interactions of MIA x VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments with section position was also found along the anterior-posterior (A-P) axis of the MES (<italic>F</italic><sub>(6,240)</sub> = 2.941, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Post hoc comparison revealed that VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment itself (CON-VIT<sub>D</sub>) increased mature mesDA number relative to control (CON-VEH), particularly in the posterior MES (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec15">
<title>MIA and VITD treatments affect the position of mesDA progenitors and mature mesDAs</title>
<p id="Par21">CellProfiler allowed us to position individual mesDAs in the floor plate (FP). We assessed the average mediolateral (ML) position, (<italic>x</italic> distance from the midline of the coronal MES section, <italic>x</italic><sub>0</sub>) and average dorsoventral (DV) position (<italic>y</italic> distance from the most ventral point of the ventricle, <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3A,B</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The effects of single and combined MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments on the coronal positioning of mature mesencephalic dopamine neurons (mesDAs). (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic image of registered floor plate (FP) in a medial coronal mesencephalic (MES) section with mediolateral (ML, <italic>x</italic>) and dorsoventral (DV, <italic>y</italic>) positions of cells. The coordinates (<italic>x</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>) were chosen as the most ventral point of ventricle (V) along the midline (*). The black dot represents the mean center positioning (<italic>x</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>, <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>) of a representative mesDA nucleus (ellipse). The ML positioning (<italic>x</italic>) of mesDA cells was measured bilaterally as the absolute distance from the center of mesDA nucleus (<italic>x</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>) to the coordinate (<italic>x</italic><sub>0</sub>) = <italic>ABS</italic> (<italic>x</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub><italic>−x</italic><sub>0</sub>). The DV positioning (<italic>y</italic>) of mesDA cell was calculated as the distance from the center of mesDA nucleus (<italic>y</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>) to the coordinate (<italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>) = (<italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>−<italic>y</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>). (<bold>B</bold>) An example of mesDA positioning in the FP. Yellow dots represent mesDA progenitors (Lmx1a+Sox2+), and green dots represent post-mitotic (Lmx1a+Sox2−) mesDAs. (<bold>C</bold>) A representative FP section showing cells that were triple-labeled by DAPI (blue), Lmx1a (green) and Sox2 (red). No significant effects of MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment were noticeable for the mean ML (<bold>D</bold>) or DV (<bold>E</bold>) positioning of mesDA progenitors (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05). (<bold>F</bold>) There were no significant effects of MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments on the mean ML positioning of post-mitotic (Lmx1a+Sox2−) mesDAs (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05). (<bold>G</bold>) There were significant interactions between MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments on the average DV positioning of post-mitotic (Lmx1a+Sox2−) (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). MIA treatment (POL-VEH) reduced the DV positioning of post-mitotic mesDAs compared to its control (CON-VEH) (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). (<bold>H</bold>) A representative FP of a coronal MES section showing cells that were triple-labeled by DAPI (blue), Nurr1 (magenta) and TH (green). There were no significant effects of MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment for the mean ML (<bold>I</bold>) or DV (<bold>J</bold>) positioning of immature (Nurr1+TH−) mesDAs in the FP (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05). (<bold>K</bold>) MIA treatment (POL) reduced the mean ML positioning of mesDAs relative to CON (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). (<bold>L</bold>) There were significant interactions between MIA x VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments in the average DV positioning of mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDAs (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Post hoc comparison revealed MIA treatment (POL-VEH) decreased the mean DV positioning relative to the control (CON-VEH) (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Additionally, the co-treatment of VIT<sub>D</sub> restored the mean DV positioning of mature mesDAs in POL-VIT<sub>D</sub> group compared to POL-VEH group (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). All values were means ± SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. n.s. represents not statistically significant. Scale bars: 50 µm.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1264" xlink:href="41598_2018_28090_Fig3_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par22">MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> had no effect on the ML or DV positioning of mesDA progenitors (Lmx1a + Sox2+) in the FP (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3C–E</xref>). There were also no significant effects of MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments on the average ML positioning of post-mitotic (Lmx1a + Sox2−) mesDAs (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3F</xref>). There was significant interactions between MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments on the average DV positioning of post-mitotic (Lmx1a + Sox2−) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 4.616, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3G</xref>). Subsequent post hoc comparison revealed that MIA treatment (POL-VEH) reduced the DV positioning of post-mitotic mesDAs compared to its control (CON-VEH) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 5.997, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
<p id="Par23">There were no significant main effects or interactions of MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments on the average ML or DV positioning of immature (Nurr1 + TH−) mesDAs in the FP (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3H–J</xref>). In contrast, there was a significant main effect of MIA treatment on the mean ML positioning of mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDAs (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,40)</sub> = 5.962, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3K</xref>). In addition, there were significant interactions between MIA x VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments in the average DV positioning of mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDAs (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,40)</sub> = 5.128, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3L</xref>). Post hoc comparisons showed that MIA treatment (POL-VEH) reduced the DV positioning of mature mesDAs compared to its control (CON-VEH) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,40)</sub> = 5.871, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Most intriguingly, abnormal DV positioning of mature mesDAs in MIA fetuses was restored by the co-administration of VIT<sub>D</sub> (POL-VIT<sub>D</sub>) (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,40)</sub> = 6.125, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec16">
<title>VITD treatment increases the expression of Lmx1a, Nurr1 and TH proteins in mesDAs</title>
<p id="Par24">mesDA proliferation, specification and differentiation are tightly regulated by the transcription factors Sox2, Lmx1a and Nurr1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. CellProfiler analysis allowed us to quantify the protein expression of these factors in individual mesDA cells by measuring the mean fluorescence intensity of these factors.</p>
<sec id="Sec17">
<title>Sox2 expression</title>
<p id="Par25">MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> had no effect on the mean intensity of Sox2 fluorescence in individual mesDA progenitors (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4B</xref>). Distribution analysis also confirmed Sox2 staining was constant across all treatments (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4C</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec18">
<title>Lmx1a expression</title>
<p id="Par26">There was a significant main effect of VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment on the mean intensity of Lmx1a expression (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 5.891, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and significant interactions between MIA x VIT<sub>D</sub> treatments (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,36)</sub> = 7.993, p &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4E</xref>). Post hoc comparisons revealed that Lmx1a expression was significantly higher in individual cells of CON- VIT<sub>D</sub> fetuses compared to CON-VEH (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and the other two treatment groups (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05). Supporting this, the distribution analysis of Lmx 1a+ demonstrated that more CON-VIT<sub>D</sub> mesDA cells expressed higher levels of Lmx1a compared to other treatment groups (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4F</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The effects of single and combined MIA and VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment on the expression of factors important in the development of mesDA neurons. (<bold>A</bold>) A representative floor plate (FP) of coronal MES section showing mesDA cells expressing Sox2 (red). (<bold>B</bold>) Neither MIA or VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment altered the mean intensity of Sox2 in mesDA progenitors (Lmx1a+Sox2+) (<italic>p’s</italic> &gt; 0.05). (<bold>C</bold>) Bar plots represent the average fluorescence of Sox2 in mesDA progenitors among treatment groups. Distribution analysis representing a nonlinear regression to predict the Gaussian distribution of mesDA progenitor number relative to the intensity of Sox2 expression. (<bold>D</bold>) A representative FP of coronal MES section showing post-mitotic mesDA cells expressing Lmx1a (green). (<bold>E</bold>) VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment significantly increased the mean intensity of Lmx1a in mesDAs compared with other treatment groups (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05). (<bold>F</bold>) Bar plots represent the average expression of Lmx1a among treatment groups. Distribution analysis showed VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment itself increased the number of cells expressing higher levels of Lmx1a compared to other treatment groups (<italic>p’s</italic> &lt; 0.05). (<bold>G</bold>) A representative FP of coronal MES section showing post-mitotic mesDA cells expressing Nurr1 (magenta). (<bold>H</bold>) VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment significantly increased the expression of Nurr1 in post-mitotic (Nurr1+) mesDAs (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). (<bold>I</bold>) Bar plots represent the average fluorescence of Nurr1 among treatment groups. Distribution analysis showed VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment increased the number of cells expressing higher levels of Nurr1 compared to VEH (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). (<bold>J</bold>) A representative FP of coronal MES section showing mature mesDAs expressing TH (green). (<bold>K</bold>) VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment increased the average fluorescence of TH in mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDAs. (<bold>L</bold>) Bar plots represent the average TH mean intensity in mature mesDAs among treatment groups. The distribution analysis verified that VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment increased the number of mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDAs that expressed higher levels of TH compared to VEH (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). All values were means ± SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01. Scale bars: 50 µm.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1549" xlink:href="41598_2018_28090_Fig4_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec19">
<title>Nurr1 expression</title>
<p id="Par27">There was a significant main effect of VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment on Nurr1 expression in individual post-mitotic mesDAs (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,40)</sub> = 14.451, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4H</xref>). Supporting this, the distribution analysis revealed significant main effects of VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment where more mesDAs had greater Nurr1 expression (<italic>F</italic><sub>(19, 684)</sub> = 6.243, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4I</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec20">
<title>TH Expression</title>
<p id="Par28">There was a significant main effect of VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment on TH expression in individual mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDAs (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,40)</sub> = 12.817, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4K</xref>). Supporting this, the distribution analysis revealed significant main effects of VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment where more mature mesDAs had greater TH expression (<italic>F</italic><sub>(19,684)</sub> = 5.301, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4L</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="Sec22">
<title>VITD abolishes MIA-induced sensitivity to AMPH</title>
<p id="Par29">Rodent models of MIA and DVD-deficiency both exhibit early molecular and behavioural abnormalities consistent with altered DA signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, suggesting a common pathogenic pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. In support of this hypothesis, the present study shows that co-administration of VIT<sub>D</sub> during gestation prevents the MIA-induced potentiation of AMPH sensitivity in adult offspring. It thus appears that the process leading to AMPH hypersensitivity in MIA offspring is initiated during early fetal development, such that interventions targeting the initiation process (e.g., through co-administration of VIT<sub>D</sub> during gestation) are capable of preventing the subsequent establishment of this phenotype.</p>
<p id="Par30">The failure of VIT<sub>D</sub> to block MIA-induced impairments in PPI may seem counterintuitive at first, given that dopaminergic mechanisms have also been implicated in this association<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. More specifically, previous studies found that acute and chronic administration of DA receptor antagonists in adulthood and adolescence, respectively, mitigated PPI deficits in adult MIA offspring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. While these findings clearly point to an involvement of the DA system in the adolescent and/or adult expression of PPI, they are not informative with regards to the underlying developmental processes occurring prior to adolescence. Based on the present data, we propose that MIA-induced alterations in PPI and AMPH sensitivity have a differential ontogeny. This hypothesis is also consistent with our previous findings showing that (i) whilst DVD-deficiency induces locomotor sensitivity to AMPH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, it does not impair PPI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, and (ii) MIA-induced PPI impairments are not critically dependent on the mesDA differentiation and maintenance factor, Nurr1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, the latter of which we find to be deregulated in the fetal brain after DVD-deficiency or MIA.</p>
<p id="Par31">The acute elevation of inflammatory cytokines is proposed as one of the primary pathways leading to neuropsychiatric phenotypes in MIA offspring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Given the well-known anti-inflammatory actions of vitamin D, this could well represent its neuroprotective mechanism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. However, we have previously reported that VIT<sub>D</sub> co-treatment in this model failed to affect poly(I:C)-induced elevations in IL-6, IL-1ß and TNF alpha, in either maternal serum or fetal brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Although there may be other inflammatory factors/processes involved<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, our current findings suggest an alternative neuroprotective mechanism. Based on our novel data presented here, we believe that maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> may exert its beneficial effects through actions on the developing DA system.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec23">
<title>Both MIA and VITD decrease mesDA progenitor numbers, but only VITD increases mature mesDA number</title>
<p id="Par32">All maternal treatments reduced mesDA progenitor (Lmx1a+Sox2+) numbers. There are likely to be distinct mechanisms for these effects, and consequences thereof as well. Whilst the MIA-induced reduction in mesDA progenitor cells was accompanied by the subsequent emergence of behavioral deficits, maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> was without consequences on offspring behavior per se. Mechanistically, the effects of MIA on mesDA progenitor numbers likely involve the inhibition of neural progenitor formation via signaling at toll-like 3 receptors (TLR3), which are expressed early in the embryonic brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. The pro-inflammatory cytokines induced by MIA can inhibit neural proliferation as well<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par33">Contrary to MIA, maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> may reduce mesDA progenitor numbers by means of shifting the progenitor cells to a more differentiated phenotype. Indeed, the pro-differentiation properties of VIT<sub>D</sub> in neurons and in the brain are well described. <italic>In vitro</italic> VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment differentiates neural stem cells into neurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>; SH-SY5Y cells into DA neurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and inhibits neural progenitor formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. In contrast, the <italic>absence</italic> of vitamin D during gestation leads to effects that are diametrically opposite to those reported here, namely an increase in mitosis across multiple brain regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> and enhanced neural progenitor formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par34">Importantly, our study further shows that VIT<sub>D</sub> and MIA have divergent effects on mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDA neuron number. Although not significant, MIA clearly appeared to reduce (Nurr1 + TH+) mesDA cell number. In contrast, VIT<sub>D</sub> increased (Nurr1+TH+) mesDA number, particularly for the more posterior mesDAs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2L</xref>). A VIT<sub>D</sub>-mediated restoration of TH cell number therefore represents one plausible mechanism for the normalization of DA-mediated behaviours in MIA exposed offspring.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec24">
<title>VITD restores MIA-induced alterations in the distribution of mesDAs</title>
<p id="Par35">For post-mitotic neurons, we show that MIA alters the mean DV positioning of post-mitotic (Lmx1a+Sox2−) mesDAs and the ML positioning of mature (Nurr1+TH+) mesDAs. VIT<sub>D</sub> co-treatment did not rescue these deficits. However when examining the DV positioning of mature mesDAs, we show a profound MIA-induced reduction in DV positioning, which was fully prevented by VIT<sub>D</sub>. Importantly, VIT<sub>D</sub> by itself had no effect on ML or DV positioning of any mesDA neuron type. Therefore, the correction of early mis-positioning of mesDA neurons by VIT<sub>D</sub> could represent another plausible mechanism for the normalization of DA-mediated behaviours in MIA-exposed offspring.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec25">
<title>VITD regulates protein expression of key mesDA factors</title>
<p id="Par36">VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment increased the expression of all mesDA-related proteins examined. In contrast, MIA by itself had no significant effects on the expression of these proteins.</p>
<p id="Par37">Here, we show that VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment upregulates the expression of Lmx1a in developing mesDAs. Lmx1a is a convergent upstream molecule from SHH-Wnt pathways that specify mesDA lineage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. SHH and Wnt signaling are affected in MIA and DVD-deficiency models respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par38">Nurr1 a direct upstream target of Lmx1a promotes mesDA differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. MIA and DVD-deficiency reduce the mRNA expression of Nurr1 in the fetal brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. This is consistent with present cell counting data, which indicates a recognizable (but not significant) reduction in Nurr1<sup>+</sup> cell number in MIA embryos. At an individual cell level, however, the remaining cells have normal Nurr1 protein expression. Therefore, the likely explanation for previous findings showing reduced Nurr1 mRNA expression in MIA fetuses is a reduction in cell number<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Importantly, genetic deficiency of Nurr1 has previously been shown to induce AMPH hypersensitivity in a similar way to MIA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. Therefore the promotion of Nurr1 expression by VIT<sub>D</sub> may represent a third mechanism for the prevention of AMPH hypersensitivity in MIA exposed offspring.</p>
<p id="Par39">Lmx1a and Nurr1 regulate the expression of TH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. We have shown VIT<sub>D</sub> elevates TH mRNA and protein in neuroblastomas in culture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Again consistent with these findings the absence of VIT<sub>D</sub> in DVD-deficiency leads to the downregulation of TH in fetal rodent brains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Here, we verified that VIT<sub>D</sub> increases the expression of TH <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p>
<p id="Par40">In summary VIT<sub>D</sub> increases the expression of the mesDA transcription factors (Lmx1a and Nurr1) and the rate-limiting enzyme in DA synthesis (TH) in developing mesDA cells. The expression of these three factors in control mesDAs clearly increases with differentiation state (Fig <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S4</xref>). Therefore VIT<sub>D</sub> acts to differentiate the remaining mesDAs in MIA-exposed embryos. This represents a highly plausible mechanism for the prevention of DA-related behavioural deficits induced by MIA. Given that VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment itself has no effect on the behaviours examined here and those examined previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, we conclude that the accelerated maturation effects of VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment alone on mesDAs is benign.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec26">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p id="Par41">Although our findings provide more data for the translational relevance of introducing dietary intervention during early pregnancy for the prevention of developmental psychiatric diseases, the direct supplementation of the hormonal form of vitamin D, 1,25OHD, to pregnant women would adversely affect calcium in the developing embryo and therefore is not clinically feasible. Therefore preclinical replication studies are now warranted using the safe to use dietary form of vitamin D, cholecalciferol. In this study, we have only investigated one developmental time point and only male foetuses. In future studies, it will be obviously important to examine the entire ontogeny of mesDA systems in both sexes to understand long-term outcomes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec27" sec-type="conclusion">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p id="Par42">This study represents a small but growing number of preclinical studies showing that the trajectory of adverse MIA-induced outcomes for adult brain function can be diminished or averted by dietary interventions. Two such studies have employed dietary interventions in MIA-exposed juvenile offspring with either a ketogenic diet or glucoraphanin to reverse certain MIA-induced behavioural phenotypes of relevance to psychiatry<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Of closer relevance to our study Weiser and colleagues have supplemented MIA dams with docosahexaenoic acid and prevented the onset of autistic-like phenotypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. We recently reported that maternal treatment with VIT<sub>D</sub> blocked the emergence of MIA-induced deficits in cognitive and social behavioural phenotypes of relevance to autism in offspring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Using a mouse model of MIA, the present study is the first to reveal preventive effects of maternal VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment on AMPH hypersensitivity, a phenotype with relevance to the positive symptoms of schizophrenia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par43">We further identify three plausible pathways via which VIT<sub>D</sub> may act to restore or support normal DA development in the event of MIA. First, MIA retarded the positioning of mesDAs particularly in the DV dimension, whereas VIT<sub>D</sub> treatment restored this at least for TH+ mesDA neurons. Second, MIA appeared to reduce TH+ cell number, while at the same time, VIT<sub>D</sub> increased TH+ mesDA cells. Third, VIT<sub>D</sub> increased the expression of proteins consistent with a more differentiated mesDA neuron. These three processes likely reflect an accelerated differentiation of DA neurons induced by VIT<sub>D</sub>, which in turn may have protected against the emergence of AMPH hypersensitivity in adult MIA offspring. By contrast, MIA-induced PPI deficiency does not seem to critically involve the same developmental pathways.</p>
<p id="Par44">This data adds to a steadily increasing literature indicating developing DA systems may be particularly vulnerable to adverse environmental factors such as MIA and DVD-deficiency and represent a plausible convergent early mechanistic pathway to psychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
<sec id="Sec28">
<p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_28090_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplemental info</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p>
<bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold>
</p>
<p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-28090-w.</p>
</fn>
<fn>
<p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>Funding bodies. This work was supported by a National Health and Medical research council grant (APP 1057883) to DWE and UM; additional financial support was received from the Swiss National Science Foundation (grant number 310030_169544) awarded to UM. We acknowledge the support of the Histology and Microscopy Facility, and the Animal Facility of Queensland Brain institute of the University of Queensland.</p>
</ack>
<notes notes-type="author-contribution">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p>W.L., S.V., U.M. and D.W.E. designed research; W.L., L.A.H. and S.V. performed research and analyzed the data; W.L., L.A.H., U.M. and D.W.E. wrote the paper.</p>
</notes>
<notes notes-type="COI-statement">
<sec id="FPar1">
<title>Competing Interests</title>
<p id="Par45">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
</sec>
</notes>
<ref-list id="Bib1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CR1">
<label>1.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Di Forti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lappin</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Risk factors for schizophrenia - All roads lead to dopamine</article-title>
<source/>European Neuropsychopharmacology
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>
<lpage>107</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2007.02.005</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR2">
<label>2.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van Os</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kenis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rutten</surname>
<given-names>BPF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The environment and schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>468</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>
<lpage>212</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09563</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21068828</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR3">
<label>3.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The environment and susceptibility to schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Progress in Neurobiology
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>
<lpage>58</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2010.09.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20955757</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR4">
<label>4.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Owen</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sawa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mortensen</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>The Lancet
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>388</volume>
<fpage>86</fpage>
<lpage>97</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)01121-6</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR5">
<label>5.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weinstein</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pathway-Specific Dopamine Abnormalities in Schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Biological Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<lpage>42</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.03.2104</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27206569</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR6">
<label>6.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Schizophrenia: do all roads lead to dopamine or is this where they start? Evidence from two epidemiologically informed developmental rodent models</article-title>
<source/>Translational Psychiatry
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>e81</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2012.6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22832818</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR7">
<label>7.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prenatal Poly(I:C) exposure and other developmental immune activation models in rodent systems</article-title>
<source/>Biological Psychiatry
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>307</fpage>
<lpage>315</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2013.07.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23938317</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR8">
<label>8.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mackay-Sim, a., McGrath, J. &amp; Feron, F. Vitamin d3 and brain development</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>641</fpage>
<lpage>653</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(03)00040-X</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12710973</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR9">
<label>9.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burne</surname>
<given-names>THJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin D, effects on brain development, adult brain function and the links between low levels of vitamin D and neuropsychiatric disease</article-title>
<source/>Frontiers in neuroendocrinology
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>47</fpage>
<lpage>64</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yfrne.2012.07.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22796576</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR10">
<label>10.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schoenrock</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tarantino</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Developmental vitamin D deficiency and schizophrenia: the role of animal models</article-title>
<source/>Genes, brain, and behavior
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>61</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gbb.12271</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26560996</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR11">
<label>11.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vuillermot</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A longitudinal examination of the neurodevelopmental impact of prenatal immune activation in mice reveals primary defects in dopaminergic development relevant to schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>1270</fpage>
<lpage>1287</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5408-09.2010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20107055</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR12">
<label>12.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kesby</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burne</surname>
<given-names>THJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Developmental vitamin D deficiency alters MK 801-induced hyperlocomotion in the adult rat: An animal model of schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Biological psychiatry
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>591</fpage>
<lpage>596</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2006.02.033</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16697353</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR13">
<label>13.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kesby</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Developmental vitamin D deficiency alters dopamine-mediated behaviors and dopamine transporter function in adult female rats</article-title>
<source/>Psychopharmacology
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>208</volume>
<fpage>159</fpage>
<lpage>168</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-009-1717-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19921153</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR14">
<label>14.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engler</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schedlowski</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Preliminary evidence for a modulation of fetal dopaminergic development by maternal immune activation during pregnancy</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>154</volume>
<fpage>701</fpage>
<lpage>709</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2008.04.031</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18495356</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR15">
<label>15.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pelekanos</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burne</surname>
<given-names>THJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal vitamin D deficiency alters the expression of genes involved in dopamine specification in the developing rat mesencephalon</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience letters
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>486</volume>
<fpage>220</fpage>
<lpage>223</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2010.09.057</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20884326</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR16">
<label>16.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Luan, W. <italic>et al</italic>. Developmental Vitamin D (DVD) Deficiency Reduces Nurr1 and TH Expression in Post-mitotic Dopamine Neurons in Rat Mesencephalon. <italic>Molecular Neurobiology</italic>, 10.1007/s12035-017-0497-3 (2017).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR17">
<label>17.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nelander</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hebsgaard</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parmar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Organization of the human embryonic ventral mesencephalon</article-title>
<source/>Gene expression patterns: GEP
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>555</fpage>
<lpage>561</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gep.2009.10.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19825428</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR18">
<label>18.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blaess</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ang</surname>
<given-names>S-L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetic control of midbrain dopaminergic neuron development</article-title>
<source/>Wiley interdisciplinary reviews. Developmental biology
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>113</fpage>
<lpage>134</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wdev.169</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25565353</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR19">
<label>19.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arenas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Denham</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Villaescusa</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>How to make a midbrain dopaminergic neuron</article-title>
<source/>Development (Cambridge, England)
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>142</volume>
<fpage>1918</fpage>
<lpage>1936</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.097394</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR20">
<label>20.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hawes</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal vitamin D deficiency alters fetal brain development in the BALB/c mouse</article-title>
<source/>Behavioural Brain Research
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>286</volume>
<fpage>192</fpage>
<lpage>200</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2015.03.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25753408</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR21">
<label>21.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pertile</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin D regulates tyrosine hydroxylase expression: N-cadherin a possible mediator</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>304</volume>
<fpage>90</fpage>
<lpage>100</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2015.07.048</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26210580</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR22">
<label>22.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pertile</surname>
<given-names>RAN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin D signaling and the differentiation of developing dopamine systems</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>333</volume>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>203</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2016.07.020</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27450565</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR23">
<label>23.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zuckerman</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weiner</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal immune activation leads to behavioral and pharmacological changes in the adult offspring</article-title>
<source/>Journal of Psychiatric Research
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>311</fpage>
<lpage>323</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2004.08.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15725430</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR24">
<label>24.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Romero</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guaza</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Castellano</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Borrell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ontogeny of sensorimotor gating and immune impairment induced by prenatal immune challenge in rats: implications for the etiopathology of schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Molecular Psychiatry
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>372</fpage>
<lpage>383</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2008.44</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18414405</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR25">
<label>25.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kesby</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Developmental vitamin D deficiency alters multiple neurotransmitter systems in the neonatal rat brain</article-title>
<source/>International Journal of Developmental Neuroscience
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2017.07.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28716540</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR26">
<label>26.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vuillermot, S. <italic>et al</italic>. Prenatal Immune Activation Interacts with Genetic Nurr1 Deficiency in the Development of Attentional Impairments. <bold>32</bold>, 436–451, 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4831-11.2012 (2012).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR27">
<label>27.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vuillermot</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin D treatment during pregnancy prevents autism-related phenotypes in a mouse model of maternal immune activation</article-title>
<source/>Molecular Autism
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13229-017-0125-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28316773</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR28">
<label>28.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schedlowski</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yee</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Towards an immuno-precipitated neurodevelopmental animal model of schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience and biobehavioral reviews
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>913</fpage>
<lpage>947</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2004.10.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15964075</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR29">
<label>29.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spencer</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Perinatal programming by inflammation</article-title>
<source/>Brain, Behavior, and Immunity
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2017.02.007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28196717</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR30">
<label>30.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bodea</surname>
<given-names>GO</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Reelin and CXCL12 regulate distinct migratory behaviors during the development of the dopaminergic system</article-title>
<source/>Development (Cambridge, England)
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>141</volume>
<fpage>661</fpage>
<lpage>673</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.099937</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR31">
<label>31.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ritter</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holliday</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Knutson</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>&amp; Strugnell, S. a. Tissue distribution and activity studies of 1,24-dihydroxyvitamin D2, a metabolite of vitamin D2 with low calcemic activity <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title>
<source/>Biochemical pharmacology
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>1289</fpage>
<lpage>1296</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2004.06.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345318</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR32">
<label>32.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The time of prenatal immune challenge determines the specificity of inflammation-mediated brain and behavioral pathology</article-title>
<source/>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>4752</fpage>
<lpage>4762</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0099-06.2006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16672647</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR33">
<label>33.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arrode-Brusés</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brusés</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal immune activation by poly I:C induces expression of cytokines IL-1β and IL-13, chemokine MCP-1 and colony stimulating factor VEGF in fetal mouse brain</article-title>
<source/>Journal of neuroinflammation
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-2094-9-83</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546005</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR34">
<label>34.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Knutson, J. C., Levun, L. W., Valliere, R., Bishop, C. W. &amp; International, B. C. Pharmacokinetics and Systemic Effect on Calcium Homeostasis of la,24-Dihydroxyvitamin D2, in Rats. <bold>53</bold>, 829–837 (1997).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR35">
<label>35.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knuesel</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal immune activation and abnormal brain development across CNS disorders</article-title>
<source/>Nature Reviews Neurology
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>643</fpage>
<lpage>660</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2014.187</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25311587</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR36">
<label>36.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spoerri</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yee</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwarz</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Evaluating early preventive antipsychotic and antidepressant drug treatment in an infection-based neurodevelopmental mouse model of schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Schizophrenia Bulletin
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>607</fpage>
<lpage>623</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbn131</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18845557</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR37">
<label>37.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vuillermot</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Nurr1 is not essential for the development of prepulse inhibition deficits induced by prenatal immune activation</article-title>
<source/>Brain, Behavior, and Immunity
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1316</fpage>
<lpage>1321</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2011.06.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21723940</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR38">
<label>38.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Estes</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McAllister</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal immune activation: Implications for neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>353</volume>
<fpage>772</fpage>
<lpage>777</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag3194</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27540164</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR39">
<label>39.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hewison</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>An update on vitamin D and human immunity</article-title>
<source/>Clinical Endocrinology
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>315</fpage>
<lpage>325</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2011.04261.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21995874</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR40">
<label>40.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The maternal interleukin-17a pathway in mice promotes autism-like phenotypes in offspring</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>351</volume>
<fpage>933</fpage>
<lpage>939</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad0314</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26822608</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR41">
<label>41.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lathia</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Toll-Like Receptor 3 Is a Negative Regulator of Embryonic Neural Progenitor Cell Proliferation</article-title>
<source/>The Journal of Neuroscience
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>13978</fpage>
<lpage>13984</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2140-08.2008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19091986</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR42">
<label>42.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang, X. <italic>et al</italic>. Interleukin-1 β mediates proliferation and differentiation of multipotent neural precursor cells through the activation of SAPK/JNK pathway. <bold>36</bold>, 343-354, 10.1016/j.mcn.2007.07.005 (2007).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR43">
<label>43.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Utani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Interleukin-6 and Neural Stem Cells: More Than Gliogenesis</article-title>
<source/>Seikagaku
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>327</fpage>
<lpage>331</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20496754</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR44">
<label>44.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ernardino, L. I. B., Gasse, F. A. A., Ilva, B. R. S., Erreira, R. A. F. &amp; Rade, S. O. G. Tumor Necrosis Factor-a Modulates Survival, Proliferation, and Neuronal Differentiation in Neonatal Subventricular Zone Cell Cultures. 2361–2371, 10.1634/stemcells.2007-0914 (2008).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR45">
<label>45.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shirazi, H. A., Rasouli, J., Ciric, B., Rostami, A. &amp; Zhang, X. 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3 enhances neural stem cell proliferation and oligodendrocyte differentiation. <bold>98</bold>, 240–245, 10.1016/j.yexmp.2015.02.004.1 (2016).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR46">
<label>46.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burne</surname>
<given-names>THJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mackay-Sim</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal vitamin D depletion alters neurogenesis in the developing rat brain</article-title>
<source/>International journal of developmental neuroscience: the official journal of the International Society for Developmental Neuroscience
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>227</fpage>
<lpage>232</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2007.03.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467223</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR47">
<label>47.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mowry</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yolken</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Low maternal vitamin D as a risk factor for schizophrenia: a pilot study using banked sera</article-title>
<source/>Schizophrenia Research
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>73</fpage>
<lpage>78</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0920-9964(02)00435-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12892860</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR48">
<label>48.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burkert</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eyles</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Maternal vitamin D3 deprivation and the regulation of apoptosis and cell cycle during rat brain development</article-title>
<source/>Brain research. Developmental brain research
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>153</volume>
<fpage>61</fpage>
<lpage>68</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devbrainres.2004.07.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15464218</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR49">
<label>49.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Wnt1-lmx1a forms a novel autoregulatory loop and controls midbrain dopaminergic differentiation synergistically with the SHH-FoxA2 pathway</article-title>
<source/>Cell stem cell
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>646</fpage>
<lpage>658</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2009.09.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19951692</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR50">
<label>50.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoekstra</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lmx1a Encodes a Rostral Set of Mesodiencephalic Dopaminergic Neurons Marked by the Wnt/B-Catenin Signaling Activator R-spondin 2</article-title>
<source/>PLoS ONE
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>12</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR51">
<label>51.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nakatani</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kumai</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mizuhara</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Minaki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ono</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lmx1a and Lmx1b cooperate with Foxa2 to coordinate the specification of dopaminergic neurons and control of floor plate cell differentiation in the developing mesencephalon</article-title>
<source/>Developmental biology
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>339</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>
<lpage>113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2009.12.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20035737</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR52">
<label>52.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saucedo-Cardenas</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Nurr1 is essential for the induction of the dopaminergic phenotype and the survival of ventral mesencephalic late dopaminergic precursor neurons</article-title>
<source/>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America
          <year>1998</year>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>4013</fpage>
<lpage>4018</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.7.4013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9520484</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR53">
<label>53.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rojas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Joodmardi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Perlmann</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ogren</surname>
<given-names>SO</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Adult mice with reduced Nurr1 expression: an animal model for schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Molecular psychiatry
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>756</fpage>
<lpage>766</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001993</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17457314</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR54">
<label>54.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jacobs</surname>
<given-names>FMJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Retinoic acid-dependent and -independent gene-regulatory pathways of Pitx3 in meso-diencephalic dopaminergic neurons</article-title>
<source/>Development (Cambridge, England)
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>138</volume>
<fpage>5213</fpage>
<lpage>5222</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.071704</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR55">
<label>55.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Veenvliet</surname>
<given-names>JV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smidt</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular mechanisms of dopaminergic subset specification: fundamental aspects and clinical perspectives</article-title>
<source/>Cellular and molecular life sciences: CMLS
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>4703</fpage>
<lpage>4727</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-014-1681-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25064061</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR56">
<label>56.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Matsuura</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dietary glucoraphanin prevents the onset of psychosis in the adult offspring after maternal immune activation</article-title>
<source/>Scientific reports
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>2158</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20538-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29391571</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR57">
<label>57.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ruskin</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Slade</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Masino</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ketogenic diet improves behaviors in a maternal immune activation model of autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>PloS one
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>e0171643</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171643</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28166277</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR58">
<label>58.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weiser</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dietary docosahexaenoic acid alleviates autistic-like behaviors resulting from maternal immune activation in mice</article-title>
<source/>Prostaglandins, leukotrienes, and essential fatty acids
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>106</volume>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>37</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plefa.2015.10.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26703213</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR59">
<label>59.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Laruelle</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>&amp; Abi-Dargham, a. Dopamine as the wind of the psychotic fire: new evidence from brain imaging studies</article-title>
<source/>Journal of psychopharmacology (Oxford, England)
          <year>1999</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>358</fpage>
<lpage>371</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/026988119901300405</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR60">
<label>60.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Laruelle</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The role of endogenous sensitization in the pathophysiology of schizophrenia: Implications from recent brain imaging studies</article-title>
<source/>Brain Research Reviews
          <year>2000</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>371</fpage>
<lpage>384</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0173(99)00054-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10719165</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR61">
<label>61.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abi-Dargham</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van de Giessen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Slifstein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kegeles</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Laruelle</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Baseline and Amphetamine-Stimulated Dopamine Activity Are Related in Drug-Naïve Schizophrenic Subjects</article-title>
<source/>Biological Psychiatry
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>1091</fpage>
<lpage>1093</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2008.12.007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19167701</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>