<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101231976</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32624</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Chem Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Chem. Biol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Nature chemical biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4450</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-4469</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29915238</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6027965</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41589-018-0071-y</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS77001</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Jumonji-C oxygenase JMJD7 catalyzes (3<italic>S</italic>)-lysyl hydroxylation of TRAFAC GTPases</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Markolovic</surname>
<given-names>Suzana</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhuang</surname>
<given-names>Qinqin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>Sarah E</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eaton</surname>
<given-names>Charlotte D</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abboud</surname>
<given-names>Martine I</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Katz</surname>
<given-names>Maximiliano J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McNeil</surname>
<given-names>Helen E</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leśniak</surname>
<given-names>Robert K</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>Charlotte</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Struwe</surname>
<given-names>Weston B</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Konietzny</surname>
<given-names>Rebecca</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>Simon</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Ming</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ge</surname>
<given-names>Wei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Benesch</surname>
<given-names>Justin LP</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kessler</surname>
<given-names>Benedikt M</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ratcliffe</surname>
<given-names>Peter J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cockman</surname>
<given-names>Matthew E</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>Roman</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wappner</surname>
<given-names>Pablo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>Rasheduzzaman</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coleman</surname>
<given-names>Mathew L</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">9</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schofield</surname>
<given-names>Christopher J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN5">9</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Chemistry Research Laboratory, Department of Chemistry, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Institute of Cancer and Genomic Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Instituto Leloir, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Target Discovery Institute, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="A5">
<label>5</label>The Francis Crick Institute, London, United Kingdom</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="present-address" id="FN1">
<label>6</label>
<p id="P1">Present address: Stanford University School of Medicine, Department
of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, Clark Center, Stanford, CA, USA.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="equal" id="FN5">
<label>7,8,9</label>
<p id="P100">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>rasheduzzaman.chowdhury@stanford.edu</email>, <email>m.coleman@bham.ac.uk</email>, <email>christopher.schofield@chem.ox.ac.uk</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>30</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>18</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>18</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>688</fpage>
<lpage>695</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/s41589-018-0071-y-->
<permissions>
<license>
<license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p id="P2">Biochemical, structural, and cellular studies reveal Jumonji-C (JmjC) domain-containing 7 (JMJD7) as a 2-oxoglutarate (2OG)-dependent oxygenase catalyzing a previously unreported type of post-translational modification, (<italic>3S</italic>)<italic>-</italic>lysyl hydroxylation. Crystallographic analyses reveal JMJD7 as more closely related to the JmjC hydroxylases rather than the JmjC demethylases. Biophysical and mutation studies show that JMJD7 has a unique dimerization mode, with interactions between monomers involving both <italic>N</italic>- and <italic>C</italic>-terminal regions and disulfide bond formation. A proteomic approach identifies two related members of the Translation Factor (TRAFAC) family of GTPases, Developmentally Regulated GTP Binding Proteins 1 and 2 (DRG1/2), as activity-dependent JMJD7 interactors. Mass spectrometric analyses demonstrate that JMJD7 catalyzes Fe(II)- and 2OG-dependent hydroxylation of a highly-conserved lysine residue in DRG1/2; amino acid analyses reveal JMJD7 catalyzes (3<italic>S</italic>)-lysyl hydroxylation. The functional assignment of JMJD7 will enable future studies to define the role of DRG hydroxylation in cell growth and disease.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S1" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="P3">Following their initial identification as pro-collagen prolyl and lysyl hydroxylases, Fe(II) and 2-oxoglutarate (2OG)-dependent oxygenases have emerged as widespread regulators of protein biosynthesis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>. The hypoxia inducible factor prolyl- and asparaginyl- hydroxylases regulate the levels and transcriptional activity of the αβ-hypoxia inducible transcription factors (HIFs). Prolyl hydroxylation, by the prolyl hydroxylase domain (PHDs/EGLNs) oxygenases, regulates HIF-α subunit levels by signaling for degradation, while asparaginyl hydroxylation (catalyzed by Factor inhibiting hypoxia inducible factor, FIH) regulates HIF transcriptional activity; the sensitivity of the PHDs and FIH catalysis to cellular oxygen availability enable them to act as hypoxia sensors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>. FIH, but not the PHDs, is a member of the Jumonji-C (JmjC) subfamily of 2OG oxygenases<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, other members of which regulate transcription via demethylation of the three histone lysine N<sup>ε</sup>-methylation states. JmjC histone demethylase (KDM) catalysis proceeds via hydroxylation to give a hemiaminal intermediate, which fragments to give the demethylated product and formaldehyde<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>. There are ~6 human JmjC KDM subfamilies, which are being studied due to their roles in transcription and links to cancer and genetic disorders resulting from mutations to them<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>. 2OG oxygenases are current therapeutic targets with compounds being developed for clinical applications in cancer (e.g. KDM5 inhibitors)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref> and anemia (PHD inhibitors)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>.</p>
<p id="P4">With the exception of FIH, there are limited reports on the ~10 human JmjC oxygenases that catalyze formation of stable alcohol products (‘JmjC hydroxylases’), which are less well-studied than the JmjC KDMs. In addition to HIF-α isoforms, FIH catalyzes modification of ankyrin repeat domains<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, and Jumonji domain-containing 6 (JMJD6) catalyzes hydroxylation of splicing regulatory proteins<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>. JmjC hydroxylases also have ancient roles in regulation of protein biosynthesis by modifying the translational machinery<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>. The ribosomal oxygenases (RiOX), MYC-induced nuclear antigen (MINA53) and nucleolar protein 66 (NO66) catalyze histidinyl hydroxylation of Rpl27a and Rpl8, respectively<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>. tRNA yW-synthesizing enzyme 5 (TYW5) is a tRNA hydroxylase<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, and Jumonji domain-containing 4 (JMJD4) catalyzes hydroxylation of eukaryotic release factor 1 (eRF1), a reaction increasing stop codon recognition efficiency<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>. In eukaryotes ranging from yeasts to humans, a 2OG oxygenase that is not a JmjC protein (human: OGFOD1; <italic>Drosophil</italic>a: Sudestada1), but which is related to the HIF PHDs, catalyzes hydroxylation of a prolyl residue in close contact with mRNA in ribosomes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>. Overall, these results indicate that multiple 2OG oxygenases are involved in regulation of protein synthesis at both transcriptional and translational levels<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>.</p>
<p id="P5">Jumonji domain-containing 7 (JMJD7) is one of the few remaining biochemically uncharacterized human JmjC oxygenases; structure-based bioinformatics predicts it is an Fe(II) and 2OG-dependent oxygenase containing a JmjC catalytic domain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). We report biochemical, crystallographic, and cellular studies revealing JMJD7 as a structurally distinct JmjC hydroxylase catalyzing a previously unreported post-translational modification (PTM), (3<italic>S</italic>)-lysyl hydroxylation, in two related members of the Translation Factor (TRAFAC) GTPase family. The results will enable future work to elucidate the biological roles of JMJD7 in protein synthesis, the regulation of cell growth, and disease.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="S3">
<title>JMJD7 suppresses cell growth in Drosophila</title>
<p id="P6">In an RNAi-based screen for variations in size of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> posterior wing compartment, we observed that knockdown of CG10133 mRNA, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> orthologue of human JMJD7 (dmJMJD7, 45% sequence identity), correlates with increased posterior wing compartment size, likely through an increase in cell size (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). Among human JmjC proteins, structure-based bioinformatics predicts JMJD7 is most closely related to FIH<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, TYW5<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, Jumonji domain-containing 5 (JMJD5)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, and the RiOXs, MINA53 and NO66<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, all of which are JmjC hydroxylases with roles in protein biosynthesis regulation (in some cases, they are also reported to have KDM activities). Because the catalytic activities and structures of the JmjC oxygenases can relate to their physiological roles<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, we undertook biochemical studies on JMJD7.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>JMJD7 is structurally similar to JmjC hydroxylases</title>
<p id="P7">Analysis of the activity of recombinant JMJD7 using <sup>1</sup>H NMR reveals slow Fe(II)-stimulated conversion of 2OG to succinate in the absence of a substrate (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). As observed for some other 2OG oxygenases, this conversion was reduced by the broad spectrum inhibitor, <italic>N</italic>-oxalylglycine (NOG)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>; alanine substitution of one of the predicted Fe(II)-binding residues (H178) also reduces 2OG turnover (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figs. 1 and 3b-c</xref>). To support biochemical characterization of JMJD7 and to investigate whether it functions as a hydroxylase and/or KDM, we then worked to solve crystal structures for human JMJD7.</p>
<p id="P8">A structure of full-length His<sub>6</sub>-tagged JMJD7 complexed with 2OG and Mn(II), an inert Fe(II) substitute, was solved by molecular replacement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). We obtained a higher resolution (2.2 Å) structure of a JMJD7 variant arising from a missense mutation (R260C) present in endometrial cancer<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref> and autism<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>), the fold of which is very similar to wildtype (0.35 Å Cα root mean squared deviation; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4 and Supplementary Table 1</xref>). JMJD7 crystallizes as an oligomer with two or four molecules in each asymmetric unit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). Biophysical analyses reveal JMJD7 as dimeric in solution, consistent with immunoprecipitation studies in cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5a-c</xref>). Uniquely among characterized JmjC proteins, JMJD7 dimerization involves hydrophobic interactions between α-helices from <italic>both N</italic>- and <italic>C</italic>-terminal regions (α1, α2, and α9, respectively) and a disulfide involving Cys-47 from two monomers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figs 5d-e and 6</xref>). The dimeric state of JMJD7 suggests a closer structural similarity to the JmjC hydroxylases, rather than the demethylases<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, since the former are commonly observed as dimers: FIH<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref> and TYW5<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref> oligomerize via <italic>C</italic>-terminal α-helical bundles, while MINA53 and NO66 oligomerize via α-helical bundles located between their JmjC and winged-helix domains<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5e</xref>).</p>
<p id="P9">The structures reveal each JMJD7 molecule is comprised of 9 α-helices, 18 β-strands, and 2-3<sub>10</sub> helices. The catalytic domain contains the characteristic 2OG oxygenase distorted double-stranded β-helix (DSBH) core barrel, formed from 8 β-strands, arranged as 2 antiparallel major (βI, βVIII, βIII, βVI) and minor (βII, βVII, βIV, βV) sheets<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>. The DSBH houses the active site, where the 2OG oxalyl group, water, and the metal-binding triad (H178, D180, and H277) coordinate the metal in an octahedral geometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). The 2OG C1 carboxylate is positioned to make a hydrogen bonding network with the amides of N184 and N289. As with most structurally characterized JmjC oxygenases, the 2OG C5 carboxylate interacts via electrostatic and hydrogen bonding interactions with a lysine (K193) on βIV<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>. Most 2OG oxygenases have 2 or 3 polar side-chains positioned to interact with the 2OG C5 carboxylate group; notably, JMJD7 has 4 such side-chains. In addition to K193, the hydroxyls of Y127, T175, and Y186 form additional hydrogen bonds with the 2OG C5 carboxylate group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). The apparently tight binding of 2OG is consistent with the observed slow substrate uncoupled 2OG turnover (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
<p id="P10">Comparison of the JMJD7 active site with those of other JmjC oxygenases reveals closer structural similarity with JmjC hydroxylases than KDMs. Notably, binding of the 2OG C1 carboxylate, involving hydrogen bonds with the N184 and N289 side-chain amides, emulates interactions made by FIH<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, i.e. with the N205<sub>FIH</sub> and N294<sub>FIH</sub> side-chains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7a</xref>). Importantly, JMJD7 lacks a hydrophobic region crucial in binding the N<sup>ε</sup>-methyl lysine group of the JmjC KDMs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>. Most JmjC KDMs tend to have an extended loop at the <italic>N</italic>-terminus of DSBH βI that is involved in substrate binding; this is shortened in JMJD7 as in other JmjC hydroxylases (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7b</xref>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>. Consistent with the absence of structural domains associated with KDM activity (e.g. characteristic histone- and nucleic acid-binding domains; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7c</xref>), a panel of histone H3.1 fragments known to be JmjC KDM substrates were not modified by JMJD7 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>). Overall, the combined biophysical analyses reveal JMJD7 as having greater structural similarity to the JmjC hydroxylases than the JmjC KDMs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title>Proteomics identifies TRAFAC GTPases as JMJD7 interactors</title>
<p id="P11">To identify potential JMJD7 substrates, we used mass spectrometry (MS) to compare the proteins interacting with wildtype and (near) inactive (H178A) JMJD7, using dimethyl-<italic>N</italic>-oxalylglycine (DMOG), a cell-penetrating precursor of NOG<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, to trap substrates. Immunoaffinity purifications from extracts of DMOG-treated cells expressing FLAG-tagged wildtype or JMJD7 H178A were analyzed. JMJD7-specific interactions ablated by the H178A mutation included two closely related GTPases, Developmentally Regulated GTP Binding Proteins 1 and 2 (DRG1/2), and their respective binding partners, DRG family regulatory proteins 1 and 2 (DFRP1/2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9a</xref>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>. Known JmjC hydroxylase substrates (e.g. eRF1, splicing factors, HIFα, Rpl27a/Rpl8), ankyrins, or KDM substrates (e.g. histones) were not detected. Activity-dependent interactions of JMJD7 with DRG1 and DRG2 were confirmed in different cell lines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9b-d</xref>). Reciprocal immunoprecipitations using FLAG-tagged DRGs confirmed the interaction with endogenous JMJD7, but not the related hydroxylase JMJD4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9e</xref>). Importantly, purification of endogenous DRG/DFRP complexes also co-precipitated endogenous JMJD7 (but not JMJD4; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). To investigate whether JMJD7 and DRG1/2 co-localize, immunofluorescence staining of co-expressed JMJD7 and DRG1 or DRG2 was performed in HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Consistent with the proteomic and co-immunoprecipitation data, we observed significant co-localization of JMJD7 with DRG1 and DRG2 in both nuclear and cytoplasmic compartments. Overall, the combined interaction and localization data support the assignment of DRG1 and DRG2 as JMJD7 interactors and potential substrates.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6">
<title>JMJD7 catalyzes DRG lysyl hydroxylation</title>
<p id="P12">To investigate whether DRG/DFRP complexes are JMJD7 substrates, HA-DRG1/2 and V5-DFRP1/2 were purified from cells overproducing control or FLAG-JMJD7, hydrolyzed by trypsin, then analyzed by MS. The results identified a single lysyl hydroxylation site in a highly conserved region in both DRG1 and DRG2, i.e. at K22/K21, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a-b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref>). Notably, in cells overexpressing JMJD7, we reproducibly observed increases in hydroxylated peptides corresponding to a ‘missed’ trypsin cleavage site in DRG1 (NK(OH)ATAHHLGLLK) and DRG2 (NK(OH)ATEYHLGLLK), suggesting that JMJD7-catalyzed hydroxylation hinders trypsin-catalyzed hydrolysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>).</p>
<p id="P13">We then tested the cellular assignment of JMJD7-mediated DRG1/2 lysyl hydroxylation by assaying 20-mer peptide fragments spanning the DRG1 sequence as substrates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>; a 25-mer peptide, DRG1<sub>16-40</sub>, was also used for biochemical characterization as described later in the text). Consistent with the cell results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a-b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9</xref>), the only peptide undergoing a JMJD7-dependent +16 Da shift was DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> (NKATAHHLGLLKARLAKLRR-NH<sub>2</sub>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>). Peptide hydroxylation was impaired by the absence of 2OG and Fe(II) and inhibited by NOG<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref> or use of a JMJD7 H178A variant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>). Incubation under <sup>18</sup>O<sub>2</sub> revealed that JMJD7 catalyzes incorporation of <sup>18</sup>O into its product, as observed for other 2OG protein hydroxylases (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 11</xref>). Alanine substitution at the hydroxylation site prevented hydroxylation and blocked interaction between isolated JMJD7 and DRG1/2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figs. 12 and 13</xref>). Interestingly, the DRG-hydroxylation sites are highly conversed in almost all animals including <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). Recombinant dmJMJD7 hydroxylates human DRG1 and 2 peptides with similar efficiency as human JMJD7 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 14a</xref>, compare to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15</xref>). Furthermore, dmJMJD7 is able to reconstitute activity-dependent interactions with endogenous DRG1 and DRG2 in human cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 14b</xref>). These analyses suggest JMJD7-catalyzed DRG hydroxylation is highly conserved in animals, possibly in a manner linked to the growth phenotype observed on <italic>dmJMJD7</italic> knockdown in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
<p id="P14">The DRG2 peptide (DRG2<sub>20-39</sub>; NKATEYHLGLLKAKLAKYRA-NH<sub>2</sub>) was a less efficient substrate than the analogous DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> substrate (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15a-b</xref>). A structure of the DRG1 homologue from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> [Ribosome-interacting GTPase 1 (RBG1), 66% sequence identity, PDB ID: 4A9A] reveals the K22 side-chain protrudes from a loop on a highly conserved region of a helix-turn-helix (HTH) motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15c</xref>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>. Strikingly, the position of K22 in the HTH of RBG1, and by implication DRG1/2, resembles that of the lysyl hydroxylation site of a JMJD4 substrate, eRF1<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15c-d</xref>). The location of K22 protruding from a turn between 2 α-helices suggests secondary structure may be important in JMJD7-substrate recognition, as for JMJD4<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>. Increasing the DRG1 fragment length at its <italic>N</italic>-terminus to include other conserved residues in the HTH (DRG1<sub>16-40</sub>; <italic>ARTQK</italic>NKATAHHLGLLKARLAKLRR-NH<sub>2</sub>) results in more efficient hydroxylation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15a-b</xref>). Importantly, the <italic>N</italic>-terminally extended DRG2<sub>15-39</sub> fragment (<italic>ARTQK</italic>NKATEYHLGLLKAKLAKYRA-NH<sub>2</sub>) undergoes efficient hydroxylation. To investigate how JMJD7 interacts with DRG1/2, we attempted to obtain JMJD7.DRG1/2 crystal structures, but have as yet been unsuccessful. We therefore modelled JMJD7.Fe.2OG.DRG1 complexes based on the crystal structures of JMJD7.Mn.2OG (PDB: 5NFO) and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> RBG1 (PDB: 4A9A). The modelling and cysteine substitution studies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 16</xref>) support the combined biochemical observations implying long-range interactions involving conserved residues distant from those immediately surrounding the hydroxylated lysine are important in productive JMJD7 binding. Overall, the combined cellular and isolated protein studies define JMJD7 as a lysyl hydroxylase acting on both DRG1 and DRG2.</p>
<p id="P15">To investigate whether JMJD7 is <italic>necessary</italic> for hydroxylation of DRGs, we immunopurified endogenous DRG1/2 from HEK293T cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 17</xref>); MS analyses identified substantial levels of both K22 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 17d</xref>) and K21 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e-f</xref>) hydroxylation, respectively. Importantly, endogenous levels of DRG2 K21 hydroxylation depended on the presence of JMJD7 expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 17b</xref>). Consistent with the overexpression analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref>), the ability of trypsin to cleave endogenous DRGs at the <italic>C</italic>-terminal side of K22/K21 was reduced following hydroxylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>). We also observed inhibition of DRG hydrolysis by hydroxylation with Lys-N, which cleaves at the <italic>N</italic>-terminal side of lysyl-residues (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 18</xref>). This phenomenon has not been reported following hydroxylation of lysine at the C4 or C5 positions by protein hydroxylases<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, implying JMJD7 catalyzes a novel form of lysyl hydroxylation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S7">
<title>JMJD7 is a (3<italic>S</italic>)-lysyl hydroxylase</title>
<p id="P16">To date, characterized 2OG oxygenases catalyze hydroxylation at the C4 (e.g. JMJD4<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>) and C5 (e.g. JMJD6 and the procollagen lysyl hydroxylases (PLODs)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>) positions of lysyl side-chains. To investigate the regio- and stereo-selectivity of JMJD7, a DRG1 peptide was hydroxylated, then hydrolyzed and subjected to amino acid analysis. Following derivatization, LC-MS revealed a new peak, not present in controls, with a mass corresponding to derivatized hydroxylysine (obsvd. 503.2162 Da; calcd. 503.2037 Da). Comparison using C3-, C4-, and C5- hydroxylysine standards<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref> reveals the product co-elutes with one of the C3 hydroxylysine enantiomeric pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 19</xref>); C3 hydroxylation is supported by NMR analyses of hydroxylated DRG1 and DRG2 peptides (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 20</xref>). Comparison with a diastereomeric mixture of C3 hydroxylysine isomers and synthetic (2<italic>S</italic>,3<italic>R</italic>)/(2<italic>R</italic>,3<italic>S</italic>)-hydroxylysine standard<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref> identified (2<italic>S</italic>,<italic>3S</italic>)-hydroxylysine as the JMJD7-catalyzed product (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 19c-d</xref>). No evidence for other isomers was observed within detection limits, revealing JMJD7 stereospecifically catalyzes (3<italic>S</italic>)<italic>-</italic>hydroxylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a-c</xref>; assuming retention of (<italic>2S</italic>)-stereochemistry), a previously undescribed PTM.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S8">
<title>DRG hydroxylation promotes ribonucleic acid binding</title>
<p id="P17">The effect of C3 lysyl hydroxylation on <italic>in vitro</italic> proteolysis suggests that this novel PTM can regulate intramolecular interactions with functional consequences. We therefore explored potential biological roles of DRG C3 lysyl hydroxylation. Unlike HIF hydroxylases, JMJD7 did not significantly regulate substrate levels: Overexpression of wildtype or H178A JMJD7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9b-d</xref>), treatment with DMOG (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9b-d</xref>), or DRG hydroxylation site mutation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figs 21 and 22</xref>) did not consistently affect the expression of DRG or DFRP proteins in cells. Furthermore, hydroxylation did not, within detection limits, change the thermal stability of full-length, isolated DRG1 (using differential scanning calorimetry; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 23</xref>). Consistent with a lack of effect on cellular stability, hydroxylation site substituted DRGs did not affect their ability to co-precipitate DFRPs, which are major regulators of DRG protein turnover<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 21</xref>). Hydroxylation also did not consistently affect GTPase activity, as determined by <sup>1</sup>H NMR or phosphate release assays using recombinant DRG1 <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 24</xref>), or using DRG1/2 purified from cells exposed to JMJD7 overexpression, shRNA knockdown, or DMOG treatment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 25</xref>).</p>
<p id="P18">As described above, the lysine residue targeted by JMJD7 is located at the apex of a highly conserved HTH motif within the <italic>N</italic>-terminal regions of DRG1/2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15c</xref>). Although the role of this domain has not previously been reported, yeast complementation studies reveal it is critical for DRG function<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>. JMJD7-mediated DRG hydroxylation is analogous to JMJD4-mediated eRF1 hydroxylation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15c-d</xref>), in the sense that both are lysyl hydroxylation events targeting HTH domains. eRF1 lysyl hydroxylation is thought to promote translation termination by supporting the interaction of eRF1 with the mRNA stop codon<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, raising the possibility that DRG lysyl hydroxylation catalyzed by JMJD7 has a related function. Indeed, we observed significant binding of DRG2 to RNA affinity columns (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 22</xref>; consistent with previous reports<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>). Furthermore, a DRG2 K21 mutant had reduced affinity, thus localizing RNA binding activity to the HTH domain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 22</xref>). Importantly, shRNA-mediated JMJD7 knockdown also reduced the RNA binding affinity of purified DRG2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 22d</xref>). These data support a role for JMJD7-mediated C3 lysyl hydroxylation in promoting the interaction of the DRG TRAFAC GTPases with RNA. Future work can focus on defining the precise nature of the JMJD7-DRG-DFRP ribonucleoprotein complexes and their biological roles.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S9" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="P19">The combined cellular and biochemical results demonstrate that JMJD7 targets highly conserved lysine residues within 2 closely related TRAFAC GTPase proteins. The finding that JMJD7 catalyzes <italic>(3S)-</italic>lysyl hydroxylation, the first time this PTM has been observed in humans, expands the repertoire of 2OG oxygenase-catalyzed modifications of basic residues, which also include histidinyl-hydroxylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>, lysyl C4 hydroxylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, lysyl (5<italic>S</italic>)- and (5<italic>R</italic>)-hydroxylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, N<sup>ε</sup>-methyl lysyl demethylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>, argininyl C3 hydroxylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref> and, possibly, N-methyl argininyl-demethylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>. The extent of 2OG oxygenase-catalyzed lysyl hydroxylation is striking. With the discovery of JMJD7-catalyzed C3 lysyl hydroxylation, a total of seven different lysine residues oxidations are now known to be catalyzed by 2OG oxygenases. Aside from the ‘not (yet) observed’ C3 and C4 stereoisomers, oxidation at the C2 and C6 positions are unidentified exceptions; although the products of such reactions are likely unstable, they have precedent in 2OG oxygenase catalyzed protein fragmentation (albeit not at lysine residues as yet) via C2 hydroxylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>.</p>
<p id="P20">In most cases, the detailed biochemical roles of lysyl hydroxylations are unclear, with the enablement of glycosylation by procollagen (5<italic>R</italic>)-lysyl hydroxylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref> and improved stop codon decoding by C4 lysyl hydroxylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref> being exceptions. Our experiments indicate that JMJD7-catalyzed hydroxylation does not substantially effect on the intrinsic stability, protein expression, or GTPase activity of DRGs. Interestingly, however, we observed that JMJD7-catalyzed C3 lysyl hydroxylation clearly impairs experimental proteolysis, at either the <italic>C</italic>- or <italic>N</italic>-terminal sides of the target lysyl-residue. While inhibition of the tested proteases is likely not biologically relevant, this observation raises the possibility of a wider role for protein hydroxylation in directly modulating protease hydrolysis. This is particularly attractive for C3 lysyl-hydroxylation and nucleophilic serine/threonine protease inhibition, where work with proteases and bacterial cell wall biosynthesis enzymes employing nucleophilic serine catalysis has revealed that substrate/inhibitor substitutions that perturb hydrolysis (or formation) of the acyl-enzyme complex can lead to inhibition<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>.</p>
<p id="P21">In addition to effects on protease hydrolysis, we observed JMJD7- and hydroxylation site-dependent regulation of RNA binding, analogous to the role of JMJD4 in promoting mRNA stop codon decoding by eRF1<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>. Although future work is required to address the physiological RNA targets, the presence of DRGs in ribosome fractions from diverse species including yeasts, plants, and humans<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref> could be consistent with an interaction with messenger or ribosomal RNA. Although the biochemical role of the DRGs in protein translation is unclear, it is consistent with their similarity to other OBG GTPases of the TRAFAC family, which have roles in ribosome biogenesis and translation control<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>. A prokaryotic 2OG-dependent prolyl hydroxylase homologous with the animal HIF prolyl hydroxylases, Elongation Factor Thermo unstable (EF-Tu), has also been found to catalyze hydroxylation of a loop region of a translation-associated GTPase<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>; thus, physical and functional interactions between 2OG oxygenases, translation factors, and RNA may have ancient origins.</p>
<p id="P22">The discovery of JMJD7-catalyzed DRG hydroxylation contributes to growing evidence on the importance of the dynamic interactions between 2OG oxygenases and their substrates/interacting partners in disease<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>. Both JMJD7 and DRG1/DRG2 are linked to cell growth in diverse cell types and species<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>. JMJD7 and DRG1/2 may also have context dependent roles in diseases including cancer and mental disorders; the <italic>DRG2</italic> gene is located in a chromosomal region implicated in the Smith-Magenis neurobehavioral syndrome<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>, and DRG1/2 SNPs have been identified in a screen of candidate genes for autism spectrum disorders<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>. In support of this, genetic studies in high-risk autism families and persons with severe intellectual disabilities have identified 2 substitutions in the <italic>JMJD7</italic> gene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>. Future work can now address whether JMJD7-catalyzed hydroxylation of DRG1/2 regulates protein synthesis and how this underlies the role of this novel pathway in growth control and disease.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S10" sec-type="methods" specific-use="web-only">
<title>Online Methods</title>
<sec id="S11">
<title>Analysis of growth phenotypes in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></title>
<p id="P23"><italic>Drosophila</italic> maintenance, engineering, and knockdowns were performed as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>. Flies used in this study were en-Gal4 from the Bloominton <italic>Drosophila</italic> stock center and white RNAi (as a control) and <italic>CG10133</italic> RNAi from the VDRC stock center. For analysis of growth phenotypes, wings from 4 day old females and males were removed and mounted in a solution containing 1:1 lactic acid/ethanol. Wings were imaged using an Olympus MVX10 stereomicroscope connected to an Olympus DP71 digital camera, and variations in the area of the posterior compartment were estimated by measuring the area comprised between veins L4, PCV and L5, using the ImageJ software (NIH, USA). To quantify variations of cell size, the number of wing hairs per square mm was counted from images taken with an Olympus BX60 microscope connected to an Olympus DP71 digital camera.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S12">
<title>Mammalian cell culture and transfection</title>
<p id="P24">Human tumor and HEK293T cell lines were cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS (Sigma) and 1% penicillin-streptomycin at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Plasmids were transfected using FuGENE6 Transfection Reagent (Promega) according to manufacturer’s instructions. siRNA oligonucleotides (Sigma MISSION) were transfected twice over consecutive days at a concentration of 25 nM using OligoFectamine (ThermoFisher), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Lentiviral particles containing doxycyline-inducible cDNA expression and shRNA vectors were generated by co-transfection of HEK293T cells with 2<sup>nd</sup> generation vectors (pMD2.G and psPAX2) and used to create puromycin-resistant stable lines in HeLa, HEK293T, A549 and SW620 cells. Doxycycline-inducible control and JMJD7 shRNA lentiviral vectors were from the pZIP-TRE3G shERWOOD Ultramir collection and purchased from Transomic.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S13">
<title>Statistics, Reagents, and Animal Models</title>
<p id="P25">Validated antibodies used in this study included those raised against HA-tag (BioLegend, clone 16B12), DRG1 (Proteintech, 13190-1-AP), DRG2 (Proteintech, 14743-1-AP), JMJD7 (St Johns Laboratory, STJ29545), JMJD4 (Ximbio, 152745), DFRP1 (SIGMA, HPA031099), DFRP2 (GeneTex, GTX120331), β-actin (Abcam, ab8227), FLAG (SIGMA, A8592), and V5 (BioRad, MCA1360P). HEK293T, HeLa, U2OS, A549, and SW620 cell lines were purchased from the ATCC and tested for mycoplasma contamination every 3 months. Cells lined are further validated by STR profiling as part of a rolling program. Statistical analyses generally involved calculation of mean and standard deviation or standard error of data obtained from a minimum of three biologically independent samples. Assays with recombinant proteins were carried out (at least) in technical triplicate. Sample sizes were designed based on prior assay experience, similar work on related projects, and pilot data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S14">
<title>Expression vectors and site-directed mutagenesis</title>
<p id="P26"><italic>JMJD7</italic>, <italic>DRG1</italic>, <italic>DRG2</italic>, <italic>DFRP1</italic>, <italic>DFRP2</italic> and <italic>dmJMJD7</italic> cDNA were cloned into the pCDNA3 vector (ThermoFisher) by PCR to incorporate the indicated <italic>N</italic>-terminal epitope tags. JMJD7 and variants with <italic>N</italic>-terminal 3x-FLAG tags were cloned into the RFP site of the doxycycline-inducible pTRIPZ vector (GE LifeSciences) (‘pTIPZ’). The pET28a-JMJD7 plasmid was prepared by Dr. Wei Ge and generated by inserting the human <italic>JMJD7</italic> gene (encoding full-length JMJD7, residues 1-316, NCBI gene accession number: 100137047) into the pET28a vector (Novagen) for production in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> with an <italic>N</italic>-terminal His<sub>6</sub>-tag and a thrombin protease cleavage site (MGSSHHHHHHSSGLVPR*GSH). The following human JMJD7 constructs (residues 1-316, 1-295, 27-316, 27-295), which were used to investigate oligomerization of JMJD7, were amplified from pET28a-JMJD7 using custom primers (Sigma Aldrich) and cloned into the pNIC28-Bsa4 vector using ligation-independent cloning, resulting in constructs with an <italic>N</italic>-terminal His<sub>6</sub>-tag and tobacco etch virus (TEV) protease cleavage site (MHHHHHHSSGVDLGTENLYFQ*SM). Genes encoding for full-length DRG1 (residues 1-367, NCBI gene accession number: 4733) and DRG2 (residues 1-364; NCBI gene accession number: 1819) were amplified from U2-OS cDNA (kindly provided by Dr Louise Walport, University of Oxford) and also inserted into the pNIC28-Bsa4 vector. Site-directed mutagenesis was performed using custom primers (Invitrogen or Sigma Aldrich) and either Phusion High-Fidelity PCR Master Mix with HF Buffer (NEB) or the Stratagene QuikChange® method with Q5 High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (NEB). PCR was carried out according to the manufacturer’s recommendations followed by DpnI (Thermo-Fisher) digestion for 60 minutes at 37°C before DNA purification and bacterial transformation. All constructs were fully DNA sequence verified.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S15">
<title>Immunofluorescence</title>
<p id="P27">HeLa cells were seeded onto glass cover slips the day before transfection with pCDNA3 FLAG-JMJD7 and/or HA-DRG1/2. After 48 hours, cells were washed three times with cold PBS before fixing and permeabilizing with 100% acetone for 7 minutes at -20°C. Immunofluorescence co-staining was achieved by incubating samples with primary antibodies at 4°C overnight. Secondary antibodies (Alexa Fluor 555 anti-mouse and Alexa Fluor 488nm anti-rabbit (ThermoFisher)) were incubated at 1:2,000 for 1 hour at room temperature prior to DAPI (Sigma) staining. Cover slips were mounted onto slides using anti-fade mounting media (NEB ProLong Gold) and imaged using Zeiss LSM510.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S16">
<title>Protein expression analyses</title>
<p id="P28">Cellular proteins were extracted using either JIES (20 mM Tris·HCl pH 7.4, 100 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5% (v/v) Igepal CA-630, and Complete protease inhibitors (Roche)) or RIPA buffer. Protein extracts were quantified and equalized using Pierce 660nm Protein Assay Reagent. Western blotting antibodies were as described above. Signals were developed using SuperSignal West Pico, Dura, or Femto chemiluminescent substrates (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S17">
<title>JMJD7 proteomic screen</title>
<p id="P29">Inducible FLAG-JMJD7 stable cell lines (wildtype and H178A variant) were treated with doxycycline (SIGMA) for 38 hours before the addition of 1 mM dimethyl-<italic>N</italic>-oxalylglycine (DMOG; SIGMA, D3695) for 16 hours, to trap substrates. Cells were lysed in JIES in the presence of 1 mM <italic>N</italic>-oxalylglycine (NOG; Cambridge Bioscience, 13944), prior to immunoprecipitation with anti-FLAG M2 Magnetic Beads (Sigma, M8823), overnight at 4°C with rotation. Samples were then washed six times in JIES before elution with 100 μg/ml 3x-FLAG peptide (SIGMA, F4799). Eluents were desalted by methanol:chloroform extraction prior to in-solution trypsin digestion using standard methods<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>. Purified tryptic peptides were analyzed by mass spectrometry (as detailed below) in technical triplicates to allow for label-free quantification.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S18">
<title>JMJD7:DRG interaction assays</title>
<p id="P30">Doxycycline-inducible FLAG-JMJD7 stable cell lines were treated with doxycycline as above before the addition, or not, of 1 mM DMOG for 10-16 hours. Cells were lysed in JIES in the presence or absence of 1 mM NOG prior to immunoprecipitation with anti-FLAG Beads, overnight at 4°C with rotation. Samples were then washed six times in JIES before elution with 100 μg/ml 3x-FLAG peptide. The interaction of transfected FLAG-DRG1/2 with endogenous JMJD7 was explored using an identical approach. Endogenous DRG/DFRP/JMJD7 complexes were analyzed by immunoprecipitation from large-scale DMOG-treated HEK293T cell extracts using DFRP antibodies bound to protein A agarose (Millipore) and eluted with 2x Laemmli buffer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S19">
<title>DRG purification for MS analyses</title>
<p id="P31">For exogenous DRG analyses, HEK293T cells were transfected with the pCDNA3 HA-DRG1/V5-DFRP1 or pCDNA3 HA-DRG2/V5-DFRP2 vectors in the presence or absence of pCDNA3 FLAG-JMJD7. Cells were incubated under standard culture conditions for 48 hours before lysis in JIES buffer and immunoaffinity purification of DRG/DFRP complexes using anti-HA agarose beads (SIGMA, A2095) at 4°C for 16 hours with rotation. Beads were washed five times with JIES before elution with anti-HA peptide (SIGMA, I2149), protease digest, and mass spectrometry analysis. For endogenous DRG analyses, large-scale cell cultures were lysed in JIES buffer before immunoaffinity purification using the antibodies described above. Beads were washed with JIES buffer and eluted with 2X Laemmli buffer and separated by SDS-PAGE. DRG1 and DRG2 protein bands were excised from Coomassie-stained gels prior to protease digest and mass spectrometry analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S20">
<title>RNA interaction assays</title>
<p id="P32">HEK293T cells were transfected with pcDNA3 FLAG-DRG1, -DRG1-K22A, -DRG2 or DRG2-K21A. Alternatively, stable HEK293T cell lines expressing conditional control and JMJD7 shRNA were treated with 1 μg/ml doxycycline for 72h prior to transfection with pCDNA3 FLAG-DRG2. Forty-eight hours after transfections cells were lysed in JIES buffer, then centrifuged (14,000 rpm, 10 minutes) to remove cell debris. Protein extracts were used directly in RNA pulldown assays, or were subject to anti-FLAG immunoprecipitation and elution (as above) to purify FLAG-DRG proteins for use in RNA pulldown assays (in the presence of JIES buffer supplemented with 1mM DTT). Samples were incubated with either 4 mg polycytidylic acid-Agarose beads (SIGMA, P9827), 4 mg polyuridylic acid-Agarose beads (SIGMA, P8563) or 20 μl control Protein A Agarose beads (Millipore, 16-156) at 4°C for 2 hours with rotation. Beads were washed five times with JIES before elution with 30 μl 2X Laemmli buffer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S21">
<title>Cellular Protein Mass Spectrometry</title>
<p id="P33">Protein samples were digested and desalted using standard methods for in-gel<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref> and in-solution<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref> digest. Desalted samples were analyzed by nLC-MS/MS with frontend separation using a Dionex Ultimate 3000 UPLC at a flowrate of 250 nl/min. Peptides were separated using a PepMAP C18 column (75 μm × 500 mm, 2 μm particle size) and a one hour gradient of 2-35% Acetonitrile in 5% DMSO/0.1% formic acid. For MS detection, we either used a Q-Exactive, Q-Exactive HF or Orbitrap Fusion Lumos (all Thermo) in HCD mode (Q-Exactives) or CID/Ion trap detection mode for MS/MS data acquisition with the following parameters: <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Q-Exactive</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Q-Exactive HF</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Orbitrap Fusion Lumos</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Resolution MS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">70000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">60000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">120000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Resolution MS2/Scan rate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">17500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">30000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">rapid</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">MS1 scan range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">380 to 1800 m/z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">375 to 1500 m/z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">375 to 1500 m/z</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">MS2 scan range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">200 to 2000 m/z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">200 to 2000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">auto</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">pAGC target MS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3.00E+06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3.00E+06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4.00E+05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">pAGC target MS2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.00E+05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">5.00E+04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2.00E+03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Top N/Speed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Dynamic Exclusion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">27 s</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">27 s</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">60 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">max. injection time MS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">100 ms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">45 ms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">max. injection time MS2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">128 ms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">100 ms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Normalized collision energy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Activation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">HCD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">HCD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">CID</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">MS2 detector</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Orbitrap</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Orbitrap</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Linear Ion Trap</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
<p id="P34">Data were searched against the UniProt Reference (UPR) <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> database (retrieved 15.10.2014) with PEAKS Studio 7.5 (Bioinformatics Solutions) with 10 ppm mass error tolerance for precursor mass and 0.05 Da (Q-Exactives) / 0.5 Da (Orbitrap Fusion Lumos) tolerance for fragment masses. Carbamidomethylation on cysteine was selected as a ‘fixed’ modification, while oxidation (M), deamidation (N, Q) and hydroxylation (P, K, D, N, R, Y) were selected as variable modifications for the database search. Using a target/decoy fusion approach, the peptide false discovery rate was set to 1%. Peptide abundance was measured as accumulated ion counts after extraction of the chromatographic elution profile of the precursor mass of interest using Qual Browser, Xcalibur 3.0.63 (Thermo).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S22">
<title><italic>In vitro</italic> JMJD7:DRG interaction assay</title>
<p id="P35">HA-DRG1, -DRG1-K22A, -DRG2, and -DRG2-K21A proteins were produced <italic>in vitro</italic> using the TNT Quick-Coupled transcription/translation system (Promega, L1170). IVVT reactions and anti-FLAG M2 Magnetic Beads (Sigma, m8823) were spiked into HEK293T cell lysates expressing either pCDNA3 or pCDNA3-FLAG-JMJD7 prior to overnight incubation at 4°C for 16 hours with rotation. Anti-FLAG beads were washed three times with JIES buffer before eluting with 50 μl 2X Laemmli buffer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S23">
<title>Protein Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) DRG1/2 analysis</title>
<p id="P36">Protein BLAST<sup>®</sup> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi?PAGE=Proteins">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi?PAGE=Proteins</ext-link>) searches identified DRG1/2 homologs from indicated organisms using the human protein sequence as the entry query (NCBI Reference IDs – <italic>H. sapiens:</italic> NP_004138.1/001379.1; <italic>X. laevis:</italic> 001084013.1/001079983.1; <italic>D. melanogaster:</italic> 536733.1/650822.1; <italic>C. elegans:</italic> 001255126.1/498808.2; <italic>A. thaliana:</italic> 195662.1/173190.1; <italic>S. cerevisiae:</italic> 009364.1/011689.1; <italic>D. discoideum:</italic> 636294.1/641633.1; <italic>T. thermophila:</italic> 001025967.2/001021328.1). Sequences were aligned using Clustal Omega (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/</ext-link>) and shaded using GeneDoc (version 2.7) as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S24">
<title>Recombinant protein production and purification</title>
<p id="P37">All recombinant JMJD7 proteins were produced with <italic>N-</italic>terminal His<sub>6</sub>-tags in <italic>E. coli</italic> Rosetta™ (DE3)pLysS cells (Novagen). Cells were grown in 2TY media at 37°C to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.6-0.8. Recombinant protein production was induced with 0.5 mM isopropyl β-D-1-thiogalactopyrandoside (ITPG); cells were then grown overnight at 18°C. Proteins were purified by nickel affinity chromatography using an AKTA FPLC system (GE Healthcare®). Recombinant protein was eluted from the column using a stepwise gradient (30 – 250 mM imidazole), and protein-containing fractions were further purified by size exclusion chromatography using a Superdex 75 10/300 GL column (Amersham Pharmacia Biosciences). Protein purity was assessed by SDS-PAGE analysis and subsequently pooled, concentrated (10-25 mg/mL), flash frozen in liquid nitrogen, then stored at -80°C in 50 mM Hepes, 200 mM NaCl, 2% glycerol, pH 7.5.</p>
<p id="P38">Recombinant DRG1 was produced and purified as reported<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>. The TEV protease was used for His<sub>6</sub>-tag cleavage (1:20, TEV:DRG1) with overnight treatment at 4 °C. DRG1 was collected as the eluent after a 5 mL HiTrap nickel column treatment. DRG1 purity was validated by SDS-PAGE and MS analyses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S25">
<title>Recombinant DRG1 hydroxylation</title>
<p id="P39">Purified, full-length DRG1 was hydroxylated by treatment with His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7. Assay mixtures contained 50 μM DRG1, 2 μM JMJD7, 100 μM ammonium iron(II) sulphate hexahydrate (Fe(II)), 500 μM 2-oxoglutarate acid disodium salt (2OG), 1 mM (+)-sodium L-ascorbate (ascorbate) in 50 mM HEPES, 500 mM NaCl, 5% glycerol, pH 7.5. The reaction was carried out for 2 h at 37°C. Hydroxylated DRG1 was collected as the eluent after a 5 mL HiTrap nickel column treatment. Hydroxylation was confirmed by MS analysis using a Xevo GS-2-S mass spectrometer (Waters). &gt;95% hydroxylation, as observed by MS, was achieved under the stated conditions. The concentration of the hydroxylated samples was determined using a ND-1000 Spectrophotometer (Nanodrop Technologies).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S26">
<title>Peptide synthesis</title>
<p id="P40">The 25-mer DRG1<sub>16-40</sub> (ARTQKNKATAHHLGLLKARLAKLRR-NH<sub>2</sub>, &gt;95%) and DRG2<sub>15-39</sub> (ARTQKNKATEYHLGLLKAKLAKYRA-NH<sub>2</sub>, &gt;95%) peptides) were commercially synthesized with <italic>C</italic>-terminal amides by either Severn Biotech (United Kingdom) or GL BioChem (China).</p>
<p id="P41">The DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> peptide (NKATAHHLGLLKARLAKLRR-NH<sub>2</sub>) was synthesized in house by solid phase synthesis using a Liberty Blue automated microwave peptide synthesizer (CEM Corporation, USA) for amino acid analysis as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>. All other peptides used for screening were synthesized using a Multipep RSi solid phase peptide synthesizer (Intavis AG Bioanalytical Instruments, Germany) on a plate module (1-5 mg scale) using Tentagel S-RAM resin as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>. All peptides were synthesized as <italic>C</italic>-terminal amides. The DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> peptide used for amino acid analysis was purified by reverse-phase high-performance liquid chromatography using a Vydac C18 column (Solvent A = 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid in water; Solvent B = 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid in acetonitrile) to &gt;90% purity as determined by LC-MS. Peptides used for screening assays were not purified.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S27">
<title>JMJD7 activity assays</title>
<sec id="S28">
<title>JMJD7 NMR activity assays</title>
<p id="P42">NMR assays were carried out as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>. 160 µL reactions were prepared in a 1.5 mL Eppendorf tube with 16 µL D<sub>2</sub>O (Sigma-Aldrich), ±100 µM Fe(II), 200 µM 2OG, ±500 µM ascorbate, ±1 mM NOG, ±10 µM JMJD7, and ±10 µM JMJD7-H178A in 20 mM Tris D-11 (Cambridge Isotope Laboratories), pH 7.5. Reactions were initiated by addition of JMJD7 or JMJD7-H178A and immediately transferred to a 3 mm Shigemi NMR tube, which was centrifuged for a few seconds in a hand centrifuge. Proton NMR spectra were acquired, and the reaction was monitored in real-time on a Bruker Avance III 700 MHz spectrometer equipped with a 5 mm inverse TCI cryoprobe at 298K and controlled by TopSpin 3.5. The AV700 was controlled by TopSpin software, and spectrometer conditions were optimized using a control sample with all reaction components except JMJD7 prior to data acquisition. The first proton spectrum was acquired with water suppression (16 scans), 325 s after mixing, following brief optimization (start of data acquisition was 225 s). Spectra were automatically acquired every 105 s for 1900 s. TopSpin 3.2 software was used to process and integrate the peaks corresponding to 2OG and succinate for analysis using Microsoft Excel 2003.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S29">
<title>MALDI-MS hydroxylation assays</title>
<p id="P43">JMJD7 assay mixtures (final volume 20 µL in 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5) containing 50 µM peptide and 10 µM His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7 were incubated for 60 minutes at 37°C with 100 µM Fe(II), 200 µM 2OG, and 500 ascorbate. Reactions were quenched by immediately spotting 1 µL of assay sample and 1 µL of α-cyano-4-hydroxycinnamic acid (CHCA) matrix solution (saturated CHCA in 50% acetonitrile, 50% water, 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid) onto a Waters 96-spot MALDI plate. The samples were analyzed using MALDI- MS and a Waters Micromass™ MALDI micro MX™ instrument in the positive ion reflectron mode. MALDI-MS spectra were analyzed using MassLynx 4.1 (Waters) by baseline subtraction (polynomial order, 15; below curve %, 10; tolerance, 0.01) and smoothing (number of smooths, 2; smooth window channels, 10; Savitzky-Golay).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S30">
<title>Co-factor/substrate dependence assays</title>
<p id="P44">Co-factor/substrate dependence assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>) were performed as described (above) with the following modifications: 50 µM DRG1<sub>16-40</sub>, ±1 µM JMJD7 or JMJD7-H178A, ±100 µM Fe(II), ±500 µM 2OG, ± 1mM ascorbate, ± 1mM NOG, and quenching after 5 minutes of incubation at 37°C with formic acid (2% final concentration) prior to spotting on the MALDI plate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S31">
<title><sup>18</sup>O<sub>2</sub> incorporation assays</title>
<p id="P45">Hydroxylation of DRG1<sub>16-40</sub> by JMJD7 was performed under atmospheres of argon, <sup>16</sup>O<sub>2</sub>, or <sup>18</sup>O<sub>2</sub> (CK Isotopes, 98%) as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>. Assays were performed under the following conditions: 50 µM DRG1<sub>16-40</sub>, ±2.5 µM JMJD7, 100 µM Fe(II), 500 µM 2OG, and 1 mM ascorbate in 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5. A solution of peptide and buffer (94 µL) in a septum-sealed glass vial was purged with N<sub>2</sub> for 30 minutes on ice using a mass flow controller (Brooks Instruments) and an escape needle. 1µL of 2OG, Fe(II), ascorbate, and JMJD7 were then sequentially added on ice using gastight Hamiltonian syringes. A balloon attached to a syringe was purged 3x with Argon then filled with the gas of choice (argon, <sup>16</sup>O<sub>2</sub>, and <sup>18</sup>O<sub>2</sub>). The reaction was initiated by slowly bubbling the gas into the solution at room temperature using an escape needle until the balloon was deflated (~10 minutes). The escape needle was removed, followed by the balloon; the solution was then incubated at 37°C for an additional 20 minutes and quenched with 100 µL of 4% formic acid. Products were analyzed by MALDI-MS as above.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S32">
<title>Non-denaturing MS</title>
<p id="P46">Stoichiometry measurements were performed using a hybrid quadrupole-Orbitrap (Thermo QExactive) and a quadrupole-time-of-flight (Waters Synapt G2Si) instrument for detection of high mass ions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>. Samples (10 µM) were buffer exchanged into 200 mM ammonium acetate using Bio-spin 6 (Bio-Rad) centrifuge columns immediately prior to analysis. Ions were generated by static nanoelectrospray using gold-coated capillaries prepared in-house. Data were obtained with a wide acquisition window (2,000-10,000 <italic>m/</italic>z); desolvation was achieved with moderate HCD voltage (QExactive; 10-50 V) or CID (Synapt; 4 V) applied. Instrument settings were: (QExactive): capillary voltage = 1.1 kV; source temperature = 50°C; max injection time = 50; S-lens RF = 100; C-trap entrance lens = 5.8. Spectra were obtained with 10 microscans, averaged over 100 scans. Instrument settings were as follows (Synapt): capillary voltage = 1.4 kV; source temperature = 50°C; sample cone = 10 V; trap DC bias = 10 V. Data were processed using XCalibur 2.1 (Thermo Scientific) and MassLynx V4.1 (Waters) software and masses were assigned using in-house software (Mass/Charge State Error Determination v 0.3; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://benesch.chem.ox.ac.uk/resources.html">http://benesch.chem.ox.ac.uk/resources.html</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S33">
<title>SEC-MALS and CD studies</title>
<p id="P47">Analysis of JMJD7 was performed using an Agilent 1260 HPLC with a Superdex 200 Increase 3.2/300 SEC column (GE Healthcare) coupled to a DAWN HELEOS II scattering detector (Wyatt Technologies) and Optilab T-rEX (Wyatt Technologies) differential refractive index detector. The MALS detector was equilibrated overnight in running buffer to ensure minimal background light scattering. ~30 μg of protein was loaded on-column (column compartment was set to 20°C) at a flow rate of 75 µL/min in 50 mM HEPES, 200 mM NaCl, 2% glycerol, pH 7.5. Data acquisition and analysis were performed with Astra 6.1 software (Wyatt Technologies).</p>
<p id="P48">CD spectra were acquired using a Chirascan CD spectrometer (Applied Photophysics model) equipped with a Peltier temperature-control cell holder. Experiments were performed at 20°C in a 0.1 cm pathlength cuvette using 0.2 mg/mL of protein in 10 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 8.0. Data were recorded in triplicate from 260 to 185 nm in 0.5 nm steps with a 1 nm bandwidth. Spectral data were baseline corrected, averaged, and smoothed using the Savitzky-Golay filter (smooth = 8).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S34">
<title>Peptide NMR analyses</title>
<p id="P49">DRG1<sub>16-40</sub> and DRG2<sub>15-39</sub> peptides (~1.4 mg) were incubated with 2 µM JMJD7, 100 µM Fe(II), 500 µM 2OG, 1 mM ascorbate in 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5 (10 mL reaction volume) for 2 hours at 37°C; reactions were quenched by adding neat formic acid dropwise until pH ~2. Peptides were purified using two Sep Pak C18 columns in tandem according to the Kessler Laboratory Proteomics Protocol (University of Oxford, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccmp.ox.ac.uk/_asset/file/sep-pak-c18.pdf">http://www.ccmp.ox.ac.uk/_asset/file/sep-pak-c18.pdf</ext-link>; all volumes doubled), eluting with 4 mL of 40% acetonitrile, 0.1% formic acid solution in double distilled water. Samples were then dried by vacuum centrifugation and resuspended in H<sub>2</sub>O/D<sub>2</sub>O (9:1) for 2D NMR analyses (HSQC, HMBC, COSY, TOCSY). Spectra were recorded using a Bruker AVIII 700 MHz NMR spectrometer equipped with a 5-mm inverse cryoprobe using 3mm MATCH NMR tubes (Cortecnet). Data were processed using a TopSpin 3.2 software (Bruker).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S35">
<title>Amino acid analyses</title>
<sec id="S36">
<title>Sample Preparation</title>
<p id="P50">Peptides (50 µM; DRG1<sub>21-40</sub>, DRG1<sub>16-40</sub>, and DRG2<sub>15-39</sub>) were incubated with 100 µM Fe(II), 200 µM 2OG, and 500 µM ascorbate in the presence or absence of 10 µM recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7 for 1 hour at 37°C in 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5 (final volume 500 µL). The reaction was quenched with 2 drops of neat formic acid; hydroxylation (~40-80%) of the peptide was confirmed by MALDI-MS. Recombinant JMJD7 was removed using a Sep Pak C18 column according to the Kessler Lab Proteomics Protocol (University of Oxford, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccmp.ox.ac.uk/_asset/file/sep-pak-c18.pdf">http://www.ccmp.ox.ac.uk/_asset/file/sep-pak-c18.pdf</ext-link>), eluting with a 15% acetonitrile, 0.1% formic acid solution in double distilled water. Samples were then dried by vacuum centrifugation and subsequently re-suspended in 60 µL of 20 mM HEPES, pH 7.5. Enzymatic hydrolysis was carried out at 37°C with a non-specific protease from <italic>Streptomyces griseus</italic> (9 µL, 1 mg mL<sup>-1</sup>, Sigma-Aldrich) overnight.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S37">
<title>LC-MS analyses</title>
<p id="P51">Hydrolyzed samples were dried by vacuum centrifugation followed by resuspension in borate buffer and derivatization with 6-aminoquinolyl-<italic>N</italic>-hydroxysuccinimidyl carbamate (AQC) according to the AccQ-Tag Ultra Derivatization Protocol (Waters). LC-MS analyses were performed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, using a Waters Acquity ultra performance liquid chromatography system coupled to a Xevo G2-S QTof mass spectrometer equipped with an electrospray ionisation source. Gradient conditions for separation were carried out as described in either the AccQ-Tag Ultra Derivatization Protocol (Waters; 10 minute gradient) or in Feng et al., 2014<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref> (30 minute gradient).</p>
<p id="P52">Conditions for ESI-MS detection: mode, positive-ion; analyzer, resolution mode; desolvation temperature, 600°C; source temperature,100°C, capillary voltage, 3000 V; sample cone voltage, 20 V; cone gas flow, 30 L/min; and desolvation gas flow 1000 L/min. MS data were acquired and extracted ion chromatograms were produced for m/z values of either 503.2, corresponding to the theoretical masses of AQC-derivatized hydroxylysine (503.2037). Extracted ion chromatograms were smoothed (number of smooths, 2; smooth window channels, 3; Savitzky-Golay) and total ion current chromatograms were further baseline subtracted (polynomial order, 1; below curve %, 40; tolerance, 0.01).</p>
<p id="P53">C3, C4, and C5 hydroxylysine standards were synthesized or commercially obtained as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>. The synthesis of the (2<italic>S</italic>,3<italic>R</italic>)/(2<italic>R</italic>,2<italic>S</italic>)-3-hydroxylysine standard has been reported elsewhere<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S38">
<title>Differential scanning calorimtery</title>
<p id="P54">Differential scanning calorimetry experiments were performed on a Malvern (Malvern, UK) VP Capillary DSC instrument at the Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford. Samples and buffer blanks were measured using a thermal ramp of 200 °C/hr between 10°C and 110°C at a pressure of 55 psi. Samples contained 80 μM full length DRG1/hydroxylated DRG1 in the presence or absence of 1 mM GDP (Sigma) in 50 mM HEPES, 500 mM NaCl, 5 % glycerol, pH 7.5. The buffer blanks consisted of 50 mM HEPES, 500 mM NaCl, 5 % glycerol, pH 7.5 (± 1 mM GDP).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S39">
<title>DRG GTPase activity assays</title>
<sec id="S40">
<title>Phosphate release assay</title>
<p id="P55">GTP hydrolysis was measured using a colorimetric assay for determination of phosphate release<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>. Recombinant, full length DRG1 and hydroxylated DRG1 (10 μM) were incubated with increasing concentrations (0–4 mM) of GTP in 100 mM Tris/HCl, pH 8, 300 mM KCl, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10% glycerol at 37 °C for 60 min. Reactions were stopped by adding 50 μL of fresh malachite green reagent. This reagent contained 2 volumes of 0.0812% malachite green, 2 volumes of bidistilled water, 1 volume of ammonium molybdate (5.72% in 6 M HCl) and 1 volume of 2.32% polyvinyl alcohol (Phosphate Assay Kit, colorimetric, Abcam). The samples were read within the next 10 min in a PheraStar plate reader at 650 nm using half-area, medium binding, clear bottom plates (Fischer Scientific). End-point assays contained the purified proteins (10 μM) that were incubated with 1 mM of GTP in 100 mM Tris/HCl, pH 8, 300 mM KCl, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10% glycerol at 42°C for 60 min. The samples were quenched and read as previously stated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S41">
<title>GTPase activity monitoring by NMR</title>
<p id="P56">Purified proteins (40 μM) were incubated with 4 mM of GTP in 50 mM Tris-D<sub>11</sub>, pH 7.5, 300 mM KCl, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, at 37 °C for 60 min. Controls contained 4 mM GTP or GDP under the same conditions. <sup>1</sup>H excitation sculpting suppression NMR spectra were recorded using a Bruker AVIII 600 MHz NMR spectrometer equipped with a BB-F/<sup>1</sup>H Prodigy N<sub>2</sub> cryoprobe using 5 mm diameter NMR tubes (Norell). Spectra were typically obtained using 252 scans, a relaxation delay of 1 s, and a prescan delay of 10 μs. A 2 ms sinc pulse was used for water suppression. Data were processed with a line broadening of 0.3 Hz using TopSpin 3.2 software (Bruker).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S42">
<title>GTPase activity assay of DRG proteins purified from human cells</title>
<p id="P57">FLAG-DRG1/2 proteins and mutants were expressed in HEK293T cells under a variety of conditions, including: co-expression of HA-JMJD7, knockdown of JMJD7 by shRNA (as detailed above), or DMOG treatment (1 mM for 16 hours). Cells were lysed in JIES prior to anti-FLAG immunoprecipitation. Beads were then washed six times in JIES before elution with 100 μg/ml 3x-FLAG peptide in 100 mm Tris-HCl pH 8, 200 mM KCl, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10% (v/v) glycerol. The purity and abundance of DRG1/2 proteins were determined by SDS-PAGE and coomassie staining. GTPase activity of purified proteins was measured using the GTPase-Glo Kit (Promega, V7681), according to the manufacturer’s guidelines, but with the following modifications. Firstly, the GTPase assay buffer was supplemented with 200 mM KCl to support DRG GTPase activity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>. Secondly, assays were performed at 37°C for either 2h (DRG2) or 8h (DRG1).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S43">
<title>Crystallization conditions</title>
<p id="P58">Crystals of His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7.Mn(II).2OG and His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7-R260C.Mn(II).2OG were obtained in sitting drops at 25°C. For wildtype JMJD7, drops were formed in a 1:1 ratio of a 25 mg/mL His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7, 2 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 4 mM 2OG solution with a 1.5 M sodium nitrate, 0.1 M sodium acetate, pH 4.6 solution. For the R260C variant, drops were formed in a 1:1 ratio of a 26 mg/mL His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7-R260C, 2 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 4 mM 2OG solution with a 1.5 M sodium nitrate, 0.1 M sodium acetate, pH 4.6 solution containing additives (0.25% β-Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate tetrasodium salt, 0.25% Adenosine 5’-triphosphate disodium salt hydrate, 0.25% N-Acetyl-D-galactosamine, 0.25% Gentamicin sulfate salt hydrate, 0.02 M HEPES sodium pH 6.8). Crystals were cryoprotected with 25% glycerol before flash freezing in liquid nitrogen.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S44">
<title>Data collection, structure solution, and refinement</title>
<p id="P59">Data were collected using single crystals at 100 K at the Diamond Light Source (DLS) beam lines I04 (PDB: 5NFN, λ=0.9795 Å) and I03 (PDB: 5NFO, λ=0.9795 Å) and processed using HKL2000<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>.</p>
<p id="P60">His<sub>6</sub>-JMJD7.Mn(II).2OG data were strongly anisotropic (the spread in values of the three principal components of scale factors is 62.37 Å<sup>2</sup>), with resolution limits of 3.5 Å, 3.5 Å, and 3.0 Å along the reciprocal axes a*, b* and c* (at an F/σ cutoff of 3). The data were ellipsoidally truncated and anisotropically scaled using the 'STARANISO anisotropy &amp; Bayesian estimation server' (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://staraniso.globalphasing.org/cgi-bin/staraniso.cgi">http://staraniso.globalphasing.org/cgi-bin/staraniso.cgi</ext-link>) with intensities renormalized for structure solution and initial rounds of refinements. An ensemble of models was generated by the ENSEMBLER built in PHENIX<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref> using crystal structures of the related JmjC-enzymes, FIH (PDB ID: 1H2K), TYW5 (PDB ID: 3AL5), JMJD5 (PDB ID: 4GJZ), and JMJD6 (PDB ID: 3K2O) as templates. To ensure maximum degree of accuracy, only JMJD7 residues that are highly conserved in these four JmjC-hydroxylases were included in the homology models. The wildtype JMJD7 structure was then solved by molecular replacement using PHASER<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>. An initial model was generated by PHENIX AUTOBUILD<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>, which included 82% of JMJD7 residues making up the four molecules in the asymmetric unit. Iterative cycles of model building and refinement using Buster<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref> were performed until converging R<sub>factor</sub>/R<sub>free</sub> no longer decreased. Final rounds of intensity-based refinements were performed using CNS<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref> and PHENIX<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>. JMJD7-R260C structure was solved by molecular replacement using PHASER<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref> with 2 molecules per asymmetric unit using the JMJD7-wt structure as the initial model and refined by CNS<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>/PHENIX<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref> until R<sub>factor</sub>/R<sub>free</sub> converged with iterative cycles model building using COOT<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>. MOLPROBITY<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref> was used to monitor the geometric quality of the models between refinement cycles. Water molecules were added to peaks (&gt; 1.5 σ 2F<sub>o</sub>F<sub>c</sub>) in electron density maps that were within H-bond distance to protein with reasonable geometry to form H-bonds.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="SM" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<label>Supplementary information</label>
<media id="d36e1877" mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS77001-supplement-Supplementary_information.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S45">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>We thank the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (BB/L009846/1, CJS), Medical Research Council (MR/N021053/1, MLC), Wellcome Trust (106244/Z/14/Z, CJS), Cancer Research UK (24552, MLC), University of Oxford Clarendon Fund (SM), and a Junior Research Fellowship from Kellogg College, University of Oxford (MIA) for support. We thank E Flashman (Department of Chemistry, University of Oxford) for assistance with the <sup>18</sup>O<sub>2</sub> experiment and K Connolly (Institute of Cancer and Genomics Sciences, University of Birmingham) for <italic>Drosophila</italic> cDNA.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN2">
<p id="P61">
<bold>Author Contributions</bold>
</p>
<p id="P62">S.M., Q.Z., S.E.W., M.J.K., P.W., R.C., M.L.C, and C.J.S. designed and conceived the research; S.M. prepared recombinant proteins; Q.Z. performed substrate discovery proteomics; S.M. performed and analyzed CD spectra and all enzyme activity assays by MALDI-MS and NMR; Q.Z. performed enzyme:substrate interaction assays; S.M. and R.C. performed the crystallography in which R.C. played both an experimental and supervisory role; C.E. performed confocal microscopy, cellular dimerization, and dmJMJD7 interaction experiments; Q.Z., C.H., and H.E.M. prepared mammalian expression constructs used by Q.Z.; W.G. and S.M. prepared plasmids for recombinant protein production; S.M. performed / analyzed amino acid analyses with guidance from S.E.W; M.I.A. performed and analyzed peptide NMR work; Q.Z. purified exogenous and endogenous proteins for MS / analyzed data with help from M.L.C; M.I.A. produced and purified recombinant DRG1, performed DRG1 stability and activity assays, and analyzed data; R.K., S.D., and R.F. performed MS (B.M.K.) and analyzed data; Q.Z. performed all JMJD7 loss-of-function experiments and DRG/DFRP interaction, GTPase, and RNA binding assays; R.K.L. prepared hydroxylysine standards; S.M. and W.B.S. performed and analyzed native MS / SEC-MALS (J.L.B.); M.J.K. and P.W. performed and analyzed <italic>Drosophila</italic> experiments; R.C. performed enzyme:substrate modelling, prepared recombinant dmJMJD7, and performed proteolysis assays; M.Y., M.E.C., and P.J.R. performed preliminary immunoprecipitations; S.M., Q.Z., S.E.W., C.E., R.C., M.L.C., and C.J.S. analyzed data; S.M., Q.Z., R.C., M.L.C., and C.J.S. wrote the manuscript.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3">
<p id="P63">
<bold>Competing Interests</bold>
</p>
<p id="P64">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN4">
<p id="P65">
<bold>Data availability</bold>
</p>
<p id="P66">Atomic coordinates and structure factors for crystal structures have been deposited in
the Protein Data Bank under the accession codes: 5NFN and 5NFO. Mass
Spectrometry data are available under PXD009263 at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.proteomexchange.org/">www.proteomexchange.org/</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Markolovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schofield</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Protein hydroxylation catalyzed by 2-oxoglutarate-dependent oxygenases</article-title>
<source/>J Biol Chem
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>290</volume>
<fpage>20712</fpage>
<lpage>20722</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26152730</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ploumakis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coleman</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>OH, the places you’ll go! Hydroxylation, gene expression, and cancer</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cell
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>729</fpage>
<lpage>741</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26046647</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Semenza</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oxygen sensing, hypoxia-inducible factors, and disease pathophysiology</article-title>
<source/>Annu Rev Pathol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>47</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23937437</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Elkins</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of factor-inhibiting hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF) reveals mechanism of oxidative modification of HIF-1α</article-title>
<source/>J Biol Chem
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>278</volume>
<fpage>1802</fpage>
<lpage>1806</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12446723</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walport</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hopkinson</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schofield</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of human histone and nucleic acid demethylases</article-title>
<source/>Curr Opin Chem Biol
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>525</fpage>
<lpage>534</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063108</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The roles of Jumonji-type oxygenases in human disease</article-title>
<source/>Epigenomics
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>89</fpage>
<lpage>120</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24579949</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morera</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lübbert</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Targeting histone methyltransferases and demethylases in clinical trials for cancer therapy</article-title>
<source/>Clin Epigenetics
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>57</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27222667</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holt-Martyn</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schofield</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ratcliffe</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pharmacological targeting of the HIF hydroxylases – A new field in medicine development</article-title>
<source/>Mol Aspects Med
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>47–48</volume>
<fpage>54</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cockman</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ratcliffe</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>FIH-dependent asparaginyl hydroxylation of ankyrin repeat domain-containing proteins</article-title>
<source/>Ann N Y Acad Sci
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>1177</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<lpage>18</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19845602</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Webby</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Jmjd6 catalyses lysyl-hydroxylation of U2AF65, a protein associated with RNA splicing</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>325</volume>
<fpage>90</fpage>
<lpage>93</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19574390</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ribosomal oxygenases are structurally conserved from prokaryotes to humans</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>510</volume>
<fpage>422</fpage>
<lpage>426</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24814345</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ge</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oxygenase-catalyzed ribosome hydroxylation occurs in prokaryotes and humans</article-title>
<source/>Nat Chem Biol
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>960</fpage>
<lpage>962</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23103944</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kato</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Crystal structure of a novel JmjC-domain-containing protein, TYW5, involved in tRNA modification</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>1576</fpage>
<lpage>1585</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20972222</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Optimal translational termination requires C4 lysyl hydroxylation of eRF1</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cell
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>645</fpage>
<lpage>654</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24486019</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhuang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coleman</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Modifying the maker: Oxygenases target ribosome biology</article-title>
<source/>Transl
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>e1009331</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Del Rizzo</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krishnan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trievel</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Crystal structure and functional analysis of JMJD5 indicate an alternate specificity and function</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cell Biol
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>4044</fpage>
<lpage>4052</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22851697</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Markolovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure-function relationships of human JmjC oxygenases—demethylases versus hydroxylases</article-title>
<source/>Curr Opin Struct Biol
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>62</fpage>
<lpage>72</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27309310</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rose</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McDonough</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>ONF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kawamura</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schofield</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of 2-oxoglutarate dependent oxygenases</article-title>
<source/>Chem Soc Rev
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>4364</fpage>
<lpage>4397</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21390379</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kandoth</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Integrated genomic characterization of endometrial carcinoma</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>497</volume>
<fpage>67</fpage>
<lpage>73</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23636398</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Matsunami</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of rare DNA sequence variants in high-risk autism families and their prevalence in a large case/control population</article-title>
<source/>Mol Autism
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24467814</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lancaster</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Disruption of dimerization and substrate phosphorylation inhibit factor inhibiting hypoxia-inducible factor (FIH) activity</article-title>
<source/>Biochem J
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>383</volume>
<fpage>429</fpage>
<lpage>437</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15239670</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ishikawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Azuma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ikawa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Semba</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of DRG family regulatory proteins (DFRPs): Specific regulation of DRG1 and DRG2</article-title>
<source/>Genes to Cells
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>
<lpage>150</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15676025</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Francis</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gas</surname>
<given-names>M-E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daugeron</surname>
<given-names>M-C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bravo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seraphin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Rbg1-Tma46 dimer structure reveals new functional domains and their role in polysome recruitment</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>11100</fpage>
<lpage>11114</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23002146</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mantri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The 2-oxoglutarate-dependent oxygenase JMJD6 catalyses oxidation of lysine residues to give 5S-hydroxylysine residues</article-title>
<source/>ChemBioChem
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>531</fpage>
<lpage>534</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22238144</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Witkop</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The application of Hudson’s lactone rule to γ- and δ-hydroxyamino acids and the question of the configuration of δ-hydroxy-L-lysine from collagen</article-title>
<source/>Experientia
          <year>1956</year>
<volume>XII</volume>
<fpage>372</fpage>
<lpage>374</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Myllyharju</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kivirikko</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Collagens and collagen-related diseases</article-title>
<source/>Ann Med
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>7</fpage>
<lpage>21</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11310942</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leśniak</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markolovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tars</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schofield</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Human carnitine biosynthesis proceeds via (2<italic>S</italic>,3<italic>S</italic>)-3-hydroxy-N<sup><italic>ε</italic></sup>-trimethyllysine</article-title>
<source/>Chem Commun
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>440</fpage>
<lpage>442</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Daugeron</surname>
<given-names>M-C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prouteau</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lacroute</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Séraphin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The highly conserved eukaryotic DRG factors are required for efficient translation in a manner redundant with the putative RNA helicase Slh1</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>2221</fpage>
<lpage>2233</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21076151</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ishikawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cloning and characterization of Xenopus laevis drg2, a member of the developmentally regulated GTP-binding protein subfamily</article-title>
<source/>Gene
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>322</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>112</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14644502</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Factor-inhibiting hypoxia-inducible factor (FIH) catalyses the post-translational hydroxylation of histidinyl residues within ankyrin repeat domains</article-title>
<source/>FEBS J
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>278</volume>
<fpage>1086</fpage>
<lpage>1097</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21251231</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<label>31</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klose</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kallin</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>JmjC-domain-containing proteins and histone demethylation</article-title>
<source/>Nat Rev Genet
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>715</fpage>
<lpage>727</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16983801</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<label>32</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walport</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Arginine demethylation is catalysed by a subset of JmjC histone lysine demethylases</article-title>
<source/>Nat Commun
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>11974</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27337104</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<label>33</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mantri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McDonough</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schofield</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autocatalysed oxidative modifications to 2-oxoglutarate dependent oxygenases</article-title>
<source/>FEBS J
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>279</volume>
<fpage>1563</fpage>
<lpage>1575</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22251775</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<label>34</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Matheisl</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berninghausen</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Becker</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beckmann</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of a human translation termination complex</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>8615</fpage>
<lpage>8626</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26384426</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<label>35</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hegde</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ramakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis for stop codon recognition in eukaryotes</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>524</volume>
<fpage>493</fpage>
<lpage>496</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26245381</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<label>36</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Powers</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Asgian</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ekici</surname>
<given-names>OD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>James</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Irreversible inhibitors of serine, cysteine, and threonine proteases</article-title>
<source/>Chem Rev
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>4639</fpage>
<lpage>4750</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12475205</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R37">
<label>37</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maas</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dekeyser</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stafstrom</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Association of DRG1 and DRG2 with ribosomes from pea, arabidopsis, and yeast</article-title>
<source/>Int J Plant Sci
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>170</volume>
<fpage>834</fpage>
<lpage>844</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R38">
<label>38</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ishikawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Akiyama</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Semba</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Independent stabilizations of polysomal Drg1/Dfrp1 complex and non-polysomal Drg2/Dfrp2 complex in mammalian cells</article-title>
<source/>Biochem Biophys Res Commun
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>390</volume>
<fpage>552</fpage>
<lpage>556</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19819225</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R39">
<label>39</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leipe</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wolf</surname>
<given-names>YI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koonin</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aravind</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Classification and evolution of P-loop GTPases and related ATPases</article-title>
<source/>J Mol Biol
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>317</volume>
<fpage>41</fpage>
<lpage>72</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11916378</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R40">
<label>40</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scotti</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Human oxygen sensing may have origins in prokaryotic elongation factor Tu prolyl-hydroxylation</article-title>
<source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>13331</fpage>
<lpage>13336</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25197067</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R41">
<label>41</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<source/>2-Oxoglutarate-dependent oxygenases. RSC Metallobiology Series No. 3
          <publisher-name>Royal Society of Chemistry</publisher-name>
<year>2015</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R42">
<label>42</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jang</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>A-R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>N-H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>I-S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DRG2 regulates G2/M progression via the cyclin B1-Cdk1 complex</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cells
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>699</fpage>
<lpage>704</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27669826</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R43">
<label>43</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DRG1 is a potential oncogene in lung adenocarcinoma and promotes tumor progression via spindle checkpoint signaling regulation</article-title>
<source/>Oncotarget
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>72795</fpage>
<lpage>72806</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27626498</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R44">
<label>44</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular cloning and expression of two closely related GTP-binding proteins from zebrafish</article-title>
<source/>DNA Seq
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>246</fpage>
<lpage>250</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15620211</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R45">
<label>45</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vlangos</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>PI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Elsea</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Assignment of developmentally regulated GTP-binding protein (DRG2) to human chromosome band 17p11.2 with somatic cell hybrids and localization to the Smith-Magenis syndrome critical interval</article-title>
<source/>Cytogenet Cell Genet
          <year>2000</year>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>285</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10828610</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R46">
<label>46</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Krom</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A common variant in DRD3 receptor is associated with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Biol Psychiatry
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>625</fpage>
<lpage>630</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19058789</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R47">
<label>47</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Ligt</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Diagnostic exome sequencing in persons with severe intellectual disability</article-title>
<source/>N Engl J Med
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>367</volume>
<fpage>1921</fpage>
<lpage>1929</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23033978</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R48">
<label>48</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Katz</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sudestada1, a Drosophila ribosomal prolyl-hydroxylase required for mRNA translation, cell homeostasis, and organ growth</article-title>
<source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>4025</fpage>
<lpage>4030</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24550463</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R49">
<label>49</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Discovery of candidate serum proteomic and metabolomic biomarkers in ankylosing spondylitis</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cell Proteomics
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>M111.013904</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R50">
<label>50</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Novel MMP-9 substrates in cancer cells revealed by a label-free quantitative proteomics approach</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cell Proteomics
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>2215</fpage>
<lpage>2228</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18596065</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R51">
<label>51</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pérez-Arellano</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spínola-Amilibia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bravo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Human Drg1 is a potassium-dependent GTPase enhanced by Lerepo4</article-title>
<source/>FEBS J
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>280</volume>
<fpage>3647</fpage>
<lpage>57</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23711155</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R52">
<label>52</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gault</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>High-resolution mass spectrometry of small molecules bound to membrane proteins</article-title>
<source/>Nat Methods
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>333</fpage>
<lpage>336</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26901650</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R53">
<label>53</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parsons</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Optimal synthetic glycosylation of a therapeutic antibody</article-title>
<source/>Angew Chemie Int Ed
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>2361</fpage>
<lpage>2367</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R54">
<label>54</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Otwinowski</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Minor</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Processing of X-ray diffraction data collected in oscillation mode</article-title>
<source/>Methods Enzymol
          <year>1997</year>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>307</fpage>
<lpage>326</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R55">
<label>55</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution</article-title>
<source/>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>213</fpage>
<lpage>221</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124702</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R56">
<label>56</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McCoy</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Phaser crystallographic software</article-title>
<source/>J Appl Crystallogr
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>658</fpage>
<lpage>674</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19461840</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R57">
<label>57</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smart</surname>
<given-names>OS</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Exploiting structure similarity in refinement: automated NCS and target-structure restraints in BUSTER</article-title>
<source/>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>368</fpage>
<lpage>380</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22505257</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R58">
<label>58</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brünger</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Crystallography &amp; NMR system: A new software suite for macromolecular structure determination</article-title>
<source/>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr
          <year>1998</year>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>905</fpage>
<lpage>921</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9757107</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R59">
<label>59</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Emsley</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cowtan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Coot: Model-building tools for molecular graphics</article-title>
<source/>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>2126</fpage>
<lpage>2132</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572765</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R60">
<label>60</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>VB</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>MolProbity: all-atom structure validation for macromolecular crystallography</article-title>
<source/>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<lpage>21</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20057044</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Structural analyses of the JmjC hydroxylase, JMJD7.</title>
<p>(<bold>a</bold>) View from a crystal structure of human JMJD7 complexed with Mn(II) (violet sphere) and 2OG (yellow) showing the unique dimerization interface, which involves regions both <italic>N</italic>- and <italic>C</italic>-terminal to the double-stranded β-helix (DSBH) core fold and the disulfide between Cys47 of each monomer (*, red). β-Strands comprising the distorted 8-stranded (I-VIII) DSBH, conserved in 2OG oxygenases, are in salmon. (<bold>b</bold>) At the active site, Mn (substituting for Fe(II), violet sphere) is octahedrally coordinated by H178, D180, H277, the 2OG oxalyl group (yellow), and water (red sphere). 2OG is apparently tightly bound by hydrogen bonding/electrostatic interactions between its C5 carboxylate and Y127, T175, Y186, and K193, and its C1 carboxylate with N184 and N289 (dotted lines, numerical values represent H-bond distances in Å).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="emss-77001-f001"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<title>JMJD7 interacts with DRG/DFRP complexes in an active site dependent manner.</title>
<p>(<bold>a</bold>) Interaction of JMJD7 and DRG/DFRP is consistent with proteomic analyses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9a</xref>). 3x-FLAG wildtype or inactive (H178A) JMJD7 were produced in doxycycline-inducible HEK293T cells before anti-FLAG immunopurification (IP) and western blotting with the indicated antibodies. Note the lack of interaction of DRG and DFRP proteins with JMJD7 H178A. The specificity of endogenous DRG antibodies was verified by siRNA knockdown (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9f</xref>). Immunoprecipitation experiments validating proteomic data were repeated three times, with similar results. Uncropped western blots are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 27</xref>. (<bold>b</bold>) Endogenous DRG/DFRP complexes contain endogenous JMJD7. Endogenous DFRP1 (left) or DFRP2 (right) complexes were immunopurified from HEK293T cells prior to western blotting with the indicated antibodies. Note that immunoprecipitation samples were diluted 1:10 prior to analyses of ‘bait’ (DFRP/DRG levels). This interaction experiment was repeated three times, with similar results. Uncropped western blots are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 28</xref>. (<bold>c</bold>) Co-localization of DRG1/2 and JMJD7. HeLa cells were transfected with control (empty vector, EV), FLAG-JMJD7 and/or HA-DRG1/2 prior to immunostaining for HA (red) and JMJD7 (green) and labeling nuclei with DAPI. This experiment was repeated three times, with similar results.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="emss-77001-f002"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<title>JMJD7 catalyzes lysyl-hydroxylation of the DRG1/2 GTPases.</title>
<p>(<bold>a</bold>) Alignment of the conserved DRG1/2 sequences hydroxylated by JMJD7 in different eukaryotes (Protein BLAST; figure was made using Clustal Omega and GeneDoc). (<bold>b</bold>) Qualitative analysis of the extent of (upper) DRG1 K22 and (lower) DRG2 K21 hydroxylation in the (left) absence or (right) presence of JMJD7 overexpression. Trypsinolysis at K22 of DRG1 and K21 of DRG2 is impeded by hydroxylation, complicating quantification: precursor signal intensities of the indicated tryptic fragments, as judged by precursor ion chromatogram analysis, were used; a shift in proportion of the fully-trypsinized peptide signal to the uncleaved trypsinized lysyl-hydroxylated peptide signal is indicative of increased hydroxylation. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref> for MS/MS fragments detected. (<bold>c</bold>) Representative MALDI mass spectra for (left) wildtype DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> and (right) K22A DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> in the absence (black) or presence (orange) of JMJD7. The K22A substitution nearly ablates peptide hydroxylation. This experiment was repeated three times, with similar results. (<bold>d</bold>) Representative MALDI-MS assays with DRG1<sub>16-40</sub> in presence/absence of co-factors/substrates and inhibitor. Ascorbate has no effect on JMJD7 activity in the linear range (the activity of some 2OG oxygenases is promoted by ascorbate<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>). The JMJD7-H178A mutant has reduced activity. Data represent the mean ± standard deviation (n = 3 replicates with a single biological sample) after incubation for 5 min at 37°C. This assay was repeated twice, with similar results. (<bold>e</bold>) MS/MS spectra of the K21 hydroxylated tryptic peptide fragment from endogenous DRG2 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig17a-c</xref> for extended data, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 17d-f</xref> for DRG1). Note that fragments of the hydroxylated peptide lose water (-18 Da, likely to give a C2/C3 dehydro- species, consistent with C3 hydroxylation), so most b-ions appear as pairs. Similar spectra were identified in multiple samples from two independent experiments. (<bold>f</bold>) Quantification of endogenous DRG2 K21 hydroxylation following control or JMJD7 siRNA. This experiment was repeated twice, with similar results.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="emss-77001-f003"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 4</label>
<caption>
<title>JMJD7 is a (3<italic>S</italic>)-lysyl hydroxylase that promotes DRG ribonucleic acid binding.</title>
<p>(<bold>a</bold>) Overlaid extracted ion chromatograms (XIC; m/z = 503.2) corresponding to: (<bold>i</bold>) C3 (dark blue), C4 (light blue), and C5 (cyan) hydroxylysine standards post-derivatization (two peaks are observed because each standard is a mixture of stereoisomers - (2<italic>S</italic>,X<italic>R</italic>)/(2<italic>R</italic>,X<italic>S</italic>) and (2<italic>S</italic>,X<italic>S</italic>)/(2<italic>R</italic>,X<italic>R</italic>); X is the hydroxylation site, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 19</xref>); (<bold>ii</bold>) hydrolyzed DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> peptide incubated with (orange) or without (black) JMJD7 prior to hydrolysis. The new product in the JMJD7-treated sample (orange) elutes at the same retention time as one of the C3 stereoisomeric pairs (C3’). (<bold>b</bold>) Overlaid XIC (m/z = 503.2) corresponding to: (<bold>i</bold>) C3 hydroxylysine standard sample (dark blue) and (2<italic>S</italic>,3<italic>R</italic>)/(2<italic>R</italic>,3<italic>S</italic>)-3-hydroxylysine standard (red) indicates the (2<italic>S</italic>,3<italic>R</italic>)/(2<italic>R</italic>,3<italic>S</italic>)-3-hydroxylysine enantiomeric pair co-elutes with the first peak of the C3 standard; (<bold>ii</bold>) hydrolyzed DRG1<sub>21-40</sub> peptide incubated with (orange) or without (black) JMJD7. The new peak in JMJD7-sample (orange) elutes at the same retention time as the standard corresponding to (2<italic>S</italic>,3<italic>S</italic>)/(2<italic>R</italic>,3<italic>R</italic>)-3-hydroxylysine (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 19</xref>). Amino acid analyses were repeated two or three times, with similar results. (<bold>c</bold>) Currently described forms of lysyl hydroxylation and their functions. (<bold>d</bold>) JMJD7 knockdown reduces the affinity of purified DRG2 for an RNA poly-C (cytidine nucleotide) agarose column. 3x-FLAG DRG2 was purified from doxycycline-inducible control shRNA cells (shCON) or two independent JMJD7 shRNA cell lines (#2 and #3) before anti-FLAG purification and incubation with poly-C agarose. Captured FLAG-DRG2 was detected by anti-FLAG western blotting (right; uncropped western blots are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 39</xref>) and quantified in three independent experiments, with similar results (left): Data represent the mean ± s.e.m. (n=3 biologically independent experiments) analyzed by 2-sided students t-test (** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01; <italic>P</italic>=0.0016 shJMJD7#2 and 0.0082 shJMJD7#3).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="emss-77001-f004"></graphic>
</fig>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>