<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0406041</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4668</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Comp Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Comp. Neurol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Journal of comparative neurology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9967</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-9861</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29464684</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6103898</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.24414</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS943978</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Neuregulin directed molecular mechanisms of visual cortical plasticity</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grieco</surname>
<given-names>Steven F.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>Todd C.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Xiangmin</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Department of Anatomy and Neurobiology, School of Medicine, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-1275</aff>
<aff id="A2">Department of Physiology and Biophysics, School of Medicine, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697- 4560</aff>
<aff id="A3">Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2715</aff>
<aff id="A4">Department of Microbiology and Molecular Genetics, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2715</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1"><label>#</label>Address all manuscript correspondence to: Dr. Xiangmin Xu, Department of Anatomy and Neurobiology, School of Medicine, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-1275, Tel: 949 824 0040 <email>xiangmin.xu@uci.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3">
<p id="P24">
<bold>Statement of conflict of interests</bold>
</p>
<p id="P25">All authors disclose no conflict of interests for this work.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>16</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>09</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>15</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>15</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>527</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>668</fpage>
<lpage>678</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/cne.24414-->
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="P1">Experience-dependent critical period plasticity has been extensively studied in the visual cortex. Monocular deprivation during the critical period affects ocular dominance, limits visual performance, and contributes to the pathological etiology of amblyopia. Neuregulin-1 (NRG1) signaling through its tyrosine kinase receptor ErbB4 is essential for the normal development of the nervous system, and has been linked to neuropsychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia. We discovered recently that NRG1/ErbB4 signaling in PV neurons is critical for the initiation of critical period visual cortical plasticity by controlling excitatory synaptic inputs onto PV neurons and thus PV-cell mediated cortical inhibition that occurs following visual deprivation. Building on this discovery, we review the existing literature of neuregulin signaling in developing and adult cortex, and address the implication of NRG/ErbB4 signaling in visual cortical plasticity at the cellular and circuit levels. NRG-directed research may lead to therapeutic approaches to reactivate plasticity in the adult cortex.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="Abs2">
<title>Graphical abstract</title>
<p id="P2">
<graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="nihms943978u1.jpg"></graphic></p>
<p id="P3">This image is associated with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> in Grieco et al. in this issue. It is an artistic rendition of their image data illustrating enhanced local excitatory inputs to monocularly deprived PV neurons (white circles) with bath applied NRG1. The eye-like overlay in black conveys that therapeutic intervention of NRG1/ErbB4 signaling can be developed to help treat critical period-relevant disorders such as amblyopia. The review article of Grieco et al. addresses a novel and critical role of NRG1/ErbB4 in regulation of visual cortical critical period plasticity.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Neuregulin-1</kwd>
<kwd>ErbB4</kwd>
<kwd>PV neurons</kwd>
<kwd>visual cortex</kwd>
<kwd>adult plasticity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>