<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0370512</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">457</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The American journal of psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0002-953X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1535-7228</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29621902</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6120790</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2018.17121383</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS958392</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>All for one and one for all: Mental disorders in one dimension</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Caspi</surname>
<given-names>Avshalom</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moffitt</surname>
<given-names>Terrie E.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Department of Psychology &amp; Neuroscience, Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences, and Center for Genomic and Computational Biology, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina; Social, Genetic and Developmental Psychiatry Centre, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology, &amp; Neuroscience, King’s College London, England</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>13</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>06</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>175</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<fpage>831</fpage>
<lpage>844</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2018.17121383-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">In both child and adult psychiatry, empirical evidence has now accrued to suggest that a single dimension is able to measure a person’s liability to mental disorder, comorbidity among disorders, persistence of disorders over time, and severity of symptoms. This single dimension of general psychopathology has been termed "<italic>p</italic>", because it conceptually parallels a dimension already familiar to behavioral scientists and clinicians: the “g” factor of general intelligence. As the g dimension reflects low-to-high mental ability, the <italic>p</italic> dimension represents low-to-high psychopathology severity, with thought disorder at the extreme. The dimension of <italic>p</italic> unites all disorders. It influences present/absent status on hundreds of psychiatric symptoms, which modern nosological systems typically aggregate into dozens of distinct diagnoses, which in turn aggregate into three overarching Externalizing, Internalizing, and Psychotic Experience domains, which finally aggregate into one dimension of psychopathology from low to high: <italic>p</italic>. Studies show that the higher a person scores on <italic>p</italic>, the worse that person fares on measures of family history of psychiatric illness, brain function, childhood developmental history, and adult life impairment. A dimension of <italic>p</italic> may help to account for ubiquitous non-specificity in psychiatry: multiple diagnoses share the same risk factors and biomarkers, and often respond to the same therapies. Here we summarize the history of the uni-dimensional idea, review modern research into <italic>p</italic>, demystify statistical models, articulate some implications of <italic>p</italic> for prevention and clinical practice, and outline a transdiagnostic research agenda going forward.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>