<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9212296</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">20207</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>European child &amp; adolescent psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1018-8827</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1435-165X</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29524018</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6131087</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00787-018-1136-x</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS980381</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Advancing the Study of Sluggish Cognitive Tempo via DSM, RDoC, and Hierarchical Models of Psychopathology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Becker</surname>
<given-names>Stephen P.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">4</xref>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9046-5183</contrib-id>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Willcutt</surname>
<given-names>Erik G.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0113-7431</contrib-id>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Division of Behavioral Medicine and Clinical Psychology, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center
</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine
</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Psychology and Neuroscience, University of Colorado Boulder
</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>4</label>Address correspondence to: Stephen P. Becker, Ph.D., Division of Behavioral Medicine and Clinical Psychology, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center, 3333 Burnet Avenue MLC 10006, Cincinnati, Ohio, 45229, USA. <email>stephen.becker@cchmc.org</email>. Telephone: +1 (513) 803-2066. Fax: +1 (513) 803-0084.
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN1">
<p id="P22"><bold>Conflict of Interest Statement:</bold> Neither author has any conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>11</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>603</fpage>
<lpage>613</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1007/s00787-018-1136-x-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Sluggish cognitive tempo (SCT) is separable from attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and other psychopathologies, and growing evidence demonstrates SCT to be associated with impairment in both children and adults. However, it remains unclear how SCT should optimally be conceptualized. In this article, we argue that multiple models of psychopathology should be leveraged in order to make substantive advances to our understanding of SCT. Both categorical and dimensional approaches should be used, including the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM) nosology, the Research Domain Criteria (RDoC) initiative, and hierarchical models of psychopathology. Studies are needed to determine whether individuals categorized with SCT can be reliably identified and differentiated from individuals without SCT in pathophysiological, neuropsychological, behavioral, and daily life functioning. Studies are also needed to evaluate the validity and utility of SCT as a transdiagnostic and dimensional construct. In considering SCT as a dimensional and potentially transdiagnostic construct, we describe ways in which SCT might be examined within the RDoC framework, including negative valence systems, cognitive systems, and arousal/regulatory systems, as well as within hierarchical models of psychopathology. Conceptualizing SCT within both categorical and dimensional models of psychopathology will help to better understand the causes, developmental pathways, and clinical implications of SCT, both as a construct in its own right and also in relation to other psychopathologies.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>ADHD</kwd>
<kwd>diagnosis</kwd>
<kwd>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</kwd>
<kwd>psychiatric diagnosis</kwd>
<kwd>nosology</kwd>
<kwd>psychopathology</kwd>
<kwd>Research Domain Criteria</kwd>
<kwd>sluggish cognitive tempo</kwd>
<kwd>transdiagnostic</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>