<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Amino Acids</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Amino Acids</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Amino Acids</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0939-4451</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1438-2199</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Springer Vienna</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30043079</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6153951</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2622</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-018-2622-7</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Plasma profile and urine excretion of amino acids in children with celiac disease on gluten-free diet after oligofructose-enriched inulin intervention: results of a randomised placebo-controlled pilot study</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5324-5982</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Drabińska</surname>
<given-names>Natalia</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<phone>+48 89 523 46 39</phone>
<email>n.drabinska@pan.olsztyn.pl</email>
<email>natalia_drabinska@wp.pl</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8580-2851</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Krupa-Kozak</surname>
<given-names>Urszula</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<phone>+48 89 523 46 18</phone>
<email>u.krupa-kozak@pan.olsztyn.pl</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8455-1429</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Ciska</surname>
<given-names>Ewa</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>e.ciska@pan.olsztyn.pl</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jarocka-Cyrta</surname>
<given-names>Elżbieta</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>ejarocka@op.pl</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1091 0698</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.433017.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry and Biodynamics of Food, </institution><institution>Institute of Animal Reproduction and Food Research of Polish Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Tuwima 10 Str., 10-748 Olsztyn, Poland </aff>
<aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2149 6795</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412607.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Pediatrics, Gastroenterology and Nutrition, Collegium Medicum, </institution><institution>University of Warmia &amp; Mazury, </institution></institution-wrap>Oczapowskiego 2, Str., 10-719 Olsztyn, Poland </aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="com">
<p>Handling Editor: F. Blachier.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>24</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>24</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>50</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>1451</fpage>
<lpage>1460</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>9</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>16</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement>
<license license-type="OpenAccess">
<license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="Par1">The circulating amino acid (AAs) concentrations are indicators of dietary protein intake and metabolic status. In celiac disease (CD), the AA imbalance is frequently observed. Prebiotics are found to alleviate nutrient deficiencies. Therefore, the aim of this study was to analyse the impact of oligrofructose-enriched inulin (Synergy 1), administered for 3 months as a gluten-free diet (GFD) supplement to children with CD, on the plasma and urine concentrations of AAs. CD children (<italic>N</italic> = 34) were randomised into two groups, receiving Synergy 1 (10 g/day) or placebo (maltodextrin) for 3 months. The AA profile and concentration was determined in plasma and urine before and after the dietary intervention by gas chromatography. 22 and 28 AAs were determined in plasma and urine samples, respectively. After the intervention, the plasma concentrations of several AAs (Ala, Pro, Asn, Glu, Tyr, Lys, His, Orn) increased significantly in both experimental groups, while Gln increased only in the Synergy 1 group. The urinary excretion of Asn, Lys and Aaa increased significantly in the Synergy 1 group, and the excretion of Asp and Met decreased (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the placebo group. The Gln:Glu ratio in urine increased in both groups after the intervention. An increased urinary excretion of AAs observed in Synergy 1 group with a simultaneous increase in the content of circulating AAs could be attributed to higher absorption or intensified metabolism of AAs, and on the other hand further healing of the intestinal mucosa being the result of continuous treatment with GFD. Moreover, the observed changes in Glu concentration suggest that oligofructose-enriched inulin could improve the intestinal condition and permeability. To conclude, a prebiotic-supplemented GFD influences beneficially the overall AAs metabolism in CD children; however, further prospective cohort studies are needed to confirm the results obtained.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group xml:lang="en">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>Amino acids</kwd>
<kwd>Celiac disease</kwd>
<kwd>Oligofructose-enriched inulin</kwd>
<kwd>Dietary intervention</kwd>
<kwd>Clinical trial</kwd>
<kwd>Gluten-free diet</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source>
<institution>Internal Project of the Institute of Animal Reproduction and Food Research PAS</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>IRZiBŻ PAS GW 20</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name>
<surname>Krupa-Kozak</surname>
<given-names>Urszula</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
<meta-value>© Springer-Verlag GmbH Austria, part of Springer Nature 2018</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="Par2">Chronic intestinal inflammation alters gut functions by weakening the intestinal barrier, damaging epithelial cells and decreasing absorption (Barker and Liu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>), which deplete the levels of important nutrients and mediators in the human body, including amino acids (AAs). AAs are essential metabolites which play a crucial role in the human body. They participate in the formation of protein structure, regulation of anabolic and catabolic metabolism, and detoxification processes. Dietary AAs act as substrates for the development of epithelial cells and mucin synthesis, they maintain the integrity of the gut barrier and play a pivotal role in the intestinal immune system (Fillmann et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2007</xref>; Ren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2014</xref>; Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2015</xref>). AAs are the precursors for the synthesis of important mediators, such as glutathione, an antioxidant with cytoprotective activity which prevents epithelial cell damage (Wu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2004</xref>). The concentrations of circulating AAs are reliable indicators of dietary protein intake and metabolic status. Recent research has focused on the AA balance and changes in AA metabolism as factors that contribute to the development of pathological conditions. Changes in the AA profile often accompany cancerogenesis, mental disorders and fatigue (Evans et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2008</xref>; Hugh Dunstan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2011</xref>; Dereziński et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>). The AA imbalance is also frequently observed in celiac disease (CD) (Di Cagno et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2011</xref>; Sevinc et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par3">CD is a chronic autoimmune enteropathy which is triggered by gluten ingestion and is observed in genetically predisposed individuals. The only treatment for CD is a gluten-free diet (GFD) which may be difficult to optimise in terms of fulfilling the patients’ nutritional needs (Roma et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2010</xref>; Ilus et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2014</xref>). CD patients who have been following a GFD for a long time are characterised by sub-optimal levels of essential AAs (EAAs) in biological fluids, compared with healthy individuals (van Hees et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2015</xref>). The psychological symptoms that accompany CD, such as anxiety, irritability, depression and apathy (Carta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2002</xref>; Addolorato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2008</xref>), are linked with a reduced intake of dietary tryptophan and, consequently, decreased synthesis of monoamines, including serotonin (Hernanz and Polanco <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1991</xref>). According to many metabolic studies (Bertini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2009</xref>; Di Cagno et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2009</xref>), the AA balance plays a very important role in CD management. Despite the above, AA profiling in CD has been scarcely researched (Sevinc et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par4">According to the literature, prebiotics could be helpful in alleviating nutrient deficiencies by regulating the composition and the activity of gut microbiota. In vitro and in vivo studies as well as clinical trials involving patients with intestinal inflammatory diseases have demonstrated that inulin-type fructans improve mineral absorption, alleviate the symptoms of inflammation and induce morphological changes in the intestines (Guarner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2007</xref>; Krupa-Kozak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2016</xref>; Shoaib et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2016</xref>). The applicability of inulin-type fructans in GFD and its effects on the AA profile in biological fluids have not been investigated to date. Therefore, the aim of this study was to analyse the impact of oligrofructose-enriched inulin, administered for 3 months as a GFD supplement to children with CD, on the plasma and urine concentrations of selected AAs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="Sec3">
<title>Experimental design</title>
<p id="Par5">A randomised, placebo-controlled, parallel-group and single-centre pilot study was performed on children and adolescents (<italic>N </italic>= 34, aged from 4 to 18 years) diagnosed with CD based on the criteria of the European Society for Paediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition (ESPGHAN) (Husby et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>), and following GFD since at least 6 months (GFD adherence in a range from 6 months to 9 years) to assess the effects of oligofructose-enriched inulin (Synergy 1; Orafti<sup>®</sup> Synergy 1, Beneo, Tienen, Belgium) on their health and nutritional status. All participants met the inclusion criteria: CD confirmed by serological, genetic and biopsy analyses; GFD for at least 6 months. The exclusion criteria included: use of antibiotics in the month preceding the study; use of medication for osteoporosis (bisphosphonates, calcium calcitonin); use of probiotics, prebiotics or fibre supplements; poor or average overall health; current enrolment in another research study; recent surgery. The detailed protocol of the clinical trial, and the demographic and anthropometric characteristics of the participants at the beginning of the study have been described previously (Krupa-Kozak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2017</xref>). The patients were randomised into two groups: based on sex and age: the Synergy 1 group (<italic>N</italic> = 18; girls = 11; age 5–17 years, average 10 years) and the placebo group (<italic>N</italic> = 16; girls = 10; age 4–16 years, average 10 years). Over a period of 3 months, the participants in the Synergy 1 group were administered oligofructose-enriched inulin at 10 g/day, and the participants in the placebo group were administered maltodextrin at 7 g/day. Patients of both groups continued to follow a strict GFD throughout the whole experiment. Among recruited subjects, 30 completed the study and were included in the final analysis, while four children were excluded, in particular two subjects who had been treated with antibiotics during the experiment and two subjects who failed to comply with the experimental requirements.</p>
<p id="Par6">Anti-tissue transglutaminase antibody (tTG) assay has been performed before and after the intervention as a part of clinical practice by Hospital’s Diagnostic Laboratory to control adherence to GFD and/or progress of the treatment. The results of tTG assay are presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Values of anti-tissue transglutaminase in CD children before and after the intervention, expressed as a median (P25–P75). Normal range is &lt; 8.0 AU/mL</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"></th><th align="left" colspan="2">T0</th><th align="left" colspan="2">T1</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Synergy 1</th><th align="left">Placebo</th><th align="left">Synergy 1</th><th align="left">Placebo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">tTG [AU/mL]</td><td align="char" char=".">2.57 (0.48–6.98)</td><td align="char" char=".">2.17 (0.85–3.74)</td><td align="char" char=".">1.22 (0.34–4.88)</td><td align="char" char=".">1.49 (0.62–4.83)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec4">
<title>Sample collection</title>
<p id="Par7">Urine and blood samples were collected from each participant at baseline and after the 3-month dietary intervention. For ethical reasons, samples were collected during regular follow-up visits (every 3 months) in the Gastroenterology Clinic of the Children’s Hospital in Olsztyn (Poland). Blood samples were collected into vacuum tubes containing an anticoagulant (heparin). Plasma was divided into aliquots (100 μL) and stored at − 80 °C until AA analyses. Approximately 50 mL of morning urine (second spontaneous urine) was collected, divided into aliquots and stored at − 80 °C until further analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec5">
<title>Amino acid analysis</title>
<p id="Par8">The AA profile in urine and plasma samples was analysed using the EZ:Faast™ Kit for Free (Physiological) Amino Acids (Phenomenex, Aschaffenburg, Germany) according to the producer’s recommendations. The chromatographic method was chosen due to its ability to detect a wide range of AAs in a single run and in a very short time (7 min) using a relatively small amount of the sample. The analytical procedure involves solid-phase extraction of 100 μL of urine or plasma, followed by derivatization and liquid–liquid extraction. AAs were identified in the Agilent 7890A gas chromatograph (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) coupled with the 5975C mass selective detector, 7683B auto-injector and a data station containing the NIST/EPA/NIH Mass Spectral Library (Version 2). The compounds were separated in the ZB-AAA EZ Faast™ capillary column (10 m × 0.25 mm). The carrier gas was helium (1.5 mL/min). The samples (2 µL) were injected in split mode (1:15). Oven temperature was initially set at 110 °C and then increased to 320 °C (30 °C/min). Injector and MS source temperatures were 250 and 240 °C, respectively. Mass spectra were obtained by electron ionisation (EI) over the range of 35–550 m/e. Electronic impact energy was 70 eV. Amino acids were identified using calibration standards for each AA, and a quantitative analysis was performed relative to the internal standard (norvaline).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec6">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p id="Par9">All analyses were performed in duplicates. Raw data were expressed as means ± SEM. The Gln:Glu ratio was presented as means ± SD. Data were processed in Statistica 12 software (StatSoft, USA). Only the data collected from participants whose reported intake of the supplements exceeded 80% were included in the final analysis. Normal distribution was evaluated in the Shapiro–Wilk test. Analyses comparing both groups at baseline and after 3 months were performed separately using the Student’s <italic>T</italic> test or the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test as appropriate. Comparison within groups between baseline and after 3 months was performed using the paired samples Student’s <italic>T</italic> test or Wilcoxon test, as appropriate. Statistical significance thresholds were set at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (<sup>*</sup>) and <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 (<sup>**</sup>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="Sec8">
<title>Amino acid profile in plasma</title>
<p id="Par10">Twenty-two AAs, including eight non-essential AAs (NEAAs) (Ala, Gly, Ser, Pro, Asn, Gln, Glu, Tyr), nine EAAs (Val, Leu, Ile, Thr, Met, Phe, Lys, Trp, His) and five non-proteinogenic AAs and derivatives (Aba, Orn, Hyp, C–C, Php), were determined in plasma samples collected from children with CD (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab2">2</xref>). At baseline, the plasma profile and the concentrations of individual AAs and total AA in did not differ between the Synergy 1 group and the placebo group.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Concentrations of AAs and derivatives in the plasma of children with celiac disease (<italic>N</italic> = 30): a comparison of the group supplemented with Synergy 1 and the placebo group at baseline and after 3 months of supplementation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3"></th><th align="left" colspan="4">T0</th><th align="left" colspan="4">T1</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">S-T0 vs. S-T1</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">P-T0 vs. P-T1</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">S-T1 vs. P-T1</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">Synergy 1 (S)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Placebo (P)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">S</th><th align="left" colspan="2">P</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Non-essential amino acids</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Alanine</td><td align="left">Ala</td><td align="char" char=".">284.70</td><td align="char" char=".">21.73</td><td align="char" char=".">280.96</td><td align="char" char=".">20.76</td><td align="char" char=".">387.94</td><td align="char" char=".">22.48</td><td align="char" char=".">406.25</td><td align="char" char=".">30.91</td><td align="char" char=".">0.008**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.012*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.629</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Glycine</td><td align="left">Gly</td><td align="char" char=".">226.80</td><td align="char" char=".">20.58</td><td align="char" char=".">210.69</td><td align="char" char=".">16.33</td><td align="char" char=".">248.97</td><td align="char" char=".">16.50</td><td align="char" char=".">229.08</td><td align="char" char=".">16.97</td><td align="char" char=".">0.110</td><td align="char" char=".">0.286</td><td align="char" char=".">0.325</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Serine</td><td align="left">Ser</td><td align="char" char=".">109.19</td><td align="char" char=".">7.72</td><td align="char" char=".">93.40</td><td align="char" char=".">5.65</td><td align="char" char=".">123.91</td><td align="char" char=".">10.26</td><td align="char" char=".">119.36</td><td align="char" char=".">8.65</td><td align="char" char=".">0.196</td><td align="char" char=".">0.008**</td><td align="char" char=".">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Proline</td><td align="left">Pro</td><td align="char" char=".">137.27</td><td align="char" char=".">6.48</td><td align="char" char=".">129.46</td><td align="char" char=".">9.59</td><td align="char" char=".">164.65</td><td align="char" char=".">9.57</td><td align="char" char=".">199.39</td><td align="char" char=".">19.38</td><td align="char" char=".">0.028*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.007**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.197</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asparagine</td><td align="left">Asn</td><td align="char" char=".">46.89</td><td align="char" char=".">3.28</td><td align="char" char=".">43.62</td><td align="char" char=".">3.30</td><td align="char" char=".">54.52</td><td align="char" char=".">2.70</td><td align="char" char=".">57.89</td><td align="char" char=".">2.72</td><td align="char" char=".">0.006**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.008*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.395</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Glutamine</td><td align="left">Gln</td><td align="char" char=".">457.39</td><td align="char" char=".">25.48</td><td align="char" char=".">411.34</td><td align="char" char=".">18.35</td><td align="char" char=".">498.93</td><td align="char" char=".">16.11</td><td align="char" char=".">473.37</td><td align="char" char=".">36.35</td><td align="char" char=".">0.015*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.092</td><td align="char" char=".">0.485</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Glutamic acid</td><td align="left">Glu</td><td align="char" char=".">22.86</td><td align="char" char=".">2.65</td><td align="char" char=".">25.69</td><td align="char" char=".">2.85</td><td align="char" char=".">48.63</td><td align="char" char=".">2.43</td><td align="char" char=".">39.41</td><td align="char" char=".">2.86</td><td align="char" char=".">0.007**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.043*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.037*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Tyrosine</td><td align="left">Tyr</td><td align="char" char=".">43.67</td><td align="char" char=".">2.64</td><td align="char" char=".">41.01</td><td align="char" char=".">2.40</td><td align="char" char=".">54.19</td><td align="char" char=".">3.84</td><td align="char" char=".">61.14</td><td align="char" char=".">6.06</td><td align="char" char=".">0.030*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.016*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.433</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Essential amino acids</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Valine</td><td align="left">Val</td><td align="char" char=".">225.65</td><td align="char" char=".">18.04</td><td align="char" char=".">202.43</td><td align="char" char=".">15.13</td><td align="char" char=".">241.97</td><td align="char" char=".">11.91</td><td align="char" char=".">244.09</td><td align="char" char=".">24.88</td><td align="char" char=".">0.743</td><td align="char" char=".">0.145</td><td align="char" char=".">0.936</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Leucine</td><td align="left">Leu</td><td align="char" char=".">101.49</td><td align="char" char=".">7.79</td><td align="char" char=".">85.91</td><td align="char" char=".">4.01</td><td align="char" char=".">110.78</td><td align="char" char=".">8.87</td><td align="char" char=".">124.23</td><td align="char" char=".">15.55</td><td align="char" char=".">0.182</td><td align="char" char=".">0.008**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.761</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Isoleucine</td><td align="left">Ile</td><td align="char" char=".">51.36</td><td align="char" char=".">3.33</td><td align="char" char=".">45.51</td><td align="char" char=".">2.33</td><td align="char" char=".">53.29</td><td align="char" char=".">1.98</td><td align="char" char=".">57.34</td><td align="char" char=".">4.50</td><td align="char" char=".">0.541</td><td align="char" char=".">0.084</td><td align="char" char=".">0.363</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Threonine</td><td align="left">Thr</td><td align="char" char=".">110.59</td><td align="char" char=".">7.94</td><td align="char" char=".">105.11</td><td align="char" char=".">11.01</td><td align="char" char=".">136.35</td><td align="char" char=".">9.31</td><td align="char" char=".">137.46</td><td align="char" char=".">9.78</td><td align="char" char=".">0.112</td><td align="char" char=".">0.047*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.935</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Methionine</td><td align="left">Met</td><td align="char" char=".">11.53</td><td align="char" char=".">0.88</td><td align="char" char=".">10.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.66</td><td align="char" char=".">13.52</td><td align="char" char=".">0.65</td><td align="char" char=".">14.65</td><td align="char" char=".">1.72</td><td align="char" char=".">0.071</td><td align="char" char=".">0.012*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.483</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Phenylalanine</td><td align="left">Phe</td><td align="char" char=".">35.81</td><td align="char" char=".">1.70</td><td align="char" char=".">35.35</td><td align="char" char=".">1.64</td><td align="char" char=".">39.15</td><td align="char" char=".">2.50</td><td align="char" char=".">41.20</td><td align="char" char=".">1.98</td><td align="char" char=".">0.186</td><td align="char" char=".">0.034*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.542</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Lysine</td><td align="left">Lys</td><td align="char" char=".">193.74</td><td align="char" char=".">8.27</td><td align="char" char=".">182.73</td><td align="char" char=".">6.81</td><td align="char" char=".">247.26</td><td align="char" char=".">10.06</td><td align="char" char=".">267.94</td><td align="char" char=".">14.36</td><td align="char" char=".">0.011*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.007**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.240</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Tryptophan</td><td align="left">Trp</td><td align="char" char=".">43.23</td><td align="char" char=".">2.49</td><td align="char" char=".">39.21</td><td align="char" char=".">1.89</td><td align="char" char=".">46.30</td><td align="char" char=".">3.46</td><td align="char" char=".">55.39</td><td align="char" char=".">4.43</td><td align="char" char=".">0.051</td><td align="char" char=".">0.018*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.070</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Histidine</td><td align="left">His</td><td align="char" char=".">65.28</td><td align="char" char=".">3.12</td><td align="char" char=".">61.36</td><td align="char" char=".">3.65</td><td align="char" char=".">75.16</td><td align="char" char=".">3.11</td><td align="char" char=".">86.36</td><td align="char" char=".">6.72</td><td align="char" char=".">0.042*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.016*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.218</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Other amino acids and derivatives</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> α-Aminobutyric acid</td><td align="left">Aba</td><td align="char" char=".">17.07</td><td align="char" char=".">1.27</td><td align="char" char=".">15.43</td><td align="char" char=".">1.11</td><td align="char" char=".">17.88</td><td align="char" char=".">1.44</td><td align="char" char=".">19.36</td><td align="char" char=".">1.75</td><td align="char" char=".">0.421</td><td align="char" char=".">0.011*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.685</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ornithine</td><td align="left">Orn</td><td align="char" char=".">47.85</td><td align="char" char=".">2.14</td><td align="char" char=".">42.45</td><td align="char" char=".">2.79</td><td align="char" char=".">59.71</td><td align="char" char=".">2.48</td><td align="char" char=".">72.95</td><td align="char" char=".">7.69</td><td align="char" char=".">0.012*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.002*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.174</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 4-hydroxyproline</td><td align="left">Hyp</td><td align="char" char=".">20.03</td><td align="char" char=".">2.78</td><td align="char" char=".">18.79</td><td align="char" char=".">2.22</td><td align="char" char=".">22.07</td><td align="char" char=".">1.88</td><td align="char" char=".">27.14</td><td align="char" char=".">3.04</td><td align="char" char=".">0.955</td><td align="char" char=".">0.008**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.164</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Cystine</td><td align="left">C–C</td><td align="char" char=".">25.94</td><td align="char" char=".">3.81</td><td align="char" char=".">23.89</td><td align="char" char=".">3.34</td><td align="char" char=".">25.08</td><td align="char" char=".">3.22</td><td align="char" char=".">35.39</td><td align="char" char=".">4.31</td><td align="char" char=".">0.953</td><td align="char" char=".">0.028*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.193</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Proline–hydroxyproline</td><td align="left">Php</td><td align="char" char=".">9.44</td><td align="char" char=".">1.27</td><td align="char" char=".">6.89</td><td align="char" char=".">1.30</td><td align="char" char=".">8.42</td><td align="char" char=".">2.64</td><td align="char" char=".">10.82</td><td align="char" char=".">3.22</td><td align="char" char=".">0.463</td><td align="char" char=".">0.089</td><td align="char" char=".">1.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are given as the mean with SEM in nmol/mL. Differences were considered significant as follow: (*) <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; (**) <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
<p id="Par11">After the 3-month dietary intervention, the concentrations of NEAAs, in particular Ala, Pro, Asn, Glu, Tyr, as well as Lys, His and Orn increased significantly (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in both groups, regardless of the applied GFD supplementation (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab2">2</xref>). The concentration of Gln increased significantly (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) only in Synergy 1 group. On the other hand, a significant increase of the concentration of majority of EAAs and of Aba, Hyp and C–C in plasma was observed only in the placebo group. Interestingly, the administration of Synergy 1 significantly increased (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) the plasma Glu level, but did not affect the Gln:Glu ratio which remained similar to baseline (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref>a). Consequently, the total AA concentration increased by 17% in the Synergy 1 group and by 32% in the placebo group relative to baseline (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>a). The total concentration of EAAs increased by 15% in the Synergy 1 group and by 23% in the placebo group, and the total concentration of NEAAs increased by 19% in both groups. The total concentration of branched-chain amino acids (BCAAs) increased by 7% in the Synergy 1 group and by 13% in the placebo group.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Box-and-whisker plots of the Gln:Glu ratio in the plasma <bold>a</bold> and urine <bold>b</bold> of children with celiac disease: a comparison of the group supplemented with Synergy 1 and the placebo group at baseline and after 3 months of supplementation; Mann–Whitney test</p></caption><graphic id="MO1" xlink:href="726_2018_2622_Fig1_HTML"></graphic></fig>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Summarized values of total concentrations of all, essential (EAAs), non-essential (NEAAs) and branched-chain (BCAAs) amino acids in plasma <bold>a</bold> and urine <bold>b</bold> of children with CD from Synergy 1 and placebo group, before (T0) and after (T1) the intervention</p></caption><graphic id="MO2" xlink:href="726_2018_2622_Fig2_HTML"></graphic></fig>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec9">
<title>Amino acid profile in urine</title>
<p id="Par12">The urinary AA profile determined in Synergy 1 and placebo groups at baseline and after the dietary intervention is presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab3">3</xref>. Twenty-eight AAs, including nine NEAAs (Ala, Gly, Ser, Pro, Asn, Asp, Gln, Glu, Tyr), nine EAAs (Val, Leu, Ile, Thr, Met, Phe, Lys, Trp, His) and ten AA derivatives and non-proteinogenic AAs (Aba, βAiB, Aaa, Apa, Orn, Hly, Cth, C–C, Gpr, Php), were identified. The total urinary concentration of AAs in both groups was similar at baseline at approximately 5300 nmol mL<sup>−1</sup>. The predominant AAs were Gly, His and Php. The main AA fractions were NEAAs which accounted for 43% of total AAs, EAAs accounted for approximately 27%, and BCAAs—for 5% of total AAs.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Urinary excretion of AAs and derivatives in children with celiac disease (<italic>N</italic> = 30): a comparison of the group supplemented with Synergy 1 and the placebo group at baseline and after 3 months of supplementation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3"></th><th align="left" colspan="4">T0</th><th align="left" colspan="4">T1</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">S-T0 vs. S-T1</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">P-T0 vs. P-T1</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">S-T1 vs. P-T1</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">Synergy 1 (S)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Placebo (P)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">S</th><th align="left" colspan="2">P</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th><th align="left">Av</th><th align="left">SEM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Non-essential amino acids</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Alanine</td><td align="left">Ala</td><td align="char" char=".">281.19</td><td align="char" char=".">23.60</td><td align="char" char=".">255.84</td><td align="char" char=".">24.19</td><td align="char" char=".">365.44</td><td align="char" char=".">35.20</td><td align="char" char=".">253.49</td><td align="char" char=".">32.15</td><td align="char" char=".">0.124</td><td align="char" char=".">0.852</td><td align="char" char=".">0.045*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Glycine</td><td align="left">Gly</td><td align="char" char=".">1073.80</td><td align="char" char=".">120.30</td><td align="char" char=".">1056.63</td><td align="char" char=".">170.99</td><td align="char" char=".">1286.25</td><td align="char" char=".">174.02</td><td align="char" char=".">924.67</td><td align="char" char=".">122.09</td><td align="char" char=".">0.116</td><td align="char" char=".">0.753</td><td align="char" char=".">0.174</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Serine</td><td align="left">Ser</td><td align="char" char=".">333.35</td><td align="char" char=".">24.78</td><td align="char" char=".">321.13</td><td align="char" char=".">27.47</td><td align="char" char=".">403.63</td><td align="char" char=".">36.02</td><td align="char" char=".">309.02</td><td align="char" char=".">34.78</td><td align="char" char=".">0.124</td><td align="char" char=".">0.917</td><td align="char" char=".">0.059</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Proline</td><td align="left">Pro</td><td align="char" char=".">9.59</td><td align="char" char=".">0.51</td><td align="char" char=".">9.26</td><td align="char" char=".">0.75</td><td align="char" char=".">10.18</td><td align="char" char=".">0.90</td><td align="char" char=".">8.38</td><td align="char" char=".">0.90</td><td align="char" char=".">0.557</td><td align="char" char=".">0.263</td><td align="char" char=".">0.170</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asparagine</td><td align="left">Asn</td><td align="char" char=".">118.38</td><td align="char" char=".">8.40</td><td align="char" char=".">115.89</td><td align="char" char=".">16.93</td><td align="char" char=".">147.43</td><td align="char" char=".">13.49</td><td align="char" char=".">101.52</td><td align="char" char=".">14.48</td><td align="char" char=".">0.034*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.499</td><td align="char" char=".">0.018*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aspartic acid</td><td align="left">Asp</td><td align="char" char=".">9.09</td><td align="char" char=".">0.98</td><td align="char" char=".">11.80</td><td align="char" char=".">1.25</td><td align="char" char=".">9.11</td><td align="char" char=".">0.70</td><td align="char" char=".">8.82</td><td align="char" char=".">0.80</td><td align="char" char=".">0.750</td><td align="char" char=".">0.028*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.836</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Glutamine</td><td align="left">Gln</td><td align="char" char=".">378.13</td><td align="char" char=".">30.79</td><td align="char" char=".">361.13</td><td align="char" char=".">47.15</td><td align="char" char=".">425.37</td><td align="char" char=".">25.67</td><td align="char" char=".">329.79</td><td align="char" char=".">22.46</td><td align="char" char=".">0.088</td><td align="char" char=".">0.128</td><td align="char" char=".">0.015*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Glutamic acid</td><td align="left">Glu</td><td align="char" char=".">35.79</td><td align="char" char=".">5.00</td><td align="char" char=".">32.14</td><td align="char" char=".">5.08</td><td align="char" char=".">17.36</td><td align="char" char=".">1.48</td><td align="char" char=".">13.32</td><td align="char" char=".">1.21</td><td align="char" char=".">0.006**</td><td align="char" char=".">0.017*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.094</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Tyrosine</td><td align="left">Tyr</td><td align="char" char=".">95.65</td><td align="char" char=".">6.92</td><td align="char" char=".">91.15</td><td align="char" char=".">10.50</td><td align="char" char=".">105.41</td><td align="char" char=".">15.06</td><td align="char" char=".">91.88</td><td align="char" char=".">11.57</td><td align="char" char=".">0.575</td><td align="char" char=".">0.799</td><td align="char" char=".">0.193</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Essential amino acids</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Valine</td><td align="left">Val</td><td align="char" char=".">43.98</td><td align="char" char=".">4.51</td><td align="char" char=".">40.29</td><td align="char" char=".">4.46</td><td align="char" char=".">46.02</td><td align="char" char=".">5.84</td><td align="char" char=".">39.14</td><td align="char" char=".">3.58</td><td align="char" char=".">0.517</td><td align="char" char=".">0.810</td><td align="char" char=".">0.369</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Leucine</td><td align="left">Leu</td><td align="char" char=".">33.42</td><td align="char" char=".">2.54</td><td align="char" char=".">31.43</td><td align="char" char=".">2.80</td><td align="char" char=".">37.64</td><td align="char" char=".">5.90</td><td align="char" char=".">30.62</td><td align="char" char=".">3.63</td><td align="char" char=".">0.310</td><td align="char" char=".">0.866</td><td align="char" char=".">0.153</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Isoleucine</td><td align="left">Ile</td><td align="char" char=".">15.91</td><td align="char" char=".">1.71</td><td align="char" char=".">15.09</td><td align="char" char=".">1.87</td><td align="char" char=".">16.43</td><td align="char" char=".">2.01</td><td align="char" char=".">13.54</td><td align="char" char=".">1.57</td><td align="char" char=".">0.515</td><td align="char" char=".">0.214</td><td align="char" char=".">0.145</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Threonine</td><td align="left">Thr</td><td align="char" char=".">121.01</td><td align="char" char=".">9.87</td><td align="char" char=".">116.83</td><td align="char" char=".">14.40</td><td align="char" char=".">149.31</td><td align="char" char=".">17.63</td><td align="char" char=".">114.96</td><td align="char" char=".">18.08</td><td align="char" char=".">0.240</td><td align="char" char=".">0.767</td><td align="char" char=".">0.142</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Methionine</td><td align="left">Met</td><td align="char" char=".">16.74</td><td align="char" char=".">2.66</td><td align="char" char=".">16.80</td><td align="char" char=".">2.90</td><td align="char" char=".">16.80</td><td align="char" char=".">3.48</td><td align="char" char=".">13.18</td><td align="char" char=".">1.76</td><td align="char" char=".">0.794</td><td align="char" char=".">0.043*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.306</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Phenylalanine</td><td align="left">Phe</td><td align="char" char=".">50.71</td><td align="char" char=".">4.36</td><td align="char" char=".">46.42</td><td align="char" char=".">5.57</td><td align="char" char=".">59.79</td><td align="char" char=".">7.31</td><td align="char" char=".">43.11</td><td align="char" char=".">4.51</td><td align="char" char=".">0.532</td><td align="char" char=".">0.678</td><td align="char" char=".">0.045*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Lysine</td><td align="left">Lys</td><td align="char" char=".">183.45</td><td align="char" char=".">21.01</td><td align="char" char=".">176.96</td><td align="char" char=".">10.80</td><td align="char" char=".">252.87</td><td align="char" char=".">32.66</td><td align="char" char=".">202.58</td><td align="char" char=".">33.39</td><td align="char" char=".">0.017*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.273</td><td align="char" char=".">0.116</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Tryptophan</td><td align="left">Trp</td><td align="char" char=".">60.43</td><td align="char" char=".">4.25</td><td align="char" char=".">65.20</td><td align="char" char=".">8.17</td><td align="char" char=".">71.08</td><td align="char" char=".">9.41</td><td align="char" char=".">64.43</td><td align="char" char=".">7.32</td><td align="char" char=".">0.646</td><td align="char" char=".">0.859</td><td align="char" char=".">0.278</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Histidine</td><td align="left">His</td><td align="char" char=".">968.44</td><td align="char" char=".">82.05</td><td align="char" char=".">879.50</td><td align="char" char=".">73.38</td><td align="char" char=".">1228.07</td><td align="char" char=".">196.18</td><td align="char" char=".">795.39</td><td align="char" char=".">112.43</td><td align="char" char=".">0.273</td><td align="char" char=".">0.893</td><td align="char" char=".">0.068</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Other amino acids and derivatives</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> α-Aminobutyric acid</td><td align="left">Aba</td><td align="char" char=".">16.05</td><td align="char" char=".">1.34</td><td align="char" char=".">16.52</td><td align="char" char=".">1.91</td><td align="char" char=".">16.68</td><td align="char" char=".">1.47</td><td align="char" char=".">16.18</td><td align="char" char=".">1.67</td><td align="char" char=".">0.253</td><td align="char" char=".">0.575</td><td align="char" char=".">0.369</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> β-Aminoisobutyric acid</td><td align="left">Baib</td><td align="char" char=".">160.46</td><td align="char" char=".">32.45</td><td align="char" char=".">161.88</td><td align="char" char=".">39.61</td><td align="char" char=".">234.65</td><td align="char" char=".">32.48</td><td align="char" char=".">181.01</td><td align="char" char=".">33.22</td><td align="char" char=".">0.116</td><td align="char" char=".">0.180</td><td align="char" char=".">0.393</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> α-Aminoadipic acid</td><td align="left">Aaa</td><td align="char" char=".">35.99</td><td align="char" char=".">4.05</td><td align="char" char=".">32.41</td><td align="char" char=".">5.08</td><td align="char" char=".">42.18</td><td align="char" char=".">3.51</td><td align="char" char=".">37.95</td><td align="char" char=".">5.96</td><td align="char" char=".">0.041*</td><td align="char" char=".">0.128</td><td align="char" char=".">0.203</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> α-Aminopimelic acid</td><td align="left">Apa</td><td align="char" char=".">12.87</td><td align="char" char=".">2.14</td><td align="char" char=".">15.38</td><td align="char" char=".">2.36</td><td align="char" char=".">17.01</td><td align="char" char=".">2.01</td><td align="char" char=".">10.42</td><td align="char" char=".">0.39</td><td align="char" char=".">0.075</td><td align="char" char=".">0.110</td><td align="char" char=".">0.013*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ornithine</td><td align="left">Orn</td><td align="char" char=".">33.35</td><td align="char" char=".">3.95</td><td align="char" char=".">34.69</td><td align="char" char=".">4.68</td><td align="char" char=".">35.41</td><td align="char" char=".">3.60</td><td align="char" char=".">31.15</td><td align="char" char=".">3.69</td><td align="char" char=".">0.155</td><td align="char" char=".">0.779</td><td align="char" char=".">0.163</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Hydroxylysine</td><td align="left">Hly</td><td align="char" char=".">83.06</td><td align="char" char=".">9.92</td><td align="char" char=".">83.44</td><td align="char" char=".">10.91</td><td align="char" char=".">102.38</td><td align="char" char=".">10.26</td><td align="char" char=".">81.66</td><td align="char" char=".">8.07</td><td align="char" char=".">0.310</td><td align="char" char=".">0.499</td><td align="char" char=".">0.081</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Cystathionine</td><td align="left">Cth</td><td align="char" char=".">109.91</td><td align="char" char=".">10.50</td><td align="char" char=".">118.54</td><td align="char" char=".">13.04</td><td align="char" char=".">124.39</td><td align="char" char=".">26.99</td><td align="char" char=".">147.71</td><td align="char" char=".">17.06</td><td align="char" char=".">0.753</td><td align="char" char=".">0.310</td><td align="char" char=".">0.597</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Cystine</td><td align="left">C–C</td><td align="char" char=".">65.88</td><td align="char" char=".">7.53</td><td align="char" char=".">59.93</td><td align="char" char=".">7.59</td><td align="char" char=".">88.86</td><td align="char" char=".">11.85</td><td align="char" char=".">64.18</td><td align="char" char=".">7.73</td><td align="char" char=".">0.514</td><td align="char" char=".">0.889</td><td align="char" char=".">0.142</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Glycyl-proline</td><td align="left">Gpr</td><td align="char" char=".">97.52</td><td align="char" char=".">9.75</td><td align="char" char=".">126.11</td><td align="char" char=".">14.12</td><td align="char" char=".">124.93</td><td align="char" char=".">13.97</td><td align="char" char=".">129.04</td><td align="char" char=".">16.56</td><td align="char" char=".">0.116</td><td align="char" char=".">0.735</td><td align="char" char=".">0.971</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Proline–hydroxyproline</td><td align="left">Php</td><td align="char" char=".">917.24</td><td align="char" char=".">92.63</td><td align="char" char=".">949.76</td><td align="char" char=".">101.12</td><td align="char" char=".">708.86</td><td align="char" char=".">63.85</td><td align="char" char=".">949.32</td><td align="char" char=".">105.60</td><td align="char" char=".">0.225</td><td align="char" char=".">0.917</td><td align="char" char=".">0.597</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are given as the mean with SEM in nmol/mL. Differences were considered significant as follows: (*) <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; (**) <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
<p id="Par13">At baseline, the urine profile and the concentrations of individual AAs and total AA did not differ between the experimental groups, whereas noteworthy changes in the urinary excretion of individual AAs were observed after the dietary intervention (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab3">3</xref>). The urinary excretion of Asn, Lys and Aaa increased significantly (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the Synergy 1 group, and the excretion of Asp and Met decreased (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the placebo group relative to baseline values. Interestingly, the urinary concentration of Glu in both experimental groups decreased by half independently on applied supplement. An analysis of individual AA concentrations in urine after the intervention revealed higher excretion of Ala, Asn, Gln, Phe and Apa in the prebiotic group than in the placebo group. Consequently, urinary excretion of total AAs, EAAs and NEAAs increased by more than 14, 25 and 18%, respectively, in the Synergy 1 group, whereas a decrease in total AA concentrations was observed in the placebo group (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>b). In the Synergy 1 group, urinary excretion of BCAAs increased by 32% from baseline and was higher than in the placebo group where only a 4% increase was noted. The urinary Gln:Glu ratio was calculated for individual patients in each group, and the results are presented in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref>b. The Gln:Glu ratio increased significantly in both groups after the intervention, compared with the baseline value.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="Par14">The disturbances in the intestinal microbiota, mainly lower number and variety of <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> sp. being capable of digesting immunogenic gliadin peptides, have great importance in CD pathophysiology and affect the metabolic profiles in biological fluids of CD patients (Cukrowska et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2017</xref>). In the present study, we analysed the impact of dietary intervention with prebiotic applied as a supplement of a GFD on the profile and the concentration of AAs in the plasma of children with CD. This is the first ever study to analyse plasma AA levels with the use of the EZ:Faast™ method; therefore, our results cannot be reliably compared with the findings of other authors. To data, only few studies have investigated the AA profile in the urine or plasma of CD patients. Sevinc et al. (Sevinc et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>) noted a lower levels of Gln and C–C and significantly higher concentrations of Ala, Asn, Glu, Hyp, Ile, Leu, Phe, Pro, Ser, Thr and Val in the plasma of children with CD children than in healthy subjects. The analysis of urinary concentrations of AAs in CD patients showed lower levels of Glu and Gln and higher excretion of Gly compared to healthy controls (Bertini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2009</xref>). Children with CD who followed a GFD were characterised by higher concentrations of Lys and Arg and lower Gln levels in urine, compared with healthy controls (Di Cagno et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2011</xref>). The observed variations in the concentrations of individual AAs between health and CD patients could be attributed to differences in dietary patterns, intestinal malabsorption and inflammatory processes (Sevinc et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>; van Hees et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2015</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par15">In general, we detected that after the 3-month dietary intervention, regardless the administered supplement, the total plasma concentration of AAs increased in children with CD. The above result could suggest that a strict GFD alone delivers benefits. The total concentrations of EAAs and NEAAs increased in both groups, which suggest that the continuation of GFD over a period of 3 months induced positive changes in the intestines. The scientific data indicated that the strict adherence to a GFD has beneficial effect on CD patients by reducing symptoms and health care consumption (Norström et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>); therefore, it can be suggested a continuous healing of the intestines in all patients could be related to a good adherence to GFD (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>). In the literature, a decrease in the concentrations of the above EAAs has been related to severe intestinal failure, and those EAAs as well as citrulline are regarded as markers of mucosal damage (Fragkos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>). Interestingly, the plasma concentrations of selected AAs, including Ser, Leu, Thr, Met, Phe, Trp, Aba, Hyp and C–C, increased only in the placebo group. The observed differences in plasma AA levels between groups could be attributed to the specific properties of the administered prebiotic. Prebiotics are substrates which are utilised by gut microbiota during the formation of short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs). Davila et al. (Davila et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2013</xref>) suggested that AAs could be used by prebiotic-activated gut microbiota to synthesise SCFAs. Gly, Ala, Thr, Glu, Lys and Asp are the precursors of acetate, whereas butyrate is derived from Glu and Lys, and propionate is synthesised from Ala and Thr (Davila et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2013</xref>). In our previous study, SCFA levels increased in children with CD after the administration of Synergy 1 (Drabińska et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2018</xref>). Therefore, lower levels of some individual AAs in the Synergy 1 group compared to the placebo group could suggest that these AAs are transformed in the metabolic pathway and/or are utilised for the production of SCFAs.</p>
<p id="Par16">In the present study, we noted that the supplementation of GFD with Synergy 1 increased the total AA concentration in urine. Increased urinary excretion of AAs with a simultaneous increase in the content of circulating AAs could be attributed to higher absorption and intensified metabolism of AAs. Therefore, the simultaneous analysis of AAs in urine and plasma seems to be reasonable to avoid misinterpretation. On the other hand, higher urinary excretion of AAs could be associated with the loss of AA caused by metabolic failure, including intestinal permeability and failure in the kidney reabsorption processes (Dunstan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2017</xref>). Urinary excretion of AAs decreases in consequence of biochemical and metabolic disorders (Evans et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2008</xref>) or impaired protein synthesis (Niblett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2007</xref>). In a group of autistic patients following a gluten-free and casein-free diet, urinary excretion of AAs increased to a level approximating that noted in healthy controls (Evans et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2008</xref>). Similar tendency was observed in our study, suggesting positive changes in the metabolism.</p>
<p id="Par17">Positive changes in Glu concentration were noted after the conducted dietary intervention. In plasma, the concentration of Glu nearly doubled in the Synergy 1 group relative to baseline values, whereas only a 50% increase was noted in the placebo group. Moreover, urinary excretion of Glu decreased in both groups. Glu is a key factor responsible for the maintenance of gut function. Plasma Glu levels are relatively low because this AA is the main substrate for intestinal epithelial cells and a precursor in the synthesis of other AAs (Ala, Aap, Orn, Pro) and mediators (glutathione) (Ruth and Field <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>). There is evidence to indicate that Glu plays an important role in the intestinal barrier function. The supplementation of animal diets with Glu changed intestinal morphology, increased villus height and mucosal thickness in the jejunum (Wu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2012</xref>). In the Synergy 1 group, the concentration of Gln, a precursor in Glu synthesis, was characterised by a minor increase in plasma samples and a significant increase in urine samples relative to the placebo group. Gln also plays an important role in the gut function, participates in the synthesis of other AAs and protein, influences redox homeostasis and the immune response (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2009</xref>; Ruth and Field <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>). Numerous in vitro and in vivo studies have shown that Gln plays a pivotal role in the maintenance of intestinal integrity (DeMarco et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2003</xref>; Nose et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2010</xref>). According to Guarner (Guarner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2007</xref>), prebiotics contribute to the preservation of gut barrier integrity. Inulin-enriched diets improved intestinal architecture in rats and mice (Kleessen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2003</xref>; Strugala et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2003</xref>; Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2016</xref>). In most randomised human trials, inulin had no effect on intestinal permeability in patients with burn injuries, critically ill patients or healthy individuals (Jain et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2004</xref>; Olguin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2005</xref>; Ten Bruggencate et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2006</xref>). Despite the above, Russo et al. observed that inulin modified the concentrations of two intestinal permeability markers, zonulin and glucagon-like peptide 2, and suggested that inulin could be used in the prevention of intestinal disorders (Russo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2012</xref>). Further research is needed to explore the ambiguous influence of prebiotics on intestinal barrier function.</p>
<p id="Par18">The Gln:Glu ratio plays an important role in nitrogen metabolism, brain functions and the gut balance (Hashimoto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2005</xref>; Abu Shmais et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>). In the present study, the Gln:Glu ratio was determined in both urine and plasma. Significant changes in Gln:Glu ratio were not observed in plasma, but the analysed parameter increased significantly in urine in both groups after the intervention. These findings could suggest that GFD on its own induces beneficial changes in the intestines. A recent study of patients with chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction demonstrated a significant decrease (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) in the urinary Gln:Glu ratio in patients diagnosed with intestinal failure in comparison with healthy controls (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2017</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par19">The present pilot study has certain limitations. The number of participants was low, and the size of the sample and the power of the study could not be determined due to the lack of information from previous studies. However, these limitations are generally associated with pilot studies, and the obtained data will be used to calculate the necessary sample size in future studies. Due to the limited number of participants, a large-scale study should be performed to confirm the results obtained in this pilot study. Last, the present trial was conducted on children whose metabolism differs from that of adults. Therefore, the following study should be performed on older patients to generalise the findings of this research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec11" sec-type="conclusion">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="Par20">The present randomised placebo-controlled study makes a pioneering attempt to evaluate the influence of a dietary prebiotic on the AA profile of children diagnosed with CD and following a GFD. Our results indicate that prebiotic-supplemented GFD impact the overall AAs metabolism in children with CD, determined in two types of bodily fluids, plasma and urine. In group supplemented with Synergy 1, an increased urinary excretion of AAs with a simultaneous increase in the content of circulating AAs was detected that could be attributed to higher absorption and/or intensified metabolism of AAs, as well as further healing of the intestinal mucosa. The observed changes in Glu concentration suggest that oligofructose-enriched inulin could improve the intestinal condition and permeability. Further research is needed to explore the effect of oligofructose-enriched inulin on intestinal permeability.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The research was supported by statutory funds of the Department of Chemistry and Biodynamics of Food in the Institute of Animal Reproduction and Food Research PAS. The article is a part of a PhD Thesis of Natalia Drabińska.</p>
</ack>
<notes notes-type="author-contribution">
<title>Author contributions</title>
<p>UKK and ND conceived the study. UKK, ND and EJC were involved in designing of the study. ND collected samples, performed the main part of experiments, analysed the results and drafted the manuscript, EC participated in the chromatographic analysis; ND UKK and EJC contributed to the further writing of the manuscript. All authors reviewed and approved the final version of manuscript.</p>
</notes>
<notes notes-type="COI-statement">
<sec id="FPar1">
<title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>As authors of this manuscript, we declare no conflict of interest, either financial or otherwise.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="FPar2">
<title>Research involving human participants and/or animals</title>
<p>This study had been approved by the Bioethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Warmia and Mazury in Olsztyn, Poland (decision No. 23/2015 of 16 June 2015). The study protocol and all procedures performed in this study involving human participants were done in accordance with the ethical principles of the World Medical Association (WMA) 1964 Declaration of Helsinki and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards. This article does not contain or report any studies with animals performed by any of the authors. The study was registered at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link> as NCT03064997.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="FPar3">
<title>Informed consent</title>
<p>Written informed consent was obtained from the parents or legal guardians of all study participants.</p>
</sec>
</notes>
<ref-list id="Bib1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CR1">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abu Shmais</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Al-Ayadhi</surname>
<given-names>LY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Al-Dbass</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>El-Ansary</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanism of nitrogen metabolism-related parameters and enzyme activities in the pathophysiology of autism</article-title>
<source/>J Neurodev Disord
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1866-1955-4-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22958445</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR2">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Addolorato</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mirijello</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>D’Angelo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>State and trait anxiety and depression in patients affected by gastrointestinal diseases: psychometric evaluation of 1641 patients referred to an internal medicine outpatient setting</article-title>
<source/>Int J Clin Pract
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>1063</fpage>
<lpage>1069</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-1241.2008.01763.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18422970</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR3">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Celiac disease: pathophysiology, clinical manifestations, and associated autoimmune conditions</article-title>
<source/>Adv Pediatr
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>349</fpage>
<lpage>365</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yapd.2008.07.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19048738</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR4">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bertini</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calabró</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De Carli</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The metabonomic signature of celiac disease</article-title>
<source/>J Proteome Res
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>170</fpage>
<lpage>177</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr800548z</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19072164</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR5">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carta</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hardoy</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boi</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Association between panic disorder, major depressive disorder and celiac disease: a possible role of thyroid autoimmunity</article-title>
<source/>J Psychosom Res
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>789</fpage>
<lpage>793</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(02)00328-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12217453</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR6">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cukrowska</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sowińska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bierła</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Intestinal epithelium, intraepithelial lymphocytes and the gut microbiota—key players in the pathogenesis of celiac disease</article-title>
<source/>World J Gastroenterol
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>7505</fpage>
<lpage>7518</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v23.i42.7505</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29204051</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR7">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davila</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blachier</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gotteland</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Re-print of “intestinal luminal nitrogen metabolism: role of the gut microbiota and consequences for the host”</article-title>
<source/>Pharmacol Res
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>114</fpage>
<lpage>126</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2013.01.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23318949</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR8">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>DeMarco</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Glutamine and barrier function in cultured caco-2 epithelial cell monolayers</article-title>
<source/>J Nutr
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>133</volume>
<fpage>2176</fpage>
<lpage>2179</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/133.7.2176</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12840174</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR9">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dereziński</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klupczynska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sawicki</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Amino acid profiles of serum and urine in search for prostate cancer biomarkers: a pilot study</article-title>
<source/>Int J Med Sci
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>12</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7150/ijms.15783</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28138303</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR10">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Di Cagno</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rizzello</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gagliardi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Different fecal microbiotas and volatile organic compounds in treated and untreated children with celiac disease</article-title>
<source/>Appl Environ Microbiol
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>3963</fpage>
<lpage>3971</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02793-08</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19376912</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR11">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Di Cagno</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De Angelis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De Pasquale</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Duodenal and faecal microbiota of celiac children: molecular, phenotype and metabolome characterization</article-title>
<source/>BMC Microbiol
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>219</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-11-219</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21970810</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR12">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Drabińska</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jarocka-Cyrta</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markiewicz</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krupa-Kozak</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The effect of oligofructose-enriched inulin on faecal bacterial counts and microbiota-associated characteristics in celiac disease children following a gluten-free diet: results of a randomized</article-title>
<source/>Placebo Controlled Trial Nutr
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>201</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR13">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dunstan</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sparkes</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Macdonald</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Diverse characteristics of the urinary excretion of amino acids in humans and the use of amino acid supplementation to reduce fatigue and sub-health in adults</article-title>
<source/>Nutr J
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>19</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12937-017-0240-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28330481</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR14">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dunstan</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rothkirch</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered amino acid excretion in children with autism</article-title>
<source/>Nutr Neurosci
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<lpage>17</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/147683008X301360</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18510798</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR15">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fillmann</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kretzmann</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>San-Miguel</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Glutamine inhibits over-expression of pro-inflammatory genes and down-regulates the nuclear factor kappaB pathway in an experimental model of colitis in the rat</article-title>
<source/>Toxicology
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>236</volume>
<fpage>217</fpage>
<lpage>226</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2007.04.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543437</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR16">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fragkos</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Samaan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>PTH-200 amino acid profiles in patient with intestinal failure: preliminary data on biochemical insights</article-title>
<source/>Gut
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>A497 LP</fpage>
<lpage>A498 LP</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR17">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guarner</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Studies with inulin-type fructans on intestinal infections, permeability, and inflammation</article-title>
<source/>J Nutr
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>2568S</fpage>
<lpage>2571S</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/137.11.2568S</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951504</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR18">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hashimoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engberg</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shimizu</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Elevated glutamine/glutamate ratio in cerebrospinal fluid of first episode and drug naive schizophrenic patients</article-title>
<source/>BMC Psychiatry
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>6</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-5-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15683541</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR19">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hernanz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Polanco</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Plasma precursor amino acids of central nervous system monoamines in children with coeliac disease</article-title>
<source/>Gut
          <year>1991</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>1478</fpage>
<lpage>1481</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.32.12.1478</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1773952</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR20">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hugh Dunstan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sparkes</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Macdonald</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered amino acid homeostasis and the development of fatigue by breast cancer radiotherapy patients: a pilot study</article-title>
<source/>Clin Biochem
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>208</fpage>
<lpage>215</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiochem.2010.10.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20950596</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR21">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Husby</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koletzko</surname>
<given-names>IR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Korponay-Szabó</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>European society for pediatric gastroenterology, hepatology, and nutrition guidelines for the diagnosis of coeliac disease</article-title>
<source/>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>136</fpage>
<lpage>160</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPG.0b013e31821a23d0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22197856</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR22">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ilus</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaukinen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Virta</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Incidence of malignancies in diagnosed celiac patients: a population-based estimate</article-title>
<source/>Am J Gastroenterol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>1471</fpage>
<lpage>1477</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajg.2014.194</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25047399</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR23">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McNaught</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>ADG</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Influence of synbiotic containing lactobacillus acidophilus La5, bifidobacterium lactis Bb 12, streptococcus thermophilus, lactobacillus bulgaricus and oligofructose on gut barrier function and sepsis in critically ill patients: a randomised controlled tr</article-title>
<source/>Clin Nutr
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>467</fpage>
<lpage>475</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clnu.2003.12.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15297081</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR24">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kleessen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hartmann</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blaut</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fructans in the diet cause alterations of intestinal mucosal architecture, released mucins and mucosa-associated bifidobacteria in gnotobiotic rats</article-title>
<source/>Br J Nutr
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>597</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/BJN2002827</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12720580</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR25">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krupa-Kozak</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Swiątecka</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bączek</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brzóska</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Inulin and fructooligosaccharide affect in vitro calcium uptake and absorption from calcium-enriched gluten-free bread</article-title>
<source/>Food Funct
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>1950</fpage>
<lpage>1958</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6FO00140H</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26965706</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR26">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krupa-Kozak</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Drabińska</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jarocka-Cyrta</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The effect of oligofructose-enriched inulin supplementation on gut microbiota, nutritional status and gastrointestinal symptoms in paediatric coeliac disease patients on a gluten-free diet: study protocol for a pilot randomized controlled trial</article-title>
<source/>Nutr J
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>47</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12937-017-0268-z</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28830428</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR27">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>T-W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cephas</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holscher</surname>
<given-names>HD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Nondigestible fructans alter gastrointestinal barrier function, gene expression, histomorphology, and the microbiota profiles of diet-induced obese C57BL/6 J Mice</article-title>
<source/>J Nutr
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>146</volume>
<fpage>949</fpage>
<lpage>956</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.115.227504</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27052535</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR28">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Niblett</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dunstan</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Hematologic and urinary excretion anomalies in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Exp Biol Med (Maywood)
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>232</volume>
<fpage>1041</fpage>
<lpage>1049</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3181/0702-RM-44</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720950</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR29">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Norström</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sandström</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lindholm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ivarsson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A gluten-free diet effectively reduces symptoms and health care consumption in a Swedish celiac disease population</article-title>
<source/>BMC Gastroenterol
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>125</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-230X-12-125</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22984893</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR30">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nose</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Glutamine prevents total parenteral nutrition-associated changes to intraepithelial lymphocyte phenotype and function: a potential mechanism for the preservation of epithelial barrier function</article-title>
<source/>J Interferon Cytokine Res
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>67</fpage>
<lpage>80</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jir.2009.0046</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20028208</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR31">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Olguin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Araya</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hirsch</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prebiotic ingestion does not improve gastrointestinal barrier function in burn patients</article-title>
<source/>Burns
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>482</fpage>
<lpage>488</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.burns.2004.11.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15896512</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR32">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Serum amino acids profile and the beneficial effects of <sc>l</sc>-arginine or <sc>l</sc>-glutamine supplementation in dextran sulfate sodium colitis</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e88335</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0088335</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24505477</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR33">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roma</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roubani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kolia</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dietary compliance and life style of children with coeliac disease</article-title>
<source/>J Hum Nutr Diet
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>176</fpage>
<lpage>182</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-277X.2009.01036.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20163513</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR34">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Russo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Linsalata</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clemente</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Inulin-enriched pasta improves intestinal permeability and modifies the circulating levels of zonulin and glucagon-like peptide 2 in healthy young volunteers</article-title>
<source/>Nutr Res
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>940</fpage>
<lpage>946</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nutres.2012.09.010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23244539</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR35">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ruth</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The immune modifying effects of amino acids on gut-associated lymphoid tissue</article-title>
<source/>J Anim Sci Biotechnol
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2049-1891-4-27</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23899038</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR36">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sevinc</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Akar</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sevinc</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Amino acid levels in children with celiac disease</article-title>
<source/>Nutr Hosp
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>
<lpage>143</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26262708</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR37">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shoaib</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shehzad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Omar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Inulin: properties, health benefits and food applications</article-title>
<source/>Carbohydr Polym
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>147</volume>
<fpage>444</fpage>
<lpage>454</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2016.04.020</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27178951</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR38">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Strugala</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dettmar</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Colonic mucin: methods of measuring mucus thickness</article-title>
<source/>Proc Nutr Soc
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>237</fpage>
<lpage>243</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/PNS2002205</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12756973</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR39">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ten Bruggencate</surname>
<given-names>SJM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bovee-Oudenhoven</surname>
<given-names>IMJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lettink-Wissink</surname>
<given-names>MLG</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dietary fructooligosaccharides affect intestinal barrier function in healthy men</article-title>
<source/>J Nutr
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>136</volume>
<fpage>70</fpage>
<lpage>74</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/136.1.70</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16365061</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR40">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van Hees</surname>
<given-names>NJM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giltay</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tielemans</surname>
<given-names>SMAJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Essential amino acids in the gluten-free diet and serum in relation to depression in patients with celiac disease</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>e0122619</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122619</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25884227</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR41">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>WW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qiao</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Amino acids and gut function</article-title>
<source/>Amino Acids
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>110</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-008-0152-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18670730</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR42">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Y-Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Glutathione metabolism and its implications for health</article-title>
<source/>J Nutr
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>134</volume>
<fpage>489</fpage>
<lpage>492</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/134.3.489</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14988435</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR43">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Effects of oral supplementation with glutamate or combination of glutamate and N-carbamylglutamate on intestinal mucosa morphology and epithelium cell proliferation in weanling piglets</article-title>
<source/>J Anim Sci
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>337</fpage>
<lpage>339</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.53752</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23365372</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR44">
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<source/>Urinary glutamine/glutamate ratio as a potential biomarker of pediatric chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction
          <year>2017</year>
<publisher-loc>Rare Dis</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Orphanet J</publisher-name>
<fpage>12</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR45">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>CAA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kovacs-Nolan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mine</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Bioactive dietary peptides and amino acids in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>
<source/>Amino Acids
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>2127</fpage>
<lpage>2141</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-014-1886-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25501277</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>