<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="article-commentary" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Exp Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EXN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spexn</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Experimental Neuroscience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1179-0695</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30450007</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6236484</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1179069518809666</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1179069518809666</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-manuscript">EXN-18-0066</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Commentary</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title><italic>CNTNAP2</italic> Heterozygous Missense Variants: Risk Factors
for Autism Spectrum Disorder and/or Other Pathologies?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Canali</surname>
<given-names>Giorgia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1179069518809666">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1179069518809666">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1179069518809666">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8712-000X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Goutebroze</surname>
<given-names>Laurence</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1179069518809666">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1179069518809666">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1179069518809666">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1179069518809666"></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1179069518809666"><label>1</label>UMR-S 839, Inserm, Paris, France</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1179069518809666"><label>2</label>Faculté des Sciences et Ingénierie,
Sorbonne Université, Paris, France</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1179069518809666"><label>3</label>Institut du Fer à Moulin, Paris,
France</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1179069518809666">Laurence Goutebroze, Institut du Fer à
Moulin, 17 rue du Fer à Moulin, F-75005 Paris, France. Email:
<email>laurence.goutebroze@inserm.fr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>09</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<elocation-id>1179069518809666</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>29</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>6</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="d35e125" page="1941" related-article-type="commentary-article" vol="27" xlink:href="10.1093/hmg/ddy102"></related-article>
<abstract>
<p>The <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> gene has been proposed to be one of the major
susceptibility genes for neurodevelopmental disorders, in which numerous
heterozygous missense variants have been identified in patients with autism
spectrum disorder (ASD). The contribution of these variants to the
manifestations of ASD is however highly controversial because numerous
heterozygous missense variants have also been identified in control subjects. In
a recent study, we set up a sensitive developmental in vitro cell assay to
clarify the potential functional impact of these variants in a heterozygous
<italic>Cntnap2</italic> background relevant for <italic>CNTNAP2</italic>
heterozygosity in patients with ASD. We showed that the cell adhesion
glycoprotein Caspr2 encoded by <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> plays a dose-dependent
role in cortical neuron axon growth and provided a proof of principle that some
variants have functional consequences, either a loss of function or a
dominant-negative effect. This indicates that phenotypes mimicking
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous and homozygous null mutation may exist
in humans. Our observations further suggest that more variants than originally
expected could be functionally deleterious and induce a high heterogeneity of
phenotypes at the scale of the whole brain. This raises the interesting
possibility that <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous missense variants could
define an overall endophenotype shaping a risk for ASD and questions whether,
beyond ASD, the variants could contribute to the development of other
neurodevelopmental disorders and/or genetically less complex pathologies.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
<kwd>
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>heterozygous missense variants</kwd>
<kwd>Caspr2</kwd>
<kwd>axon growth</kwd>
<kwd>loss-of-function</kwd>
<kwd>dominant-negative effect</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>January-December 2018</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><bold>Comment on:</bold> Canali G, Garcia M, Hivert B, Pinatel D, Goullancourt A,
Oguievetskaia K, Saint-Martin M, Girault J-A, Faivre-Sarrailh C, Goutebroze L. Genetic
variants in autism-related CNTNAP2 impair axonal growth of cortical neurons. <italic>Hum
Mol Genet</italic>. 2018;27(11):1941–1954. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddy102">10.1093/hmg/ddy102</ext-link>.
PubMed PMID: 29788201. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29788201">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29788201</ext-link>.</p>
<sec id="section1-1179069518809666">
<title>Commentary</title>
<p>The <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> gene, encoding the neuronal cell adhesion transmembrane
glycoprotein Caspr2, has been proposed to be one of the major susceptibility genes
for neurodevelopmental disorders, including autism spectrum disorder (ASD), Gilles
de la Tourette syndrome, intellectual disability, obsessive-compulsive disorder,
cortical dysplasia-focal epilepsy (CDFE) syndrome, schizophrenia, and
attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1179069518809666">1</xref></sup>
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> genetic alterations identified in patients with ASD include
complex genomic rearrangements, heterozygous intragenic deletions, and especially a
large number of heterozygous missense variants distributed over the entire
extracellular domain of Caspr2.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1179069518809666">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1179069518809666"></xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1179069518809666">3</xref></sup>
<italic>Cntnap2</italic> knock-out mice display ASD-related behavioral deficits
supporting human genetic data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1179069518809666">4</xref></sup> However, a large sequencing study did not find evidence for statistical
differences between <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous missense variants in ASD
and control subjects,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1179069518809666">3</xref></sup> and more than 500 missense variants have been identified in individuals of
the global population reported in the Exome Aggregation Consortium (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://exac.broadinstitute.org">http://exac.broadinstitute.org</ext-link>), thus questioning the clinical
significance of the variants identified in patients with ASD. In a recent study, we
attempted to unravel this question by developing biochemical approaches and a
sensitive developmental in vitro cell assay to clarify the potential functional
impact of various <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> missense variants in a heterozygous
<italic>Cntnap2</italic> background relevant for <italic>CNTNAP2</italic>
heterozygosity in patients with ASD.</p>
<p>Caspr2 was originally identified as a component of axo-glial contacts in matured
myelinated axons, forming a cytoskeleton-associated complex in <italic>cis</italic>
and in <italic>trans</italic> with the immunoglobulin cell-adhesion molecule
CNTN2/Contactin2/TAG-1 at the juxtaparanodal regions of the nodes of Ranvier, where
it is required for the clustering of <italic>Shaker</italic>-type voltage-gated
potassium channels (Kv1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1179069518809666">Figure
1A</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1179069518809666">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1179069518809666">6</xref></sup>
Since <italic>Cntnap2</italic> is expressed in mouse brain as early as embryonic day
14.5, we asked whether Caspr2 could play additional roles in the axons during early
development. Performing cortical neuron cultures from mouse embryos, we demonstrated
that Caspr2 plays a dose-dependent role in axon growth in vitro. Loss of one
<italic>Cntnap2</italic> allele is sufficient to elicit axonal growth decrease,
revealing a situation that may be relevant for <italic>CNTNAP2</italic>
heterozygosity in patients with ASD. This offered a reliable assay to identify the
effects of the variants.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1179069518809666" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Structure and cell-adhesion function of Caspr2. (A) Axo-glial complexes at
the juxtaparanodal regions of the nodes of Ranvier in matured myelinated
axons. The protein 4.1B mediates the interaction of Caspr2 with the axonal
cytoskeleton. (B) Domain organization of Caspr2 and position of the variants
studied. F58C, discoidin domain; L1-L4, laminin G domains; FBR,
fibrinogen-like domain; EGF, EGF-like domains; GNP, “Glycophorin C-Neurexin
IV-Paranodin” motif mediating the interaction with the
cytoskeleton-associated proteins 4.1B; PDZ-B, PDZ-binding motif. (C)
Vertical and horizontal orientations of the ectodomain organized into 3
lobes, which could influence the ability of Caspr2 to recruit different
<italic>cis</italic> (B, B′) and <italic>trans</italic> (A, A′)
interacting partners in the extracellular space between the cells at contact
sites.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069518809666-fig1"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>The extracellular domain of Caspr2, where all missense variants have been detected,
is composed of 8 defined structural domains: a discoidin (F58C) domain, 4 laminin G
(L1-L4) domains, 2 epidermal growth factor (EGF)-like domains, and a fibrinogen
(FBR)-like domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1179069518809666">Figure
1B</xref>). Electron microscopy studies indicate that this ectodomain probably
displays a very compact F-shaped monomeric architecture organized into 3 major
lobes, which could harbor 2 main orientations, vertical or horizontal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1179069518809666">Figure 1C</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1179069518809666">7</xref></sup> The 3 lobes are composed of the L4 domain, L3 and FBR domains, and L1, L2,
and F58C domains, respectively, while the EGF-like domains may serve as molecular
hinges permitting the lobes to flex with respect to each other. Such a complex
architecture implies that Caspr2 has to pass multiple biosynthetic quality-control
checkpoints during its maturation in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and the Golgi
apparatus to make sure that only properly folded and glycosylated membrane molecules
reach their sites of action in cells. Initial studies showed that some
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> missense variants lead to Caspr2 misfolding and
retention in the ER, but the impact of other variants on protein maturation was not clear.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1179069518809666">8</xref></sup> Showing that the transport of Caspr2 from the ER to the plasma membrane in
transfected COS-7 cells can be monitored by a change in migration on sodium dodecyl
sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), we re-evaluated the impact of
8 ASD missense variants identified by Bakkaloglu et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1179069518809666">2</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1179069518809666">Figures 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1179069518809666">3A</xref>). We confirmed that some
variants indeed induce strong protein retention in the ER (R1119H, D1129H). Because
oligomerization in the ER is one of the mechanisms known to ensure protein
maturation controls, we then asked whether Caspr2 variant proteins could interact
with wild-type (WT) Caspr2, impair its trafficking, subcellular localization, and/or
function at the plasma membrane. Using multiple biochemical approaches, we showed
that Caspr2 is able to self-associate through its extracellular domain during its
intracellular processing but not at the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069518809666">Figure 2A</xref>), an observation consistent with
the monomeric status of the extracellular domain observed by electron microscopy,
indicating that Caspr2 probably interacts with its extracellular partners in its
monomeric form. Co-expressing variant proteins with WT Caspr2 to mimic
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygosity in humans, we then found that all
variant proteins are able to interact with WT Caspr2 and that the interaction with
the variants strongly retained in the ER leads to WT Caspr2 retention in the ER and
consequently to a decrease in functional protein at the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069518809666">Figure 2B</xref>). Testing one of
these ER-retained variants (R1119H) in heterozygous <italic>Cntnap2</italic>
cortical neurons in culture, we found that it has a dominant-negative effect on axon
growth, arguing that phenotypes mimicking homozygous <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> null
mutation may exist in humans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069518809666">Figure 2B</xref>). We next take advantage that Caspr2 is able to interact with
Contactin2/TAG-1 in vitro to evaluate whether variant proteins could present
adhesion defects. We identified 2 variants (I869T and G731S) which likely present
structural changes preventing their interactions with Contactin2/TAG-1 and showed
that they do not rescue the heterozygous axon growth phenotype in cortical neurons,
indicating a loss of function and arguing that phenotypes related to
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygosity may also exist in humans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069518809666">Figure 2B</xref>). Thus, our
observations provided a proof of principle that some variants have functional
consequences in a genetic background relevant for <italic>CNTNAP2</italic>
heterozygosity in ASD. Of interest, experiments in COS-7 cells further showed that
variant proteins studied display a gradient of intracellular retention rather than
being either strictly retained in the ER or strictly addressed at the plasma
membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1179069518809666">Figure 3A</xref>). This
indicates that Caspr2 is highly sensitive to missense mutations, likely because of
the complex architecture of its extracellular domain. It also strongly suggests that
the phenotypic consequences of a large number of variants could result from the
combination of a dominant-negative effect on WT Caspr2 function through retention in
the ER and a loss of function at the plasma membrane because of structural changes.
Therefore, one can speculate that ASD variants could induce a continuum of
phenotypes depending on the total level of functional protein at the plasma
membrane, rather than discrete phenotypes strictly mimicking
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous or homozygous null mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1179069518809666">Figure 3B</xref>). Remarkably, some
additional mechanisms could lead to Caspr2 function impairments and increase the
impact spectrum of the variants since we also identified a variant (N407S) which is
well localized at the membrane and properly binds to Contactin2/TAG-1 but plays a
dominant-negative effect on axon growth.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1179069518809666" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Hypothetic model showing how <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous missense
variants could impact Caspr2 functions when dose-dependent. (A) In wild-type
condition, Caspr2 self-associates during its intracellular processing but is
expressed in a monomeric form at the plasma membrane where it interacts with
its <italic>cis</italic> and <italic>trans</italic> extracellular partners.
(B) <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous conditions. After oligomerization
during intracellular processing, adhesion-defective variant proteins are
correctly addressed to the plasma membrane but do not interact with their
extracellular partners (loss-of-function), a situation leading to phenotypes
mimicking <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygosity. On the other hand,
misfolded variant proteins retain wild-type Caspr2 in the endoplasmic
reticulum (ER), leading to a decrease in functional protein at the plasma
membrane (dominant-negative effect) and phenotypes mimicking homozygous
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> null mutation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069518809666-fig2"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-1179069518809666" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p><italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous missense variants could induce a
continuum of phenotypes when Caspr2 functions are dose-dependent. (A)
Variant proteins display a gradient of intracellular retention in
transfected COS-7 cells. Percentage of intracellular form for each variant
protein normalized to its total expression, evaluated by immunoblot. Data
are means ± SEM of 3 independent experiments (see original manuscript). (B)
The phenotypic consequences of each variant could result from the
combination of a dominant-negative effect on wild-type Caspr2 function
through retention in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and a loss of function
at the plasma membrane (adhesion defects) because of structural changes,
leading to variable level of functional protein at the plasma membrane, and
as a whole to a continuum of phenotypes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069518809666-fig3"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Our observations predict that <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> variants may lead to a high
heterogeneity of phenotypes at the scale of the whole brain. Recent data provide
evidence that Caspr2 may have a broad range of functions during embryonic and early
post-natal neurodevelopment and contribute to normal neuronal network assembly and
activity, being notably required for the normal development of cortical neuron
dendritic arborization and spines, synaptic strength, AMPA receptors trafficking,
and myelination.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1179069518809666">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1179069518809666"></xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1179069518809666">11</xref></sup> The ability of
adhesion molecules to recruit partners is influenced by how these molecules are
positioned in the extracellular space between the cells at the contact sites,
notably how their overall dimensions, domains, and molecular hinges fit in the
cleft. Electron microscopy studies suggest that the extracellular domain of Caspr2
harboring a horizontal orientation (~90 Å) could fit in the narrow cleft of the
juxtaparanodes (~74-150 Å) and the inhibitory synapses (~100-120 Å), while the
extracellular domain harboring a vertical orientation (~145 Å) could be accommodated
at the excitatory synaptic contacts (~160-240 Å) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1179069518809666">Figure 1C</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1179069518809666">7</xref></sup> As lobes can flex with respect to each other, they may also change their
conformation upon protein partner binding so that the molecule could fit in
alternative way in the clefts. Thus, it is likely that each variant which does not
strongly impair protein trafficking could have specific impacts on the structure of
Caspr2 at the plasma membrane and on its ability to interact with its partners
depending on the sites of cell contacts. In addition, it has been shown that
<italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>+/–</sup> fast-spiking PV<sup>+</sup> cortical
interneurons also exhibit an intermediate electrophysiological phenotype between WT
and <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>–/–</sup> interneurons, while the maturation of
PV<sup>+</sup> GABAergic cortical interneurons is only altered in
<italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup>–/–</sup> mice,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1179069518809666">10</xref></sup> indicating that several functions of Caspr2 are probably dose-sensitive but
not all. In the latter case, adhesion-defective variants are not expected to have a
functional impact in a <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous background. Thus,
Caspr2 functions may be differentially affected by each individual variant,
depending both on their sensitivity to Caspr2 level and the direct impact of the
variants on the trafficking, structure, and/or interactions of the protein.</p>
<p>Considering these complex structure-function relationships, one can expect that the
consequences of <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> variants are hardly predictable by
bioinformatics analyses and that more variants than originally predicted are
functionally deleterious. Accordingly, the variants N407S and I869T were predicted
to be “tolerated” and “benign” (SIFT software)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1179069518809666">3</xref></sup> and therefore not expected to induce major functional impairments such as we
observed. There is thus no rational reason to think that the variants found in
control subjects, which are also distributed over the entire extracellular domain of
Caspr2, could have strictly different or no biological consequences when compared
with variants identified in patients with ASD. It does not however exclude the
possibility that <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> missense variants could contribute to ASD,
but rather highlights the interesting hypothesis that <italic>CNTNAP2</italic>
variants could define an overall endophenotype shaping a risk for ASD, the
development of ASD-related phenotypes being dependent on the interaction with
additional genetic and/or environmental risk factors. This hypothesis is supported
by the fact that the <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> variants identified in patients with
ASD are inherited from a non-affected parent (Bakkaloglu et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1179069518809666">2</xref></sup> and our unpublished observations in French ASD families).</p>
<p>Our observations further question whether, beyond ASD, <italic>CNTNAP2</italic>
missense variants could confer susceptibility and/or contribute to the development
of additional pathologies including neurodevelopmental disorders but also
genetically less complex disorders. Epilepsy is frequently associated with the core
manifestations of ASD. <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> genomic alterations have been
identified in patients with epilepsy and <italic>Cntnap2</italic> knock-out mice
display epileptic seizures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1179069518809666">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1179069518809666">4</xref></sup>
It is therefore possible that <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> variants contribute to
epileptic symptoms independently of ASD. The implication of Caspr2 in axon
outgrowth, myelination, and Ranvier node organization also questions whether
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> variants could contribute to disorders such as
peripheral neuropathies or axon recovery and remyelination impairments after injury
or demyelination, notably in patients with multiple sclerosis who show a large
interindividual heterogeneity of myelin repair capacity. Besides, one can question
whether <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> variants could be implicated in the development
and/or malignancy progression of neuroblastoma and glioma, where Caspr2 has been
proposed to function as a tumor suppressor protein.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1179069518809666">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1179069518809666">13</xref></sup>
<italic>CNTNAP2</italic> methylation and heterozygous genomic rearrangements, but
also a heterozygous missense mutation (A25T), have been detected in glioma, where
Caspr2 levels are strongly decreased as compared to controls. Finally, using
chromosome substitution strain-based mapping strategy in mouse, Buchner et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1179069518809666">14</xref></sup> identified a <italic>Cntnap2</italic> missense variant (H538Q) which
regulates diet-induced obesity, the effects being either obesity-promoting or
obesity-resistant, depending on the genetic background. This raises the intriguing
possibility that <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> variants constitute susceptibility factors
for obesity,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1179069518809666">14</xref></sup> which interestingly presents a positive association with ASD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1179069518809666">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>In conclusion, our study provides evidence that <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> heterozygous
missense variants could contribute to the pathophysiology of ASD and possibly to the
development of other pathologies. It also indicates that, in non-pathological
conditions, the variants could act as modulators of multiple functions of Caspr2 by
modifying the total level of functional protein at the plasma membrane of the cells,
maybe contributing to interindividual phenotypic diversity. Further research in vivo
is now required to strengthen these hypotheses.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p><bold>Funding:</bold>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or
publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> LG designed and wrote the manuscript; GC contributed to manuscript design and
figure drawing.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Laurence Goutebroze <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069518809666-img1.jpg"></inline-graphic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8712-000X">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8712-000X</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1179069518809666">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Connecting the CNTNAP2 networks with neurodevelopmental
disorders</article-title>. <source/>Mol Syndromol.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25852443</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1179069518809666">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakkaloglu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Roak</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Louvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular cytogenetic analysis and resequencing
of contactin associated protein-like 2 in autism spectrum
disorders</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18179895</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1179069518809666">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murdoch</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>No evidence for association of autism with rare
heterozygous point mutations in contactin-associated protein-like 2
(CNTNAP2), or in other contactin-associated proteins or
contactins</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>:e1004852.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1179069518809666">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penagarikano</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrahams</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Absence of CNTNAP2 leads to epilepsy, neuronal
migration abnormalities, and core autism-related deficits</article-title>.
<source/>Cell.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21962519</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1179069518809666">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poliak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhanany</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Juxtaparanodal clustering of Shaker-like K+
channels in myelinated axons depends on Caspr2 and TAG-1</article-title>.
<source/>J Cell Biol.
<year>2003</year>;<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>1149</fpage>–<lpage>1160</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1179069518809666">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Aguilera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Elst</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Loss of Cntnap2 causes axonal excitability
deficits, developmental delay in cortical myelination, and abnormal
stereotyped motor behavior</article-title> [published online ahead of print
December 28, 2017]. <source/>Cereb Cortex. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhx341.</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1179069518809666">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular architecture of contactin-associated
protein-like 2 (CNTNAP2) and its interaction with contactin 2
(CNTN2)</article-title>. <source/>J Biol Chem.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>291</volume>:<fpage>24133</fpage>–<lpage>24147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27621318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1179069518809666">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falivelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De Jaco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Favaloro</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Inherited genetic variants in autism-related
CNTNAP2 show perturbed trafficking and ATF6 activation</article-title>.
<source/>Hum Mol Genet.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>4761</fpage>–<lpage>4773</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22872700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1179069518809666">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varea</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-de-Saavedra</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopeikina</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic abnormalities and cytoplasmic glutamate
receptor aggregates in contactin associated protein-like 2/Caspr2 knockout
neurons</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>6176</fpage>–<lpage>6181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25918374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1179069518809666">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>KKA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Mouse Cntnap2 and human CNTNAP2 ASD alleles cell
autonomously regulate PV+ cortical interneurons</article-title>.
<source/>Cereb Cortex.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3868</fpage>–<lpage>3879</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1179069518809666">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Galfin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Malenka</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudhof</surname><given-names>TC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Candidate autism gene screen identifies critical role for
cell-adhesion molecule CASPR2 in dendritic arborization and spine
development</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>18120</fpage>–<lpage>18125</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23074245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1179069518809666">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Caren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Verification of genes differentially expressed
in neuroblastoma tumours: a study of potential tumour suppressor
genes</article-title>. <source/>BMC Med Genomics.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>2</volume>:53.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1179069518809666">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bralten</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gravendeel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloosterhof</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The CASPR2 cell adhesion molecule functions as a
tumor suppressor gene in glioma</article-title>. <source/>Oncogene.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>6138</fpage>–<lpage>6148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20711234</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1179069518809666">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchner</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Geisinger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The juxtaparanodal proteins CNTNAP2 and TAG1
regulate diet-induced obesity</article-title>. <source/>Mamm Genome.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22752552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1179069518809666">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aigner</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haegele</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of overweight and obesity among US
youth with autism spectrum disorder</article-title> [published online ahead
of print August 13, 2018]. <source/>Autism. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1362361318791817.</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>