<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0217764</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4079</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Horm Behav</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Horm Behav</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Hormones and behavior</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0018-506X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-6867</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29763587</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6261494</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yhbeh.2018.05.010</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1512167</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mice Exposed to Bisphenol A Exhibit Depressive-like Behavior with Neurotransmitter and Neuroactive Steroid Dysfunction</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xin</surname>
<given-names>Frances</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>Erin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krapp</surname>
<given-names>Christopher</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krizman</surname>
<given-names>Elizabeth N.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>Yemin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mesaros</surname>
<given-names>Clementina</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>Nathaniel W.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">e</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bansal</surname>
<given-names>Amita</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">f</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">g</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>Michael B.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Simmons</surname>
<given-names>Rebecca A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">f</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">g</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bartolomei</surname>
<given-names>Marisa S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Epigenetics Institute, Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104 USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Center for Excellence in Environmental Toxicology, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104 USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Department of Pediatrics and Department of Systems Pharmacology and Translational Therapeutics, Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia and University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104 USA</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>d</label>Center for Cancer Pharmacology, Department of Pharmacology, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia Pennsylvania 19104 USA</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>e</label>A.J. Drexel Autism Institute, Drexel University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104 USA</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>f</label>Division of Neonatology, Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia and University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104 USA</aff>
<aff id="A7"><label>g</label>Center for Research on Reproduction and Women’s Health, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104 USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">Corresponding author and person to whom reprint requests should be addressed: Marisa S. Bartolomei, Ph.D., 9-123 SCTR, 3400 Civic Center Boulevard, Philadelphia, PA 19104, Tel: +1 215 898 9063, <email>bartolom@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>12</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>18</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>93</fpage>
<lpage>104</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.yhbeh.2018.05.010-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Fetal exposure to endocrine disrupting chemicals (EDCs) has been associated with adverse neurobehavioral outcomes across the lifespan and can persist across multiple generations of offspring. However, the underlying mechanisms driving these changes are not well understood. We investigated the molecular perturbations associated with EDC-induced behavioral changes in first (F1) and second (F2) filial generations, using the model EDC bisphenol A (BPA). C57BL/6J dams were exposed to BPA from preconception until lactation through the diet at doses (10 μg/kg bw/d-lower dose or 10 mg/kg bw/d-upper dose) representative of human exposure levels. As adults, F1 male offspring exhibited increased depressive-like behavior, measured by the forced swim test, while females were unaffected. These behavioral changes were limited to the F1 generation and were not associated with altered maternal care. Transcriptome analysis by RNA-sequencing in F1 control and upper dose BPA-exposed adult male hippocampus revealed neurotransmitter systems as major pathways disrupted by developmental BPA exposure. High performance liquid chromatography demonstrated a male-specific reduction in hippocampal serotonin. Administration of the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor fluoxetine (20 mg/kg bw) rescued the depressive-like phenotype in males exposed to lower, but not upper, dose BPA, suggesting distinct mechanisms of action for each exposure dose. Finally, high resolution mass spectrometry revealed reduced circulating levels of the neuroactive steroid dehydroepiandrosterone in BPA-exposed males, suggesting another potential mechanism underlying the depressive-like phenotype. Thus, behavioral changes associated with early life BPA exposure may be mediated by sex-specific disruptions in the serotonergic system and/or sex steroid biogenesis in male offspring.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Bisphenol A</kwd>
<kwd>behavior</kwd>
<kwd>hippocampus</kwd>
<kwd>RNA sequencing</kwd>
<kwd>serotonin</kwd>
<kwd>dehydroepiandrosterone</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>