<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ILAR J</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ILAR J</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ilarjournal</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>ILAR Journal</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1084-2020</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1930-6180</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28838069</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6279127</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ilar/ilw042</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ilw042</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Genomic Tools for the Use of Nonhuman Primates in Translational Research</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>John D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="ilw042af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="ilw042cor1"></xref>
<!--<email>hardingarts@gmail.com</email>-->
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="ilw042af1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>John D. Harding, PhD, recently retired after several years of service at the National Institutes of Health in Bethesda, Maryland, where he was program officer for grants funding the US National Primate Research Centers</addr-line>.</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="ilw042cor1"><label>*</label>Address correspondence and reprint requests to Dr. John D. Harding at <email>hardingarts@gmail.com</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>01</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date iso-8601-date="2017-07-27" pub-type="epub">
<day>27</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>58</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Bridging the Gap between Reproducibility and Translation: Data Resources and Approaches</issue-title>
<fpage>59</fpage>
<lpage>68</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>19</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>20</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author 2017. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Institute for Laboratory Animal Research. All rights reserved. For permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="ilw042.pdf"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title>
<p>Nonhuman primates (NHPs) are important preclinical models for understanding the etiology of human diseases and for developing therapies and vaccines to cure or eliminate disease. Most human diseases have genetic components. Therefore, to be of maximal utility, the NHP species used for translational science should be as well characterized in regard to their genome and transcriptome as possible. This article reviews the current status of genomic information for the five NHP species used most often in translational research: rhesus macaque, cynomolgus macaque, vervet (African green) monkey, baboon, and marmoset NHP. These species have published whole genome sequences (with the exception of the baboon) and relatively well-characterized transcriptomes. Some have also been characterized in regard to specific genetic loci that are particularly related to translational concerns, such as the major histocompatability complex and the cytochrome P40 genes. Genomic resources to aid in stratifying captive populations in regard to genetic and phenotypic characteristics have been developed as an aid to enhancing reproducibility and facilitating more efficient use of animals. Taken together, the current genomic resources and numerous studies currently underway to improve them should enhance the value of NHPs as preclinical models of human disease.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>nonhuman primate</kwd>
<kwd>genome</kwd>
<kwd>transcriptome</kwd>
<kwd>rhesus</kwd>
<kwd>cynomolgus</kwd>
<kwd>vervet</kwd>
<kwd>baboon</kwd>
<kwd>marmoset</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<page-count count="10"></page-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>