<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0375361</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4604</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Child Psychol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Child Psychol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of child psychology and psychiatry, and allied disciplines</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9630</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1469-7610</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29889314</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6289898</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpp.12934</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS968623</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Infant temperament reactivity and early maternal caregiving: independent and interactive links to later childhood attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder symptoms</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>Natalie V.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Degnan</surname>
<given-names>Kathryn A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hane</surname>
<given-names>Amie A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fox</surname>
<given-names>Nathan A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chronis-Tuscano</surname>
<given-names>Andrea</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Department of Human Development and Quantitative Methodology, University of Maryland, College Park, MD</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Department of Psychology, The Catholic University of America, Washington, DC</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Psychology, Williams College, Williamstown, MA</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Department of Psychology, University of Maryland, College Park, MD USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: Natalie Miller, 3304 Benjamin Building, College Park, MD 20742-1131. <email>nvmiller@umd.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>Conflict of interest statement: No conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>18</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>60</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>43</fpage>
<lpage>53</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1111/jcpp.12934-->
<abstract>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Background</title>
<p id="P1">ADHD is a neurodevelopmental disorder with origins early in life. There is growing evidence that individual differences in temperament reactivity are predictive of ADHD symptoms, yet little is known about the relations between temperament reactivity in early infancy and later ADHD symptoms or the combined effect of reactivity with early environmental factors on ADHD symptom development. Using a nine-year prospective longitudinal design, this study tested the independent and interactive contributions of infant reactivity and maternal caregiving behaviors (MCB) on parent- and teacher-reported childhood ADHD symptoms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="P2">Participants included 291 children (132 male; 159 female) who participated in a larger study of temperament and social-emotional development. Reactivity was assessed by behavioral observation of negative affect, positive affect, and motor activity during novel stimuli presentations at four months of age. MCB were observed during a series of semi-structured mother-infant tasks at nine months of age. Finally, ADHD symptoms were assessed by parent- and teacher-report questionnaires at seven and nine years, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results</title>
<p id="P3">Reactivity was predictive of ADHD symptoms, but results were sex specific. For boys, infant motor activity was positively predictive of later ADHD symptoms, but only at lower-quality MCB. For girls, infant positive affect was positively predictive of later ADHD symptoms at lower-quality MCB, and—unexpectedly—infant positive affect and motor activity were negatively predictive of later ADHD symptoms at higher-quality MCB.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P4">These results point to early parenting as a moderating factor to mitigate temperament-related risk for later ADHD, suggesting this as a potential intervention target to mitigate risk for ADHD among reactive infants.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>ADHD</kwd>
<kwd>parenting</kwd>
<kwd>temperament</kwd>
<kwd>infancy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>