<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0236217</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6077</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuropharmacology</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neuropharmacology</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Neuropharmacology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0028-3908</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-7064</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29890190</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6349417</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2018.06.011</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1007546</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dysregulation and restoration of homeostatic network plasticity in fragile X syndrome mice</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jewett</surname>
<given-names>Kathryn A</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Kwan Young</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eagleman</surname>
<given-names>Daphne E</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Soriano</surname>
<given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>Nien-Pei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Molecular and Integrative Physiology, School of Molecular and Cellular Biology, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL 61801, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Neuroscience Program, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL 61801, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">AUTHORS’ CONTRIBUTIONS</p>
<p id="P2">KAJ, KYL, SS, DEE and NPT designed and performed the experiments. KAJ, KYL and NPT analyzed the data. KAJ, DEE and NPT wrote and edited the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: Nien-Pei Tsai, Ph.D., 407 South Goodwin Ave., Urbana, IL 61801, USA, Tel: 217-244-5620 Fax: 217-333-1133, <email>nptsai@illinois.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>22</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>08</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>138</volume>
<fpage>182</fpage>
<lpage>192</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.neuropharm.2018.06.011-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P3">Chronic activity perturbations in neurons induce homeostatic plasticity through modulation of synaptic strength or other intrinsic properties to maintain the correct physiological range of excitability. Although similar plasticity can also occur at the population level, what molecular mechanisms are involved remain unclear. In the current study, we utilized a multielectrode array (MEA) recording system to evaluate homeostatic neural network activity of primary mouse cortical neuron cultures. We demonstrated that chronic elevation of neuronal activity through the inhibition of GABA(A) receptors elicits synchronization of neural network activity and homeostatic reduction of the amplitude of spontaneous neural network spikes. We subsequently showed that this phenomenon is mediated by the ubiquitination of tumor suppressor p53, which is triggered by murine double minute-2 (Mdm2). Using a mouse model of fragile X syndrome, in which fragile X mental retardation protein (FMRP) is absent (<italic>Fmr1</italic> knockout), we found that Mdm2-p53 signaling, network synchronization, and the reduction of network spike amplitude upon chronic activity stimulation were all impaired. Pharmacologically inhibiting p53 with Pifithrin-α or genetically employing <italic>p53</italic> heterozygous mice to enforce the inactivation of p53 in <italic>Fmr1</italic> knockout cultures restored the synchronization of neural network activity after chronic activity stimulation and partially corrects the homeostatic reduction of neural network spike amplitude. Together, our findings reveal the roles of both <italic>Fmr1</italic> and Mdm2-p53 signaling in the homeostatic regulation of neural network activity and provide insight into the deficits of excitability homeostasis seen when <italic>Fmr1</italic> is compromised, such as occurs with fragile X syndrome.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Fmr1</kwd>
<kwd>FXS</kwd>
<kwd>p53</kwd>
<kwd>Mdm2</kwd>
<kwd>neural network</kwd>
<kwd>plasticity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>