<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSOB</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">royopenbio</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Open Biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2046-2441</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30958120</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6367134</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsob.180177</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">rsob180177</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>1001</subject>
<subject>33</subject>
<subject>42</subject>
<subject>133</subject>
<subject>31</subject>
<subject>58</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="leader">
<subject>Review Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Opportunities and challenges for the use of induced pluripotent stem cells in modelling neurodegenerative disease</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="short">iPSCs model neurodegenerative disease</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1512-3308</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Yi-Ying</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an1">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chiu</surname>
<given-names>Feng-Lan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an1">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>Chan-Shien</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an1">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuo</surname>
<given-names>Hung-Chih</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Cellular and Organismic Biology, Academia Sinica</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei 11529</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country></aff>
<aff id="af2"><label>2</label><institution>Genomics Research Center, Academia Sinica</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei 11529</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country></aff>
<aff id="af3"><label>3</label><institution>Graduate Institute of Medical Genomics and Proteomics, College of Medicine, National Taiwan University</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">e-mail: <email>kuohuch@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con" id="an1">
<label>†</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>A contribution to the special collection commemorating the 90th anniversary of Academia Sinica.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>9</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>9</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>180177</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>3</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2019 The Authors.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Published by the Royal Society under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="rsob-9-180177.pdf"></self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="reviewer_comments" xlink:href="rsob180177_review_history.pdf"></self-uri>
<self-uri xlink:href="rsob180177.thumb.gif" xlink:role="icon"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Adult-onset neurodegenerative diseases are among the most difficult human health conditions to model for drug development. Most genetic or toxin-induced cell and animal models cannot faithfully recapitulate pathology in disease-relevant cells, making it excessively challenging to explore the potential mechanisms underlying sporadic disease. Patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) can be differentiated into disease-relevant neurons, providing an unparalleled platform for <italic>in vitro</italic> modelling and development of therapeutic strategies. Here, we review recent progress in generating Alzheimer's, Parkinson's and Huntington's disease models from patient-derived iPSCs. We also describe novel discoveries of pathological mechanisms and drug evaluations that have used these patient iPSC-derived neuronal models. Additionally, current human iPSC technology allows researchers to model diseases with 3D brain organoids, which are more representative of tissue architecture than traditional neuronal cultures. We discuss remaining challenges and emerging opportunities for the use of three-dimensional brain organoids in modelling brain development and neurodegeneration.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>neurodegenerative disease</kwd>
<kwd>Alzheimer's disease</kwd>
<kwd>brain organoid</kwd>
<kwd>Huntington's disease</kwd>
<kwd>induced pluripotent stem cells</kwd>
<kwd>Parkinson's disease</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>January 2019</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<label>1.</label>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Neurodegenerative diseases are often characterized by progressive atrophy of neurons and tissue, which corresponds to a loss of neuronal function and results in impaired cognition and/or movement. Each specific neurodegenerative disease preferentially affects a defined population of neurons, leading to distinctive age-related clinical profiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C1">1</xref>]. However, many neurodegenerative diseases share common molecular features that precede neuronal death and dysfunction, including mitochondrial dysfunction, axonal damage and abnormal protein aggregation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C3">3</xref>]. Aberrant processing and aggregation of misfolded proteins cause complex and distinctive pathophysiological profiles in several neurodegenerative proteinopathies. Some well-known hallmarks of these diseases include Amyloid <italic>β</italic> (A<italic>β</italic>) plaques and phosphorylated Tau (pTau)-containing tangles in Alzheimer's disease (AD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C4">4</xref>], <italic>α</italic>-synuclein-associated Lewy bodies in Parkinson's disease (PD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C5">5</xref>] and mutant huntingtin (Htt)-containing inclusion bodies in Huntington's disease (HD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C6">6</xref>]. These aggregated proteins may act via loss-of-function or gain-of-toxicity mechanisms to cause neuronal axon damage and cellular vulnerability. Thus, clearance of neurotoxic aggregation is a major focus of phenotypic assays for drug development, which includes methods to monitor autophagy-lysosomal network function, chaperone-mediated folding and clearance, and ubiquitin-proteasome protein degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C3">3</xref>]. Many pathogenic mutations are associated with protein processing and/or aggregation. For example, HD is a monogenic disease caused by a polyglutamine expansion in mutant Htt, which causes the protein to aggregate. Likewise, several known pathogenic mutations in AD are associated with A<italic>β</italic> production. However, the majority of AD and PD cases are idiopathic, which makes exploring disease mechanisms very difficult without access to damaged tissue in the patient's nervous system. Post-mortem brain tissues have provided essential pathological information for each disease, but it is not suitable for identifying the biological changes during initial stages of disease. Furthermore, transgenic animals are valuable models for phenotypic and preclinical testing during drug development, but microenvironment and species differences may be major reasons that transgenic animals have been largely unable to sufficiently recapitulate disease phenotypes. Current approaches to drug discovery have not delivered effective therapeutics to reduce neurodegeneration in AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C7">7</xref>], and other neurodegenerative suffer from a lack of therapeutic options. Thus, the current models may be complemented by access to patient-derived disease-relevant neural cell types, greatly aiding preclinical drug evaluation for neurodegenerative disease.</p>
<p>Recent advances in the ability to reprogram patient somatic cells into inducible pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) have provided a novel means to generate disease-relevant cells for <italic>in vitro</italic> disease modelling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C9">9</xref>]. Human iPSC technology was launched by Yamanaka and colleagues when they first introduced the transcription factors, OCT4, SOX2, KLF4 and c-MYC, to somatic cells, generating a novel method for producing stem cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C10">10</xref>]. In principle, human iPSCs can differentiate into any cell type of human body; thus, patient iPSCs can provide a source of cells that harbour a precise constellation of genetic variants, which is associated with pathogenesis in the appropriate microenvironment. As such, iPSCs are often used in well-established models of human disease, including both developmental and adult-onset diseases, in the form of either two-dimensional (2D) cell cultures or three-dimensional (3D) organoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C16">16</xref>]. Importantly, cells derived from patient iPSCs have been shown to recapitulate phenotypes of various human neurodegenerative diseases, including AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C18">18</xref>], amyotrophic lateral sclerosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C20">20</xref>], HD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C21">21</xref>] and fragile X syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C22">22</xref>]. Also, improvements in iPSC culture and the development of robust differentiation protocols have made it possible to carry out phenotype-based drug screening in iPSC-derived disease-target cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C23">23</xref>]. Expandable iPSCs can give rise to a large number of disease-related cells, providing an excellent opportunity for large-scale drug testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C9">9</xref>]. However, several technical considerations should be taken into account when applying this approach. For example, one key issue is that variability in the phenotypes of iPSC lines from individual patients necessitates a large cohort of lines to eliminate misleading pathological mechanisms or drug effects. In order to address this issue, the use of current gene-editing technology has allowed researchers to standardize genetic background by using isogenic control lines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C25">25</xref>]. Thus, coupling of gene editing technologies with patient-derived iPSCs has enabled the generation of a set of genetically defined human iPSC lines for disease modelling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C24">24</xref>]. Another hurdle for modelling disease with iPSC-derived cells is that the maturity of derived neurons and differentiation time required for phenotypes to emerge may be variable across iPSC lines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C26">26</xref>]. This variability issue can be addressed by the use of multiple well-characterized iPSC lines and isogenic controls. Moreover, for most diseases of ageing, multiple or chronic treatments are required to promote the expression of disease-associated phenotypes in cellular models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C27">27</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C33">33</xref>]. This challenge is significant, but may be addressed in many cases by the use of long-term 3D organoid cultures. These complex structures provide unique human organ-like tissue that is amenable to long-term culturing for disease modelling. The self-organizing capability of iPSCs can recapitulate several key features of human cortical development, including progenitor zone organization, neurogenesis, gene expression and distinct human-specific outer radial glia cell layers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C34">34</xref>]. Furthermore, the complex structures promote disease pathogenesis by accelerating neuronal differentiation and maturation, providing excellent laboratory models for human neurodegenerative disease.</p>
<p>The great potential for the use of iPSC technology in developing treatments for human disease is evident [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C25">25</xref>]. In this review, we provide an overview of iPSC technology in modelling neurodegenerative diseases of the central nervous system (especially AD, PD and HD), including methods for differentiating disease-relevant neurons, important findings in drug development, and current trends for improving treatment of neurodegenerative disease. We also discuss the use of iPSC-derived 3D brain organoids to study the central nervous system and current findings from this technology with regard to neurological diseases. The advantages and disadvantages of iPSC 3D organoid modelling and potential new treatments for neurodegenerative diseases are highlighted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<label>2.</label>
<title>iPSC-based disease modelling and drug discovery in Alzheimer's disease</title>
<p>AD is the most common form of dementia in the elderly, affecting more than 40 million people worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C35">35</xref>]. The primary gross pathology of the disease is brain volume reduction and hippocampal degeneration, while the pathological hallmarks are extracellular A<italic>β</italic> plaques and aggregation of hyperphosphorylated tau in neurofibrillary tangles. The result of these pathological processes is that AD patients suffer progressive memory impairment and acute cognitive dysfunction during late-stage disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C4">4</xref>]. Experimental therapies that target A<italic>β</italic> deposition have been thus far unsuccessful in clinical trials. Although current medications, which include cholinesterase and N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) inhibitors, cannot stop neuronal loss, the drugs may lessen and stabilize cognitive defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C4">4</xref>].</p>
<p>Both genetic and environmental factors are likely to be involved in AD pathogenesis. Most genetic forms of AD result in disease onset before age 60 and are termed early-onset or familial AD. By contrast, the most pervasive form of AD is idiopathic with increasing incidence after 65 years of age; this category is denoted late-onset AD or sporadic AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C36">36</xref>]. Importantly, familial AD-associated gene mutations are all involved in A<italic>β</italic> production and include amyloid-<italic>β</italic> precursor protein (<italic>APP</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C37">37</xref>], presenilin1 (<italic>PSEN1</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>] and presenilin 2 (<italic>PSEN2</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C39">39</xref>]. Theoretically, these genetic mutations cause Amyloid <italic>β</italic> 1–42 (A<italic>β</italic>42) production and result in extracellular A<italic>β</italic> aggregation. However, the causes of sporadic AD are poorly understood. A few genetic factors, including apolipoprotein E (<italic>APOE</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C40">40</xref>], sortilin-related receptor (<italic>SORL1</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C41">41</xref>] and SMI-1 (<italic>SMI1</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C42">42</xref>], were reported to be associated with late-onset AD. It has also been suggested that complex interactions between genetic risk factors and other host factors, such as diabetes mellitus, hypertension and obesity, play important roles in the aetiology of late-onset AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C43">43</xref>]. Nevertheless, the specific causes and mechanisms underlying the occurrence and progression of sporadic AD are still elusive.</p>
<p>iPSCs have been widely used to explore disease pathogenesis associated with both inherited monogenetic mutations and sporadic AD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOB180177TB1">table 1</xref>). Since multiple neuronal types are susceptible in AD, protocols have been developed to generate different subtypes of forebrain neurons from AD-iPSCs for use as <italic>in vitro</italic> models of disease (<xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOB180177TB2">table 2</xref>). The accumulation of A<italic>β</italic> peptide, which is produced from APP via sequential cleavage by <italic>β</italic>-secretase and γ-secretase, is thought to be a causative factor of AD pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C54">54</xref>], and the elevation of A<italic>β</italic> was found to result from pathogenic mutations in <italic>APP</italic>, <italic>PSEN1</italic> and <italic>PSEN2</italic>. <italic>PSEN1</italic> encodes a subunit of γ-secretase that releases soluble APP from the cellular membrane. Several mutations in presenilin1 (<italic>PSEN1</italic>) have been identified, including A79 V [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C45">45</xref>], Y115C, M146I [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>], A264E [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C48">48</xref>], G265C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C47">47</xref>], G384A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C49">49</xref>], T449C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C47">47</xref>], S169del [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C48">48</xref>] and a single nucleotide deletion in intron 4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>]. Additionally, all of these mutations have been shown to elevate A<italic>β</italic>42 secretion in AD-iPSC derived cortical neurons. <italic>PSEN1</italic>(P117R) was associated with reduced neurite length and susceptibility to inflammatory response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C46">46</xref>]. It was also shown that hyper-phosphorylation of microtubule-associated protein Tau (pTau) occurs in AD-iPSC-derived neurons carrying <italic>PSEN1</italic> mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C48">48</xref>]. Moreover, AD-iPSC-derived neural progenitors with S169del or A264E mutations were shown to exhibit low rates of proliferation and high rates of apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C48">48</xref>]. Similarly, <italic>PSEN2</italic> encodes the catalytic subunit of γ-secretase and is involved in amyloid-<italic>β</italic> precursor protein (APP) cleavage. <italic>PSEN2</italic>(N141I) was associated with increased A<italic>β</italic>42 secretion and decreased action potential in neurons derived from patent iPSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C51">51</xref>]. Mutations in <italic>APP</italic> involving V717 (either V717I or V717 L) and <italic>APP</italic> duplication have been shown to cause the elevation of A<italic>β</italic>, Tau and pTau in AD-iPSC-derived forebrain neurons and astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C52">52</xref>]. The elevated Tau expression was reduced by A<italic>β</italic> antibody treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic>APP</italic>(E693del) was associated with accumulation of intracellular A<italic>β</italic> oligomers and susceptibility to stress response in forebrain neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C27">27</xref>]. In general, A<italic>β</italic>42 secretion was reduced in familial AD iPSC-derived neurons after treatment with <italic>β</italic>- or γ-secretase inhibitors, including BSI-IV, compound E, compound W or DAPT. NSAID or imidazole-based modulators of γ-secretase activity were also shown to be effective at reducing A<italic>β</italic>42 secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C45">45</xref>].
<table-wrap id="RSOB180177TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Alzheimer's disease modelling based on patient iPSCs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">iPSC genotypes</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">main finding</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">β or γ-secretase inhibitors</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">other treatments</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">differentiated cell type</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> cell markers</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">refs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>familial Alzheimer's disease</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN1</italic> (A246E, M146I, Y115C, intronic single nucleotide deletion)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>42↑A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑, carboxypeptidase activity↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">compound E/DAPT/E2012: A<italic>β</italic>↓; compound W: A<italic>β</italic>42↓ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical neurons, basal forebrain cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJI, CTIP/TBR1, CHAT/VACHT/Nkx2.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yagi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C39">39</xref>]; Duan <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C44">44</xref>]; Moore <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN1</italic>(P79V)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>40↓ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">high-level NSAID-based γ-secretase modulators: A<italic>β</italic>42/40↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mertens <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN1</italic>(P117R)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurite length↓; susceptibility for inflammatory stress↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">apigenin: neurite length↑; stress susceptibility↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Balez <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN1</italic> (G265C, T449C)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>40↑ A<italic>β</italic>42↑, APP↑ APP-CTF↑, pTau↑, activated GSK-3<italic>β</italic>↑ stress susceptibility↑; <italic>PSEN1</italic> mutations: A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cholinergic neurons, dopaminergic neurons, glutamatergic neurons, GABAergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, VACHT, TH, VGLUT1/2, GAD2/1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ochalek <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN1</italic> (A246E, S169del)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">premature NPCs: proliferation↓ apoptosis↑; Neurons: A<italic>β</italic>42↑ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑ pTau↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN1</italic> knockdown: rescues NPC prematuration</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN1</italic>(G384A)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>40↓ A<italic>β</italic>42↑ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BSI-IV or GSM: A<italic>β</italic>↓ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 pharmaceutical compounds: A<italic>β</italic>↓, A<italic>β</italic>42/40↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TBR2, SATB2, VGLUT1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kondo <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C49">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PSEN2</italic>(N141I)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>42↑, A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑, AP number↓ First AP height↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">compound E: A<italic>β</italic>↓; compound W: A<italic>β</italic>42↓ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">insulin: A<italic>β</italic>42↓, calcium flux↑; correction of <italic>PSEN2-N141I</italic>: restores all deficits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">basal forebrain cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, FOXG1, p75/CHAT/VACHT/Nkx2.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yagi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C39">39</xref>]; Ortiz-Virumbrales <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C50">50</xref>]; Moreno <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APP</italic> (E693Δ, APP-V717 L)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APP-E693</italic>Δ: A<italic>β</italic>↓; <italic>APP-V717 L</italic>: A<italic>β</italic>42↑ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑; <italic>APP-E693</italic>Δ</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BSI-IV: A<italic>β</italic>↓ sAPP<italic>β</italic>↓ A<italic>β</italic> oligomer↓, stress responses↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DHA: stress responses↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, TBR1/SATB2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kondo <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C49">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APP</italic>(K724N)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>40↓ A<italic>β</italic>42↑ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">high-level NSAID-based GSM: A<italic>β</italic>42/40↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mertens <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APP</italic> (V171I)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>↑, A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑, sAPP<italic>β</italic>↑, tTau↑pTau↑; GABAergic neurons: the highest A<italic>β</italic> level; astrocytes: secreting high level of A<italic>β</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DAPT: A<italic>β</italic>↓ sAPP<italic>β</italic>↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic> specific antibody: Tau↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">forebrain neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, TBR1/CUX1, VGLUT1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muratore <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C37">37</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APP</italic> (V717I, APP<sup>DP</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APP-V717I</italic>: A<italic>β</italic>40↓ A<italic>β</italic>42↑ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑; <italic>APP<sup>DP</sup></italic>: A<italic>β</italic>↑; Both: tTau↑ pTau↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DAPT/E2012: A<italic>β</italic>↓, altered pTau and Tau level; DAPT: APP-C83/99↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cerebral cortex neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TUJ1, CTIP/TBR1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moore <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>]; Liao <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C52">52</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APP<sup>Dp</sup></italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>40↑, pTau(S231)↑, activated GSK-3<italic>β</italic>↑, early endosome accumulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">compound E/DAPT: A<italic>β</italic>40↓; BSI-II/OM99-2: A<italic>β</italic>40↓ pTau↓ active GSK-3<italic>β</italic>↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">glutamatergic neurons, GABAergic neurons, cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, VGLUT1, GAD67/GABA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Israel <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C17">17</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>sporadic Alzheimer's disease</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APOE3/E4</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>42↑ A<italic>β</italic>42/40↑; neurotoxic susceptibility↑ calcium transient↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">compound E/DAPT: no effects</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">basal forebrain cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, CHAT/ VACHT/Nkx2.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duan <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C44">44</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APOE3/3</italic> or <italic>E4/E4</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>↑ pTau↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ApoE4 structure corrector: A<italic>β</italic>↓ pTau↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GABAergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, GABA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>APOE4</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>42↑ pTau↑; synapse number↑; A<italic>β</italic> uptake ↓; microglia-like cells: morphology changes; astrocytes: cholesteral accumulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">astrocyte, microglia-like cells, neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, S100<italic>β</italic>, Iba1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lin <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C53">53</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>SORL1</italic>-5'-end SNPs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BDNF in normal neurons: <italic>SORL1</italic>↑ A<italic>β</italic>↓; BDNF in sAD: no effects</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">glutamatergic neurons, GABAergic neurons, cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, VGLUT1, GAD67/GABA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Young <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>BMI1</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>BMI1</italic> ↓, A<italic>β</italic>42↑ A<italic>β</italic> oligomer↑ Tau↑ p-Tau↑, apoptosis in GABAergic neurons↑, amyloid plaques and p-Tau tangles formation, PSD-95 and synaptophysin↓, GSK-3<italic>β</italic>↑ p-p53↑, MAPT expression↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BSI-IV, DAPT, GSM-XXII: A<italic>β</italic>↓ p-Tau↓ apoptosis↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">caffeine, DNA-PK inhibitor or p53 inhibitor: amyloid↓ p-Tau↓; ATM/ATR inhibitor or ATM inhibitor: apoptosis↓; GSK-3<italic>β</italic> inhibitor: amyloid↓ p-Tau↓ apoptosis↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GABAergic neurons, glutamatergic neurons, cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, GABA, VGLUT1, ChAT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Flamier <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">unkown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurite length↓; A<italic>β</italic>42↑, apoptosis or cytotoxicity from oxidative/nitrosative stress↑, hyper-excitability↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">apigenin: neurite length↑; apoptosis and hyper-excitability↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Balez <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic>40↑ A<italic>β</italic>42↑, APP↑ APP-CTF↑, pTau↑, activated GSK-3<italic>β</italic>↑ stress susceptibility↑ early endosome accumulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">compound E/DAPT: A<italic>β</italic>40↓; BSI-II/OM99-2: A<italic>β</italic>40↓ pTau↓ active GSK-3<italic>β</italic>↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cholinergic neurons, dopaminergic neurons, glutamatergic neurons, GABAergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, VACHT, TH, VGLUT1/2, GAD2/1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ochalek <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C47">47</xref>]; Israel <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C17">17</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">intracellular A<italic>β</italic> oligomer↑, stress responses↑</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BSI-IV: A<italic>β</italic>↓ sAPP<italic>β</italic>↓ A<italic>β</italic> oligomer↓, stress responses↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DHA: stress responses↓</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, TBR1/SATB2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kondo <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C49">49</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>BSI: <italic>β</italic>-secretase inhibitor; GSM: γ-secretase modulator.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="RSOB180177TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Differentiation protocols for AD relevant neurons.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">methods for neuronal induction</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">supplement for NPCs generation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">supplement for differentiation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">neuronal markers</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">differentiated cell type</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">refs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>EB formation</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="7">no bFGF, with or without dual SMAD inhibitors/dorsomorphin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurosphere formation: B27, insulin, progesterone, FGF2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">B27, insulin, progesterone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yagi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurosphere formation: N2, SB431542, dorsomorphin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">B27, BDNF/GDNF/NT-3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, TBR1/SATB2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kondo <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C27">27</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EB attachment and rosette formation: N2 → NPC expansion: N2, B27, FGF2/EGF2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, cAMP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, CTIP/TBR1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mertens <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C45">45</xref>]; Moore <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C38">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EB attachment and rosette formation: N2, heparin, SHH → neurosphere formation: N2, B27, heparin, cAMP, IGF1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, BDNF/GDNF/IGF1, cAMP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, TBR1, CUX1, VGLUT1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">forebrain neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muratore <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C37">37</xref>]; Liao <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C52">52</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EB attachment and rosette formation: N2, heparin → neurosphere formation: N2, B27, heparin, bFGF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, SHH/FGF-8 → N2, B27, SHH/FGF-8, AA, cAMP, BDNF/GDNF/IGF-1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Balez <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EB attachment and rosette formation: N2, B27, heparin, bFGF/EGF → neurosphere formation: N2, B27, heparin, bFGF/EGF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, BDNF/GDNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, GABA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GABAergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurosphere formation: N2, heparin, bFGF/EGF → neuceofection of Lhx8/Gbx1-IRES-EGFP: SHH/FGF8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">sorting GFP<sup>+</sup> cells: B27, bFGF, NGF, cytosine arabinoside</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, CHAT/ VACHT/Nkx2.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">basal forebrain cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duan <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C44">44</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>NPC induction</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RA, sodium bicarbonate.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurosphere formation: N2, heparin, bFGF/EGF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">N2, B27, BDNF/GDNF/CNTF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">MAP2, TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Yang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, Noggin, SB431542, sodium bicarbonate</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EB attachment and rosette formation: N2, B27, bFGF</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, LDN, SB431542, bFGF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, EGF/bFGF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, AA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, VACHT, TH, VGLUT1/2, GAD2/1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cholinergic neurons, dopaminergic neurons, glutamatergic neurons, GABAergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ochalek <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, LDN, Noggin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> N2, B27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">B27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, GABA, VGLUT1, ChAT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">GABAergic neurons, glutamatergic neurons, cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Flamier <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PA6 co-cultured, Noggin, SB431542 for NPCs isolation (CD184<sup>+</sup>, CD15<sup>+</sup>, CD44<sup>−</sup>, CD271<sup>−</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, bFGF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2, B27, BDNF/GDNF, cAMP for isolating neurons (CD24<sup>+</sup>, CD184<sup>−</sup>CD44<sup>−</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, VGLUT1, GAD67/GABA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Israel <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C17">17</xref>]; Young <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> B27, doxycycline hydrochloride</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">B27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TBR2, SATB2, VGLUT1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kondo <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C27">27</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LDN, SB431542, SAG, purmorphamine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p75<sup>+</sup> NPCs isolation : Brainphys medium, B27 neurosphere formation: Brainphys medium, B27, NGF/BDNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brainphys medium, B27, NGF/BDNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2, TUJ1, FOXG1, p75/CHAT/VACHT/Nkx2.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">basal forebrain cholinergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ortiz-Virumbrales <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C50">50</xref>]; Moreno <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C51">51</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AA, ascorbic acid; RA, retinoic acid; NPC, neural progenitor cell.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p>The majority of AD cases are diagnosed as sporadic or polygenic, suggesting that AD is most often a multifactorial disease that arises from genetic variants and environmental factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C43">43</xref>]. Genome-wide association studies (GWASs) have identified numerous genetic variants associated with sporadic AD, such as GRB2-associated binding protein (<italic>GAB2)</italic>, galanin-like peptide (<italic>GALP</italic>), piggyBac transposable element derived 1 (<italic>PGBD1</italic>), tyrosine kinase, non-receptor 1 (<italic>TNK1</italic>) and clusterin (<italic>CLU</italic>, also known as apolipoprotein J) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C55">55</xref>]. <italic>APOE</italic> encodes Apolipoprotein E, a cholesterol carrier lipoprotein in the brain, which has several isoforms or alleles. The <italic>APOE4</italic> allele was the first gene risk factor to be identified for sporadic AD and is still the most significant. Patients with <italic>APOE4</italic> have elevated risk compared with those carrying <italic>APOE3</italic>, while <italic>APOE2</italic> is considered to be a protective allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C56">56</xref>]. <italic>APOE4</italic> codes for APOE(C112R), which has altered binding affinity towards lipoproteins and A<italic>β</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C57">57</xref>]. In human iPSC-derived forebrain neurons, the <italic>APOE4</italic> allele was associated with high levels of pTau, A<italic>β</italic> secretion and GABAergic neuron degeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C53">53</xref>]. These AD-related phenotypic events were reduced by treating cells with the <italic>APOE4</italic> structure corrector, PH002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C40">40</xref>]. In <italic>APOE3/E4</italic> neurons, apigenin, an anti-inflammatory drug, showed neuroprotective effects by reducing Ca<sup>2+</sup> signalling frequency and caspase 3/7-mediated apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C46">46</xref>]. In <italic>APOE3/E4</italic> forebrain cholinergic neurons, neurotoxicity was increased when cells were treated with ionomycin, and cell viability was reduced while calcium was elevated upon glutamate treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C44">44</xref>]. SORL1 is functionally associated with directing APP to endocytic pathways. A certain genetic variation in the <italic>SORL1</italic> 5′ region is known as a gene-risk factor for sporadic AD, and it has been shown that this variant reduces expression of <italic>SORL1</italic> in AD-iPSC-derived neurons. Additionally, BDNF treatment cannot induce <italic>SORL1</italic> expression to reduce A<italic>β</italic> secretion by contrast with wild-type <italic>SORL1</italic> carriers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C41">41</xref>]. <italic>BMI1</italic> encodes polycomb complex protein BMI1, and is associated with transcriptional repression of several genes through Ring1 mediated E3-mono-ubiquitin ligase activity. In cortical neurons generated from sporadic AD patient-derived iPSCs, BMI1 was downregulated and associated with AD phenotypes including A<italic>β</italic> secretion/extracellular deposition, Tau phosphorylation and neuronal degeneration. Mechanistically, BMI1 was associated with transcript repression of microtubule-associated protein tau (<italic>MAPT</italic>) and destabilization of glycan synthase kinase-3<italic>β</italic> (GSK-3<italic>β</italic>) and p53. Thus, several drugs that target these mechanisms were effective for reducing phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C42">42</xref>]. Also, the AD-associated phenotypes, such as elevations in A<italic>β</italic> secretion and Tau phosphorylation, and activation of GSK-3<italic>β</italic> were identified in neurons generated from sporadic AD patient-derived iPSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C58">58</xref>]. These phenotypes could be reduced by treating AD-iPSC-derived neurons with the <italic>β</italic>-secretase inhibitors <italic>β</italic>Si-II and OM99-2; however, γ-secretase inhibitors (Compound E and DAPT) had no rescue effects on the sporadic AD-iPSC-derived neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C17">17</xref>].</p>
<p>As AD-iPSC-derived neurons can recapitulate pathological features of disease, these cells provide a promising platform for the identification of potential drug targets and further drug development. Drug screening has been carried out in AD-iPSC-derived neurons to search for compounds that can reduce A<italic>β</italic> toxicity-mediated cell death. Accordingly, cyclin-dependent kinase 2 inhibitors were identified as agents that can robustly reduce A<italic>β</italic> neurotoxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C18">18</xref>]. Furthermore, six pharmaceutical compounds were also identified for the ability to lower A<italic>β</italic> production. Among these compounds, a combination of bromocriptine, cromolyn and topiramate showed potent anti-A<italic>β</italic> effects in AD-iPSC-derived neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C49">49</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<label>3.</label>
<title>iPSC-based disease modelling and drug discovery in Parkinson's disease</title>
<p>PD is one of the most common adult-onset neurodegenerative diseases, affecting 1% of people over the age of 60 worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C59">59</xref>]. The core pathology of PD involves selective loss of A9-type dopaminergic neurons that project from the substantia nigra (SN) in the midbrain to the dorsal striatum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C60">60</xref>]. The pathological hallmark of PD is Lewy bodies, which consist of intra-neuronal aggregates of the synaptic protein α-synuclein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C61">61</xref>]. PD clinical manifestations include motor deficits, such as tremor, rigidity, akinesia and postural instability. At present, there is no cure for PD, but dopamine (DA) replacement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C62">62</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C64">64</xref>] or deep brain stimulation may be prescribed for relief of motor symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C65">65</xref>].</p>
<p>Both genetic and environmental factors are likely to be involved in PD pathogenesis. About 10% of PD cases are caused by inherited genetic mutations; most of the responsible genes are involved in regulation of mitochondrial function and oxidative stress, including <italic>SNCA</italic> (α-synuclein) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C29">29</xref>], <italic>PARK2</italic> (Parkin) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C66">66</xref>], <italic>PINK1</italic> (PTEN-induced kinase 1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C67">67</xref>], <italic>PARK7</italic> (protein deglycase DJ-1), <italic>LRRK2</italic> (leucine-rich repeat kinase) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C67">67</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C69">69</xref>] and <italic>ATP13A2</italic> (ATPase type 13A). GWASs have also identified SNPs and triplication of <italic>SNCA</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C70">70</xref>], <italic>LRRK2</italic>, <italic>GBA1</italic> (β-Glucocerebrosidase), <italic>MAPT</italic> (microtubule-associated protein tau) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C59">59</xref>] and <italic>GAK</italic> (cyclin G-associated kinase) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C71">71</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C73">73</xref>] as being highly associated with sporadic PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C75">75</xref>]. Certain environmental factors have also been shown to be associated with PD pathogenesis, including exposures to certain pesticides, herbicides, heavy metals and bacteria. For modelling PD in animals, parkinsonism may be experimentally induced by disrupting mitochondrial function with MPTP (1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C76">76</xref>] or 6-OHDA (6-hydroxydopamine) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C77">77</xref>].</p>
<p>Modelling PD with disease iPSCs has been widely used to explore pathogenesis associated with inherited monogenetic mutations as well as sporadic PD (summary in <xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOB180177TB3">table 3</xref>). <italic>SNCA</italic> encodes α-synuclein and is the first gene that was linked to PD. Although the function of α-synuclein is not well understood, α-synuclein aggregation in Lewy bodies is a major pathological phenotype of PD. <italic>SNCA</italic>(A53T) was shown to be associated with α-synuclein aggregation and Lewy body-like deposition in dopaminergic neurons derived from PD-iPSCs. Moreover, neuronal death was caused by mitochondrial dysfunction due to nitrosative and oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C32">32</xref>]. Triplication of <italic>SNCA</italic> leads to doubling of α-synuclein expression in dopaminergic neurons derived from PD-iPSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C78">78</xref>], and this genetic aberration is linked to cell death with mitochondrial swelling in cortical neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C79">79</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic>SNCA</italic> (A53T and triplication) was associated with ER and nitrosative stress in PD-iPSC-derived cortical neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C29">29</xref>]. Oligomeric α-synuclein was identified in cortical neurons harbouring <italic>SNCA</italic> triplication and was associated with neuronal death. Mechanistically, oligomeric α-synuclein selectively induced oxidation of the ATP synthase β-subunit, leading to permeability transition pore-associated cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C79">79</xref>]. Although the pathological role of α-synuclein structure is contentious, Lewy bodies are known to consist mainly of fibrils and are composed of insoluble α-synuclein β-sheet structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C82">82</xref>]. Autosomal dominant <italic>LRRK2</italic> (leucine-rich repeat kinase 2) encodes a protein containing multiple-functional domains including a protein kinase, GTPase and protein-interacting regions. Mutations in <italic>LRRK2</italic> have been correlated with both familial and sporadic PD. <italic>LRRK2</italic>(G2091S) was associated with upregulation of α-synuclein protein, elevated expression of key oxidative stress-response genes and mitochondrial dysfunction in dopaminergic neurons that were derived from PD-iPSCs. GW50764 (an LRRK2 kinase inhibitor) prevented neuronal cell death, implying that blocking LRRK2 kinase activity may be a valuable drug mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C67">67</xref>]. Moreover, PD-iPSC-derived dopaminergic neurons were sensitive to apoptosis after exposure to stressors including hydrogen peroxidase, MG132 and 6-OHDA. This enhanced sensitivity is consistent with our current understanding of early PD phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C69">69</xref>]. In neural stem cells, <italic>LRRK2</italic>(G2091S) was associated with defective self-renewal and neuronal differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C68">68</xref>]. <italic>LRRK2</italic>(G2091S) was also surprisingly correlated with the disintegration of nuclear envelope, which was associated with ageing in other human diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C83">83</xref>]. This iPSC-based research suggested that the nuclear pore structure may be useful for early diagnosis of PD and could become a therapeutic target. Mitochondrial abnormalities are a commonly studied mechanism of dysfunction in PD research. As such, a recessively inherited early-onset form of PD is caused by a mutation in <italic>PINK1</italic> (PTEN-induced putative kinase 1) encoding a mitochondria-localized kinase, which accumulates on the outer membrane of damaged mitochondria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C84">84</xref>]. Similar to mutations in <italic>LRRK2</italic>, mitochondrial dysfunction was associated with cell death in <italic>PINK1</italic>(Q456X)-carrying dopaminergic neurons. Cell viability could be rescued by antioxidant reagents, coenzyme Q10 and rapamycin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C67">67</xref>]. In dopaminergic neurons with induced ageing by overexpression of progerin (a truncated nuclear envelope protein laminin A), the <italic>PINK1</italic>(Q456X) and <italic>PARK2</italic>(V324A) mutants exhibited neuron-specific neuromelanin accumulation. In the same neurons, other PD-associated phenotypes were recapitulated, such as loss of tyrosine hydroxylase (converts L-tyrosine to L-DOPA), Lewy-body inclusions and enlarged mitochondria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C33">33</xref>]. This report was consistent with the previous findings that impairment of nuclear pore structure is associated with PD, and the overexpression of progerin provides a tool to accelerate the ageing process and study late-onset age-related PD for drug development. Another PD-related gene, <italic>PARK2</italic> (Parkin), is an E3 ubiquitin ligase that targets mitochondria with PINK1 accumulation for degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C84">84</xref>]. Mutations in <italic>PARK2</italic> are associated with an autosomal recessive early-onset familial PD and are correlated to loss tyrosine hydroxylase-positive dopaminergic neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C66">66</xref>]. An exon deletion that results in the loss of Parkin expression leads to increased oxidative stress, reduced DA uptake and increased spontaneous DA release in dopaminergic neurons derived from PD-iPSCs. These observations suggest that Parkin is involved in controlling DA neurotransmission and suppressing DA oxidation in human midbrain dopaminergic neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C80">80</xref>].
<table-wrap id="RSOB180177TB3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Parkinson's disease modelling based on patient iPSCs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gene mutation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">main findings</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">differentiated cell type</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">marker</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">main components</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">days</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">refs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>familial Parkinson's disease</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="6"><italic>SCNA</italic> (A53T)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">decreased α-synuclein ratio of tetramer: monomer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">MAP2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">AA, Dorsomorphin, FGF2, Noggin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Dettmer <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C5">5</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">monomer initiate pathology and further neurotoxity and inclusion</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">nitrosative /oxidative stress caused S-nitrosylation of MEF2C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">DA neuron</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">OTX2, FOXA2, LMX1A, TH, NURR1, GIRK2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">AA, cAMP, BDNF, CHIR99021, DAPT, FGF8, GDNF, LDN193189, Noggin, PMA, SB431542, SHH, TGF-<italic>β</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">Ryan <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C32">32</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">inhibition of MEF2C-PGC1<italic>α</italic> contribute to mitochondria dysfunction and cell death</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">gene-environment interaction(GxE) involved in PD pathogenesis</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">small-molecule high-throughput screening identify MEF2C-PGC1<italic>α</italic> as a therapeutic target</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><italic>SCNA</italic> (A53T or triplication)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">early phenotype: nitrosative and ER stress</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">BDNF, cAMP, GDNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Chung <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C29">29</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">accumulation of ER degradation and the substrate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><italic>SCNA</italic> (triplication)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">upregulated α-synuclein expression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TUJ1, TH, LMX1, NURR1, DAT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AA, BDNF, Dorsomorphin, Dkk1 blocking ab, Noggin, FGF2, GDNF, SB43152, SHH, TGF-β, Wnt1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Devine <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C78">78</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">α-synuclein monomer improves ATP synthase efficiency</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">BDNF, GDNF, LDN, SB431542</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">70–90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Ludtmann <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C79">79</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">oligomers selectively increase oxidation of ATP synthase and mitochondrial lipid peroxidation</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">opening permeability transition pore, mitochondrial swelling and cell death</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><italic>LRRK2</italic> (G2019S)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">upregulation of α-synuclein</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">TH, PITX, FOXA2, NURR1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">AA, BDNF, cAMP, FGF8, GDNF, Noggin, SB431542, TGF-β</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Nguyen <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C69">69</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">elevated stress response induced by hydrogen peroxide</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> sensitive to 6-OHDA, MG132 and hydrogen peroxide</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><italic>LRRK2</italic> (G2019S)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">impairment of nuclear envelop organization</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">NSC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">SOX2, PAX6, Nestin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">AA, BDNF, CHIR99021, Comp. E, cAMP, Dorsomorphin, FGF8, GDNF, LIF, PMA, SB431542, TGF-β</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C68">68</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">defective self-renewal and neuronal differentiation</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">sensitive to MG132 induced cell death</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><italic>LRRK2</italic> (G2019S), <italic>PINK1</italic> (Q456X)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitochondrial dysfunction</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">TH, TUJ1, FOXA2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">AA, BDNF, cAMP, FGF8, GDNF, Enzo, Noggin, Retinoic acid, TGF-β, WNT1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">53</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">Cooper <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C67">67</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cell vulnerabilities</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">reduce cell death by treating antioxidants: coenzyme Q10 and rapamycin,</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">reduce cell death by treating LRRK2 kinase inhibitor GW5074</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>PINK1</italic>(Q456X),</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">progerin induces DA neurons ageing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">TH, TUJ1, mAP2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">BDNF, CHIR99021, cAMP, DAPT, FGF8, GDNF, LDN193189, Noggin, PMA, SB431542, SHH, TGF-β</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">20–32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Miller <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C33">33</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><italic>PARK2</italic> (V324A)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">dendrite degeneration, loss of TH cells</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lewy-body precursor</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><italic>PARK2</italic> (R42P, exon 3 deletion, exon 3,4 deletion, R275 W)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">reduced capability of differentiation into DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">TH, TUJ1, FOXA2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">BDNF, cAMP, FGF2, FGF8, GDNF, LIF, SHH, TGF-<italic>β</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Shaltouki <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C66">66</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">altered mitochondrial: cell volume fraction</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><italic>PARK2</italic> (exon3,5 deletion or exon3 deletion)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">enhanced oxidative stress</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">TH, EN-1, FOXA2, DAT, VMAT2, NR1, MAP2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">AA, BDNF, cAMP, FGF2, FGF8, GDNF, Noggin, SB431542, TGF-β, SHH</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C80">80</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">increased dopamine release</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">decreased dopamine uptake</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>sporadic Parkinson's disease</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>SCNA</italic> (SNPs)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">brain specific transcription factors, EMX2 and NKX6-1, regulated expression of <italic>SCNA</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TUJ1, MAP2, TH, NeuN, GFAP, vGlut1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AA, Dorsomorphin, FGF2, Noggin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25–31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Soldner <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C70">70</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><italic>GBA</italic> (N370S and L444P)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">elevated α-synuclein expression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">TH, MAP2, TUJ1,</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">BDNF, CHIR99021, cAMP, DAPT, FGF8, GDNF, LDN193189, Noggin, PMA, SB431542, SHH, TGF-β</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">Woodard <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C72">72</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">decreased glucocerebrosidase activity</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">lower dopamine level, increased monoamine oxidase B (MAO-B) expression</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">overexpression of wild-type GBA and MAO-B inhibitors are potential treatment</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><italic>GBA1</italic> (N370S)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">decreased glucocerebrosidase activity and protein</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">TH, TUJ1, FOXA2, NURR1, GIRK2, VMAT2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">AA, BDNF, cAMP, CHIR99021, DAPT, FGF8, GDNF, LDN193189, PMA, SB431542, SHH, TGF-<italic>β</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">20–34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Schondorf <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C71">71</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">associated with autophagic and lysosomal defects</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cell death associated with increased neuronal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding protein 2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T lymphocytes induce cell death through IL-17R and NF-κB activation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">DA neuron</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">TH, TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">AA, CHIR99021, cAMP, FGF8, GDNF, LDN193189, PMA, SB431542, TGF-β</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Sommer <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C81">81</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IL-17 antibody, secukinumab, rescued neuron death</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>cell replacement therapy in Parkinson's disease based on human iPSC</bold></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>models</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>main findings</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>cell types</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>marker</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>main components</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>days</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>refs</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">rat</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">transplantation method for DA neurons in striatum of PD rat without damaged host striatum</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">DA neuron</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">transplantation: NCAM, TH, TUJ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">AA, BDNF, cAMP, FGF8, GDNF, SHH, TGF-<italic>β</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Hargus <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C62">62</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">transplanted DA neurons containing long term survival</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">graft validation: TH, NCAM, GIRK2, L1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DA neurons projected into host striatum</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">primate (<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">improve movement after transplanted CORIN<sup>+</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">DA progenitor/DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">transplantation: CORIN</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">AA, A83-01, BDNF, cAMP, CHIR99021, LDN193189, GDNF, PMA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">Kikuchi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C63">63</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">extended DA neuron neurites in host striatum</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">graft validation: FOXA2, NURR1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">various neuron grafted and survival rates in host</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">no tumour formation from CORIN sorted cells for 2 years' study</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">monkey</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">improved motor behaviour after transplantation with LRTM1<sup>+</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">DA progenitor/DA neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">transplantation: LRTM1, FOXA2, LMX1A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">A83-01, CHIR99021, FGF8, LDN193189, PMA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">Samata <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C64">64</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">DA neuron survival; no tumour formation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Graft validation:</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GIRK2, NURR1, TH</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>NSC, neuron stem cell; DA neurons, dopaminergic neurons; TH, tyrosine hydroxylase; A83-01, TGF<italic>β</italic> kinase/activing receptor-like kinase (ALK 5) inhibitor; Enzo: Smoothened agonist; SHH, Sonic Hedgehog; 6-OHDA, 6-hydroxydopamine; AA, ascorbic acid; PMA, purmorphamine.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p>Apart from monogenic inherited PD, several genes have been identified as risk factors for sporadic PD<italic>.</italic> Mutated <italic>GBA1</italic> is a well-validated risk factor for PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C85">85</xref>]. <italic>GBA1</italic> encodes the lysosomal enzyme β-glucocerebrosidase, which is involved in glycolipid metabolism. Mutations in <italic>GBA1</italic> (N370S and L444P) were correlated to lowered β-glucocerebrosidase activity and α-synuclein accumulation in dopaminergic neurons derived from PD-iPSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C72">72</xref>]. The substrate of β-glucocerebrosidase, glucosylceramide, was accumulated in cells with either <italic>GBA1</italic> mutations or defects in autophagic and lysosomal machinery. In <italic>GBA1</italic>(N370S)-carrying dopaminergic neurons, DA synthesis and release were reduced. Monoamine oxidase B (MAO-B) expression was upregulated, and the inhibitor, rasagiline, rescued DA regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C72">72</xref>]. Moreover, <italic>NECAB2</italic> (neuronal calcium-binding protein 2) was increased, causing the dysregulation of neuronal calcium homeostasis and increasing the vulnerability of cells to stress from cytosolic calcium elevation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C72">72</xref>]. In an iPSC-based platform, MAO-B inhibitors or overexpression of wild-type <italic>GBA1</italic> were shown to be potential therapeutic strategies for PD treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C72">72</xref>]. Recently, the adaptive immune system was suggested to be associated with PD after researchers detected higher Th17 frequency in blood and upregulated T lymphocytes in post-mortem tissues. In co-culture with activated T lymphocytes, cell death was induced via upregulation of IL-17 receptor and NF-κB activation in dopaminergic neurons derived from sporadic PD-iPSCs. Blockade of IL-17 by the IL-17 antibody, secukinumab, provided a potential method for rescue of neuronal cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C81">81</xref>].</p>
<p>Disease modelling with 2D iPSC-derived cultures may not be ideal due to a lack of complexity and neuronal immaturity, which are especially disadvantageous for modelling adult-onset sporadic diseases. Recently developed methods to generate brain organoids may help to create complex 3D models of midbrain tissue from iPSCs. These midbrain organoids are attractive models for mechanistic studies and drug discovery for PD due to the inclusion of well-characterized neurons, astroglia and oligodendrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C86">86</xref>]. Indeed, the genetic signatures of the brain and intestinal organoids derived from PD-iPSCs carrying the <italic>LRRK2</italic>(G2019S) mutation were altered compared to controls. Although further work is needed to elucidate the molecular pathology caused by the PD-associated mutations, these studies demonstrate the utility of the 3D organoid platform for PD research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C87">87</xref>]. 3D brain or midbrain organoids will allow the exploration of multiple factors that contribute to PD and broaden the potential targets for drug development to neuron-adjacent cells.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<label>4.</label>
<title>iPSC-based disease modelling and drug discovery in Huntington's disease</title>
<p>HD is an autosomal dominant, fatal, progressive neurodegenerative disorder which is monogenic with exonic CAG repeat in the huntingtin (<italic>HTT</italic>) gene. The expanded CAG repeat encodes a polyglutamine tract that causes a toxic gain of function and leads to preferential death of GABAergic projection neurons in the striatum. Typically, HD symptoms typically manifest in midlife with motor deficits. Healthy individuals have an average number of CAG repeats ranging from 10 to 35, and HD patients have 36 or more expanded CAGs. Notably, CAG repeat length is highly correlated to disease severity and the onset age. Most importantly, there is no cure for HD, and the only treatments available are for the management of symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C88">88</xref>].</p>
<p>Since striatal medium spiny neurons (MSNs) are the major susceptible cell type in HD, many differentiation protocols have been developed to generate MSNs from hESCs and human iPSCs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOB180177TB4">table 4</xref>). Although it is now possible to derive highly enriched MSNs from HD patient-derived iPSCs for disease modelling, the recapitulation of HD-relevant phenotypes, including neuronal degeneration and aggregation of mutant huntingtin (mHtt) protein in HD-iPSC-derived neurons often requires the addition of other cellular stressors. For example, it has been shown that HD-iPSC-derived MSNs cultured <italic>in vitro</italic> have elevated levels of caspase activity upon growth factor withdrawal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C91">91</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C95">95</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C96">96</xref>], hydrogen peroxide treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C89">89</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C90">90</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C95">95</xref>] or glutamate stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C95">95</xref>]. Moreover, the formation of mHtt aggregates in the HD-iPSC-derived neurons is rare. So far, only a few studies have indicated that EM48-positive mHtt aggregation can be detected in long-term cultured HD-iPSC-derived neurons with the treatment of the proteasome inhibitor, MG132 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C90">90</xref>], or in the HD-NPCs engrafted into neonatal rat brains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C6">6</xref>].
<table-wrap id="RSOB180177TB4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Differentiation protocols for HD relevant neurons.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAG repeat length</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">differentiated cell type</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">markers</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">differentiation duration</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">patterning factor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">stressor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">main finding</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">compound testing</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">refs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1"><bold>HD iPSC-derived striatal neurons</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">MSNs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">TUJ1/MAP2, GABA, GAD65, Calbindin, or DARPP32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">16 weeks</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">N2B27 media with bFGF→B27 media</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">hydrogen peroxide</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced more DNA damage and cell death in HD-MSNs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">A<sub>2A</sub>R antagonist: SCH5826; PKA inhibitor: H-89</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Chiu <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C89">89</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> protective effect via A<sub>2A</sub>R antagonist</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">40, 42, 47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">GABA MSN-like neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">TUJ1, GAT1, or DARPP32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">40–80 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">B27 media with BDNF, Forskolin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">proteasome inhibitor (MG132)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MG132 induced more EM48<sup>+</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Quinazoline derivative: EVP4593</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Nekrasov <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C90">90</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">enhanced SOC activity in HD-MSNs and reduced by EVP4593</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28, 33, 60, 180</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">striatal neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TUJ1, MAP2, GABA, DARPP32, Bcl11B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NIM with SHH, DKK1, BDNF→NIM with cAMP, Valproic acid, BDNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hydrogen peroxide; autophagy inhibitor (3-MA); glutamate; BDNF withdrawal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">increased striatal neurons death</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HD-iPSC Consortium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C28">28</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4">72</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HD-NSCs and striatal neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TUJ1, GABA, Calbindin, DARPP32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NDM with SHH, DKK1, BDNF, Y27632→ NDM with cAMP, Valpromide, BDNF, Y27632</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">growth factor withdrawal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">enhanced capase3/7 activity in HD-NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C91">91</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">HD-NSCs and MSNs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">TUJ1, GABA, Calbindin, DARPP32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">NDM with SHH, DKK1, BDNF, Y27632→ NDM with cAMP, Valpromide, BDNF, Y27632</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">growth factor withdrawal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">more vulnerable to cell death in HD-NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">An <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C92">92</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">elevated capase3/7 activity</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">decreased mitochondrial bioenergetics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">72</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">MSNs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">DARPP32, GSH-2, DLX2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">N2 media with bFGF→N2 media with BDNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">proteasome inhibitor (MG132)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MG132 induced more EM48+ cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Jeon <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C6">6</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell engrafted into neonatal brain after 33 weeks post-transplantation</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1"><bold>HD iPSC-derived astrocytes</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50, 109</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">astrocyte</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GFAP, s100<italic>β</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11–16 weeks</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">astrocyte medium (ScienCell)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">time-dependent cytoplasmic vacuolation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Juopperi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C93">93</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">astrocyte</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GFAP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 weeks</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N2B27 media with bFGF→N2B27 medium with ciliary neurotrophic factor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">proinflammtory cytokines</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytokine-induced iNOS protected by Xpro1595 (TNF-α inhibitor)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Xpro1595</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hsiao <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C94">94</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>NDM, neural differentation media. NIM, neural induction media.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p>The recent advance of genome editing technology provides an excellent opportunity to create isogenic HD-iPSC pairs for better <italic>in vitro</italic> HD modelling via correction of the CAG locus in the <italic>HTT</italic> gene of HD-iPSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C92">92</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C97">97</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C98">98</xref>]. An <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C92">92</xref>] were the first to generate genetically corrected isogenic HD-iPSC clones by homologous recombination. The neurons derived from the isogenic line showed rescue of disease phenotypes, including cell death and mitochondrial abnormalities caused by trophic factor withdrawal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C92">92</xref>]. Using CRISPR/Cas9 technology, genetically corrected isogenic lines were also generated for <italic>in vitro</italic> neuronal induction. Xu <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C98">98</xref>] used neuronal progenitor cells derived from HD patients, isogenic controls and non-related healthy controls to show that differential gene expression levels caused by genetic background variation were eliminated by using isogenic iPSCs as controls. Among the genes identified in this study, HD-iPSCs carrying CAG<sub>180</sub> exhibited dysregulation of <italic>CHCHD2</italic>, a genetic risk factor associated with mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation in late-onset PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C99">99</xref>]. This result suggests that isogenic lines can provide specific controls for studying disease mechanisms and exploring new phenotypes.</p>
<p>Use of cell-based therapy in HD rodent models revealed that motor deficits could be rescued by transplanting human iPSC-derived neural stem cells, but the treatment did not improve striatum function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C92">92</xref>]. These results indicate that grafted cells were not sufficiently functional as MSNs, or that other types of cells (e.g. striatal interneurons or non-neuronal cells) were required for optimum functional recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C92">92</xref>]. Glial dysfunction and pathology have been implicated in the pathogenesis of neurodegenerative diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C94">94</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C100">100</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C102">102</xref>]. In HD, glial pathology was shown to be associated with striatal neuron dysfunction and other disease phenotypes. In rodent models, striatal transplantation of glia functioned to reduce disease phenotypes, including improving behavioural outcomes, restoring interstitial potassium homeostasis, slowing disease progression and extending lifespan. These results suggest a functional role of glia in HD, implying the potentials for iPSC-based glial replacement therapies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C102">102</xref>]. Thus, we provide a summary of protocols for iPSC differentiation into HD-relevant cells, including MSNs and astrocytes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOB180177TB4">table 4</xref>).</p>
<p>Several studies have used iPSC-derived neurons to investigate HD-associated pathogenesis and identify effective therapeutic strategies or chemical compounds. DNA damage, including damage response and repair machinery, was shown to be involved in HD pathogenesis. ATM-p53 signalling was enhanced by phosphorylation of p53 and H<sub>2</sub>AX in HD-iPSC-derived neurons. Accordingly, neocarzinostatin treatment improved cell viability through activating DNA damage repair pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C103">103</xref>]. Chiu <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C89">89</xref>] showed activation of the A<sub>2</sub>AR-PKA pathway protected HD-iPSC-derived MSNs from oxidative stress-induced DNA damage and cell death. In addition, microglia exhibited proinflammatory gene expression in HD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C104">104</xref>], suggesting inflammatory processes may be associated with HD pathology. In co-cultured MSNs and astrocytes, both derived from HD-iPSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C93">93</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C94">94</xref>], MSN death was reduced after treatment with a TNF-α inhibitor, Xpro1595. This result suggests that reducing cytokine-induced iNOS expression in astrocytes can reduce HD phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C94">94</xref>]. Store-operated channel (SOC) was associated with calcium influx in HD-iPSC-derived MSNs, and an NF-κB inhibitor effectively decreased SOC-mediated calcium entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C90">90</xref>]. Moreover, inhibitors in the forms of microRNAs and peptides have been explored as therapeutic strategies for HD. The miR196a reduced mHtt aggregation through mediating the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C105">105</xref>], while P110-TAT, a peptide inhibitor of dynamin-related protein (Drp1), reduced HD phenotypes, including excessive mitochondrial fission and cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C106">106</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5">
<label>5.</label>
<title>Modelling neurodegenerative diseases with three-dimensional brain organoids</title>
<p>2D culture systems have been widely used as human cell-based platforms for modelling neurodegenerative disease, and these models have been useful for the discovery of potential treatments. However, 2D culture systems are not suitable to mimic the intricately structured <italic>in vivo</italic> environment. Therefore, 3D culture systems have become valuable tissue models, which include extracellular matrix and cell–cell interactions that are necessary for proper differentiation, proliferation and cell-based functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C107">107</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C108">108</xref>]. Hence, human iPSCs grown in a 3D culture system represents a straightforward substrate for fundamental studies on the pathophysiology of human neurodegenerative disease.</p>
<p>PSCs have the capacity for self-organization and can develop into 3D structures resembling mini-organs, including the cerebral cortex. ESCs and iPSCs both exhibit the capability of developing through self-regulated processes into cortical neuroepithelial structures with multilayered neuroepithelium that resembles the progenitor zones of the embryonic cortex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C109">109</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C110">110</xref>]. Therefore, this culture system is rapidly becoming an important platform for modelling human cortical development and neurodegenerative disease. However, these self-organizing cerebral spheres still lack essential developmental and patterning cues to develop into fully formed and mature organs. Thus, strategies are under development to identify and provide appropriate physico-chemical cues for transforming brain organoids into the same tissue patterns as occur <italic>in vivo</italic>. For example, cells have been embedded in scaffolding materials such as matrigel, self-assembling peptide (SAP) matrix and PNIPAAm-PEG hydrogel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C86">86</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C87">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C111">111</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C119">119</xref>]. To increase oxygen uptake, culture conditions and vessels have been adjusted, including raising the oxygen percentage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C116">116</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C120">120</xref>], use of a culture shaker, and growth of cultures in a spinning bioreactor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C86">86</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C87">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C112">112</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C113">113</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C115">115</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C121">121</xref>]. Therefore, a growing number of protocols has been developed for generating cortex-like tissue <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOB180177TB5">table 5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="RSOB180177TB5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Human iPSC-derived 3D neural models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">brain region in organoid</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">starting cells</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">patterning factor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">extracellular scaffold</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">device/ bioreactor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">days</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">main finding</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">refs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cerebral cortex organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hiPSC-derived NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DKK1, BMPRIA-Fc, SB431542</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Matrigel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">approximately 50 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">polarized radial glia, intermediate progenitor, and spectrum of layer-specific cortical neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mariani <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C114">114</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cerebral organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESC/hiPSC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">insulin, vitamin A, Retinoic acid</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Matrigel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">spinning bioreactor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 months (survived for 10 months)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">well-organized progenitor zone surrounded with outer radial glial stem cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lancaster <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cerebral cortex organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hiPSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">FGF2, EGF, BDNF, NT3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">180 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">laminated cerebral cortex-like structure contain deep and superficial cortical layers and functional neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pasca <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C122">122</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">forebrain, midbrain and hypothalamic organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">hiPSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>forebrain organoids</bold>: AA, BDNF, GDNF, TFG-<italic>β</italic>, cAMP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">mini-spinning bioreactor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>forebrain</bold>: &gt;80 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>forebrain organoids</bold>: progenitor zone, neurogenesis, human specific outer radial glia layer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Qian <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C121">121</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>midbrain organoids</bold>: SHH, LDN-193189, CHIR99021, PUR, FGF-8, BDNF, GDNF, AA, TFG-b, cAMP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>midbrain</bold>: 75 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>midbrain organoids</bold>: TH<sup>+</sup> neurons co-expressing dopaminergic neuron markers (FOXG2, DAT, NURR1, PITX3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>hypothalamic organoids</bold>: Wnt-3A, SHH, PUR, FGF-2, CTNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>hypothalamus</bold>: 40 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>hypothalamic organoids</bold>: peptidergic neuronal markers (POMC, VIP, OXT, NPY, OTP)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">forebrain organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hiPSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cAMP, insulin, BDNF, GDNF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BME matrix</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">rocking cell culture shaker</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">forebrain-like structure: ventricular zone, inner and outer subventricular zone, cortical plate-like area</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Krefft <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C119">119</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">midbrain organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hiPSC-derived NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BDNF, GDNF, db-cAMP, AA, TFG-<italic>β</italic>, PUR</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BD Matrigel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">orbital shaker</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">approximately 60 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">structure organized, dopaminergic neurons, astroglial (4%) and oligodendrocute (29.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monzel <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C86">86</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">midbrain organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">hPSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">SB431542, Noggin, CHIR99021; SHH, FGF8; BDNF, GDNF, AA, db-cAMP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">BD Matrigel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">orbital shaker</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">65–84 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">functional dopaminergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jo <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C123">123</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">substantia nigra-like tissue (neuromelanin-like granules)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3D nigrostriatal dopaminergic neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hiPSC-derived NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AA, BDNF, GDNF, TGF-<italic>β</italic>3, cAMP, PMA,</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BD Matrigel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">microfluidic bioreactor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">electrophysiologically active dopaminiergic neurons; 19% of tryosine hroxylase-positive neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moreno <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C115">115</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3D striatal neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hESC/hiPSC-derived striatal NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DKK-1, PUR, BDNF, GDNF, cAMP, IGF-1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PNIPAAm-PEG hydrogel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">functional striatal neurons; cell population diversity: 43% DARPP32 neurons and 27% glial; Transplantation 3D-derived striatal progenotor into HD mice improved motor coordination and increased survival</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adil <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C111">111</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>PUR, purmophamine; AA, ascorbic acid; PMA, phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p>Human iPSCs showed the capability of developing into a dorsal telencephalon-like structure through self-organized 3D cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C114">114</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C124">124</xref>]. Lancaster <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C15">15</xref>] used a spinning bioreactor to improve diffusion of oxygen and nutrient supply to the spheroids, meanwhile promoting non-neural cell production without neuroectoderm formation by blocking TGF-ß and BMP pathways. These cerebral cortex organoids recapitulated features of human cortical development including characteristic progenitor zone organization with abundant outer radial glial stem cells. Pasca <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C122">122</xref>] expanded self-organized cortical spheroids that contained astrocytes surrounding electrophysiologically matured and functional neuronal synapses. Furthermore, defined culture conditions were used to generate forebrain, midbrain and hypothalamic organoids in a spinning bioreactor. Human iPSC-derived brain organoids recapitulated human-specific outer radial glia cell layers in cortical development and other key features, including progenitor zone organization, neurogenesis and gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C121">121</xref>]. Moreover, Jo <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C123">123</xref>] generated 3D ventral midbrain-like organoids that contain functional midbrain dopaminergic neurons and neuromelanin granule, similar to human substantia nigra tissue. Thus, 3D neural organoids faithfully mimic the basic processes of brain development and functional patterning of brain regions, providing a highly advantageous model for studying human neurodegenerative diseases or other neurological disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C34">34</xref>].</p>
<p>It is clear that iPSC-derived spheroids or organoids could recapitulate neurodevelopmental processes, potentially allowing the investigation of developmental disorders related to the human cerebral cortex (<xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOB180177TB6">table 6</xref>). Recently, patient-derived iPSCs carrying a <italic>CDK5RAP2</italic> mutation were used by Lancaster <italic>et al</italic>. to successfully model primary microcephaly in 3D cerebral organoids; the cultures recapitulated premature neural differentiation and decreased numbers of radial glial cells, producing overall smaller organoids than wild-type controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C15">15</xref>]. This study provided a striking example of modelling neurodevelopmental disorders in human cell culture systems, which have not been successfully recapitulated in mouse models. Miller–Dieker syndrome (MDS), a brain malformation (lissencephaly) syndrome, is a contiguous gene deletion of chromosome 17p13.3 involving the <italic>LIS1</italic> and/or <italic>YWHAE</italic> genes (coding for 14.3.3<italic>ɛ</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C127">127</xref>]. MDS-iPSC-derived organoids mimicked brain malformations with a smaller size, which was likely caused by premature neurogenesis and alterations of cortical niche architecture. Based on this model system, the authors further discovered that the LIS1/NDEL1/14.3.3<italic>ɛ</italic> complex was associated with cortical niche architecture and the deletion leads to non-cell-autonomous disturbance of β-catenin signalling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C113">113</xref>]. Models of idiopathic autism spectrum disorder (ASD) based on patient-derived iPSCs revealed that the ASD organoids recapitulated human first-trimester telencephalic development, but with over-production of neuronal progenitors due to a shorter cell cycle length. Also, the production of GABAergic neurons was induced due to increased expression of FOXG1, a transcription factor involved in early cortical neuron production and associated with prenatal microcephaly of some ASDs subtype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C125">125</xref>]. Furthermore, Srikanth <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C117">117</xref>] modelled a neuropsychiatric disease using DISC1-disrupted iPSCs to generate cerebral organoids. DISC1-mutant cerebral organoids display disorganized structural morphology and impaired proliferation. The authors further reported that DISC1 isoforms were associated with elevation of baseline WNT signalling in NPCs, which resulted in morphological and neurodevelopmental consequences through alterations in cell fate and progenitor migration. Recently, Zika virus was linked to infants born with microcephaly. Human brain organoids showed Zika virus affected neural stem cells, and pure forebrain organoids showed Zika virus affected cell proliferation in the ventricular zone. These findings supported the notion that the pathogen directly affects fetal brain development processes and suggested that Zika virus may be involved in apoptosis of neuron progenitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C128">128</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C129">129</xref>].
<table-wrap id="RSOB180177TB6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>Modelling neurological disorder with 3D brain organoids derived from disease iPSCs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3D brain-like tissue</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">model disease</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">gene mutation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">starting cells</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">patterning factor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">extracellular scaffold</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">bioreactor/oxygen</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">differentiation period</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">main finding</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">refs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1"><bold>neurodevelopmental disorder</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">forebrain organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">sever microcephaly (MCPH)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><italic>CDK5RAP2</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">MCPH-iPSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">AA, BDNF, GDNF, TGF-<italic>β</italic>, cAMP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">mini-spinning bioreactor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">2 months</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCPH-forebrain organoids: premature neural differentiation (only occasional neuroepithelial region)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Lancaster <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">decreased numbers of radial glia</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">telencephalic organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">autism spectrum disorder (ASD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">idiopathic ASD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">ASD-iPSC-derived NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">DKK1 BMPRIA-Fc, SB431542</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Matrigel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">ultralow-attachment plates</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">4–5 weeks</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ASD-cortical organoids reflect human midfetal telencephalic development</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Mariani <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C125">125</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">accelerated cell cycle; Overproduction GABAergic inhibitory neurons cause by increased FOXG1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">forebrain organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Miller–Dieker syndrome (MDS)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><italic>LIS1, YWHAE</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">MDS-iPSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">A83, LDN, IWR-1, CHIR99021</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">BME matrix</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">rocking cell culture shaker</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">35 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MSD-forebrain organoids: reduced expansion rate caused by premature neurogenesis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Iefremova <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C113">113</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">cortical niche alterations architecture leading to a non-cell-autonomous disturbance of <italic>β</italic>-catenin signalling</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">cerebral organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">neuro-psychiatric disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><italic>DISC1</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">DISC1-disrupted-iPSC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">XAV939, CHIR99021</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Matrigel droplets</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">ultralow-attachment plates</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">19 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DISC1-disrupted cerebral organoids: disorganized structure morphology and impaired proliferation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Srikanth <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C117">117</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">rescued with a WNT antagonist</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1"><bold>neurodegenerative disease</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">hiPSC-derived 3D neural tissue</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A<italic>β</italic> oligomer added</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">iPSC-derived NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SHH, FGF8, NGF, BMP9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAP matrix</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">poly-L-ornithine-Laminin coated dish</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p21-activated kinase mediated A<italic>β</italic> oligomers sensing and connected to AD processes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C118">118</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AD-iPSC-derived 3D neuro-spheroids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">sporadic AD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AD-iPSC-derived NSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">dorsomorphin, SB431542, FGF2, EGF, BDNF, NT3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ultralow-attachment plates</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 weeks</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BACE1 or γ-secretase inhibitors showed less effects on A<italic>β</italic> production in 3D neuro-spheroids than 2D neurons</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lee <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C126">126</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">AD-iPSC-derived 3D neural tissue</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">AD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><italic>APP</italic> duplication, <italic>PSEN1</italic> (M146 L), <italic>PSEN1</italic> (A246E)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">AD-iPSCs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">A83, LDN, bFGF, EGF, BDNF, NT3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Matrigel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">non-adherent Petri-dish; 40% O2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">90 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">recapitulate AD-like pathologies (A<italic>β</italic> aggregation, hyperphosphorylated tau protein, endosome abnormalities)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">Raja <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C116">116</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">reduction of amyloid and tau pathology treated with β- and γ-secretase inhibitors</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">fPD-iPSC-derived 3D neurospheroids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">fPD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>LRRK2</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">fPD-iPSC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">bFGF, EGF, LIF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ultralow-attachment plates</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">changes of gene expression in synaptic transmission, Toll-like receptor signalling pathways and neurotransmitter level regulation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Son <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C87">87</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">HD-iPSC-derived cortical organoids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">HD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><italic>mHtt</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">HD-iPSC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">retinoic acid</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Matrigel droplets</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">orbital shaker</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">105 days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HD organoids: abnormality in neural rosette formation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3">Conforti <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C112">112</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">disrupted cytoarchitecture in cortical organoids</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">the impairment can be rescued by molecular and pharmacological approaches</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AA, ascorbic acid; LDN, LDN193189; SAP matrix, self-assembling peptide matrix.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p>Brain organoids show faithful recapitulation of brain development and organization of functional cells. These highly complex and dynamic 3D networks among neurons and glia also provide a means to further understand neurodegenerative disorders from a more systemic view. As previously noted, additional cellular insults are often required to generate disease-relevant phenotypes while modelling with iPSC-derived neurons. Currently, explorations into the modelling of neurodegenerative disorder phenotypes using 3D organoids for therapeutic development are becoming increasingly prevalent.</p>
<p>For recapitulating AD pathology, 3D culture systems were shown to exhibit extracellular deposition of A<italic>β</italic> and increased pTau level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C116">116</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C118">118</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C126">126</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C130">130</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C131">131</xref>]. Using genetically modified immortalized hNPCs with familial AD mutations (<italic>APP</italic> and <italic>PSEN1</italic>), the aforementioned phenotypes were shown along with higher expression of four-repeat adult Tau (4R Tau) isoforms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C130">130</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C131">131</xref>]. Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C118">118</xref>] used a 3D hydrogel-based culture system to shorten the time necessary of generating functional neurons and applied treatments to diminish A<italic>β</italic> oligomer production in AD organoids. In addition, 3D organoids have been used to reveal new disease phenotypes as well as AD pathology. For example, Raja <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C116">116</xref>] identified endosome abnormalities associated with different mutations in <italic>APP</italic> (duplication) or <italic>PSEN1</italic> (M146 L, A246E) by using AD-iPSC-derived brain organoids. Finally, using iPSCs derived from sporadic AD patients, Lee <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C126">126</xref>] recapitulated both A<italic>β</italic> and pTau pathology with NPC-derived 3D neurospheroids.</p>
<p>3D organoids also exhibit certain phenotypes, which are not observed in 2D culture systems. In HD-iPSC-derived brain organoids, the length of CAG repeat was associated with neural differentiation capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C112">112</xref>]. The HD-iPSCs carrying longer CAG repeats (Q109 and Q180) exhibited complete failure of neuroectodermal acquisition; however, shorter CAG repeats (Q60) showed milder abnormalities in neural rosette formation and disrupted cytoarchitecture in cortical organoids. These findings were not observed in 2D culture systems and suggest that 3D culture conditions can accelerate neuronal maturation and recapitulate disease pathogenesis. From this handful of studies using a 3D culture system for modelling neurological diseases, one can easily see that this platform holds immense opportunities and the potential for studying human-specific neurological diseases. However, it should be borne in mind that certain limitations will continue to hamper the study of all neuropathologies, and especially adult-onset diseases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s6">
<label>6.</label>
<title>The applications and challenges of iPSC-derived three-dimensional cultures</title>
<p>The self-organization of brain organoids without embryonic surroundings allows researchers to inspect neurodevelopmental process. Current models have clearly demonstrated that exogenous cues are essential for organoids to develop into well-patterned mature brains. Also, variability in quality and brain regions are important issues for disease modelling and drug testing. For modelling of adult-onset diseases, immature structures or neuron-only organoids may not be sufficient to reflect complex neurobiological processes and drug effects. These factors will impact test results from the laboratory to the clinic. Therefore, robust and mature 3D organ culture models will help to accelerate neurological research and neuropharmaceutical development.</p>
<p>3D neuronal organoids allow penetration of small molecules and sufficient oxygen and nutrient supply that are essential for the survival of the innermost cells. Thus, the 3D-iPSC model enables researchers to analyse molecular and pharmacological effects in a complex tissue system. Taking AD as an example, the different culture systems show different responses to test compounds. For example, in an AD patient iPSC-derived 3D culture system, amyloid and Tau pathology were significantly reduced after treatment with β- and γ-secretase inhibitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C116">116</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C126">126</xref>]; however, Lee <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C126">126</xref>] indicated that β- and γ-secretase inhibitors work more effectively in decreasing A<italic>β</italic> levels in AD-NPCs-derived 2D neurons than in 3D spheroids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C132">132</xref>]. Additionally, it was shown that p21-activated kinase was associated with A<italic>β</italic> oligomer-mediated AD pathogenesis in the 3D organoids, which was not observed in 2D culture-derived neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C118">118</xref>]. Potentially, drug responses and pathogenesis may vary according to the cell population and environment that is present, suggesting the 3D culture systems may more reliably reflect the conditions in patient brains. Moreover, the pathogenesis of adult-onset neurodegenerative diseases is generally considered to result from long-term chronic exposure to neurotoxicants. The cells in 3D-cultured organoids are viable for much longer times than 2D-cultured neurons, as long as nutrients and oxygen are efficiently supplied. Therefore, the 3D culture system provides an exciting platform for exploring pathogenesis caused by long-term neurotoxicant exposure and chronic cellular response. Smirnova <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C133">133</xref>] administered neurotoxicants (MPP<sup>+</sup> and rotenone) to dopaminergic neurons in 3D neuronal models derived from PD-iPSCs, and reported that dopaminergic neurons responded to toxicant exposure by upregulating one-carbon metabolism, transsulfuration pathways (ASS1, CTH and SHTM2) and α-synuclein associated microRNAs. This report provided a pioneering example of using a human cell model for investigating neurotoxicology and sporadic PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C133">133</xref>]. 3D-iPSC models provide a more realistic platform to investigate neurodevelopment and neurological disorders, providing an excellent multifaceted system with which to investigate chronic effects of drug treatment.</p>
<p>Despite the great potential of 3D organoids, low numbers of non-neuronal cells and lack of vascularization may limit their utility. The interaction between non-neuronal cell populations and neuronal function has become one of the most important features that can be modelled by 3D cerebral organoids. For example, the neuronal function was characterized by synaptic connections and electrophysiological activity in midbrain organoids, which contained organized dopaminergic neurons, astroglia (4%) and oligodendrocytes (29.6%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C86">86</xref>]. Likewise, striatal neurons fired action potentials in Hydrogel-embedded 3D culture systems that contained 27% glia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C86">86</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C111">111</xref>]. In a mouse model of HD, motor coordination and lifespan were improved after transplantation with 3D striatal progenitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C111">111</xref>]. Pasca <italic>et al</italic>. also indicated that neuronal synapse function was improved when surrounded by astrocytes (approx. 20%) in cortical spheroids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C122">122</xref>]. The complexity of the extracellular environment in 3D culture systems presents a relatively realistic platform for studying neurobiology and neurological diseases. Additionally, the vasculature is not present in the early developing neocortex ahead of blood vessel invasion; however, vascularization is essential for neuronal progenitor differentiation in the subventricular zone during late development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C134">134</xref>]. This limitation also hampers PD modelling because degeneration of nigrostriatal projection neurons is the primary cause of PD symptoms, and vascularization would be an essential first step to begin the enormous task of rebuilding a functional nigrostriatal circuit in a culture setting. Strategies such as building a vascular microenvironment by microfluidic chambers have been developed to address the lack of vascularization, further mimicking the physiological niche for neurogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C135">135</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C137">137</xref>]. In the tissue scaffold, pre-capillary networks were built by co-culture of pericytes and early vascular cells derived from hPSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C138">138</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C139">139</xref>]. This approach was able to facilitate the generation of physiologically relevant vascular networks for neurogenesis. Thus, perfusion-based human iPSC-derived 3D brain organoid platforms represent increasingly realistic <italic>in vitro</italic> models for neurodegenerative diseases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s7">
<label>7.</label>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Accumulating evidence demonstrates that human iPSCs can be used as a reliable basis for the generation of disease-relevant cell types to explore the mechanisms underlying human disease. Through continuous propagation and efficient differentiation of patient-derived iPSCs into specific neuronal subtypes and 3D organoids, we are now able to better recapitulate the cellular progression toward neurodegeneration <italic>in vitro</italic>. This capability allows researchers to discover new methods to manipulate iPSC-derived neurons, uncovering novel disease phenotypes <italic>in vitro</italic> in the hope of eventually identifying novel clinical interventions. For example, age and disease-associated phenotypes can be recapitulated by progerin impairment, and this accelerated ageing may be used in combination with PD-iPSC-derived neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C33">33</xref>]. The shortening of telomeres is a typical feature of ageing, which can be induced by overexpression of progerin in neurons, helping to drive the development of PD phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C33">33</xref>]. This discovery suggests that ageing-accelerated disease modelling may be applicable in several neurodegenerative diseases, including AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C140">140</xref>], PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C141">141</xref>] and HD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C83">83</xref>]. Since impairment of nuclear pore structures has been identified in all of the aforementioned diseases, researchers should be aware of which cellular consequences stem from progerin overexpression and which are specifically related to the disease. In addition, region-specific brain organoids provide a platform to investigate early-stage phenotypes, which may potentially serve as biomarkers for early diagnosis and drug targets for preventing disease progression. A key to fulfilling the promise of iPSC technology to discover new medicines for the human neurodegenerative disease will be to incorporate the findings from iPSCs with other successful models. Since brain organoids lack vascularization, patterning cues and complex cell-cell interactions, such as those found in the nigrostriatal pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSOB180177C142">142</xref>], animal models will continue to provide essential readouts for drug evaluation, especially those related to physiological interactions and disease-associated behavioural phenotypes (e.g. cognitive impairment in AD and motor defects in PD and HD). We summarize current progress and applications of human iPSCs in neurodegenerative diseases including AD, PD and HD in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOB180177F1">figure 1</xref>. Although there are still many obstacles to overcome before iPSC-based technology can be used directly in clinical applications, the combination of iPSC technology with genome editing, organoid engineering and other technologies will certainly accelerate the development of new medicines for human neurodegenerative disease and eventually may cure these devastating diseases by cell replacement therapy.
<fig id="RSOB180177F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Applications of human induced pluripotent stem cells in neurodegenerative disease.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsob-9-180177-g1"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d35e187">
<caption>
<title>Reviewer comments</title>
</caption>
<media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="rsob180177_review_history.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="s8">
<title>Data accessibility</title>
<p>This article has no additional data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s9" sec-type="COI-statement">
<title>Competing interests</title>
<p>We declare we have no competing interests.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s10">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This work was supported by grants from Academia Sinica (Thematic Project, AS-106-TP-B13) and the Ministry of Science and Technology (MOST107-2321-B-010-007).</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="RSOB180177C1">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roselli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caroni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>From intrinsic firing properties to selective neuronal vulnerability in neurodegenerative diseases</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>901</fpage>–<lpage>910</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.12.063</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25741719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C2">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Neurofilaments as biomarkers in neurological disorders</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Neurol.
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41582-018-0058-z</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30171200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C3">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Promoting the clearance of neurotoxic proteins in neurodegenerative disorders of ageing</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd.2018.109</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30116051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C4">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blennow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Dis. Primers.
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>15056</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2015.56</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27188934</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C5">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dettmer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Parkinson-causing α-synuclein missense mutations shift native tetramers to monomers as a mechanism for disease initiation</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>7314</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8314</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26076669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C6">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Neuronal properties, <italic>in vivo</italic> effects, and pathology of a Huntington's disease patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cells (Dayton, Ohio)
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2054</fpage>–<lpage>2062</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1135</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C7">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onos</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sukoff Rizzo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Toward more predictive genetic mouse models of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Brain Res. Bull.
<volume>122</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainresbull.2015.12.003</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26708939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C8">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchetto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mummery</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Induced pluripotent stem cells: the new patient?</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>726</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm3448</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23034453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C9">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Induced pluripotent stem cell technology: a decade of progress</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd.2016.245</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27980341</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C10">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ichisaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomoda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Induction of pluripotent stem cells from adult human fibroblasts by defined factors</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>861</fpage>–<lpage>872</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2007.11.019</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18035408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C11">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Redox signalling directly regulates TDP-43 via cysteine oxidation and disulphide cross-linking</article-title>. <source/>EMBO J.
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1241</fpage>–<lpage>1252</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2011.471</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22193716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C12">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Discovery of inhibitors of microglial neurotoxicity acting through multiple mechanisms using a stem-cell-based phenotypic assay</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>620</fpage>–<lpage>632</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2012.07.005</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064101</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C13">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ananiev</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Musser</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maglaque</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Establishment of reporter lines for detecting fragile X mental retardation (FMR1) gene reactivation in human neural cells</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cells (Dayton, Ohio)
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.2463</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C14">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawatou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masumoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morinaga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Modelling torsade de pointes arrhythmias <italic>in vitro</italic> in 3D human iPS cell-engineered heart tissue</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1078</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-01125-y</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29057872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C15">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Cerebral organoids model human brain development and microcephaly</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>501</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12517</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C16">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Directed differentiation of human pluripotent stem cells into intestinal tissue <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>470</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09691</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21151107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C17">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Probing sporadic and Familial Alzheimer's disease using induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>482</volume>, <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10821</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22278060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C18">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Prevention of β-amyloid induced toxicity in human iPS cell-derived neurons by inhibition of Cyclin-dependent kinases and associated cell cycle events</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cell Res.
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scr.2012.11.005</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23305945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C19">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimos</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Induced pluripotent stem cells generated from patients with ALS can be differentiated into motor neurons</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>321</volume>, <fpage>1218</fpage>–<lpage>1221</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1158799</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18669821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C20">
<label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkhardt</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>A cellular model for sporadic ALS using patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Cell Neurosci.
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2013.07.007</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23891805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C21">
<label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Disease-specific induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>886</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.07.041</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18691744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C22">
<label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>High-throughput screening using iPSC-derived neuronal progenitors to identify compounds counteracting epigenetic gene silencing in fragile X syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J. Biomol. Screen.
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1101</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1087057115588287</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26024946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C23">
<label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Establishment of IL-7 expression reporter human cell lines, and their feasibility for high-throughput screening of IL-7-upregulating chemicals</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e0161899</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0161899</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27589392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C24">
<label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hockemeyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaenisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Induced pluripotent stem cells meet genome editing</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2016.04.013</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27152442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C25">
<label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>From genomics to gene therapy: induced pluripotent stem cells meet genome editing</article-title>. <source/>Annu. Rev. Genet.
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-genet-112414-054926</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26407033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C26">
<label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Markesbery</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Decreased levels of proteasome activity and proteasome expression in aging spinal cord</article-title>. <source/>Neuroscience
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C27">
<label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Modeling Alzheimer's disease with iPSCs reveals stress phenotypes associated with intracellular Aβ and differential drug responsiveness</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>496</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2013.01.009</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23434393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C28">
<label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>HD-iPSC Consortium</collab>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Induced pluripotent stem cells from patients with Huntington's disease show CAG-repeat-expansion-associated phenotypes</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2012.04.027</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22748968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C29">
<label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Identification and rescue of α-synuclein toxicity in Parkinson patient-derived neurons</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>342</volume>, <fpage>983</fpage>–<lpage>987</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1245296</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24158904</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C30">
<label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Izpisua Belmonte</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Gating neural development and aging via nuclear pores</article-title>. <source/>Cell Res.
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1212</fpage>–<lpage>1214</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2012.35</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22410792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C31">
<label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Drug screening for ALS using patient-specific induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Sci Transl. Med.
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>145ra104</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3004052</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C32">
<label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Isogenic human iPSC Parkinson's model shows nitrosative stress-induced dysfunction in MEF2-PGC1α transcription</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>155</volume>, <fpage>1351</fpage>–<lpage>1364</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.11.009</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C33">
<label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Human iPSC-based modeling of late-onset disease via progerin-induced aging</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2013.11.006</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24315443</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C34">
<label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moors</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rockel</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gassmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Human neurospheres as three-dimensional cellular systems for developmental neurotoxicity testing</article-title>. <source/>Environ. Health Perspect.
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>1131</fpage>–<lpage>1138</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.0800207</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19654924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C35">
<label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>The changing prevalence and incidence of dementia over time - current evidence</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Neurol.
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2017.63</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28497805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C36">
<label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Alzheimer's disease: genes, proteins, and therapy</article-title>. <source/>Physiol. Rev.
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>766</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.2001.81.2.741</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C37">
<label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muratore</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srikanth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Pearse</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The Familial Alzheimer's disease APPV717I mutation alters APP processing and Tau expression in iPSC-derived neurons</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>3523</fpage>–<lpage>3536</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddu064</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24524897</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C38">
<label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>APP metabolism regulates tau proteostasis in human cerebral cortex neurons</article-title>. <source/>Cell Rep.
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>696</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2015.03.068</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25921538</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C39">
<label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akamatsu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nihei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshizaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Modeling Familial Alzheimer's disease with induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>4530</fpage>–<lpage>4539</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddr394</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C40">
<label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Gain of toxic apolipoprotein E4 effects in human iPSC-derived neurons is ameliorated by a small-molecule structure corrector</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Med.
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-018-0004-z</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29632371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C41">
<label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Elucidating molecular phenotypes caused by the SORL1 Alzheimer's disease genetic risk factor using human induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>385</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2015.02.004</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25772071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C42">
<label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flamier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El Hajjar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adjaye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdouh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Modeling late-onset sporadic Alzheimer's disease through BMI1 deficiency</article-title>. <source/>Cell Rep.
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2653</fpage>–<lpage>2666</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.04.097</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29847796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C43">
<label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soldner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaenisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Dissecting risk haplotypes in sporadic Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2015.03.010</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25842969</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C44">
<label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belmadani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Stem cell derived basal forebrain cholinergic neurons from Alzheimer's disease patients are more susceptible to cell death</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Neurodegener.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1326-9-3</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24401693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C45">
<label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>APP processing in human pluripotent stem cell-derived neurons is resistant to NSAID-based gamma-secretase modulation</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cell Rep.
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stemcr.2013.10.011</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C46">
<label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Neuroprotective effects of apigenin against inflammation, neuronal excitability and apoptosis in an induced pluripotent stem cell model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Sci Rep.
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>31450</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep31450</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27514990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C47">
<label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochalek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Neurons derived from sporadic Alzheimer's disease iPSCs reveal elevated TAU hyperphosphorylation, increased amyloid levels, and GSK3B activation</article-title>. <source/>Alzheimers Res Ther.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13195-017-0317-z</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29191219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C48">
<label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Early pathogenic event of Alzheimer's disease documented in iPSCs from patients with PSEN1 mutations</article-title>. <source/>Oncotarget
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>7900</fpage>–<lpage>7913</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.13776</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27926491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C49">
<label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>iPSC-based compound screening and <italic>in vitro</italic> trials identify a synergistic anti-amyloid β combination for Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Cell Rep.
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2304</fpage>–<lpage>2312</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.10.109</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29166618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C50">
<label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortiz-Virumbrales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>CRISPR/Cas9-Correctable mutation-related molecular and physiological phenotypes in iPSC-derived Alzheimer's PSEN2 (N141I) neurons</article-title>. <source/>Acta Neuropathol. Commun.<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40478-017-0475-z</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29078805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C51">
<label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>iPSC-derived Familial Alzheimer's PSEN2 (N141I) cholinergic neurons exhibit mutation-dependent molecular pathology corrected by insulin signaling</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Neurodegener.
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13024-018-0265-5</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29945658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C52">
<label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muratore</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierahn</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srikanth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Jager</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Pearse</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Single-cell detection of secreted Aβ and sAPPα from human IPSC-derived neurons and astrocytes</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci.
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>1730</fpage>–<lpage>1746</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2735-15.2016</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26843653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C53">
<label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>APOE4 causes widespread molecular and cellular alterations associated with Alzheimer's disease phenotypes in human iPSC-derived brain cell types</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>1141</fpage>–<lpage>1154 e1147</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2018.05.008</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29861287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C54">
<label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musiek</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holtzman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Three dimensions of the amyloid hypothesis: time, space and ‘wingmen’</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci.
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>800</fpage>–<lpage>806</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4018</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26007213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C55">
<label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Meta-analysis of 74,046 individuals identifies 11 new susceptibility loci for Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>1452</fpage>–<lpage>1458</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2802</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24162737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C56">
<label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parsadanian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bales</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holtzman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Human and murine ApoE markedly alters Aβ metabolism before and after plaque formation in a mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Neurobiol. Dis.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nbdi.2002.0483</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11950276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C57">
<label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Efficient genome editing in plants using a CRISPR/Cas system</article-title>. <source/>Cell Res.
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1232</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2013.114</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23958582</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C58">
<label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossini</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Induced pluripotent stem cell-derived neuronal cells from a sporadic Alzheimer's disease donor as a model for investigating AD-associated gene regulatory networks</article-title>. <source/>BMC Genomics
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>84</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1262-5</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25765079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C59">
<label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abeliovich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gitler</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Defects in trafficking bridge Parkinson's disease pathology and genetics</article-title>. <source/>Nature.
<volume>539</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature20414</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27830778</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C60">
<label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornykiewicz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1962</year>
<article-title>Dopamine (3-hydroxytyramine) in the central nervous system and its relation to the Parkinson syndrome in man</article-title>. <source/>Dtsch. Med. Wochenschr.
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>1807</fpage>–<lpage>1810</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0028-1114024</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14448985</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C61">
<label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Pathoanatomy of Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurol.
<volume>247</volume>(<issue>Suppl 2</issue>), <fpage>II3</fpage>–<lpage>I10</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00007758</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10991663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C62">
<label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Differentiated Parkinson patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells grow in the adult rodent brain and reduce motor asymmetry in Parkinsonian rats</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>15 921</fpage>–<lpage>15 926</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1010209107</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C63">
<label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Human iPS cell-derived dopaminergic neurons function in a primate Parkinson's disease model</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>548</volume>, <fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature23664</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28858313</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C64">
<label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samata</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kakuta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Purification of functional human ES and iPSC-derived midbrain dopaminergic progenitors using LRTM1</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>13097</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms13097</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27739432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C65">
<label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Postmortem studies of deep brain stimulation for Parkinson's disease: a systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source/>Cell Tissue Res.
<volume>373</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00441-017-2672-2</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28836072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C66">
<label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaltouki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sivapatham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerencser</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Momcilovic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Mitochondrial alterations by PARKIN in dopaminergic neurons using PARK2 patient-specific and PARK2 knockout isogenic iPSC lines</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cell Rep.
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stemcr.2015.02.019</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C67">
<label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Pharmacological rescue of mitochondrial deficits in iPSC-derived neural cells from patients with Familial Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Sci. Transl. Med.
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>141ra190</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3003985</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C68">
<label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Progressive degeneration of human neural stem cells caused by pathogenic LRRK2</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>491</volume>, <fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>607</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11557</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23075850</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C69">
<label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>LRRK2 mutant iPSC-derived DA neurons demonstrate increased susceptibility to oxidative stress</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2011.01.013</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21362567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C70">
<label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soldner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Parkinson-associated risk variant in distal enhancer of α-synuclein modulates target gene expression</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>533</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature17939</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27096366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C71">
<label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schondorf</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>iPSC-derived neurons from GBA1-associated Parkinson's disease patients show autophagic defects and impaired calcium homeostasis</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>4028</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms5028</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24905578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C72">
<label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodard</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>iPSC-derived dopamine neurons reveal differences between monozygotic twins discordant for Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Cell Rep.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.10.023</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25456120</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C73">
<label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumitriu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Cyclin-G-associated kinase modifies α-synuclein expression levels and toxicity in Parkinson's disease: results from the GenePD Study</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1478</fpage>–<lpage>1487</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddr026</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21258085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C74">
<label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satake</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide association study identifies common variants at four loci as genetic risk factors for Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1303</fpage>–<lpage>1307</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.485</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19915576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C75">
<label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon-Sanchez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide association study reveals genetic risk underlying Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1308</fpage>–<lpage>1312</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.487</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19915575</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C76">
<label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopin</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>MPTP: an industrial chemical and contaminant of illicit narcotics stimulates a new era in research on Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Environ. Health Perspect.
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3319563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C77">
<label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deumens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blokland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prickaerts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Modeling Parkinson's disease in rats: an evaluation of 6-OHDA lesions of the nigrostriatal pathway</article-title>. <source/>Exp Neurol.
<volume>175</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/exnr.2002.7891</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12061862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C78">
<label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Parkinson's disease induced pluripotent stem cells with triplication of the α-synuclein locus</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>440</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms1453</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21863007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C79">
<label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ludtmann</surname><given-names>MHR</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>α-synuclein oligomers interact with ATP synthase and open the permeability transition pore in Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>2293</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04422-2</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29895861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C80">
<label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Parkin controls dopamine utilization in human midbrain dopaminergic neurons derived from induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>668</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms1669</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22314364</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C81">
<label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Th17 lymphocytes induce neuronal cell death in a human iPSC-based model of Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>131 e126</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2018.06.015</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29979986</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C82">
<label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luk</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kehm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Pathological α-synuclein transmission initiates Parkinson-like neurodegeneration in nontransgenic mice</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>338</volume>, <fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>953</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1227157</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23161999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C83">
<label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Mutant huntingtin disrupts the nuclear pore complex</article-title>. <source/>Neuron.
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>107 e106</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2017.03.023</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28384479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C84">
<label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickrell</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youle</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The roles of PINK1, parkin, and mitochondrial fidelity in Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.12.007</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25611507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C85">
<label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westenberger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genetics of Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source/>Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Med.
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>a008888</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a008888</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22315721</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C86">
<label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monzel</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Derivation of human midbrain-specific organoids from neuroepithelial stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cell Rep.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1144</fpage>–<lpage>1154</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stemcr.2017.03.010</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C87">
<label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Distinctive genomic signature of neural and intestinal organoids from Familial Parkinson's disease patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Neuropathol. Appl. Neurobiol.
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nan.12396</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28235153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C88">
<label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>An update on Huntington's disease: from the gene to the clinic</article-title>. <source/>Curr. Opin. Neurol.
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/wco.0000000000000116</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24978638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C89">
<label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Elucidating the role of the A2A ade.nosine receptor in neurodegeneration using neurons derived from Huntington's disease iPSCs</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>6066</fpage>–<lpage>6079</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddv318</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26264576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C90">
<label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nekrasov</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Manifestation of Huntington's disease pathology in human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived neurons</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Neurodegener.
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13024-016-0092-5</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27080129</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C91">
<label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montoro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellerby</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Characterization of human Huntington's disease cell model from induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Curr.
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>Rrn1193</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/currents.RRN1193</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21037797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C92">
<label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montoro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittkop</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellerby</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genetic correction of Huntington's disease phenotypes in induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2012.04.026</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22748967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C93">
<label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juopperi</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Astrocytes generated from patient induced pluripotent stem cells recapitulate features of Huntington's disease patient cells</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Brain
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-6606-5-17</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22613578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C94">
<label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chern</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Inhibition of soluble tumor necrosis factor is therapeutic in Huntington's disease</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>4328</fpage>–<lpage>4344</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddu151</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698979</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C95">
<label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>HD_iPSC_Consortium</collab>. <year>2017</year>
<article-title>Developmental alterations in Huntington's disease neural cells and pharmacological rescue in cells and mice</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci.
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>660</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4532</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28319609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C96">
<label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattis</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>HD iPSC-derived neural progenitors accumulate in culture and are susceptible to BDNF withdrawal due to glutamate toxicity</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>3257</fpage>–<lpage>3271</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddv080</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25740845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C97">
<label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De La Cruz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellerby</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Polyglutamine disease modeling: epitope based screen for homologous recombination using CRISPR/Cas9 system</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Curr.
<volume>6</volume> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/currents.hd.0242d2e7ad72225efa72f6964589369a</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C98">
<label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Reversal of phenotypic abnormalities by CRISPR/Cas9-mediated gene correction in huntington disease patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cell Rep.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>619</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stemcr.2017.01.022</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C99">
<label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Varied pathological and therapeutic response effects associated with CHCHD2 mutant and risk variants</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mutat.
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>987</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.23234</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28432706</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C100">
<label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Expression of mutant huntingtin in glial cells contributes to neuronal excitotoxicity</article-title>. <source/> J. Cell Biol.
<volume>171</volume>, <fpage>1001</fpage>–<lpage>1012</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200508072</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16365166</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C101">
<label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Astrocyte Kir4.1 ion channel deficits contribute to neuronal dysfunction in Huntington's disease model mice</article-title>. <source/>Nat Neurosci.
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>694</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3691</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24686787</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C102">
<label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benraiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Human glia can both induce and rescue aspects of disease phenotype in Huntington disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Commun.
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>11758</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms11758</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27273432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C103">
<label>103</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tidball</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genomic instability associated with p53 knockdown in the generation of Huntington's disease human induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e0150372</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0150372</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26982737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C104">
<label>104</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The choreography of neuroinflammation in Huntington's disease</article-title>. <source/>Trends Immunol.
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.it.2015.04.007</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26001312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C105">
<label>105</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>miR-196a ameliorates phenotypes of Huntington disease in cell, transgenic mouse, and induced pluripotent stem cell models</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2013.05.025</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810380</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C106">
<label>106</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Disatnik</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monbureau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shamloo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mochly-Rosen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Inhibition of mitochondrial fragmentation diminishes Huntington's disease-associated neurodegeneration</article-title>. <source/>J. Clin. Invest.
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>5371</fpage>–<lpage>5388</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci70911</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C107">
<label>107</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breslin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Driscoll</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Three-dimensional cell culture: the missing link in drug discovery</article-title>. <source/>Drug Discov. Today
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2012.10.003</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23073387</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C108">
<label>108</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pampaloni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reynaud</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stelzer</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The third dimension bridges the gap between cell culture and live tissue</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>839</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2236</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17684528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C109">
<label>109</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eiraku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Self-formation of layered neural structures in three-dimensional culture of ES cells</article-title>. <source/>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>768</fpage>–<lpage>777</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2012.02.005</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22405989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C110">
<label>110</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eiraku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Self-organized formation of polarized cortical tissues from ESCs and its active manipulation by extrinsic signals</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2008.09.002</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18983967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C111">
<label>111</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adil</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramadoss</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>hPSC-derived striatal cells generated using a scalable 3D hydrogel promote recovery in a Huntington disease mouse model</article-title>. <source/>Stem Cell Rep.
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1481</fpage>–<lpage>1491</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stemcr.2018.03.007</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C112">
<label>112</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conforti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Faulty neuronal determination and cell polarization are reverted by modulating HD early phenotypes</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>E762</fpage>–<lpage>E771</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1715865115</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29311338</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C113">
<label>113</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iefremova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>An organoid-based model of cortical development identifies non-cell-autonomous defects in Wnt signaling contributing to Miller–Dieker syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Cell Rep.
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.03.047</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28380362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C114">
<label>114</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simonini</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palejev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomasini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szekely</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Modeling human cortical development <italic>in vitro</italic> using induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>12 770</fpage>–<lpage>12 775</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1202944109</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C115">
<label>115</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trietsch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumuratov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hankemeier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vulto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwamborn</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Differentiation of neuroepithelial stem cells into functional dopaminergic neurons in 3D microfluidic cell culture</article-title>. <source/>Lab Chip
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>2419</fpage>–<lpage>2428</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c5lc00180c</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25902196</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C116">
<label>116</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mungenast</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdurrob</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Self-organizing 3D human neural tissue derived from induced pluripotent stem cells recapitulate Alzheimer's disease phenotypes</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e0161969</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0161969</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27622770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C117">
<label>117</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srikanth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lagomarsino</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muratore</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arellano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Pearse</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Shared effects of DISC1 disruption and elevated WNT signaling in human cerebral organoids</article-title>. <source/>Transl. Psychiatry
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-018-0122-x</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29643329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C118">
<label>118</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pekkanen-Mattila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shahsavani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A 3D Alzheimer's disease culture model and the induction of P21-activated kinase mediated sensing in iPSC derived neurons</article-title>. <source/>Biomaterials
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1420</fpage>–<lpage>1428</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2013.11.028</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C119">
<label>119</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krefft</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jabali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iefremova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ladewig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Generation of standardized and reproducible forebrain-type cerebral organoids from human induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>J. Visualized Exp. JoVE
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>56768</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/56768</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C120">
<label>120</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sora</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muguruma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Self-organizing cortex generated from human iPSCs with combination of FGF2 and ambient oxygen</article-title>. <source/>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.
<volume>498</volume>, <fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2018.03.049</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29524419</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C121">
<label>121</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Brain-region-specific organoids using mini-bioreactors for modeling ZIKV exposure</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>165</volume>, <fpage>1238</fpage>–<lpage>1254</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.04.032</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27118425</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C122">
<label>122</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasca</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Functional cortical neurons and astrocytes from human pluripotent stem cells in 3D culture</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Methods
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3415</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26005811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C123">
<label>123</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Midbrain-like organoids from human pluripotent stem cells contain functional dopaminergic and neuromelanin-producing Neurons</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2016.07.005</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27476966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C124">
<label>124</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadoshima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eiraku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Self-organization of axial polarity, inside-out layer pattern, and species-specific progenitor dynamics in human ES cell-derived neocortex</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>20 284</fpage>–<lpage>20 289</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1315710110</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C125">
<label>125</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>FOXG1-dependent dysregulation of GABA/glutamate neuron differentiation in autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>162</volume>, <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.06.034</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26186191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C126">
<label>126</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Velazquez Sanchez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Three dimensional human neuro-spheroid model of Alzheimer's disease based on differentiated induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source/>PLoS ONE
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e0163072</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163072</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27684569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C127">
<label>127</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blazejewski</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bennison</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toyo-Oka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Neurodevelopmental genetic diseases associated with microdeletions and microduplications of chromosome 17p13.3</article-title>. <source/>Front. Genet.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>80</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2018.00080</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628935</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C128">
<label>128</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Using brain organoids to understand Zika virus-induced microcephaly</article-title>. <source/>Development
<volume>144</volume>, <fpage>952</fpage>–<lpage>957</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.140707</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28292840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C129">
<label>129</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Zika virus infects human cortical neural progenitors and attenuates their growth</article-title>. <source/>Cell Stem Cell
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2016.02.016</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26952870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C130">
<label>130</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A three-dimensional human neural cell culture model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>515</volume>, <fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13800</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25307057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C131">
<label>131</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>A 3D human neural cell culture system for modeling Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Protoc.
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>985</fpage>–<lpage>1006</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2015.065</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26068894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C132">
<label>132</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bejoy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Neural patterning of human induced pluripotent stem cells in 3-D cultures for studying biomolecule-directed differential cellular responses</article-title>. <source/>Acta Biomater.
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2016.06.027</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27345135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C133">
<label>133</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smirnova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valadares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pamies</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogberg</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waldmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>A LUHMES 3D dopaminergic neuronal model for neurotoxicity testing allowing long-term exposure and cellular resilience analysis</article-title>. <source/>Arch. Toxicol.
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>2725</fpage>–<lpage>2743</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00204-015-1637-z</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26647301</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C134">
<label>134</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javaherian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kriegstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A stem cell niche for intermediate progenitor cells of the embryonic cortex</article-title>. <source/>Cereb Cortex.
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>), <fpage>i70</fpage>–<lpage>i77</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhp029</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C135">
<label>135</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingber</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Microfluidic organs-on-chips</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Biotechnol.
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>760</fpage>–<lpage>772</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2989</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25093883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C136">
<label>136</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giobbe</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michielin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giulitti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martewicz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Floreani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elvassore</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Functional differentiation of human pluripotent stem cells on a chip</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Methods
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3411</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26030445</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C137">
<label>137</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seok Heo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Reconstituting vascular microenvironment of neural stem cell niche in three-dimensional extracellular matrix</article-title>. <source/>Adv. Healthc. Mater.
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1457</fpage>–<lpage>1464</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adhm.201300569</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24523050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C138">
<label>138</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusuma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanjaya-Putra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerecht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Self-organized vascular networks from human pluripotent stem cells in a synthetic matrix</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>12 601</fpage>–<lpage>12 606</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1306562110</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C139">
<label>139</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanotelli</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Stable engineered vascular networks from human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived endothelial cells cultured in synthetic hydrogels</article-title>. <source/>Acta Biomater.
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2016.03.001</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26945632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C140">
<label>140</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eftekharzadeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Tau protein disrupts nucleocytoplasmic transport in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>925</fpage>–<lpage>940</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2018.07.039</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30189209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C141">
<label>141</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Da Cruz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>CELL BIOLOGY. Disrupted nuclear import-export in neurodegeneration</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>351</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad9872</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26744395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="RSOB180177C142">
<label>142</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>An <italic>in vivo</italic> model of functional and vascularized human brain organoids</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Biotechnol.
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.4127</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29658944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>