<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0370512</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">457</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The American journal of psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0002-953X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1535-7228</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30220221</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6408273</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2018.17121311</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS970630</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Maternal immune activation and neuropsychiatric illness: A translational research perspective</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Alan S.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>M.D, M.P.H.</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>Urs</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>a</label>New York State Psychiatric Institute, Columbia University Medical Center, New York, NY</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>b</label>Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, University of Zurich-Vetsuisse, Zurich, Switzerland</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>c</label>Neuroscience Center Zurich, University of Zurich and ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="FN1">All correspondence should be addressed to: Alan S. Brown, M.D., M.P.H., New York State Psychiatric Institute, 1051 Riverside Drive, Unit 23, New York, NY, 10032, USA, Tel. 646-774-6417, Fax. 646-774-6408, <email>asb11@cumc.columbia.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p>Conflict of Interest: The authors report no competing interests.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>20</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>17</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>01</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>175</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>1073</fpage>
<lpage>1083</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2018.17121311-->
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Epidemiologic studies, including prospective birth cohort investigations, have implicated maternal immune activation in the etiology of neuropsychiatric disorders. Maternal infectious pathogens and inflammation are plausible risk factors for these outcomes and have been associated with schizophrenia, autism spectrum disorders, and bipolar disorder. Concurrent with epidemiologic work are animal models of prenatal immune activation, which have documented behavioral, neurochemical, neuroanatomic, and neurophysiologic disruptions that mirror phenotypes observed in these neuropsychiatric disorders. Epidemiologic studies of maternal immune activation offer the advantage of directly evaluating human populations, but are limited with respect to the inability to uncover pathogenic mechanisms. Animal models, on the other hand, are limited with regard to their generalizability to psychiatric disorders, but have made significant strides toward discovering causal relationships and biological pathways between maternal immune activation and neuropsychiatric phenotypes. Incorporating these risk factors in “reverse translational” animal models of maternal immune activation has yielded a wealth of data supporting the predictive potential of the epidemiologic studies. To further enhance the translatability between epidemiology and basic science, we propose a complementary approach that includes deconstructing neuropsychiatric outcomes of maternal immune activation into key pathophysiologically defined phenotypes that are identifiable in humans and animals, and that evaluates the inter-species concordance regarding interactions between maternal immune activation and genetic as well as epigenetic factors, including processes involving intergenerational disease transmission.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>