<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0406041</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4668</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Comp Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Comp. Neurol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Journal of comparative neurology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9967</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-9861</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28472858</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6432783</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.24232</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1018868</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Selective neuronal expression of the SoxE factor, Sox8, in direct pathway striatal projection neurons of the developing mouse brain</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Merchan-Sala</surname>
<given-names>Paloma</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nardini</surname>
<given-names>Diana</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Waclaw</surname>
<given-names>Ronald R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>Kenneth</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Developmental Biology, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, 3333 Burnet Avenue, Cincinnati OH 45229, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Division of Neurosurgery, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, 3333 Burnet Avenue, Cincinnati OH 45229, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Division of Experimental Hematology and Cancer Biology, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, 3333 Burnet Avenue, Cincinnati OH 45229, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">ROLE OF AUTHORS</p>
<p id="P2">All authors contributed significantly to the research that led to preparation of this article. All authors had full access to all the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. Study concept and design: PMS, RRW, KC. Acquisition of data: PMS, DN, RRW. Analysis and interpretation of data: PMS, RRW, KC. Drafting of the manuscript: PMS, RRW, KC. Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content: PMS, RRW, KC. Obtained funding: KC. Administrative, technical, and material support: PMS, DN, RRW, KC. Study supervision: RRW, KC.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Corresponding author:</bold>
<email>kenneth.campbell@cchmc.org</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p id="P45">CONFLICT OF INTEREST</p>
<p id="P46">None of the authors have a known or potential conflict of interest including any financial, personal or other relationships with other people or organizations within three years of beginning the submitted work that could inappropriately influence, or be perceived to influence, the work presented in this article.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>19</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>22</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>25</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>525</volume>
<issue>13</issue>
<fpage>2805</fpage>
<lpage>2819</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/cne.24232-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P3">The striatum is the major component of the basal ganglia and is well known to play a key role in the control of motor function via balanced output from the indirect (iSPNs) and direct pathway striatal projection neurons (dSPNs). Little is known, however, about the molecular genetic mechanisms that control the formation of the iSPNs versus dSPNs. We show here that the SoxE family member, Sox8, is co-expressed with dSPN marker, Isl1, in the developing striatum. Moreover, dSPNs, as marked by <italic>Isl1-cre</italic> fate map, express Sox8 in the embryonic striatum and <italic>Sox8-EGFP</italic> BAC transgenic mice specifically reveal the direct pathway axons during development. These EGFP<sup>+</sup> axons are first observed to reach their midbrain target, the substantia nigra pars reticulata (SNr), at E14 in the mouse with a robust connection observed already at birth. The selective expression of EGFP in dSPNs of <italic>Sox8-EGFP</italic> BAC mice is maintained at postnatal time points. Sox8 is known to be expressed in oligodendrocyte precursor cells (OPCs) together with other SoxE factors and we show here that the EGFP signal co-localizes with the OPC markers throughout the brain. Finally, we show that <italic>Sox8-EGFP</italic> BAC mice can be used to interrogate the altered dSPN development in <italic>Isl1</italic> conditional mutants including aberrant axonal projections detected already at embryonic time points. Thus Sox8 represents an early and specific marker of embryonic dSPNs and the <italic>Sox8-EGFP</italic> BAC transgenic mice are an excellent tool to study the development of basal ganglia circuitry.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Basal ganglia</kwd>
<kwd>Development</kwd>
<kwd>Neural circuit</kwd>
<kwd>Striatonigral pathway</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>