<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8704565</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4529</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0890-8567</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1527-5418</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30768420</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6488452</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2018.09.431</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1511033</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Quantifying the Optimal Structure of the Autism Phenotype: A Comprehensive Comparison of Dimensional, Categorical, and Hybrid Models</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>Hyunsik</given-names>
<prefix>Mr.</prefix>
</name>
<degrees>MA</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Keifer</surname>
<given-names>Cara</given-names>
<prefix>Ms.</prefix>
</name>
<degrees>MA</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez-Seijas</surname>
<given-names>Craig</given-names>
<prefix>Mr.</prefix>
</name>
<degrees>MA</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eaton</surname>
<given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
<prefix>Dr.</prefix>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lerner</surname>
<given-names>Matthew</given-names>
<prefix>Dr.</prefix>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gadow</surname>
<given-names>Kenneth</given-names>
<prefix>Dr.</prefix>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Stony Brook University, NY.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Authorship Contribution</p>
<p id="P2">Dr. Nicholas Eaton developed the study concept. All authors contributed to the study design. Testing and data collection were performed by Dr. Kenneth Gadow, and Hyunsik Kim performed the data analysis and interpretation under the supervision of Drs. Nicholas Eaton, Matthew Lerner, and Kenneth Gadow. Hyunsik Kim, Cara Keifer, and Craig Rodriguez-Seijas drafted the paper, and Drs. Nicholas Eaton, Matthew Lerner, and Kenneth Gadow provided critical revisions. All authors approved the final version of the paper for submission.</p>
<p id="P3">Dr. Eaton developed the study concept. All authors contributed to the study design. Testing and data collection were performed by Dr. Gadow, and Mr. Kim performed the data analysis and interpretation under the supervision of Drs. Eaton, Lerner, and Gadow. Mr. Kim, Ms. Keifer, and Mr. Rodriguez-Seijas drafted the paper, and Drs. Eaton, Lerner, and Gadow provided critical revisions. All authors approved the final version of the paper for submission.</p>
<p id="P4">Dr. Eaton served as the statistical expert for this research.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1">Correspondence to Hyunsik Kim, MA, Department of Psychology, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11794; <email>hyunsik.kim2@gmail.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p id="P46">Author Conflicts of Interest/Disclosures</p>
<p id="P47">Authors report no conflicts of interest, except Kenneth D. Gadow, PhD, of Stony Brook University, who is a shareholder in Checkmate Plus, publisher of the Child and Adolescent Symptom Inventory-4R.</p>
<p id="P48">Disclosure: Dr. Gadow is a shareholder in Checkmate Plus, publisher of the Child and Adolescent Symptom Inventory-4R. Drs. Eaton and Lerner, Mr. Kim, Ms. Keifer, and Mr. Rodriguez-Seijas report no biomedical financial interests or potential conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>9</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>29</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>58</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<fpage>876</fpage>
<lpage>886.e2</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.jaac.2018.09.431-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<sec id="S1">
<title>Objective:</title>
<p id="P5">The two primary – seemingly contradictory – strategies for classifying child psychiatric syndromes are categorical and dimensional; conceptual ambiguities appear to be greatest for polythetic syndromes such as autism spectrum disorder (ASD). Recently, a compelling alternative has emerged that integrates both categorical and dimensional approaches (ie, hybrid model) thanks to the increasing sophistication of analytic procedures. This study aimed to quantify the optimal phenotypic structure of ASD by comprehensively comparing categorical, dimensional, and hybrid models.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Method:</title>
<p id="P6">The sample comprised 3,825 youth, who were consecutive referrals to a university developmental disabilities or child psychiatric outpatient clinic. Caregivers completed the Child and Adolescent Symptom Inventory-4R (CASI-4R), which includes an ASD symptom rating scale. A series of latent class analyses, exploratory and confirmatory factor analyses, and factor mixture analyses was conducted. Replication analyses were conducted in an independent sample (<italic>N</italic>=2,503) of children referred for outpatient evaluation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results:</title>
<p id="P7">Based on comparison of 44 different models, results indicated that the ASD symptom phenotype is best conceptualized as multi-dimensional versus a categorical or categorical-dimensional hybrid construct. ASD symptoms were best characterized as falling along three dimensions (ie, social interaction, communication, and repetitive behavior) on the CASI-4R.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p id="P8">Findings reveal an optimal structure with which to characterize the ASD phenotype using a single, parent-report measure, supporting presence of multiple correlated symptom dimensions that traverse formal diagnostic boundaries and quantify the heterogeneity of ASD. These findings inform understanding of how neurodevelopmental disorders can extend beyond discrete categories of development and represent continuously-distributed traits across the range of human behaviors.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
<kwd>ASD phenotype</kwd>
<kwd>classification</kwd>
<kwd>dimensional models</kwd>
<kwd>Child and Adolescent Symptom Inventory</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>