<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8800478</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">1990</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Brain Behav Immun</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Brain Behav. Immun.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Brain, behavior, and immunity</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0889-1591</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1090-2139</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29902514</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6526722</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2018.06.010</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1026041</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Principles of inflammasome priming and inhibition: Implications for psychiatric disorders</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Herman</surname>
<given-names>Francis J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pasinetti</surname>
<given-names>Giulio Maria</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Department of Neurology, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, New York, NY 10029, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Department of Genomic Sciences, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, New York, NY 10029, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Bronx, NY 10468, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Neurology, The Mount Sinai School of Medicine, 1 Gustave L. Levy Place, Box 1137, New York, NY 10029, USA., <email>giulio.pasinetti@mssm.edu</email> (G.M. Pasinetti).</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN1">
<p id="P42">8. Declaration of interest</p>
<p id="P43">None.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>10</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>20</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>66</fpage>
<lpage>84</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.bbi.2018.06.010-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">The production of inflammatory proteins by the innate immune system is a tightly orchestrated procedure that allows the body to efficiently respond to exogenous and endogenous threats. Recently, accumulating evidence has indicated that disturbances in the inflammatory response system not only provoke autoimmune disorders, but also can have deleterious effects on neuronal function and mental health. As inflammation in the brain is primarily mediated by microglia, there has been an expanding focus on the mechanisms through which these cells initiate and propagate neuroinflammation. Microglia can enter persistently active states upon their initial recognition of an environmental stressor and are thereafter prone to elicit amplified and persistent inflammatory responses following subsequent exposures to stressors. A recent focus on why primed microglia cells are susceptible to environmental insults has been the NLRP3 inflammasome. Its function within the innate immune system is regulated in such a manner that supports a role for the complex in gating neuroinflammatory responses. The activation of NLRP3 inflammasome in microglia results in the cleavage of zymogen inflammatory interleukins into functional forms that elicit a number of consequential effects in the local neuronal environ ment. There is evidence to support the principle that within primed neuroimmune systems a lowered threshold for NLRP3 activation can cause persistent neuroinflammation or the amplified production of inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-1β and IL-18. Over the course of an individual’s lifetime, persistent neuroinflammation can subsequently lead to the pathophysiological signatures that define psychological disorders. Therefore, targeting the NLRP3 inflammasome complex may represent an innovative and consequential approach to limit neuroinflammatory states in psychiatric disorders, such as major depressive disorder.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>NLRP3 inflammasome</kwd>
<kwd>Microglia</kwd>
<kwd>Psychiatric disorders</kwd>
<kwd>Innate immune system</kwd>
<kwd>Immune priming</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>