<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DMSO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">dmso</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Diabetes, Metabolic Syndrome and Obesity: Targets and Therapy</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1178-7007</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31190930</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6526182</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">201525</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DMSO.S201525</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Research</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Vitamin D receptor rs7975232, rs731236 and rs1544410 single nucleotide polymorphisms, and 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels in Egyptian children with type 1 diabetes mellitus: effect of vitamin D co-therapy</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Ahmed et al</alt-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Ahmed et al</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>Ahmed El-Abd</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sakhr</surname>
<given-names>Hala M</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>Mohammed H</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>El-Amir</surname>
<given-names>Mostafa I</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ameen</surname>
<given-names>Hesham H</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0004">4</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, South Valley University</institution>, <addr-line>Qena</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff>
<aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Medical Biochemistry, Faculty of Medicine, South Valley University</institution>, <addr-line>Qena</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff>
<aff id="AFF0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, South Valley University</institution>, <addr-line>Qena</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff>
<aff id="AFF0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Clinical Pathology, Faculty of Medicine, Al-Azhar University (Assiut Branch)</institution>, <addr-line>Assiut</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Mohammed H Hassan<institution>Department of Medical Biochemistry, Faculty of Medicine, South Valley University</institution>, <addr-line>Qena</addr-line><addr-line>83523</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country><phone>Tel +20 109 847 3605</phone>Email <email xlink:href="Mohammedhosnyhassaan@yahoo.com">Mohammedhosnyhassaan@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>703</fpage>
<lpage>716</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>03</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>04</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2019 Ahmed et al.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ahmed et al.</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
<license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Purpose:</bold> We aimed to examine the possible association role of vitamin D and vitamin D receptor (VDR) single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) development, glycemic control and complications among a cohort of Egyptian children.</p>
<p><bold>Subjects and methods:</bold> A prospective case-control study has been conducted on 50 Egyptian children with T1DM who were comparable with 50 controls. Vitamin D and HbA1c were measured. VDR-SNPs [<italic>Apa</italic>I (rs7975232), <italic>Taq</italic>I (rs731236) and <italic>Bsm</italic>I (rs1544410)] detection was done by polymerase chain reaction through restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR-RFLP) technique. Vitamin D supplements were given to the included T1DM children with low vitamin D and reassessments of both HbA1c% and 25(OH)D serum levels were performed in those children three months later.</p>
<p><bold>Results:</bold> Eighty percent of the included diabetic patients have poor glycemic control. Vitamin D was deficient in 68% and insufficient in 16% of diabetic patients. Significant improvements in both vitamin D and glycemic status among T1DM children, who have low vitamin D and received vitamin D supplementations. There were significantly negative correlations between serum levels of vitamin D with both HbA1c % (r= –0.358, <italic>P</italic>˂0.05) and daily insulin dose (r=−0.473, <italic>P</italic>˂0.05). Compared with controls, T1DM children presented more commonly with <italic>Apa</italic>I a allele (OR: 2.87; 95%CI: 1.39–5.91, <italic>P</italic>˂0.05) and <italic>Bsm</italic>I b allele (OR: 4.38; 95%CI: 2.30–8.33, <italic>P</italic>˂0.05). <italic>Taq</italic>I t allele wasn’t significantly differing among patients and controls (<italic>P</italic>˃0.05). Aa+aa and Bb+bb genotypes were significantly higher among T1DM vs the controls (OR: 3.08;, 95%CI: 1.33–7.15, <italic>P</italic>˂0.05 and OR: 9.33; 95%CI: 3.61–24.17, <italic>P</italic>˂0.05respectively).</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion:</bold>
<italic>Apa</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>I were associated with risk of T1DM development among Egyptian children. Low vitamin D status was frequently occurring among T1DM with significant improvement in the glycemic control of such children when adding vitamin D supplements to the standard insulin therapy.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="video">
<title>Video abstract</title>
<p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="UF0001" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
<graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="DMSO-12-703-g0001"></graphic>
</fig>
</p>
<p>Point your SmartPhone at the code above. If you have a QR code reader the video abstract will appear. Or use:</p>
<p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://youtu.be/zUkSWhQ4mwM">https://youtu.be/zUkSWhQ4mwM</ext-link>
</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>vitamin D receptor single nucleotide polymorphisms</kwd>
<kwd>genomic DNA</kwd>
<kwd>vitamin D</kwd>
<kwd>type 1 diabetes mellitus</kwd>
<kwd>Egyptian children</kwd>
<kwd>vitamin D therapy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4"></fig-count>
<table-count count="4"></table-count>
<ref-count count="88"></ref-count>
<page-count count="14"></page-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S0001">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) is an autoimmune disease characterized by multiple genetic and environmental factors which are implicated in disease pathogenesis.<sup>1 </sup>T1DM occurs due to destruction of beta cells of pancreas resulting in deficiency of insulin<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref> , is one of the most rapidly growing diseases, and is the most frequent type in childhood accounting for about two-thirds of newly diagnosed DM in patients ≤19 years old in the US.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">2</xref> In Egypt, calculated age-adjusted T1DM incidence in 1996, 2006, and 2011 was 0.7, 2.0 and 3.1/10<sup>5</sup>/year, respectively, while age-adjusted T1DM prevalence in the same years was 1.9, 15.5 and 26.8/10<sup>5</sup>/year, respectively.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref></p>
<p>Vitamin D (25(OH)D) plays an essential role as a transcription factor that regulates the insulin secretion from pancreatic beta cells through vitamin D receptor (VDR), which belongs to the nuclear hormone receptors superfamily.1,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref> In addition, vitamin D has an immune-modulator function via enhancing the differentiation of monocytes and inhibiting the proliferation of lymphocytes and the secretion of cytokines<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref> Furthermore, vitamin D decreases the Fas expression and major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I molecules with subsequent inhibition of pancreatic β-cell apoptosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref> Polymorphisms of the VDR gene are accompanied by altered gene function or expression and was found to be associated with many autoimmune disorders in humans, but its role in T1DM pathogenesis is still unclear despite several studies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref></p>
<p>VDR gene is located on the chromosomes no. 12 and 14, with four commonly identified single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) (<italic>Apa</italic>I, <italic>Taq</italic>I, <italic>Bsm</italic>I and <italic>Fok</italic>I).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">13</xref> The focus of the present study was to investigate the possible associations between T1DM, its complications and glycemic control, and vitamin D status with SNPs in the VDR (<italic>Apa</italic>I, <italic>Taq</italic>I, and <italic>Bsm</italic>I) and analysis of their distribution in a cohort of Egyptian children with T1DM. The present research was also to assesse the correlation between vitamin D and HbA1c, and to study the effect of vitamin D replacement therapy on glycemic control in relation to the studied genetic variants among T1DM children who exhibited vitamin D deficiency.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0002">
<title>Patients and methods</title>
<sec id="S0002-S2001">
<title>Study design and participants</title>
<p>The current prospective case-control, hospital-based study, has been conducted on 50 Egyptian children with T1DM, who were diagnosed according to the American Diabetes Association for T1DM.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0014">14</xref> They were recruited from the outpatients‘ pediatric clinics and inpatients‘ Pediatric Departments of the University Hospital, South Valley University, Qena, Egypt, which is a major tertiary referral centre in upper Egypt. The included pediatric patients were comparable with 50 unrelated healthy, age and sex matched children selected as controls. The recruitment of patients and controls in the present study was done in accordance with the guidelines laid down in the Declaration of Helsinki, and all children‘s parents were informed about the aim of the study and their written informed consent was obtained, after approval of the University Hospital Ethics Committee. The total duration of the study was one year, from December 1, 2017 to November 30, 2018. We adjusted the size of the sample to achieve 80% power and 5% confidence of significance (type 1 error).</p>
<p>The included patients who have vitamin D insufficiency received oral cholecalciferol 800 units daily for 3 months,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">15</xref> while patients with vitamin D deficient children received 4,000 units of oral cholecalciferol daily for 3 months with calcium supplementation (50 mg/kg/day),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0016">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0019">19</xref> and reassessments of both glycemic control (HbA1C) and vitamin D levels after 3 months were performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>).<fig fig-type="figure" id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the study participants and methodology.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="DMSO-12-703-g0002"></graphic></fig></p>
<p>Children who received calcium or vitamin D supplements or glucocorticoids for the last 3 months or with renal or liver diseases or other nondiabetic related autoimmune disorders, or had undergone immunosuppressive therapy, any other systemic disease, were all excluded from the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0002-S2002">
<title>Clinical evaluation of the included children</title>
<p>Detailed medical history was taken from every included patient’s parents in the form of age of the patient, age at onset of diabetes as determined by the time of the first insulin dose administration,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0020">20</xref> duration of diabetes in years, family history of T1DM, type and doses of insulin therapy,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0021">21</xref> history of diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0022">22</xref> medical history suggestive of associated autoimmune disease (as regards thyroid, Addison’s and celiac diseases), nutritional history, and symptoms of exercise intolerance or musculoskeletal pain and numbness.</p>
<p>Weight and height were recorded, and individual body mass index (BMI) was calculated (weight, kg/height, m<sup>2</sup>) both for patients and for controls and evaluated.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0023">23</xref> Assessment of puberty in adolescent patients was done according to sexual maturity rating and cases of delayed puberty are identified as regards absence of breast development in girls more than 13 years old or testicular volume less than 4 ml in boys older than 14 years old.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0024">24</xref> Complete general physical, systemic and neurological examination was conducted.</p>
<p>According to Glastras et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0025">25</xref> prepubertal children with at least 5 years duration of diabetes or pubertal children with at least 2 years duration were screened for diabetic complications. For detection of retinopathy, fundus examination was performed after topical mydriatic application,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0026">26</xref> by an experienced ophthalmologist, a morning urine sample for urinary albumin/creatinine ratio (UACR) and microalbumin assays was done to determine the presence or absence of microalbuminuria (30–300 mg/day) in at least two consecutive specimens for diabetic nephropathy screening.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0027">27</xref> In addition, electrophysiological studies using multiple channel apparatus (MEB-9400, Nihon Kohden Inc, Tokyo, Japan), with the presence of at least two independent and abnormal neurophysiological nerve parameters as the criteria for peripheral nervous system involvement<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0028">28</xref> to confirm occurrence of diabetic neuropathy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0002-S2003">
<title>Laboratory workup</title>
<sec id="S0002-S2003-S3001">
<title>Blood samples</title>
<p>A total of 6 mL of peripheral blood venous samples were drawn from an antecubital vein which was divided into two vacutainer tubes. A total of 4 mL was collected on two EDTA tubes, 2 ml each, one was used for genotyping (stored at −80°C till time of analysis) and the other was used for HbA1C assay. The remaining 2 mL of venous blood was evacuated into serum separator gel tubes, where the samples were allowed to clot for 30 minutess at 37°C before centrifugation for 15 minutes at 3,500 rpm. Separated sera were used for vitamin D3 assays.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0002-S2003-S3002">
<title>Biochemical assays</title>
<p>Vitamin D assays were performed using commercially available sandwich ELISA kit, supplied by Chongqing Biospes Co., Ltd (Chongqing, People’s Republic of China) with the catalog number: BYEK1472 using microplate ELISA reader (EMR−500, Labomed, Inc., LA, USA). Vitamin D deficiency was defined as a 25-OHD level of ≤20 ng/ml and vitamin D insufficiency as 21–29 ng/ml and optimal level as ≥30 ng/ml.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0029">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0032">32</xref></p>
<p>HbA1c assays were done using cobas c311, Hitachi, Roche Diagnostics, Germany. The patients were considered as poor glycemic control when their HbA1c ˃8%, while those having their HbA1c≤8% were categorized as having good glycemic control.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref></p>
<p>Three months later, HbA1C and Vitamin D assays were repeated for vitamin D deficient patients who received vitamin D replacement therapy in addition to the routine insulin therapy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0002-S2003-S3003">
<title>DNA extraction</title>
<p>Genomic DNA was extracted from the whole blood by using G-spinTM total DNA extraction kit protocol (iNtRON Biotechnology, Inc., Korea) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. The extracted DNA was stored at −20 °C for further genetic analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0002-S2003-S3004">
<title>VDR genotyping</title>
<p>All the included children were genotyped using polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR-RFLP), for three restriction sites in the VDR gene, <italic>Apa</italic>I (rs7975232), <italic>Taq</italic>I (rs731236), and <italic>Bsm</italic>I (rs1544410) SNPs using specific primer sequences (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>), available at the PubMed (NCBI Reference Sequence: NG_008731.1), in concordance with previous protocols.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0034">34</xref><table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>PCR primer sequences used to amplify VDR SNPs and length of DNA fragments of VDR gene polymorphism</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">SNP</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR primer sequences (5‘-3‘)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fragment size</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Apa</italic>I</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Forward</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGG ACG CTG AGG GAT GGC AGA GC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">A:716 bp<break></break>a:481 bp, 235 bp</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Reverse</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGA AAG GGG TTA GGT TGG ACA GGA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Taq</italic>I</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Forward</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGG ACG CTG AGG GAT GGC AGA GC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T:716 bp<break></break>t:419 bp, 297 bp</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Reverse</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGA AAG GGG TTA GGT TGGACAGGA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Bsm</italic>I</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Forward</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAA CCA AGA CTA CAA GTA CCG CGT CAG TGA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">B:825 bp<break></break>b:649 bp, 176 bp</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Reverse</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AAC CAG CGG AAG AGG TCA AGG G</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> VDR, vitamin D receptor; SNPs, single nucleotide polymorphisms.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
<p>After mixing 25 μL from the PCR master mix solution (Catalog no. 25028, iNtRON Biotechnolog, Korea) with 1 μL forward primer, 1 μL reverse primer (both primers with concentration of 10 nmol), 21 μL nuclease free water, and 2 μL from the extracted DNA, the PCR condition used for <italic>Apa</italic>I and <italic>Taq</italic>I amplifications was as follows: 10 minutes of initial denaturation at 94°C, and the following temperature profile was used for 30 cycles as follows: 94°C for 1 minute, 62°C for 1 minute, 72°C for 1 minute, and a final extension of 5 minutes, using Biometra thermal cycler (serial no. 2603204, Biometra, Germany). The PCR products, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>), were 716-bp in size (for A or T alleles), using 50-bp DNA ladder (Catalog No. 24072, iNtRON Biotechnolog, Korea) and were digested using <italic>Apa</italic>I (Catalog No. ER 1411, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) and <italic>Taq</italic>I (Catalog No. R051S, Enzynomics Co., Ltd, Korea), where 10 μL of the PCR reaction mixture added to 2 μL of 10X buffer, 2 μL of the restriction enzyme and mixed with 18 μL nuclease-free water to be incubated at 37°C and 65°C for 2 hours respectively, then loaded in gel electrophoresis (serial no. 283BR11101, Bio-Rad-pac 300, Bio-Rad Laboratories Inc., Hercules, CA, USA), using 2% agarose gel stained with 5 μL ethidium bromide).<fig fig-type="figure" id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Gel electrophoresis of the PCR products (<bold>A</bold>) Numbers refer to lanes. Lane 1 shows 50 bp DNA ladder. Lanes 2–5 showed amplified DNA segments of length 716 bp: Lanes 2 and 3 for <italic>Apa</italic>I alleles, Lanes 4 and 5 for <italic>Taq</italic>1 alleles (both have the same size 716 bp); Lanes 6, 7 and 8 for <italic>Bsm</italic>I alleles (with DNA fragment size of 825 bp). Detection of <italic>Apa</italic>I polymorphism using PCR-RFLP method (<bold>B</bold>) Lane 1: 50 bp DNA ladder, Lane 2 mutant (235 bp and 481 bp) homozygote (aa), Lanes 3, 4, 6, and 8 are mutant heterozygote (Aa), Lanes 5, 7 are wild type homozygote (AA), nonmutant. Detection of <italic>Taq</italic>1 polymorphism using PCR-RFLP method (<bold>C</bold>) Lane 1: 50 bp DNA ladder, Lanes 5, 9: mutant (297 bp and 419 bp) homoozygote (tt), Lanes 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11, and 12 are mutant heterozygote (Tt). Detection of <italic>Bsm</italic>I polymorphism using PCR-RFLP method (<bold>D</bold>) Lane 1: 50 bp DNA ladder, Lane 2: mutant (649 bp and 176 bp) homozygote (bb), Lane 3 is mutant heterozygote (Bb), Lane 5 is wild type homozygote (BB), nonmutant.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="DMSO-12-703-g0003"></graphic></fig></p>
<p>Visualization of DNA fragments was done under ultraviolet light (using U.V. Transilluminator 2000, serial no. 642–1045, Bio-Rad Laboratories Inc.) using 50-bp DNA ladder. The <italic>Apa</italic>I restriction fragments lengths were 481 and 235-bp (mutant allele, a), while those for <italic>Taq</italic>I were 419 and 297-bp (mutant allele t). Thus the <italic>Apa</italic>I (rs7975232, NM_000376.2: c.1025-49G&gt;T), located in intron 8 of VDR gene, results in T (variant “A”) changing into G (variant “a”); AA (TT); Aa (TG); Aa (GG),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0035">35</xref> and the <italic>Taq</italic>I (rs731236, NM_000376.2: c.1056T&gt;C), observed in exon 9, results in T(variant “T”) changing into C (variant “t”); TT (TT), Tt (TC), tt (CC),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0036">36</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<p>The PCR condition used for <italic>Bsm</italic>I amplification as follows: 5 minutes of initial denaturation at 94°C, and the following temperature profile was used for 30 cycles as follows: 94°C for 1 minutes, 56°C for 1 minute, 72°C for 1 minute, and a final extension of 5 minutes. The PCR products were 825-bp long (B allele), and their digestion was performed using Mva12691 (<italic>Bsm</italic>I, Catalog No. ER 0961, Thermo Fisher Scientific) via incubation at 37°C for 3 hours. The length of the restriction fragments were 649 and 176-bp (mutant allele, b), so the <italic>Bsm</italic>I (rs1544410, NM_000376.2: c.1024+283G˃A), detected in itron 8, causes a changes of A (variant “B“) into G (variant ”b”); BB (AA), Bb (AG), bb (GG),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0037">37</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S0003">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Date entry and data analysis were done using SPSS version 22 (Statistical Package for Social Science). Data were presented as number, percentage, mean, standard deviation. Chi-squared test and Fisher's Exact test were used to compare qualitative variables. Independent t-test (unpaired t-test) was used to compare quantitative variables between two different groups and ANOVA test for more than two groups.  Paired samples t-test was done to compare quantitative variables between before and after treatment within the same group. Pearson correlation was done to measure correlation between quantitative variables. <italic>P</italic>-value considered statistically significant when <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05. The studied SNPs were followed the Hardy–Weinberg (HW) equation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0038">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0039">39</xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0004">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The present study included 50 children with T1DM, 24 males and 26 females, with a mean age of 11.16 years ±3.27 SD and a mean BMI of 17.50±3.24 SD. They were comparable to 50 healthy age, sex and BMI-matched children who were selected as controls; the control children (25 males and 25 females) had a mean age of 10.97 years ±2.77 SD and a mean BMI of 17.32±2.92 SD, which were not significantly different from those of the included cases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0002">Table 2</xref>)<table-wrap id="T0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Demographic, clinical and biochemical characteristics of the study groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cases<break></break>(N=50)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Controls<break></break>(N=50)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold> N, (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">0.841</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (48.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (52.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold> (years, mean ±SD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.16±3.27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.97±2.77</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.782</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age at onset</bold>: (years, mean ±SD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.00±3.09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Duration of T1DM</bold><break></break>(years, mean±SD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.20±3.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Family history of T1DM</bold>, N, (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (32.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (68.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Weight</bold> (kg, mean ±SD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.70±13.56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.07±12.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.105</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Height</bold> (cm, mean ±SD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">132.16±19.91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">139.92±14.61</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.060</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI</bold> (kg/m<sup>2</sup>mean ±SD)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.50±3.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.32±2.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.694</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Frequency of diabetic complications</bold> N, (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (50.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (50.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Type of complications</bold> N, (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•History of DKA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (44.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Neuropathy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (16.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Nephropathy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (20.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Retinopathy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (8.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Pubertal delay</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (14.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>HbA1c</bold>, %, mean ±SD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.72±2.22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.20±0.94</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Glycemic control</bold> N., (%)<break></break>•Good (HbA1c≤8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (20.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (100.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Poor (HbA1c &gt;8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (80.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Serum 25(OH)D<sub>3</sub></bold> ng/ml, mean ±SD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.46±10.50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.03±2.46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Serum vitamin D status</bold> N, (%)<break></break>•Deficient &lt;20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (68.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">•Insufficient 20 – &lt;30<break></break>•Sufficient ≥30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (16.0%)<break></break>8 (16.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)<break></break>50 (100.0%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> *Significant <italic>P</italic>-value (<italic>P</italic>˂0.05).</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> T1DM, type 1 diabetes mellitus; BMI, body mass index; DKA, diabetic ketoacidosis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
<p>Positive family history of T1DM was present in 16% of cases, while diabetic complications were frequent in 50% of the included patients with the highest frequency was for history of DKA (44%) and diabetic retinopathy was the less frequent complication (8%). Poor glycemic control was frequent in 80% of the included cases, and optimal serum vitamin D level was present in only 16% of patients with 68% of them had vitamin D deficiency and 16% had insufficient vitamin D status (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<p>Regarding mean ±SD of HbA1c and serum vitamin D among T1DM children in relation to glycemic control, vitamin D status, occurrence of diabetic complications and effect of vitamin D therapy, there was significantly lower (mean ±SD) serum vitamin D among T1DM with poor glycemic control (11.46±8.95 ng/ml) versus those with good glycemic control (21.48±12.80 ng/ml), also patients with diabetic complications exhibited significantly lower vitamin D serum levels (7.97±5.82 ng/ml) than those without diabetic complications (18.95±11.34 ng/ml). There was significantly higher HbA1c level (11.13±2.07%) among T1DM who have decreased vitamin D levels (mean insulin dose was 1.25 U/kg ±0.43), with nonsignificant difference between the vitamin D deficient and insufficient subgroups, when compared with those having normal level of vitamin D (8.56±1.75%), (mean insulin dose was 0.90 U/kg ±0.24), with <italic>P</italic> ˂0.05 for all (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0003">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap id="T0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mean ±SD of HbA1c and serum vitamin D among T1DM children in relation to glycemic control, vitamin D status, occurrence of diabetic complications and effect of vitamin D therapy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1DM patients (total N=50)/variables</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HbA1c (%, mean±SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serum 25(OH)D<sub>3</sub> (ng/ml, mean±SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Glycemic control</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good glycemic control (N=10)<break></break>Poor glycemic control (N=40)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.15±1.7<break></break>10.07±4.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.48±12.80<break></break>11.46±8.95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.015*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Vitamin D status</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Optimal (N=8)<break></break>Decreased (N=42)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.56±1.75<break></break>11.13±2.07</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.37±2.03<break></break>13.46±10.50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>T1DM complication</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1DM with complication (N=25)<break></break>T1DM without complication (N=25)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.20±1.19<break></break>9.25±2.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.97±5.82<break></break>18.95±11.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Effect of vitamin D therapy</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pretherapy levels (N=42)<break></break>Post-therapy levels (N=42)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.72±2.22<break></break>8.83±1.58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.46±10.50<break></break>38.70±13.56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> *Significant <italic>P</italic>-value (<italic>P</italic>˂0.05).</p><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> T1DM, type 1 diabetes mellitus.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
<p>Patients with low vitamin D and received vitamin D replacement therapy (N=42, 36 of them (85.7%) have poor glycemic control) exhibited significant decrease in their mean HbA1c % (pre-therapy =10.72±2.22% versus post-therapy =8.83±1.58%, with nonsignificant difference between the vitamin D deficient and insufficient subgroups) with significant improvement in their vitamin D serum levels (pre-therapy =13.46±10.50 ng/mL versus post-therapy=38.70±13.56 ng/mL, with nonsignificant difference between the vitamin D deficient and insufficient subgroups), with <italic>P</italic>˂0.05 for all (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0003">Table 3</xref>). Regarding vitamin D status in those patients, 36 out of 42 patients (85.7%) became sufficient after 3 months of vitamin D replacement therapy; 11 out of 36 (30.5%) exhibited good glycemic control after co-therapy with vitamin D.</p>
<p>Regarding to the correlations between serum 25(OH)D levels and some variables among patients‘ group, there were significantly negative correlations between serum levels of vitamin D with both HbA1c % (r= –0.358, <italic>P</italic>=0.011) and daily insulin requirement (r=−0.473, <italic>P</italic>=0.001), with nonsignificant correlations with BMI, age at onset or duration of DM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>).<fig fig-type="figure" id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Negative correlations between serum vitamin D with both HbA1c (<bold>A</bold>), and insulin dose requirements (<bold>B</bold>).</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="DMSO-12-703-g0004"></graphic></fig></p>
<p>The allelic and genotype frequencies of the VDR gene at <italic>Apa</italic>I, <italic>Taq</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>I polymorphic sites were evaluated in T1DM patients in comparison to the controls and were presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T0004">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>. Regarding to the genetic analysis, the frequencies of <italic>Apa</italic>I genotypes determined from T1DM children were 48% for AA and 52% for (Aa + aa), while in controls, the frequency of AA and Aa + aa were present in a percentage of 74% and 26% respectively, with significantly higher allelic frequency for (a) among patients vs controls (30% and 13% respectively) and significantly higher frequency for A allele among the controls vs the patients group (87% and 70%). This indicated that <italic>Apa</italic>I polymorphism is associated with an increased risk of T1DM (AA vs (Aa + aa): OR: 3.08; 95%CI: 1.33–7.15, <italic>P</italic>=0.008) also, A vs a (OR: 2.87; 95%CI: 1.39–5.91, <italic>P</italic>=0.003). For <italic>Bsm</italic>I geneotypic frequencies, BB and (Bb + bb) were 16% and 84% respectively among T1DM while among the controls were 64% and 36% respectively, with significantly higher allelic frequency for (b) among T1DM vs the control group (49% and 18% respectively) together with significantly higher frequency for B allele among controls vs patients (82% and 51% respectively). Thus, Bb and bb genotypes, and b allele making the population at risk of T1DM development (BB vs (Bb+bb): OR: 9.33; 95%CI: 3.61–24.17, <italic>P</italic>=0.000; B vs.b (OR: 4.38; 95%CI: 2.30–8.33, <italic>P</italic>=0.000), (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0004">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>).<table-wrap id="T0004" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Genotypes and alleles frequencies of <italic>Apa</italic>I, <italic>Taq</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>I in T1DM patients in comparison to the controls</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study groups</th><th colspan="18" rowspan="1">Variables</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="14" rowspan="1"><italic>Apa</italic>I genotypes</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>Apa</italic>I alleles</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">AA</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Aa</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">aa</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">AA+Aa</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">aa</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">AA</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Aa+aa</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">A</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">a</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1DM (n=50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Controls<break></break>(n=50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value (χ <sup>2</sup>)</td><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">0.011*(9.09)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.117(4.17)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.008*(7.10)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.003* (8.56)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">3.08 (1.33-7.15)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">2.87 (1.39-5.91)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="14" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Taq</italic>I genotypes</bold></td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Taq</italic>I alleles</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>TT</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Tt</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>tt</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>TT+Tt</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>tt</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>TT</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Tt+tt</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>T</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>t</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1DM<break></break>(n=50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Controls<break></break>(n=50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value (χ <sup>2</sup>)</td><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">0.603 (0.27)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.603 (0.27)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.774 (0.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.92 (0.52-1.62)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="14" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Bsm</italic>I Ggenotypes</bold></td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Bsm</italic>I alleles</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>BB</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Bb</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>bb</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>BB+Bb</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>bb</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>BB</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Bb+bb</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>B</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>b</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1DM<break></break>(n=50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Controls<break></break>(n=50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value (χ <sup>2</sup>)</td><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">0.000*(26.85)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.012* (7.53)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.000* (24.00)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">0.000* (21.57)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95%CI)</td><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">--</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">9.33 (3.61-24.17)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">4.38 (2.30-8.33)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> *Significant <italic>P</italic>-value (<italic>P</italic>˂0.05).</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> T1DM, type 1 diabetes mellitus; χ<sup>2</sup>, chi-squared.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of vitamin D receptor <italic>Apa</italic>I and alleles (A and a) genotypes (<bold>A</bold>); <italic>Taq</italic>I (<bold>B</bold>); <italic>Bsm</italic>I (<bold>C</bold>) in patients with T1DM in comparison to the controls.</p><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> T1DM, type 1 diabetes mellitus.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="DMSO-12-703-g0005"></graphic></fig></p>
<p>As regards <italic>Taq</italic>I polymorphisms, our study did not show any frequency for TT, with nonsignificant difference in the genotypic frequency of (Tt+tt) or allelic frequency (T and t) among T1DM patients (100%, 42% and 58% respectively) when compared with the control group (100%, 40% and 60% respectively), <italic>P</italic>˃0.05 for all, (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0004">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<p>There were nonsignificant differences in the frequency of VDR polymorphisms among the patients group with regard to good or poor glycemic control, occurrence of complications and vitamin D status, mean ±SD of HbA1c and serum 25(OH)D, gender, family history and age at onset. Additionally, there were nonsignificant differences in the frequency of VDR polymorphisms in relation to the response to vitamin D replacement therapy using its effects on vitamin D and glycemic status among the patients' group, with <italic>P</italic> ˃0.05 for all.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0005">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The exact etiology and natural history of T1DM are still undetermined, although both genetics and environmental factors contribute to its development.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">40</xref> T1DM is considered as a T-cell mediated disease that completely destroys the body's ability to synthesize and secrete insulin associated with pancreatic β cells apoptosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0042">42</xref> Vitamin D plays an immune-modulatory effects in T1DM prevention,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0043">43</xref> as it decreases the proinflammatory cytokines expression involved in T1DM pathogenesis, thus pancreatic β cells became less prone to inflammation with subsequent reduction in T-cell recruitment and infiltration, and suppression of the autoimmune process with immune tolerance.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0044">44</xref></p>
<p>The findings of the current study regarding serum vitamin D among T1DM revealed that 84% of cases have abnormally low vitamin D status (vitamin D deficiency and insufficiency). This was in line with Abd-Allah et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0045">45</xref> who reported that 75% of T1DM exhibited vitamin D deficiency or insufficiency among Egyptian children with T1DM. Liu et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0046">46</xref> in their meta-analysis study suggested that low vitamin D level is associated with T1DM in children. Also, Rasoul et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0047"><sup>47</sup></xref> reported significant frequency of vitamin D insufficiency and deficiency among T1DM children and concluded that serum vitamin D status is a major contributor in T1DM prevalence among Kuwaiti children. Additionally, Liu et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0048">48</xref> and Alshawi et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0049">49</xref> both reported significantly lower 25(OH)D serum levels among children with T1DM in comparison with the controls. The immunomodulatory effects of vitamin D are well-known in preventing T1DM development proved by in vitro inhibition of apoptosis induced by cytokines in the pancreatic islets of humans.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref></p>
<p>The findings of the current study revealed more significantly decreased vitamin D levels among those having poor glycemic control. Additionally, T1DM children with low vitamin D serum levels required a higher daily insulin dose than those with normal levels of vitamin D. In agreement, Savastio et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0050">50</xref> reported significant higher insulin requirements and HbA1c among T1DM with vitamin D deficiency than those with normal vitamin D status.</p>
<p>Our results showed significantly lower vitamin D among children with T1DM who developed diabetic complications, in the form of recurrent DKA, diabetic neuropathy, diabetic nephropathy, diabetic retinopathy and pubertal delay, than those with uncomplicated T1DM. Vitamin D is essential for maintenance of normal renal podocyte health. Vitamin D insufficiency and deficiency may contribute to the pathogenesis of albuminuria and the progression of kidney disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0051">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0052">52</xref> In line with our findings, Peng and Li<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0053">53</xref> reported significant lower serum 25(OH)D in patients with diabetes with diabetic nephropathy (DN) compared with those without DN with significant negative correlation of serum 25(OH)D with albumin:creatinine ratio.</p>
<p>Also vitamin D plays a role in the pathogenesis of diabetic retinopathy as evidenced by its potent inhibitory effect on retinal neovascularization in mouse model with oxygen induced ischemic retinopathy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0054">54</xref> Since vitamin D receptors are extensively expressed in the retina.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0055">55</xref> In agreement with the current study findings, Inukai et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0056">56</xref> reported significant lower serum vitamin D in patients with diabetic retinopathy when compared with those without diabetic microangiopathy.</p>
<p>Luo et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0057">57</xref> in a meta-analysis study, concluded the presence of strong association between vitamin D deficiency and increased risk of diabetic nephropathy. Furthermore, vitamin D plays an essential promoter for secretion of nerve growth factor (NGF) which inturn regulates the sensitivity and phenotype of nociceptor fiberes, and its defective secretion results in clinical diabetic small nerve fiber neuropathy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0058">58</xref> Ozuguz et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0059">59</xref> reported significant positive correlation between serum NGF and vitamin D in T1DM patients with neuropathy, which confirms the mechanism of neuropathy in diabetic patients with vitamin D deficiency. In line with our results, Shillo et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0060">60</xref> suggested a possible role of vitamin D in the pathogenesis of diabetic neuropathy as evidenced in their study by reporting significant lower serum vitamin D levels in diabetic patients with peripheral neuropathy.</p>
<p>In addition, Huynh et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0061">61</xref> concluded that T1DM may disturb vitamin D metabolism among children or alternatively, vitamin D deficiency may contribute to risk of presentation with DKA as evidenced in their study by the presence of significant association between acidosis and low serum vitamin D. Also, Salvation et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0050">50</xref> reported a significant inverse correlation between vitamin D and DKA severity among T1DM.</p>
<p>Rodland et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0062">62</xref> reported altered regulatory mechanisms of vitamin D endocrine system among diabetic children at puberty with failure to attain an increase in the vitamin D normally seen during pubertal stages of maximal growth velocity confirming the involvement of vitamin D deficiency in occurrence of pubertal delay among T1DM children, which was consistent with our study results.</p>
<p>In our study, patients with low vitamin D and received vitamin D replacement therapy showed significant decrease in their HbA1c% with significant improvement in their vitamin D serum levels. In accordance, Savastio et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0050"><sup>50</sup></xref> Mohammadian et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0063">63</xref> Buhary et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0064">64</xref> Wierzbicka et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0065">65</xref> Giri et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0066">66</xref> Sharma et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0067">67</xref> Dehkordi et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0068">68</xref> Felício et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0069">69</xref> Deda,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0070">70</xref> noticed significant improvement in HbA1c% following vitamin D supplementation among these patients.</p>
<p>In the present study, there were significant negative correlations between serum levels of vitamin D with both HbA1c% and daily insulin requirement. These results were in agreement with many investigators,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0045">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0048">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0050">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0064">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0071">71</xref> and they reported an inverse correlation between serum 25(OH)D and HbA1c in T1DM patients with poor gylcemic control among diabetic patients having vitamin D deficiency. Moreover, Savastio et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0050">50</xref> reported significant negative correlation between vitamin D serum levels and daily insulin requirements among T1DM children. This suggests a mechanistic link between diabetes, vitamin D and diabetic complications. Vitamin D affects the insulin secretion and sensitivity and its deficiency may be linked to impaired glucose tolerance, diabetes predisposition and development.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0064">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0072">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0073">73</xref></p>
<p>VDRs have been demonstrated to be expressed in many tissues including pancreatic β cells, making vitamin D acts as a potential direct modulator for the response of insulin to high blood glucose and indirect action via calcium homeostasis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0074">74</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0076">76</xref> Genotype of VDR appeared to be an important determining factor in individual susceptibility of developing T1DM.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0077">77</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0078">78</xref></p>
<p>Notably, various studies have emerged recently to investigate possible association between VDR polymorphisms and T1DM, with conflicting results; some revealed significant associations, while, others failed to reach statistical significance.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0079">79</xref></p>
<p>The results of the current study revealed statistically significant association between <italic>Apa</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>I polymorphisms allele and genotypic distributions and an increased risk of T1DM with nonsignificant association found regarding <italic>Taq</italic>I polymorphism. In agreement, two meta-analysis studies<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0080">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0081">81</xref> reported significant association of <italic>Bsm</italic>I polymorphism with T1DM risk especially in East Asians, but with nonsignificant association for the other two polymorphisms. Lemos et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0082">82</xref> reported lack of association of any of the studied VDR-SNPS with susceptibility of T1DM in the Portuguese population. Similarly, Angel et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0034">34</xref> reported these findings among Chilean subjects. Mohammadnejad et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0083">83</xref> demonstrated that allele t was the risk allele for T1DM development among the Iranian population with nonsignificant associations between <italic>Apa</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>I SNPs and disease susceptibility. Bonakdaran et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0084">84</xref> reported significant higher genotype frequencies of both <italic>Apa</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>I in the patients group with nonsignificant difference regarding <italic>Taq</italic>I polymorphism between patients and controls in T1DM among children of the Khorasan Province, Islamic Republic of Iran. El-Kafoury et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0085">85</xref> reported nonsignificant difference for SNP <italic>Bsm</italic>I in their study which included 60 T1DM patients comparable with 60 controls recruited from the Diabetes Clinic, Alexandria University Children’s Hospital, Egypt. Abd-Allah et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0045">45</xref> reported that <italic>Bsm</italic>I Bb and bb genotypes were associated with T1DM risk with lack of association of VDR <italic>ApaI</italic> and <italic>Taq</italic>I polymorphisms with T1DM among sample of Egyptian children from Zagazig, Egypt. Cheon et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0086">86</xref> reported protective role of T and b <italic>Taq</italic>I and <italic>Bsm</italic>I against T1DM in the Korean population with nonsignificant difference regarding <italic>Apa</italic>I. Khalid et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref> suggested that <italic>Bsm</italic>I and <italic>Taq</italic>I SNPs confer T1DM susceptibility among Sudanese with nonsignificant difference regarding <italic>Apa</italic>I. Kandala and Abdul Ridha<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0087">87</xref> have concluded that VDR SNP <italic>Bsm</italic>I may have significant effect on the occurrence of T1DM in the Iraqi population. Mukhtar et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0088">88</xref> reported significant association of allelic and genotypic frequencies of <italic>Apa</italic>I with T1DM risk, while <italic>Taq</italic>I did not depict any association with T1DM at allelic or genotypic levels among Pakistanis. The differences between the involved studies could attribute to ethnic differences related to VDR polymorphisms distributions, geographic differences, other environmental and genetic factors involved in T1DM pathogenesis.</p>
<p>To the best of our knowledge, studies traced in the literature regarding the association of VDR polymorphisms with diabetic complications among children with T1DM or the onset of the disease, family history, or gender were scarce, The current study revealed lack of association of SNPs of VDR with diabetic complications or vitamin D status or glycemic control or the onset of the disease, or family history, or gender. This was in agreement with Bonakdaran et al,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0084">84</xref> who reported nonsignificant differences between the genotype frequencies and the onset pattern or chronic complications of T1DM. Nasreen et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref> reported nonsignificant association between VDR polymorphism and vitamin D levels.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0006">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>VDR polymorphisms could be considered as an important risk factor in T1DM development among Egyptian children. In addition, serum vitamin D level should be regularly screened in children with T1DM to add benefits to T1DM children with abnormally low vitamin D status from the therapeutic effects of vitamin D supplements in both glycemic controls and postponing diabetic complications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S0007">
<title>Limitations of the study</title>
<p>Lack of the long-term follow-up of T1DM children who have been received vitamin D supplements, regarding glycemic control and development of diabetic complications, which could be approached in further studies.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="S0008" sec-type="COI-statement">
<title>Disclosure</title>
<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CIT0001">
<label>1.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nasreen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lone</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khaliq</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serum vitamin D levels and gene polymorphisms (Fok1 and Apa1) in children with type I diabetes and healthy controls</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Pak Med Assoc</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1215</fpage>–<lpage>1220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27686292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0002">
<label>2.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lipton</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drum</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burnet</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obesity at the onset of diabetes in an ethnically diverse population of children: what doesit mean for epidemiologists and clinicians?</article-title>
<source/><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>e553</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15867020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0003">
<label>3.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Ziny</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salem</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Hawary</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epidemiology of childhood type 1 diabetes mellitus in Nile Delta, northern Egypt - a retrospective study</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Res Pediatr Endocrinol</italic>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24637304</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0004">
<label>4.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Panierakis</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goulielmos</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mamoulakis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms and susceptibility to type 1 diabetes in Crete Greece</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Clin Immunol</italic>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19734102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0005">
<label>5.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Uitterlinden</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Meurs</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genetics and biology of vitamin D receptor polymorphisms</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Gene</italic>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>338</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15315818</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0006">
<label>6.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hahn</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuttler</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathieu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>1, 25- Dihydroxyvitamin D3 reduced MHC-antigen expression on pancreatic β-cells in vitro</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Cell Transplant</italic>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0007">
<label>7.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Riachy</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vandewalle</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moerman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>1, 25-Dihydroxyvitamin D3 protects human pancreatic islets against cytokine-induced apoptosis via down-regulation of the Fas receptor</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Apoptosis</italic>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16502254</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0008">
<label>8.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Etten</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verliden</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giulietti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The vitamin D receptor gene FokI polymorphism: functional impact on the immune system</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Immunol</italic>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17274004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0009">
<label>9.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khalid</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms in Sudanese children with type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">AIMS Genet</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0010">
<label>10.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miyamoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kesterson</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamamoto</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Structural organization of the human vitamin D receptor chromosomal gene and its promoter</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Mol Endocrinol</italic>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1165</fpage>–<lpage>1179</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9212063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0011">
<label>11.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor gene polymorphism influences susceptibility to type 1 diabetes mellitus in the Taiwanese population</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Clin Endocrinol</italic>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0012">
<label>12.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Audí</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martí</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esteban</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>VDR gene polymorphism at exon 2 start codon (FokI) may have influenced type 1 diabetes mellitus susceptibility in two Spanish populations</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabet Med</italic>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15049946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0013">
<label>13.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Capoluongo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pitocco</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Concolino</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Slight association between type 1 diabetes and “ff” VDR FokI genotype in patients from the Italian Lazio Region. Lack of association with diabetes complications</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Clin Biochem</italic>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>888</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16806146</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0014">
<label>14.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab>. <article-title>Diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0015">
<label>15.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pearce</surname>
<given-names>SHS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheetham</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of vitamin D deficiency</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Br Med J</italic>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>340</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0016">
<label>16.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huh</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency in children and adolescents: epidemiology, impact and treatment</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Rev Endocr Metab Disord</italic>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18175220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0017">
<label>17.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Aljabri KS, Bokhari SA, Khan MJ.</collab>
<article-title>Glycemic changes after vitamin D supplementation in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and vitamin D deficiency</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Ann Saudi Med</italic>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21060157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0018">
<label>18.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hafez</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Musa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D status in Egyptian children with type 1 diabetes and the role of vitamin D replacement in glycemic control</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27997353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0019">
<label>19.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rusińska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Płudowski</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walczak</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D supplementation guidelines for general population and groups at risk of vitamin D deficiency in poland-recommendations of the polish society of pediatric endocrinology and diabetes and the expert panel with participation of national specialist consultants and representatives of scientific societies-2018 update</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29904370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0020">
<label>20.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>DIAMOND project Group</collab>. <article-title>Incidence and trends of childhood type 1 diabetes worldwide 1990-1999</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabet Med</italic>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>857</fpage>–<lpage>866</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0021">
<label>21.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Danne</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillip</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buckingham</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>ISPAD clinical practice consensus guidelines 2018: insulin treatment in children and adolescents with diabetes</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Diabetes</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29999222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0022">
<label>22.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wolfsdorf</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allgrove</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Craig</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, et al.; <collab>ISPAD Clinical Practice Consensus Guidelines 2014 Compendium; Diabetic ketoacidosis and hyperglycemic hyperosmolar state</collab>. <article-title>A consensus statement from the international society for pediatric and adolescent diabetes: diabetic ketoacidosis and hyperglycemic hyperosmolar state</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Diabetes</italic>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25041509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0023">
<label>23.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Egyptian growth curves</collab>. <article-title>Diabetes endocrine metabolism pediatric unit Cairo University Children’s Hospital</article-title>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dempuegypt.blogspot.com">http://dempuegypt.blogspot.com</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>8</month><day>13</day>, 2012</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0024">
<label>24.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Busiah</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belien</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dallot</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnosis of delayed puberty</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Arch Pediatr</italic>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1101</fpage>–<lpage>1110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17658248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0025">
<label>25.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Glastras</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohsin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donaghu</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Complications of diabetes mellitus in childhood</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Clin North</italic>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1735</fpage>–<lpage>1753</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0026">
<label>26.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Demirel</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tepe</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kara</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Microvascular complications in adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Res Pediatr Endocrinol</italic>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24072081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0027">
<label>27.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ting</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Factors associated with diabetic nephropathy in children, adolescents, and adults with type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Formos Med Assoc</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>924</fpage>–<lpage>932</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfma.2017.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29070437</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0028">
<label>28.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hasani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khosrawi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashemipour</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and related risk-factors of peripheral neuropathy in children with insulin- dependent diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Res Med Sci</italic>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23914216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0029">
<label>29.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalenceof vitamin D deficiency in patients with lumbar spinal stenosis and its relationship with pain</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Pain Physician</italic>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23511683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0030">
<label>30.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Desoky</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fayed</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biochemical assessments of thyroid profile, serum 25-hydroxycholecalciferol and cluster of differentiation 5 expression levels among children with autism</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2397</fpage>–<lpage>2403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28979127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0031">
<label>31.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Taieb</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>25-Hydroxy cholecalciferol, anti-Müllerian hormone, and thyroid profiles among infertile men</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Aging Male</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13685538.2018.1538338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29394114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0032">
<label>32.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abd-Elmaged</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nada</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lesional and circulating levels of interleukin-17 and 25-hydroxycholecalciferol in active acne vulgaris: correlation to disease severity</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Cosmet Dermatol</italic>. <year>2018</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jocd.12715</pub-id> [<comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment>].</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0033">
<label>33.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pani</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knapp</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donner</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor allele combinations influence genetic susceptibility to type 1 diabetes in Germans</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10868975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0034">
<label>34.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Angel</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santos</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrasco</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor polymorphism and susceptibility to type 1 diabetes in Chilean subjects: a case-parent study</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Epidemiol</italic>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1085</fpage>–<lpage>1087</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15678787</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0035">
<label>35.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Faraco</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morrison</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>ApaI dimorphism at the human vitamin D receptor gene locus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>2150</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2564666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0036">
<label>36.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morrison</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tokita</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prediction of bone density from vitamin D receptor alleles</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>367</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8161378</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0037">
<label>37.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morrison</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeoman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Contribution of trans-acting factor alleles to normal physiological variability: vitamin D receptor gene polymorphism and circulating osteocalcin</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>6665</fpage>–<lpage>6669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1353882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0038">
<label>38.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hardy</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mendelian proportions in a mixed population</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic>. <year>1908</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17779291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0039">
<label>39.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stark</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A clarification of the Hardy-Weinberg law</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Genetics</italic>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>1695</fpage>–<lpage>1697</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16702429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0040">
<label>40.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Banin</surname>
<given-names>PF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rimondi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Togni</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Type 1 diabetes (T1DM) in children and adolescents of immigrated families in Emilia-Romagna (Italy)</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Acta Biomed</italic>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20857851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0041">
<label>41.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cnop</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Welsh</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jonas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mechanisms of pancreatic beta-cell death in type 1 and type 2 diabetes: many differences, few similarities</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0042">
<label>42.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>American Diabetes A</collab>. <article-title>Diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23959568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0043">
<label>43.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van Etten</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathieu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Immunoregulation by 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3: basic concepts</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</italic>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0044">
<label>44.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elsayed</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohamed</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency and its correlation to hemoglobin A1C in adolescent and young adult type 1 diabetes mellitus patients</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Aamj</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0045">
<label>45.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abd-Allah</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pasha</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagrass</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin d status and vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms and susceptibility to type 1 diabetes in Egyptian children</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Gene</italic>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>536</volume>:<fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24370753</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0046">
<label>46.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Correlation of serum vitamin d level with type 1 diabetes mellitus in children: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Nutr Hosp</italic>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1591</fpage>–<lpage>1594</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26545522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0047">
<label>47.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rasoul</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Mahdi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Kandari</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Low serum vitamin-D status is associated with high prevalence and early onset of type-1 diabetes mellitus in Kuwaiti children</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pediatr</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27422640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0048">
<label>48.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Serum vitamin D deficiency in children and adolescents is associated with type 1 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Endocr Connect</italic>. <year>2018</year>. Epub 2011 Oct 1.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0049">
<label>49.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alshawi</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Agha</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Althibiti</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical presentations, glycemic control, complications, and associated autoimmune diseases among children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes in the western region of Saudi Arabia</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Curr Pediatr Res</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0050">
<label>50.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Savastio</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cadario</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Genoni</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency and glycemic status in children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0162554</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27607348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0051">
<label>51.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Boer</surname>
<given-names>IH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ioannou</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kestenbaum</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>25-Hydroxyvitamin D levels and albuminuria in the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES III)</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Am J Kidney Dis</italic>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17591526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0052">
<label>52.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Renoprotective role of the vitamin D receptor in diabetic nephropathy</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Kidney Int</italic>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17928826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0053">
<label>53.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D level and diabetic nephropathy in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Int Urol Nephrol</italic>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>983</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25902763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0054">
<label>54.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Albert</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheef</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Calcitriol is a potent inhibitor of retinal neovascularization.</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Investig Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>2327</fpage>–<lpage>2334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17460298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0055">
<label>55.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taverna</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Selam</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slama</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between a protein polymorphism in the start codon of the vitamin D receptor gene and severe diabetic retinopathy in C-peptide-negative type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>4803</fpage>–<lpage>4808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15899948</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0056">
<label>56.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Inukai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fujiwara</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tayama</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Alterations in serum levels of 1 alpha, 25(OH)2 D3 and osteocalcin in patients with early diabetic nephropathy</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Res Clin Pract</italic>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9347246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0057">
<label>57.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between vitamin D deficiency and diabetic retinopathy in type 2 diabetes: a meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Nutrients</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<page-range>pii: E307</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu9030307</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0058">
<label>58.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Anand</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Terenghi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warner</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The role of endogenous nerve growth factor in human diabetic neuropathy</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Nat Med</italic>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8640566</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0059">
<label>59.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ozuguz</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oruc</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ulu</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does vitamin D have any role in the improvement of diabetic peripheral neuropathy in type 1 diabetic patients?</article-title>
<source/><italic toggle="yes">J Endocrinol Invest</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1411</fpage>–<lpage>1417</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27436228</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0060">
<label>60.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shillo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Selvarajah</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greig</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reduced vitamin D levels in painful diabetic peripheral neuropathy</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabet Med</italic>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30102801</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0061">
<label>61.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greer</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nyunt</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between ketoacidosis and 25(OH)-vitamin D levels at presentation in children with type 1 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Diabetes</italic>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18761649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0062">
<label>62.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rødland</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markestad</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aksnes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Plasma concentrations of vitamin D metabolites during puberty of diabetic children</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetologia</italic>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3877653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0063">
<label>63.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mohammadian</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fatahi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaeri</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of vitamin d3 supplement in glycemic control of pediatrics with type 1 diabetes mellitus and vitamin d deficiency</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Diagn Res</italic>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0064">
<label>64.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buhary</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almohareb</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aljohani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of glycosylated hemoglobin levels with vitamin D status</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med Res</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1018</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29163736</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0065">
<label>65.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wierzbicka</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szalecki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pludowski</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D status, body composition and glycemic control in Polish adolescents with type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Minerva Endocrinol</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26982098</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0066">
<label>66.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Giri</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pintus</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burnside</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treating vitamin D deficiency in children with type I diabetes could improve their glycaemic control</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">BMC Res Notes</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28882195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0067">
<label>67.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biswal</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bethou</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does vitamin D supplementation improve glycaemic control in children with type 1 diabetes mellitus? - A randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Diagn Res</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0068">
<label>68.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dehkordi</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dehkordi</surname>
<given-names>VH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fatemi</surname>
<given-names>SMR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of vitamin D supplement therapy on HbA1C and IGF1 levels in children with type 1 diabetes mellitus and vitamin D deficiency</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Electron J Gen Med</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>em69</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0069">
<label>69.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Felício</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Souza</surname>
<given-names>ACCB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neto</surname>
<given-names>JFA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Glycemic variability and insulin needs in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus supplemented with vitamin D: a pilot study using continuous glucose monitoring system</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Curr Diabetes Rev</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28618984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0070">
<label>70.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deda</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeshayahu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Improvements in peripheral vascular function with vitamin D treatment in deficient adolescents with type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Diabetes</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29063654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0071">
<label>71.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Desy Wulandari</surname>
<given-names>HAC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Widjajanto</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Puryatni</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Low levels of vitamin D correlate with hemoglobin A1c and interleukin-10 levels in pediatric type 1 diabetes mellitus patients</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">J Trop Life Sci</italic>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0072">
<label>72.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hutchinson</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Figenschau</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Njolstad</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels are inversely associated with glycated haemoglobin (HbA(1c)). The Tromso Study</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Clin Lab Invest</italic>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21517716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0073">
<label>73.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pittas</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitri</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Plasma 25-hydroxyvitamin D and progression to diabetes in patients at risk for diabetes: an ancillary analysis in the Diabetes Prevention Program</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22323410</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0074">
<label>74.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Forouhi</surname>
<given-names>NG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Baseline serum 25- hydroxy vitamin D3 is predictive of future glycemic status and insulin resistance: the Medical Research Council Ely Prospective Study 1990–2000</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>2619</fpage>–<lpage>2625</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18591391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0075">
<label>75.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeLuca</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Where is the vitamin D receptor?</article-title>
<source/><italic toggle="yes">Arch Biochem Biophys</italic>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>523</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22503810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0076">
<label>76.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kanakaraju</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ranganathan</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shankar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlation of vitamin D3 levels and the blood sugar parameters among the patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Int J Contemp Med Res</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>847</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0077">
<label>77.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ban</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taniyama</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yanagawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor initiation codon polymorphism influences genetic susceptibility to type 1 diabetes mellitus in the Japanese population</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">BMC Med Genet</italic>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11445000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0078">
<label>78.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nejentsev</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godfrey</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Analysis of the vitamin D receptor gene sequence variants in type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>2709</fpage>–<lpage>2712</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15448105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0079">
<label>79.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lopera</surname>
<given-names>NG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toro</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>VDR gene haplotypes associate with type 1 diabetes and suggest interaction with HLA, IL2RA and CTLA4 loci in Colombian Families</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Curr Res Diabetes Obes J</italic>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>555688</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19080/CRDOJ.2018.06.555688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0080">
<label>80.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reilly</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quantitative assessment of the associations between four polymorphisms (FokI, ApaI, BsmI, TaqI) of vitamin D receptor gene and risk of diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Mol Biol Rep</italic>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>9405</fpage>–<lpage>9414</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22814767</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0081">
<label>81.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between two polymorphisms (FokI and BsmI) of vitamin D receptor gene and type 1 diabetes mellitus in Asian population: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e89325</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24603699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0082">
<label>82.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lemos</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fagulha</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coutinho</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lack of association of vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms with susceptibility to type 1 diabetes mellitus in the Portuguese population</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Hum Immunol</italic>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18361940</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0083">
<label>83.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mohammadnejad</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghanbari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ganjali</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms and type 1 diabetes mellitus in Iranian population</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Mol Biol Rep</italic>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>831</fpage>–<lpage>837</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21584699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0084">
<label>84.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bonakdaran</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbaszadegan</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dadkhah</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms in type 1 diabetes mellitus: a new pattern from Khorasan Province, Islamic Republic of Iran</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">East Mediterr Health J</italic>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22888618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0085">
<label>85.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Kafoury</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haroun</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Embaby</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association of polymorphic sites in some genes with type 1 diabetes mellitus in a sample of Egyptian children</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Egypt J Med Hum Genet</italic>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0086">
<label>86.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheon</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nam</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms and type 1 diabetes mellitus in a Korean population</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Int</italic>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>870</fpage>–<lpage>874</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25808747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0087">
<label>87.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kandala</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdul Ridha</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of genetic polymorphisms in a sample of Iraqi patients with type1 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Int J Curr Microbiol Appl Sci</italic>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CIT0088">
<label>88.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mukhtar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Batool</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wajid</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms influence T1D susceptibility among Pakistanis</article-title>. <source/><italic toggle="yes">Int J Genom</italic>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/4171254</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>