<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101280339</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">33033</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Res</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Translational research : the journal of laboratory and clinical medicine</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1931-5244</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1878-1810</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30904443</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6527448</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trsl.2019.02.012</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1023638</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Epigenetic therapy of Prader–Willi syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>KIM</surname>
<given-names>YUNA</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>WANG</surname>
<given-names>SUNG EUN</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>JIANG</surname>
<given-names>YONG-HUI</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Department of Pediatrics, Duke University of School of Medicine, Durham, North Carolina; Department of Neurobiology, Duke University of School of Medicine, Durham, North Carolina; Department of Program in Genetics and Genomics, Duke University of School of Medicine, Durham, North Carolina; Department of Program in Cellular and Molecular Biology, Duke University of School of Medicine, Durham, North Carolina.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">Reprint requests: Yong-hui Jiang, Division of Medical Genetics, Department of Pediatrics and Neurobiology, Duke University School of Medicine, GSRB1 4004, 905 S. LaSalle St, Durham, NC 27710. <email>yong-hui.jiang@duke.edu</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>17</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>05</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>208</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>118</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.trsl.2019.02.012-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Prader–Willi syndrome (PWS) is a complex and multisystem neurobehavioral disorder. The molecular mechanism of PWS is deficiency of paternally expressed genes from the chromosome 15q11-q13. Due to imprinted gene regulation, the same genes in the maternal chromosome 15q11-q13 are structurally intact but transcriptionally repressed by an epigenetic mechanism. The unique molecular defect underlying PWS renders an exciting opportunity to explore epigenetic-based therapy to reactivate the expression of repressed PWS genes from the maternal chromosome. Inactivation of H3K9m3 methyltransferase SETDB1 and zinc finger protein ZNF274 results in reactivation of <italic>SNRPN</italic> and <italic>SNORD116</italic> cluster from the maternal chromosomes in PWS patient iPSCs and iPSC-derived neurons, respectively. High content screening of small molecule libraries using cells derived from transgenic mice carrying the SNRPN-GFP fusion protein has discovered that inhibitors of EHMT2/G9a, a histone 3 lysine 9 methyltransferase, are capable of reactivating expression of paternally expressed <italic>SNRPN</italic> and <italic>SNORD116</italic> from the maternal chromosome, both in cultured PWS patient-derived fibroblasts and in PWS mouse models. Treatment with an EMHT2/G9a inhibitor also rescues perinatal lethality and failure to thrive phenotypes in a PWS mouse model. These findings present the first evidence to support a proof-of-principle for epigenetic-based therapy for the PWS in humans.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>