<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9100095</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">8509</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Cell Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Cell. Neurosci.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Molecular and cellular neurosciences</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1044-7431</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9327</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26655799</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6535231</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2015.12.002</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS749240</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Modeling synaptogenesis in Schizophrenia and Autism using human iPSC derived neurons</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Habela</surname>
<given-names>Christa W.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Hongjun</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ming</surname>
<given-names>Guo-li</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute for Cell Engineering, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA.</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA.</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>The Solomon Snyder Department of Neuroscience, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA.</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA.</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">Correspondence should be addressed to: Christa Habela, M.D. &amp; Ph.D., Department of Neurology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, 733 N. Broadway, MRB 706, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA, <email>chabela1@jhmi.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>24</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>02</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>26</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>52</fpage>
<lpage>62</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.mcn.2015.12.002-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Schizophrenia (SCZ) and autism spectrum disorder (ASD) are genetically and phenotypically complex disorders of neural development. Human genetic studies, as well as studies examining structural changes at the cellular level, have converged on glutamatergic synapse formation, function, and maintenance as common pathophysiologic substrates involved in both disorders. Synapses as basic functional units of the brain are continuously modified by experience throughout life, therefore they are particularly attractive candidates for targeted therapy. Until recently we lacked a system to evaluate dynamic changes that lead to synaptic abnormalities. With the development of techniques to generate induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) from patients, we are now able to study neuronal and synaptic development in cells from individual patients in the context of genetic changes conferring disease susceptibility. In this review, we discuss recent studies focusing on neural cells differentiated from SCZ and ASD patient iPSCs. These studies support a central role for glutamatergic synapse formation and function in both disorders and demonstrate that iPSC derived neurons offer a potential system for further evaluation of processes leading to synaptic dysregulation and for the design and screening of future therapies.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>