<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8910645</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">20550</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dev Psychopathol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dev. Psychopathol.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Development and psychopathology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-5794</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1469-2198</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30009717</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6540979</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0954579418000718</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1029283</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Proopiomelanocortin (POMC) sequencing and developmental delay: Preliminary evidence for a SNP in the 3’ UTR region of the <italic>POMC</italic> gene—Possible relevance for biological risk and self-injurious behavior</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>DAMEROW</surname>
<given-names>JOHN A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>TERVO</surname>
<given-names>RAYMOND C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>EHRHARDT</surname>
<given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>PANOSKALTSIS-MORTARI</surname>
<given-names>ANGELA</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>SYMONS</surname>
<given-names>FRANK J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>a</label>University of Minnesota</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Mayo Clinic</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Gillette Children’s Specialty Healthcare</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">Address correspondence and reprint requests to: Frank Symons, Department of Educational Psychology, Educational Sciences Building, 56 River Road, College of Education and Human Development, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN 55455; <email>Symon007@UMN.edu</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>15</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>16</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>29</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>433</fpage>
<lpage>438</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1017/S0954579418000718-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">The proopiomelanocortin (POMC) molecule has been implicated in models of self-injurious behavior (SIB) in neurodevelopmental disorders, but it has never been specifically sequenced in search of base specific polymorphisms. The empirical focus of this preliminary study was to sequence the <italic>POMC</italic> gene in 11 children (mean age = 41.8 months, range = 12–60 months; 73% male) with clinical concerns regarding global developmental delay, 5 with reported self-injury. Genomic DNA was extracted from blood samples, and the <italic>POMC</italic> gene was amplified by specific oligonucleotide primers via polymerase chain reaction. The amplified gene products were sequenced by the University of Minnesota Genomic Center, and the results were analyzed using Sequencher software. A single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP), 1130 C&gt;T, was found in the 3’ untranslated region (UTR) of two samples (one of whom had SIB). The program TargetScanHuman was used to predict the function of this mutation. Variant c.1130 C&lt;T was predicted to be located in the target site of two microRNAs (miRNAs; hsa-mir-3715 and hsa-mir-1909), and the variant allele T may result in an increased minimum free energy for the two miRNAs. Further work with much larger samples is needed to continue the investigation of <italic>POMC</italic>’s possible function as a risk factor for the development of SIB in children with developmental delay/disability. The findings presented in this study show that the SNP found in the 3’ UTR could alter the binding of miRNAs to <italic>POMC</italic> 3’UTR, thus, increasing <italic>POMC</italic> expression and affecting several biological systems with high relevance to the biology of self-injury. There was a significant difference in β-endorphin levels between SIB (<italic>M =</italic> 169.25 pg/mL) and no SIB (<italic>M =</italic> 273.5 pg/mL, <italic>SD =</italic> 15.2) cases ( <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). Intervention implications are tied to prior observations of individual differences among SIB responders and nonresponders to treatment with the opioid antagonist naltrexone. Stratifying individuals with SIB by <italic>POMC</italic> mutation status may provide a potential tailoring-like variable to guide the selection of who is more (or less) likely to respond to opiate antagonist treatment. Currently, opioid antagonistic treatment for SIB is empiric (trial and error).</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>