<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cold Spring Harb Mol Case Stud</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cold Spring Harb Mol Case Stud</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">cshmcs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">cshmcs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cshmcs</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Cold Spring Harbor Molecular Case Studies</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2373-2873</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30622101</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6549549</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/mcs.a003608</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="medline">MCS003608Mur</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Xia–Gibbs syndrome in adulthood: a case report with insight into the natural history of the condition</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Xia–Gibbs syndrome in adulthood</alt-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Xia–Gibbs syndrome in adulthood</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murdock</surname>
<given-names>David R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Yunyun</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wangler</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Khayat</surname>
<given-names>Michael M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sabo</surname>
<given-names>Aniko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Juusola</surname>
<given-names>Jane</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McWalter</surname>
<given-names>Kirsty</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schatz</surname>
<given-names>Krista Sondergaard</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gunay-Aygun</surname>
<given-names>Meral</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gibbs</surname>
<given-names>Richard A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="af1"><label>1</label>Human Genome Sequencing Center, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas 77030, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af2"><label>2</label>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas 77030, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af3"><label>3</label>Texas Children's Hospital, Houston, Texas 77030, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af4"><label>4</label>GeneDx, Gaithersburg, Maryland 20877, USA;</aff>
<aff id="af5"><label>5</label>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, Institute of Genetic Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland 21287, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp>Corresponding author: <email>agibbs@bcm.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>a003608</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>17</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>3</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molecularcasestudies.cshlp.org/site/misc/terms.xhtml">© 2019 Murdock et al.; Published by Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</ext-link>
</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License</ext-link>, which permits reuse and redistribution, except for commercial purposes, provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="MCS003608Mur.pdf"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>A 55-yr-old male with severe intellectual disability, behavioral problems, kyphoscoliosis, and dysmorphic features was referred for a genetic evaluation. Chromosomal microarray, RASopathy gene panel, mitochondrial sequencing, and fragile X testing were all negative. Subsequent whole-exome sequencing revealed a heterozygous, truncating variant in the <italic>AHDC1</italic> gene, consistent with a diagnosis of Xia–Gibbs syndrome (XGS). Review of his clinical history showed many classic dysmorphic and clinical features of XGS, but no major health issues in adulthood other than intellectual disability. This individual is the oldest published XGS case to date, demonstrates the wide phenotypic spectrum of the disorder, and provides information on the condition's natural history. As more adults undergo genomic studies, we will continue to learn about the adult phenotypes of genetic conditions typically diagnosed in the pediatric setting.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>intellectual disability, severe</kwd>
<kwd>severe global developmental delay</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="funding-1">
<funding-source>Baylor-Hopkins Center for Mendelian Genomics</funding-source>
<award-id>HG006542</award-id>
</award-group>
<award-group id="funding-2">
<funding-source>Texas Institute for Advanced Studies</funding-source>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<page-count count="9"></page-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>De novo truncating variants in the AT-hook DNA-binding motif-containing 1 (<italic>AHDC1</italic>) gene cause autosomal dominant Xia–Gibbs syndrome (XGS: MIM 615829) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC17">Xia et al. 2014</xref>). XGS is a multisystemic disorder characterized by significant intellectual disability. Affected individuals may also have hypotonia, dysmorphic features, seizures, and brain anomalies among other findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC19">Yang et al. 2015</xref>). Approximately 100 patients worldwide have been identified with XGS, nearly all of them in the pediatric age range and the oldest being 29 yr of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC4">García-Acero and Acosta 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC12">Popp et al. 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC5">Jiang et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC15">Ritter et al. 2018</xref>). To date, genomic scale sequencing has been widely adopted in the pediatric setting, where it has demonstrated a diagnostic rate of ∼25% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC18">Yang et al. 2014</xref>). Despite examples of its benefit in older patients, it remains underutilized as a diagnostic tool in adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC13">Posey et al. 2016</xref>). Here we describe the use of whole-exome sequencing (WES) to diagnose an adult male with intellectual disability and further define the natural history of XGS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2" sec-type="results">
<title>RESULTS</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Clinical Presentation and Family History</title>
<p>The major clinical features of this individual are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="MCS003608MURTB1">Table 1</xref>. Prenatal and early-childhood information is unavailable for the individual, except that he failed to meet developmental milestones for walking and speech. His first words occurred around 2 yr of age and he did not have the ability to speak in short sentences until after age 5 yr. His family describes his language issues as that of a person for whom “English is a second language, but they don't have a first language.” Other than a hernia operation at 2 mo of age, there were no severe childhood illnesses or surgeries until the age of 13 yr when he had his first grand mal seizure. He was treated with antiseizure medication (phenobarbital, ethotoin) until the age of 40 yr and has had no recurrence since stopping treatment. Other neurological symptoms include occasional severe frontal lobe headaches and hand tremors. He has an ataxic gait with poor balance. He is able to walk independently on flat ground but requires assistance if the ground is uneven. Brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at age 52 yr was unremarkable except for generalized brain atrophy. Hearing and ophthalmologic exams have been normal.</p>
<table-wrap id="MCS003608MURTB1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Clinical features of this individual compared to previously described Xia–Gibbs syndrome (XGS) cases</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1"/>
<col align="left" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGS features</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Present in this case</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Common</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Developmental delay</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Noted at 6 mo of age</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Speech delay</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">First words at age 2 yr, short sentences at 5 yr</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Intellectual disability</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe (IQ 30–40)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Motor abnormalities</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ataxic gait, poor balance</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dysmorphic features</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Macrocephaly, prominent forehead, large ears</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Growth deficiencies</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Short stature</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Abnormal brain imaging</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mild atrophy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hypotonia</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Airway obstruction</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rare</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Spine anomalies</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kyphoscoliosis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Seizure history</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes, but none in last 15 yr (off medication)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Behavioral issues</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Impulse control, aggression, anxiety</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Connective tissue abnormality</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Soft, loose skin</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Vision/hearing impairment</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Craniosynostosis</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Joint laxity</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Notable unique features</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Neoplasms</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thyroid mass, nerve sheath tumor, melanoma</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hypertension</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Well controlled with medication</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn>
<p>Common and rare features of XGS were seen in &gt;50% and &lt; 50% of reported cases, respectively.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The individual was diagnosed with kyphoscoliosis around age 10 yr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCS003608MURF1">Fig. 1</xref>). Bracing was unsuccessful and corrective surgery was discussed but not pursued. Despite imaging showing 56° right thoracic scoliosis, he continues to be managed conservatively by his orthopedic surgeon with no related complications or pain. In his late 40s, he underwent resection of a nasal anterior skull base peripheral sheath tumor (detected incidentally by brain MRI) with pathology favoring a benign Schwannoma. A benign growth was removed from his thyroid at age 35 yr and he had melanoma in situ ×2 on his back. A baseline colonoscopy at age 52 yr was normal. Other notable chronic medical issues included severe bruxism, chronic constipation, and hypertension.</p>
<fig id="MCS003608MURF1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Photo of patient's back demonstrating the significant right thoracic kyphoscoliosis measuring 56°. Loose skin is also evident.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="MCS003608Mur_F1"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>His neuropsychological history was significant for problems with impulse control, self-injurious, and aggressive behavior beginning in childhood. Such episodes are typically triggered by frustration, pain, fatigue, or unfamiliar stressful situations. He was once committed to a psychiatric hospital for extreme anxiety and violent behavior. He has had some success in reducing these episodes of anxiety with benzodiazepines. Cognitive testing as a child revealed a full-scale IQ between 30 and 40. He has been consistently talkative and social, and his expressive language is more advanced compared to other cognitive measures. He has lived with family members or in group homes his entire life and has not been formally schooled. He understands speech but is unable to read or write. Sleep disturbances have been lifelong.</p>
<p>Beginning in his mid 40s, he has exhibited slowly progressive cognitive decline. He can follow simple commands but usually cannot follow complex (two-step or more) commands. He is able to answer binary but not open-ended questions. His speech has slowed but his overall ability and the number of words is stable. Many daily activities require assistance, including using the toilet and showering, but he is able to feed and dress himself. Urinary and fecal incontinence began in his early 50s and he now wears a diaper at all times.</p>
<p>The individual is the third child of his parents who had an additional pregnancy that ended in a spontaneous miscarriage. Parents were of Irish ancestry without any known consanguinity. He has two generally healthy older siblings, although the brother's history is significant for obesity, a desmoid tumor, and macular degeneration and the sister has a history of obesity, macular degeneration, and a basal cell carcinoma. The remainder of the family history was negative for congenital anomalies, intellectual disability, multiple miscarriages/stillbirths, or known genetic diseases. The patient's mother died at age 65 yr from metastatic lung cancer with a positive smoking history. His father died in his 70s with a history of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, macular degeneration, prostate and squamous cell cancers, and two abdominal aortic aneurysms in his 60s.</p>
<p>The individual was evaluated at a clinical genetics clinic at age 55. On physical exam, he had short stature with a height of 1.6 m (5′3′′) and a weight of 62.1 kg (136.7 lb). Dysmorphic features included macrocephaly (head circumference &gt;99 percentile), narrow palpebral fissures, prominent forehead, large thickened ears, wide mouth, and a hypoplastic maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCS003608MURF2">Fig. 2</xref>). Soft, loose skin was present on the face, neck, back, dorsal, and palmar/plantar sides of hands and feet. Significant kyphoscoliosis, reduced elbow extension, small hands and feet, and high foot arches were also noted. He had a protruding chest and widely spaced nipples. Because of the intellectual disability and dysmorphic features, a chromosomal microarray was performed. Fragile X testing was also sent secondary to the history of a male with large ears, attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), seizures, and intellectual disability. A Noonan spectrum and RASopathy gene panel were also sent with the phenotypic overlap with Costello syndrome. Those tests were nondiagnostic, and so clinical testing was advanced to WES with mitochondrial DNA analysis.</p>
<fig id="MCS003608MURF2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Front and side images of patient's head. From the front (<italic>A</italic>), the macrocephaly, prominent forehead, loose skin, and wide mouth are evident. Profile view (<italic>B</italic>) shows the large, thickened ears and hypoplastic maxilla. Hand photo (<italic>C</italic>) demonstrates soft, loose skin over the palmar side.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="MCS003608Mur_F2"></graphic>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2b">
<title>Whole-Exome Sequencing</title>
<p>Determination of the DNA sequence of the coding regions of the genomes of the individual and his unaffected brother and sister by WES revealed that he harbored a heterozygous variant in the <italic>AHDC1</italic> gene that would be predicted to lead to protein truncation, consistent with the diagnosis of XGS. The individual's parents were deceased and unavailable to confirm de novo status. However, neither unaffected sibling harbored the variant. The observed variant [NM_001029882.2:c.979C&gt;T (p.Gln327*)] is predicted to cause the disorder either through the presence of the truncated form of the protein (i.e., a dominant negative effect) or else through haploinsufficiency, via the absence of sufficient normal protein. The <italic>AHDC1</italic> c.979C&gt;T (p.Gln327*) variant was not observed in the Genome Aggregation Database (gnomAD) or ExAC databases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC7">Lek et al. 2016</xref>) and was predicted to be damaging, by in silico algorithms (<xref ref-type="table" rid="MCS003608MURTB2">Table 2</xref>). Per ACMG criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC14">Richards et al. 2015</xref>), this <italic>AHDC1</italic> variant was classified as “likely pathogenic.”</p>
<table-wrap id="MCS003608MURTB2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Allele frequency, predicted pathogenicity of variants detected on exome, and mitochondrial sequencing</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1"/>
<col align="left" span="1"/>
<col align="left" span="1"/>
<col align="left" span="1"/>
<col align="left" span="1"/>
<col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
<col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
<col align="left" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genomic location (GRCh37)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nucleotide change</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amino acid change</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zygosity</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CADD Phred</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max allele freq<sup>a</sup></th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ACMG interpretation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>AHDC1</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chr 1:27877648G &gt; A</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM_001029882.2:c.979C &gt; T</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p.Gln327*</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterozygous</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Likely pathogenic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>NSUN5</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chr 7:72721622G &gt; A</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM_018044.4:c.349C &gt; T</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p.Arg117Trp</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterozygous</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.2</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0022</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">VUS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>NSUN5</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chr 7:72721419C &gt; G</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM_018044.4:c.472G &gt; C</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p.Gly158Arg</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterozygous</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.6</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00047</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">VUS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>MT-TH</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NC_012920.1:m.12191C &gt; T</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Homoplasmic</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">VUS</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn>
<p>(VUS) Variant of uncertain significance; (*) gnomAD frequency.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Whole-exome sequencing also revealed two variants of uncertain significance (VUSs) in the <italic>NSUN5</italic> gene [NM_018044.4:c.349C&gt;T (p.Arg117Trp) and c.472G&gt;C (p.Gly158Arg)]. Segregation analysis confirmed these variants to be in <italic>trans</italic> as each unaffected sibling carried one of the alleles. The contribution of the <italic>NSUN5</italic> variants to the individual's phenotype is unknown at this time, because this gene has no current disease association. Mitochondrial genome sequencing identified a homoplasmic VUS in the <italic>MT-TH</italic> gene (NC_012920.1:m.12191C&gt;T) in the individual. Targeted testing in an unaffected maternal aunt showed the same homoplasmic variant, suggesting that it was most likely noncontributory to the individual's phenotype.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion">
<title>DISCUSSION</title>
<p>At age 55 yr at the time of diagnosis, this individual is the oldest known case of XGS, an autosomal dominant disorder caused by de novo truncating variants in the <italic>AHDC1</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC17">Xia et al. 2014</xref>). XGS has traditionally been diagnosed in the pediatric setting, with the majority of cases less than 10 yr of age at diagnosis and the oldest being 29 yr old (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC4">García-Acero and Acosta 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC5">Jiang et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC15">Ritter et al. 2018</xref>). Affected individuals commonly have hypotonia, intellectual disability, dysmorphic features, and brain anomalies, but the phenotype can be variable. The patient described here shares many of those features, including the dysmorphisms, intellectual disability, and brain atrophy. There are notable differences, however, that may be important in the management of aging patients with XGS and may provide insight into the natural history of the disorder. The common, rare, and unique features in this case compared to those previously described are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="MCS003608MURTB1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<p>One notable difference in this case is the absence of hypotonia, a finding in 90% of previously described cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC5">Jiang et al. 2018</xref>). This individual's tone was normal, and he was actually quite strong on exam. Nevertheless, he has significant coordination difficulties with an ataxic gate and poor balance. Sleep apnea is another common finding with XGS that was not seen here despite the presence of general sleep disruption. Craniosynostosis has been reported in 3/19 (15.8%) XGS cases recently described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC15">Ritter et al. 2018</xref>) but was not noted on this individual's exam or imaging. Interestingly, this individual had significant macrocephaly (head circumference &gt;99 percentile), a finding that can occasionally be seen with Muenke syndrome, an <italic>FGFR3</italic>-related craniosynostosis condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC6">Kruszka et al. 1993</xref>). At this time, however, it is unclear what role, if any, <italic>AHDC1</italic> mutations play in this condition of premature cranial suture closure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC10">Miller et al. 2017</xref>).</p>
<p>The patient's unique history of a benign thyroid mass, nerve sheath tumor (benign Schwannoma), and melanoma is notable and suggests a possible increased risk for malignancy. The function of <italic>AHDC1</italic> is not well understood but it shares a domain with <italic>REV3L</italic>, a gene implicated in DNA translesion repair (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCS003608MURF3">Fig. 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC3">Gan et al. 2008</xref>). Inherited defects in DNA repair mechanisms are known to carry a higher cancer risk, for example skin cancer in xeroderma pigmentosa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC3">Gan et al. 2008</xref>). Until we better understand the complete function of <italic>AHDC1</italic>, it is important for patients with XGS to receive age-appropriate cancer screening (colonoscopy, mammogram, etc.) and to have a low threshold for specialist referral if indicated. Similarly, as individuals with XGS progress into adulthood, they should receive proper screening and management of conditions like hypertension, as was done in this case.</p>
<fig id="MCS003608MURF3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Graphical depiction of the known XGS-associated <italic>AHDC1</italic> variants. Amino acid positions are on the <italic>x</italic>-axis with purple and yellow circles representing frameshift and nonsense mutations, respectively. This individual's p.Gln327* mutation is indicated by the red circle. Rectangles represent different protein domains, including AT-hook domains in pink, <italic>REV3L</italic> homology domains in green, <italic>KIAA2022</italic> homology domains in orange, and both <italic>REV3L</italic> and <italic>KIAA2022</italic> homology domains in blue.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="MCS003608Mur_F3"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>One striking finding on physical exam was the individual's significant kyphoscoliosis, measuring 56° in the thoracic spine (&gt;40° is considered severe) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCS003608MURF1">Fig. 1</xref>). We recently reported scoliosis in 20% of surveyed individuals with XGS, which is a significant increase compared to a general prevalence of 5% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC5">Jiang et al. 2018</xref>). Scoliosis occurs in connective tissue disorders, like Marfan syndrome, because of bone overgrowth and ligamentous laxity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC1">Dietz 1993</xref>). It is also common in neuromuscular conditions, including Duchenne muscular dystrophy, Friedreich ataxia, and cerebral palsy. In these neurologic conditions, the hypothesized etiology is disorganized control of trunk muscles leading to progressive spinal imbalance and eventually to scoliosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC16">Vialle et al. 2013</xref>). It is likely that scoliosis in XGS is due to a similar process as a result of neurologic deficits. However, a connective tissue component cannot be excluded given that this individual also had soft, loose skin. Furthermore, a recent cohort study described connective tissue abnormalities, including the skin, in 9/19 (47%) cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC15">Ritter et al. 2018</xref>). Regardless of the etiology, early recognition of scoliosis in XGS permits interventions to prevent complications like life-threatening cardio-respiratory compromise.</p>
<p>Another notable finding in this adult with XGS is his neuropsychiatric history. Behavioral issues were first observed in some XGS patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC19">Yang et al. 2015</xref>), and a more recent description of additional individuals noted instances of problems with impulse control, self-injurious and aggressive behavior, inappropriate social responses, and marked problems with sleep (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC5">Jiang et al. 2018</xref>). This adult had some of these behaviors that have required care of medical professionals and pharmacologic intervention. It should be noted that these features are variable in XGS patients and many are not aggressive in any way. As in all neurodevelopmental conditions, such behaviors can have profound negative impact on patient and family quality of life, jeopardizing educational opportunities or leading to residential placement, for example (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC9">McGuire et al. 2016</xref>). Thus, it is crucial to refer patients with XGS early to the appropriate specialists if they exhibit behavioral or mental health issues.</p>
<p>The mechanism of pathogenesis for <italic>AHDC1</italic> mutations remains unresolved. All XGS-associated mutations described to date are presumed de novo truncating variants, possibly acting through a dominant negative mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC17">Xia et al. 2014</xref>). One recently published case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC11">Park et al. 2017</xref>) and others in the DECIPHER database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC2">Firth et al. 2009</xref>) with developmental delay and deletions of <italic>AHDC1</italic> and other genes suggest haploinsufficiency should also be considered as a disease mechanism. It has also been suggested that patients with early mutations in <italic>AHDC1</italic> may have milder phenotypes and slightly higher measures of cognitive ability than those with more distal mutations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC5">Jiang et al. 2018</xref>). However, there is significant variability, even among individuals with the same mutation, making it difficult to draw any conclusions. The frameshift mutation described here is located very early in the gene, toward the amino terminus of the encoded protein (p.Gln327*), which could suggest a milder predicted phenotype. However, though the patient is generally healthy, he has severe intellectual disability with an IQ of 30–40. In contrast, a 29-yr-old male with XGS and a very distal mutation (p.Cys1499Valfs*9) was recently described as having only moderate intellectual disability, is trilingual, and employed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC15">Ritter et al. 2018</xref>). Thus, a larger number of cases and a better understanding of the disease mechanism is needed to elucidate any true genotype-phenotype correlations.</p>
<p>Until recently, XGS has largely been considered a disorder of childhood. Of the &gt;100 XGS cases described to date, the three oldest are only in their 20s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC5">Jiang et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC15">Ritter et al. 2018</xref>), demonstrating that our understanding of the natural history of XGS is limited. Genetic diseases are often well described in the pediatric age range because that is when they are typically diagnosed. In a recent study describing data from 2000 WES cases performed in a clinical setting, only 12% were adult patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC18">Yang et al. 2014</xref>). The adult phenotype may not be well defined or may be unfamiliar to the adult physician. For example, a recent study of screening copy number variation in adults demonstrated that only one in 12 adults had been correctly diagnosed with the 22q11.2 deletion syndrome though 10 of 12 had clinical features consistent with the diagnosis (e.g., congenital heart defect, neurodevelopmental disorder) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC8">Maxwell et al. 2017</xref>). Phenotypic expression may also be subtler in adulthood, because of mosaicism or variable expressivity. As a consequence, WES may currently be underutilized in adults with intellectual disability in whom phenotypes are less defined. Nevertheless, the diagnostic utility of WES in adults has been demonstrated, for example in one study in which a molecular diagnosis was made in 17.5% of adults undergoing WES, rising to 27.7% in those with neurodevelopmental abnormalities like this case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="MCS003608MURC13">Posey et al. 2016</xref>). It may also suggest that <italic>AHDC1</italic> might be implicated in some fraction of institutionalized adults that have never undergone a genetic evaluation.</p>
<p>In conclusion, this case represents the oldest individual diagnosed with XGS to date. Overall, he remains healthy well into his 50s, suggesting that life span may not be dramatically altered in XGS. With continued support and interventions, such individuals may continue to thrive into adulthood. This report suggests that XGS should be considered in the differential diagnosis of adults with unexplained intellectual disability and dysmorphic features. Last, it demonstrates the need to generally consider classically defined pediatric conditions in adults.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
<title>METHODS</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Whole-Exome Sequencing</title>
<p>Using genomic DNA from the submitted specimens, the exonic regions and flanking splice junctions of the genome were captured and sequenced at GeneDx on an Illumina system with 150-bp paired-end reads. Reads were aligned to human genome build GRCh37/UCSC hg19 and then analyzed for sequence variants. Potentially pathogenic variants were confirmed with Sanger sequencing. Mean depth of coverage was 123×, and 98.7% of the targeted region was sequenced to a coverage of at least 10× (<xref ref-type="table" rid="MCS003608MURTB3">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="MCS003608MURTB3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Whole-exome sequencing metrics</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1"/>
<col align="left" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean depth of coverage</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">123×</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Percentage of exome with at least 10× coverage</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.70%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Percentage of <italic>AHDC1</italic> coding region with at least 10× coverage</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s5">
<title>ADDITIONAL INFORMATION</title>
<sec id="s5a" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data Deposition and Access</title>
<p>The confirmed genetic variant was deposited to ClinVar (<uri xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/</uri>) under accession number SCV000618821. Whole-exome sequencing data are not publicly available because consent could not be obtained.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5b">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>Written consent for the case report and pictures was obtained from the individual's guardian. The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Baylor College of Medicine.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5c">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We thank the subject of this case report and his family for their generous contributions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5d">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p>All authors were involved in the study design, manuscript preparation, and data analysis, as well as reviewing, of the final manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5e">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This work was supported by the Baylor-Hopkins Center for Mendelian Genomics (HG006542) and by a private donation. R.A.G. was also supported as a visiting scholar of the Texas Institute for Advanced Studies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5f">
<title>Competing Interest Statement</title>
<p>Jane Juusola and Kirsty McWalter are employees of GeneDx.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Dietz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <year>1993</year>
<source/>Marfan syndrome. <publisher-name>University of Washington</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Firth</surname>
<given-names>HV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bevan</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corpas</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Vooren</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moreau</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pettett</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>NP</given-names></string-name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>DECIPHER: <italic>d</italic>atabas<italic>e</italic> of <italic>c</italic>hromosomal <italic>i</italic>mbalance and <italic>p</italic>henotype in <italic>h</italic>umans using <italic>e</italic>nsembl <italic>r</italic>esources</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>524</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2009.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19344873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gan</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wittschieben</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wittschieben</surname>
<given-names>BØ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>DNA polymerase zeta (pol ζ) in higher eukaryotes</article-title>. <source/>Cell Res
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2007.117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18157155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>García-Acero</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Acosta</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>
<article-title>Whole-exome sequencing identifies a de novo <italic>AHDC1</italic> mutation in a Colombian patient with Xia–Gibbs syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Mol Syndromol
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000479357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29230160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wangler</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGuire</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lupski</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Posey</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khayat</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murdock</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanchez-Pulido</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponting</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>The phenotypic spectrum of Xia–Gibbs syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet Part A
<volume>176</volume>: <fpage>1315</fpage>–<lpage>1326</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.a.38699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29696776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Kruszka</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Addissie</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agochukwu</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doherty</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muenke</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <year>1993</year>
<article-title>Muenke syndrome</article-title>. In <source/>GeneReviews® (Internet) (ed. <string-name><surname>Adam</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ardinger</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pagon</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wallace</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bean</surname>
<given-names>LJH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stephens</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amemiya</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>). <publisher-name>University of Washington</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc>, <publisher-loc>WA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lek</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karczewski</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minikel</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samocha</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fennell</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O'Donnell-Luria</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ware</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cummings</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Analysis of protein-coding genetic variation in 60,706 humans</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>536</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature19057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27535533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maxwell</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Packer</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O'Dushlaine</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hare-Harris</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Staples</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonzaga-Jauregui</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fetterolf</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faucett</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leader</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Profiling copy number variation and disease associations from 50,726 DiscovEHR Study exomes</article-title>. <source/>bioRxiv
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/119461</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McGuire</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fung</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagopian</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vasa</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahajan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silberman</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coury</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hardan</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Irritability and problem behavior in autism spectrum disorder: a practice pathway for pediatric primary care</article-title>. <source/>Pediatrics
<volume>137</volume>: <fpage>S136</fpage>–<lpage>S148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2015-2851L</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Twigg</surname>
<given-names>SRF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGowan</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phipps</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fenwick</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wall</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noons</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rees</surname>
<given-names>KEM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tidey</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Diagnostic value of exome and whole genome sequencing in craniosynostosis</article-title>. <source/>J Med Genet
<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jmedgenet-2016-104215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27884935</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jang</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>
<article-title>Phenotype of a patient with a 1p36.11-p35.3 interstitial deletion encompassing the <italic>AHDC1</italic></article-title>. <source/>Ann Lab Med
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3343/alm.2017.37.6.563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28841002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Popp</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ekici</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thiel</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiesener</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kraus</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zweier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>
<article-title>Exome Pool-Seq in neurodevelopmental disorders</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Hum Genet
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1364</fpage>–<lpage>1376</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41431-017-0022-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29158550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Posey</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bainbridge</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dhar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiszniewski</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akdemir</surname>
<given-names>ZHC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gambin</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Molecular diagnostic experience of whole-exome sequencing in adult patients</article-title>. <source/>Genet Med
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/gim.2015.142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26633545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aziz</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bale</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bick</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gastier-Foster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grody</surname>
<given-names>WW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hegde</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lyon</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spector</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Standards and guidelines for the interpretation of sequence variants: a joint consensus recommendation of the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics and the Association for Molecular Pathology</article-title>. <source/>Genet Med
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/gim.2015.30</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25741868</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ritter</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McDougall</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skraban</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medne</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bedoukian</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asher</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balciuniene</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Denenberg</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Variable clinical manifestations of Xia–Gibbs syndrome: findings of consecutively identified cases at a single children's hospital</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet Part A
<volume>176</volume>: <fpage>1890</fpage>–<lpage>1896</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.a.40380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30152016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vialle</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thévenin-Lemoine</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mary</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Neuromuscular scoliosis</article-title>. <source/>Orthop Traumatol Surg Res
<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>S124</fpage>–<lpage>S139</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.otsr.2012.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23337438</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bainbridge</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wangler</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheuerle</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zackai</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harr</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sutton</surname>
<given-names>VR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nalam</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>De novo truncating mutations in <italic>AHDC1</italic> in individuals with syndromic expressive language delay, hypotonia, and sleep apnea</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>784</fpage>–<lpage>789</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2014.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24791903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muzny</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Person</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braxton</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buhay</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Molecular findings among patients referred for clinical whole-exome sequencing</article-title>. <source/>J Am Med Assoc
<volume>312</volume>: <fpage>1870</fpage>–<lpage>1879</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.14601</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="MCS003608MURC19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Douglas</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monaghan</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Retterer</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Escobar</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoler</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodan</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal></etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>De novo truncating variants in the <italic>AHDC1</italic> gene encoding the AT-hook DNA-binding motif-containing protein 1 are associated with intellectual disability and developmental delay</article-title>. <source/>Mol Case Stud
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>a000562</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/mcs.a000562</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>