<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101573691</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">39703</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Rep</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell Rep</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Cell reports</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2211-1247</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30605686</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6555418</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.12.018</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1517849</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Augmented Reticular Thalamic Bursting and Seizures in <italic>Scn1a</italic>-Dravet Syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ritter-Makinson</surname>
<given-names>Stefanie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clemente-Perez</surname>
<given-names>Alexandra</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Higashikubo</surname>
<given-names>Bryan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>Frances S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holden</surname>
<given-names>Stephanie S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>Eric</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chkaidze</surname>
<given-names>Ana</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rooda</surname>
<given-names>Oscar H.J. Eelkman</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cornet</surname>
<given-names>Marie-Coralie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoebeek</surname>
<given-names>Freek E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yamakawa</surname>
<given-names>Kazuhiro</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cilio</surname>
<given-names>Maria Roberta</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Delord</surname>
<given-names>Bruno</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Paz</surname>
<given-names>Jeanne T.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A14">14</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Gladstone Institute of Neurological Disease, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94158, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurology, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94158, USA</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Physiology, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94158, USA</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Neurosciences Graduate Program, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94158, USA</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Neuroscience, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94158, USA</aff>
<aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Pediatrics, Catholic University of Louvain, Louvain, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="A9"><label>9</label>NIDOD Institute, Wilhelmina Children’s Hospital, University Medical Center Utrecht and Brain Center Rudolf Magnus, Utrecht, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Laboratory for Neurogenetics, RIKEN Brain Science Institute, Wako, Japan</aff>
<aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Institut des Systèmes Intelligents et de Robotique (ISIR), Sorbonne University, 4 Place Jussieu, 75005 Paris, France</aff>
<aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Kavli Institute for Fundamental Neuroscience, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94158, USA</aff>
<aff id="A13"><label>13</label>These authors contributed equally</aff>
<aff id="A14"><label>14</label>Lead Contact</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</p>
<p id="P2">Concept Development and Experimental Design, S.R.-M. and J.T.P.; Surgeries, Chronic Implants, and Thalamic Recordings, S.R.-M. and J.T.P.; <italic>In Vivo</italic> and Slice Network Oscillation Experiments, S.R.-M.; Patch-Clamp Recordings, A.C.-P., F.S.C., S.S.H.; Data Analysis, S.R.-M., A.C.-P., F.S.C., B.H., E.B., O.H.J.E.R., F.E.H., B.D., and J.T.P.; Histology, S.R.-M. and A.C.; Human EEG Acquisition and Analysis, M.R.C. M.-C.C., and B.H.; Computational Modeling, B.D.; Writing, S.R.-M., A.C.-P., B.D., and J.T.P. K.Y. provided the DS mice.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>jeanne.paz@gladstone.ucsf.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>7</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>02</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>07</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>54</fpage>
<lpage>64.e6</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.celrep.2018.12.018-->
<permissions>
<license license-type="open-access">
<license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="ABS1">
<title>SUMMARY</title>
<p id="P3">Loss of function in the <italic>Scn1a</italic> gene leads to a severe epileptic encephalopathy called Dravet syndrome (DS). Reduced excitability in cortical inhibitory neurons is thought to be the major cause of DS seizures. Here, in contrast, we show enhanced excitability in thalamic inhibitory neurons that promotes the non-convulsive seizures that are a prominent yet poorly understood feature of DS. In a mouse model of DS with a loss of function in <italic>Scn1a</italic>, reticular thalamic cells exhibited abnormally long bursts of firing caused by the downregulation of calcium-activated potassium SK channels. Our study supports a mechanism in which loss of SK activity causes the reticular thalamic neurons to become hyperexcitable and promote non-convulsive seizures in DS. We propose that reduced excitability of inhibitory neurons is not global in DS and that non-GABAergic mechanisms such as SK channels may be important targets for treatment.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="ABS2">
<title>Graphical Abstract</title>
<p id="P4">
<graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="nihms-1517849-f0001.jpg"></graphic>
</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary" id="ABS3">
<title>In Brief</title>
<p id="P5">In a mouse model of Dravet syndrome (DS) resulting from voltage-gated sodium channel deficiency, Ritter-Makinson et al. find that inhibitory neurons of the reticular thalamic nucleus are paradoxically hyperexcitable due to compensatory reductions in a potassium SK current. Boosting this SK current treats nonconvulsive seizures in DS mice.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S1">
<title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p id="P6"><italic>SCN1A</italic> encodes the alpha subunit of the voltage-gated sodium channel Nav1.1, which is widely expressed in the brain and heart. As regulators of cardiac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Auerbach et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Kalume et al., 2013</xref>) and brain rhythms, mutations in <italic>SCN1A</italic> dramatically affect human health. <italic>SCN1A</italic> is one of the most commonly mutated genes associated with epilepsy, including Dravet syndrome (DS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Claes et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">2009</xref>). This age-dependent, early-onset epileptic encephalopathy is characterized by non-convulsive and convulsive seizures, developmental delay, intellectual and motor disabilities, autistic features, sleep impairment, and a high risk of sudden death. Non-convulsive seizures are often intractable and may account for the cognitive decline, behavioral disorders, and reduction in social life associated with DS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Guzzetta, 2011</xref>). The absence of non-convulsive seizures is typical of borderline forms of DS, in which cognitive ability is at least partially preserved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Dalla Bernardina et al., 1986</xref>).</p>
<p id="P7">In mouse models of DS, reduced <italic>Scn1a</italic> function in GABAergic cortical and hippocampal inhibitory neurons reduces action potential (AP) firing and network inhibition, which is thought to lead to runaway excitation (altered excitatory-inhibitory balance) and convulsive seizures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Cheah et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Dutton et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Ogiwara et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Tai et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Yu et al., 2006</xref>). Knockout of <italic>Scn1a</italic> in parvalbumin and somatostatin neurons increases the susceptibility to thermally induced convulsive seizures, whereas selective knockout in either neuron subtype phenocopies distinct DS neuropsychiatric behavioral phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Rubinstein et al., 2015</xref>). Identifying the molecular and brain circuit mechanisms by which reduced <italic>SCN1A</italic> causes non-convulsive seizures could lead to novel therapeutic strategies.</p>
<p id="P8">Although less studied, another hub of <italic>Scn1a</italic>-expressing GABAergic neurons exists in the nucleus reticularis thalami (nRT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Papale et al., 2013</xref>), which dynamically modulates interactions between the thalamus and cerebral cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Crick, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Halassa and Acsády, 2016</xref>). The nRT neurons are intrinsic oscillators that inhibit the excitatory relay thalamic nuclei (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Gentet and Ulrich, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Houser et al., 1980</xref>), positioning them to regulate thalamocortical oscillations, including seizures. Given the abundant expression of <italic>Scn1a</italic> in nRT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Papale et al., 2013</xref>) and that disruptions in nRT correlate with neurological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Makinson et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Paz et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Slaght et al., 2002</xref>) and psychiatric disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Ferrarelli and Tononi, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>), we asked whether <italic>Scn1a</italic> deficiency results in nRT pathology and is involved in non-convulsive seizures using a well-established mouse model containing a human <italic>Scn1a</italic> mutation (DS mice; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Ogiwara et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>RESULTS</title>
<sec id="S3">
<title><italic>Scn1a</italic> Deficiency Alters the Electric Membrane Excitability of nRT Neurons</title>
<p id="P9">We first investigated the effect of <italic>Scn1a</italic> deficiency on GABAergic parvalbumin-positive nRT neurons. The input resistance (Rin) of nRT neurons was increased in DS mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1A</xref>), while the membrane capacitance was not significantly reduced (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1A</xref>), indicating a decrease in the total membrane conductance. Moreover, the AP threshold was depolarized and the AP width was increased in DS mice, as expected from <italic>Scn1a</italic> reduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Cheah et al., 2012</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1B</xref>). However, nRT neurons from DS mice fired more APs in response to depolarization (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1C</xref>), consistent with an increased Rin.</p>
<p id="P10">Given that post-hyperpolarization rebound bursting plays a critical role in thalamic function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Beenhakker and Huguenard, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Paz and Huguenard, 2015</xref>), we investigated whether <italic>Scn1a</italic> deficiency altered rebound bursting in nRT cells. In response to similar hyperpolarizations, the number of APs within the rebound burst was higher in nRT neurons from DS mice (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A and 1B</xref>), indicating that GABAergic nRT neurons exhibit enhanced intrinsic excitability in DS mice.</p>
<p id="P11">We next examined the effects of <italic>Scn1a</italic> deficiency on thalamocortical (TC) neurons in the somatosensory ventrobasal thalamus (VB), which has also been reported to express <italic>Scn1a</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Ogiwara et al., 2013</xref>). We observed no differences in the passive membrane, tonic, or rebound firing properties of TC<sub>VB</sub> neurons in DS mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S2A–S2C</xref>). Finally, spontaneous excitatory synaptic currents were not altered in nRT and TC<sub>VB</sub> neurons from DS mice (Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S1E</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">2D–2F</xref>, respectively) and were similar to those reported in our previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Paz et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>SK Current Deficit Underlies Enhanced Cellular Burst Firing in nRT Neurons</title>
<p id="P12">Low-threshold T-type calcium and calcium-activated small potassium (SK) conductances play a major role in nRT post-inhibitory rebound bursts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Jahnsen and Llinás, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>). In DS mice, the peak T-current (<italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub>) density, voltage dependence, and biophysical properties of the steady-state inactivation (SSI) <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> were not altered in nRT neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C–1G</xref>) and were comparable in size and kinetics to <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> previously measured in the nRT neurons of normal rodents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Paz et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>). These results suggest that enhanced rebound burst firing in DS nRT neurons is not due to a stronger <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub>.</p>
<p id="P13">We next asked whether alterations in SK channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>) underlie the enhanced burst firing. Whole-cell patch-clamp recordings showed a reduced density of SK currents (<italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub>) in DS nRT neurons (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1H, 1I</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S1G</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S1H</xref>). qPCR of nRT isolated from DS mice showed reduced levels of <italic>Kcnn2S</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1J and 1K</xref>), which is the predominant SK2 sub-type in nRT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Wimmer et al., 2012</xref>). In a rescue experiment, the SK agonist 1-ethyl-2-benzimidazolinone (EBIO) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>) was sufficient to normalize the rebound bursting properties in DS nRT neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1L</xref>), but it did not affect the firing of TC<sub>VB</sub> neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S2G and S2H</xref>).</p>
<p id="P14">In a biophysical model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Adelman et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Destexhe et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Paz et al., 2013</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1M</xref>), reducing SK conductance phenocopied the changes observed in DS nRT neurons, namely the enhanced number of APs within the rebound burst (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1N</xref>) and the enhanced Rin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1F</xref>). The increased Rin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1F</xref>) and mean AP number (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1O</xref>) were robust across the parameter domains tested. Notably, reducing the transient sodium conductance altered neither the number of APs in the rebound burst nor the Rin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S3J and S3K</xref>), suggesting that SK reduction is sufficient to cause enhanced Rin and AP firing in the nRT, independent of changes in transient sodium conductance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title><italic>Scn1a</italic> Deficiency Leads to Thalamic Microcircuit Hyperexcitability</title>
<p id="P15">Rebound burst firing in nRT neurons is important for generating and maintaining oscillatory activity in the intra-thalamic microcircuit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Beenhakker and Huguenard, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Jahnsen and Llinás, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Bazhenov et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Deschênes et al., 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Steriade et al., 1987</xref>). The rebound burst in nRT neurons provides phasic GABAergic inhibition onto excitatory thalamic relay neurons, which leads to rebound burst firing in relay cells and subsequent re-excitation of the nRT, with this sequence reiterating to maintain thalamic network oscillation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Beenhakker and Huguenard, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Paz and Huguenard, 2015</xref>). Therefore, we asked whether the intra-thalamic microcircuit between the nRT and relay nuclei is hyperexcitable in <italic>Scn1a</italic>-deficient mice.</p>
<p id="P16">To assess this, we used horizontal thalamic slice preparations that conserve the connectivity between nRT and VB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Huntsman et al., 1999</xref>). In wild-type (WT) mice, stimulation of the internal capsule consistently evoked rhythmic oscillatory bursting activity in VB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>) in the spindle frequency range (~7–10 Hz), similar to previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Paz et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Huntsman et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Barthó et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Sorokin et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Halassa et al., 2011</xref>). Evoked repetitive bursting in VB necessitates “ping-pong”-type interactions between nRT and VB; when these connections are severed, no circuit oscillations are observed in VB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">von Krosigk et al., 1993</xref>). Similar stimulations in DS mice induced longer circuit oscillations in the thalamus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>), with more bursts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>) occurring at a lower frequency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>) in DS mice. These metrics support the intrathalamic nRT-VB microcircuit being hyperexcitable in DS mice.</p>
<p id="P17">We then assessed the impact of reduced SK conductance at the circuit level in our computational model, including TC<sub>VB</sub> and nRT neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>). Reduced SK elicited enhanced network oscillations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F</xref>), displaying longer oscillations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2G and 2H</xref>), more bursts within each oscillation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2I and 2J</xref>), and lower oscillation frequency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2K and 2L</xref>) in the DS domain. Longer nRT bursts and the consequent TC<sub>VB</sub> hyperpolarization account for the counterintuitive decrease in the frequency of bursting in DS mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2K and 2L</xref>).</p>
<p id="P18">In the WT domain (at normal SK conductance levels), a 10% reduction in the sodium maximal conductance did not affect burst AP number and Rin in the nRT neuron model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S1J and S1K</xref>) or oscillation properties in the nRT-TC<sub>VB</sub> circuit model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S1L–S1N</xref>) (i.e., it did not account for experimental observations). Moreover, reduced sodium conductance left unchanged the effects of reduced SK conductance in the DS domain in both the nRT and nRT-TC<sub>VB</sub> models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S1J–S1N</xref>) (i.e., it did not preclude the mechanistic effect unraveled between reduced SK and the nRT-TC<sub>VB</sub> microcircuit hyperexcitability). Even a 50% decrease in the sodium maximal conductance did not affect these conclusions (data not shown). The model thus suggests that in nRT neurons, reduced SK, but not reduced sodium conductance, renders the thalamus “epileptic like” by enhancing thalamic rhythmogenesis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6">
<title>“Silent” Non-convulsive Seizures in Human and Mouse DS</title>
<p id="P19">Given that the nRT is a powerful modulator of cortical rhythms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Steriade et al., 1993</xref>), we next asked whether enhanced bursting in the nRT-VB circuit could underlie seizures in DS mice. DS presents with a complex seizure phenotype that includes non-convulsive seizures (e.g., typical and atypical absence seizures) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Dravet, 2011</xref>). The cellular mechanisms underlying these seizures remain unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Dravet, 2011</xref>), and non-convulsive seizures have not been described in DS mouse models.</p>
<p id="P20">Thus, we set out to compare the seizure phenotype in DS mice to human DS patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Non-convulsive seizures occurred in mice on average 15 ± 8 times per hour, lasting0.5–6 s (n = 9), and 7 ± 4 times per hour, lasting on average 10 s in DS patients (n = 3). Notably, non-convulsive seizures in DS mice and DS patients exhibited similar spectral electroencephalogram (EEG) signatures with fundamental frequencies of 4–7 Hz that varied, depending on the cortical region (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4</xref>), characterized by poly-spike-and-wave components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, note the similarities between 3C and 3G), which were different from the spike-and-wave discharges of typical absence seizures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S7">
<title>SK Enhancement Treats Non-convulsive Seizures in DS Mice</title>
<p id="P21">Recordings in nRT and VB showed high-frequency burst firing, phase locked to cortical poly-spikes during spontaneously occurring non-convulsive seizures (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S5A–S5D</xref>) and during the convulsive hyperthermia-triggered seizures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S5E and S5F</xref>) in freely behaving mice. Pharmacological boosting of SK channels in the nRT by acute infusion of EBIO reduced the number of spontaneous non-convulsive seizures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4A and 4B</xref>). Given the close apposition of nRT and VB, we cannot exclude the potential that intra-nRT infusions of EBIO also affected the VB. However, the lack of EBIO effects on the firing of TC<sub>VB</sub> neurons <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S2G and S2H</xref>) suggests that the abrogation of seizures mainly resulted from the effects of EBIO on the nRT. Next, we investigated more clinically tractable systemic injections of EBIO and found that these also reduced the number of seizures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4C–4F</xref>). Thus, pharmacological enhancers of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> could be a treatment for non-convulsive seizures in DS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Optogenetic Toggling of Thalamic Bursting Modulates Seizures in <italic>Scn1a</italic>-Deficient Mice</title>
<p id="P22">The nRT exerts its effects on cortical rhythms through its TC relay targets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Pinault, 2004</xref>), and non-convulsive seizures are prominent in the S1 cortex. Therefore, we hypothesized that if nRT → VB → S1 was causally involved in seizures, interrupting the bursting in VB should disrupt the seizures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>). To test this, we perturbed VB firing using stable step function opsin (SSFO), a bistable opsin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Yizhar et al., 2011</xref>) that can switch the firing of TC<sub>VB</sub> cells from bursting to tonic mode (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Sorokin et al., 2017</xref>). Unilateral SSFO activation in VB after seizure detection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>) rapidly eliminated VB bursts, toggled tonic firing, and stopped ongoing seizures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5C–5E</xref>). Thus, VB bursting output may maintain non-convulsive seizures in DS. The light itself did not disrupt seizures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6</xref>), demonstrating that optical disruption of seizures requires SSFO activation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S9">
<title>DISCUSSION</title>
<p id="P23">Here, we discovered that in DS, <italic>Scn1a</italic> deficiency and subsequent reduction of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> in the nRT drives thalamic hyperexcitability to promote non-convulsive cortical seizures.</p>
<sec id="S10">
<title>Less Is More: How Does Scn1a Deficiency in nRT Neurons Lead to Thalamic Network Hyperexcitability?</title>
<p id="P24">Our finding that GABAergic nRT neurons in DS mice have a more depolarized AP threshold is expected, and confirms previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Kalume et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hedrich et al., 2014</xref>). However, we also found that nRT neurons exhibit an overall increase in excitability, displaying stronger spiking during depolarizing current pulses and stronger post-hyperpolarization rebound bursts of APs. This is at least in part due to a compensatory decrease in SK channel expression and consequent shift of the current balance toward inward currents and increased Rin. These changes were sufficient to maintain abnormal oscillations in the intrathalamic network formed by reciprocal connections between nRT and relay TC neurons in the somatosensory thalamus. Although many other compensations likely occur in DS, the reduction in <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> is particularly powerful because of its known role in thalamic rhythmogenesis. Our findings are in agreement with previous studies showing that blockade of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> with apamin causes cellular and circuit hyperexcitability in thalamic slices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Kleiman-Weiner et al., 2009</xref>). The thalamic hypersynchrony due to blockade of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> is not as strong as that obtained with GABA blockers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Kleiman-Weiner et al., 2009</xref>), which may explain how SK deficiency in nRT results in atypical spike-and-wave discharge absence seizures.</p>
<p id="P25">The identification of SK2 as a modifier of DS non-convulsive seizures adds to the list of genetic modifiers of <italic>SCN1A</italic> epilepsies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Calhoun et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Hawkins and Kearney, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Hawkins et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Martin et al., 2007</xref>). Notably, we not only found that <italic>Kcnn2</italic> is reduced in the nRT but also that pharmacological enhancement of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> in nRT can treat non-convulsive seizures in our DS mouse model. Intra-cerebellar or systemic injections of the SK channel booster EBIO have previously been used to reduce burst firing in the cerebellum, to enhance motor performance, and to reduce dyskinesia in tottering mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Walter et al., 2006</xref>); systemic administration of chlorzoxazone—a Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved activator of SK channels—has been shown to improve motor performance in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Gao et al., 2012</xref>) and in human patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Feil et al., 2013</xref>). Although systemic EBIO treatment likely affects structures other than the nRT, our observation that local intra-nRT injections of EBIO are sufficient to treat seizures suggests that the thalamus could be a target to treat non-convulsive seizures in DS. Furthermore, TC<sub>VB</sub> neurons, known not to express SK2, exhibited normal firing properties in DS mice and were not affected by EBIO.</p>
<p id="P26">We propose the following working model of thalamic involvement in DS pathology: <italic>Scn1a</italic> deficiency leads to a compensatory reduction of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> in nRT neurons, which contributes to enhanced Rin and a shift toward inward currents, which enhance the intrinsic excitability of nRT neurons in response to both hyperpolarization (rebound bursts) and depolarizing stimuli (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6F</xref>). The increased excitability of nRT neurons results in enhanced bursts of APs following activation from either excitatory TC<sub>VB</sub> neurons or cortex. Enhanced output from nRT neurons leads to longer-lasting hyperpolarizations in the target TC<sub>VB</sub> neurons, resulting in stronger rebound bursting that re-excites nRT neurons. This cycle iterates to maintain non-convulsive seizures.</p>
<p id="P27">Our model fits within the framework of the dysfunctional cortex in DS. A hyperactive cortex could recruit the nRT via glutamatergic projections to amplify abnormal cortical inputs due to the intrinsic hyperexcitability of nRT cells (enhanced Rin) and via extensive projections from nRT onto sensory and limbic TC nuclei. It may be that the seizures initiate in the cortex, which in turn recruits the nRT and thalamus to maintain the seizure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5D</xref>). While further investigation is needed, it is clear that the thalamus, both nRT and VB, is required for seizure maintenance and is thus a promising target.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S11">
<title>Treatment Strategies for DS: What Are the Implications of Enhanced Excitability of GABAergic nRT in Light of Reduced GABAergic Function in the Cortex?</title>
<p id="P28">Previous work on DS showed that sodium channel deficits in GABAergic neurons result in reduced firing, leading to the hypothesis that reduced network inhibition in the neocortex and hippocampus promotes convulsive seizures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Cheah et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Dutton et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Ogiwara et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Tai et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Yu et al., 2006</xref>). This model suggests that the optimal treatment of seizures would be to enhance firing of GABAergic neurons. However, our study shows that in contrast to the cortex, thalamic GABAergic neurons of the nRT show enhanced intrinsic excitability and rebound burst firing that result in thalamic network hyperexcitability. If cortical hyperexcitability is due to reduced firing of GABAergic cells, but thalamic hyperexcitability is due to enhanced firing of GABAergic cells, then drug treatments that enhance firing of GABAergic cells in both regions will not yield optimal results or may even worsen seizures. Moreover, given that thalamic modulation treats non-convulsive seizures and that the thalamus is implicated in sleep, cognition, and motor planning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Beenhakker and Huguenard, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Saalmann and Kastner, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Karussis et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Guo et al., 2017</xref>), we propose that the thalamus could be an important target for treating non-convulsive seizures and perhaps associated comorbidities such as sleep impairments and cognitive dysfunction in DS. When designing new therapeutic strategies to enhance GABAergic neuron function, it will be important to keep in mind that these should be combined with drugs that reduce nRT bursting. Our results align with the recent finding that although reduced firing in GABAergic neurons occurs during development in DS, this change is temporary and does not contribute to the chronic epilepsy in DS mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Favero et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S12">
<title>What Are the Implications for Understanding DS Pathophysiology Beyond Seizures?</title>
<p id="P29">Mice lacking SK2 show fragmented sleep patterns and reduced sleep spindles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>), similar to DS mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Kalume et al., 2015</xref>), supporting the idea that reductions in SK2 underlie thalamic circuit dysfunction and sleep impairments in DS. Over-expressing SK2 increases sleep spindles and reduces sleep fragmentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Wimmer et al., 2012</xref>), indicating that enhancement of SK function in DS may restore sleep impairments, in addition to treating seizures.</p>
<p id="P30">Here, we describe a cellular and circuit mechanism underlying non-convulsive seizures in DS and compare this phenomenon with human patients. Non-convulsive seizures are debilitating, account for the cognitive decline in human patients with DS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Guzzetta, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Dalla Bernardina et al., 1986</xref>), and are comorbid with autism spectrum disorders in multiple mouse models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Holder and Quach, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Jung et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Gheyara et al., 2014</xref>). It remains to be elucidated which subnetworks of nRT, in addition to the somatosensory subnetwork, are affected in their firing pattern, and if so, how these pathological firing patterns may spread to the different thalamic nuclei. Unraveling the cognitive impact of the DS mutations requires cell-specific and inducible mouse models. Given the recently uncovered framework of nRT organization and function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>) and the role of nRT SK channels in attention deficit disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Wells et al., 2016</xref>), we speculate that the nRT could be a key brain substrate and thus therapeutic target for the comorbid neurological (seizure) and psychiatric (autism) components of DS.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S13">
<title>STAR★METHODS</title>
<p id="P120">Detailed methods are provided in the online version of this paper
and include the following:</p>
<sec id="S14">
<title>CONTACT FOR REAGENT AND RESOURCE SHARING</title>
<p id="P31">Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Jeanne Paz (<email>jeanne.paz@gladstone.ucsf.edu</email>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S15">
<title>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS</title>
<sec id="S16">
<title>DS mice</title>
<p id="P32">We performed all experiments per protocols approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the University of California, San Francisco and Gladstone Institutes. Precautions were taken to minimize stress and the number of animals used in each set of experiments. Mice were separately housed after surgical implants. Mice modeling DS, <italic>Scn1a</italic><sup><italic>R1407X</italic>+/−</sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Ogiwara et al., 2007</xref>), hereafter referred to as DS mice, and WT littermates were used in this study and maintained on a mixed background (80%–88% C57BL6J (Jax 000664)/12%–20% C3HeB/FeJ (Jax 000658). DS mice that are homozygous for the <italic>Scn1a</italic> mutation die by age post-natal 15 (P15) and therefore were not studied here. Heterozygous DS mice have a high mortality rate between post-natal days 20 and 71 and a 31-fold higher risk of death than WT littermates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Gheyara et al., 2014</xref>). By 73 days, only 18% of Scn1a<sup>RX/+</sup> mice remain alive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Gheyara et al., 2014</xref>) and could be recorded with chronic multioptrode devices. Both male and female mice were used for these experiments and ages ranged between postnatal days 18–80.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S17">
<title>Human Subjects</title>
<p id="P33">All procedures were approved by the Regional and Institutional Committee of Science and Research Ethics of Scientific Council of Health. Per institutional guideline, this clinical case study was exempted from IRB approval. The total number of human subjects cited in this study (n = 3) are also reported in the text of the results. The subjects ages ranged from 5–7 years and included 1 boy and 2 girls.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S18">
<title>METHOD DETAILS</title>
<sec id="S19">
<title>Viral injections</title>
<p id="P34">Stereotaxic viral injections were carried out as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Paz et al., 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Paxinos and Franklin, 2012</xref>). Briefly, in WT or DS mice, adeno-associated virus carrying genes for eYFP alone (rAAV5/CamkIIa-eYFP) (7.4 ×10<sup>12</sup> genome copies per ml)) or Stable Step Function Opsin (SSFO; rAAV5/CamkIIa-hChR2(C128S;D156A)-eYFP (5.2×10<sup>12</sup> genome copies per ml)) was injected into the ventrobasal nucleus of the thalamus (VB) using the following coordinates: 1.6 mm posterior to Bregma, 1.6 lateral relative to midline, and two separate injections of 400 nL of virus at 3.2 and 3.5 mm ventral to the cortical surface (total injected volume, 800 nl). Viruses were acquired from (UNC Vector Core SCR_002448). We allowed the viruses to express for anywhere between 3 weeks and 6 months, depending on the nature of the experiment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S20">
<title>Immunostaining, microscopy, and image analysis</title>
<p id="P35">Mice were anesthetized with a lethal dose of ketamine (300 mg/kg) and xylazine (30 mg/kg) and perfused with 4% paraformaldehyde in 1× PBS. Serial coronal sections (50 μm thick) were cut on a Leica SM2000R Sliding Microtome. Sections were mounted in an antifade medium (Vectashield) and imaged using a Biorevo BZ-9000 Keyence microscope at 10×–20×. The expression of the viral constructs in different brain regions was confirmed using the mouse brain atlas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Paxinos and Franklin, 2012</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S21">
<title>Slice preparation</title>
<p id="P36">Mice were euthanized with 4% isoflurane, perfused with ice-cold sucrose cutting solution containing 234 mM sucrose, 2.5 mM KCl, 1.25 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 10 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 26 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, and 11 mM glucose, equilibrated with 95% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, pH 7.4, and decapitated. We prepared 250-μm (for patch-clamp electrophysiology) or 400-μm (for thalamic microcircuit studies)-thick horizontal thalamic slices containing VB thalamus and nRT with a Leica VT1200 microtome (Leica Microsystems). We incubated the slices, initially at 32°C for 1 h and then at 24–26°C, in artificial cerebro-spinal fluid (aCSF) containing 126 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM KCl, 1.25 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 26 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, and 10 mM glucose, equilibrated with 95% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, pH 7.4. The thalamic slice preparation was performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Paz et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Paz et al., 2013</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S22">
<title>Patch-clamp electrophysiology from thalamic slices</title>
<p id="P37">Recordings were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Paz et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Paz et al., 2013</xref>). We visually identified nRT and TC neurons by differential contrast optics with a Zeiss (Oberkochen) Axioskop microscope and an infrared video camera. Recording electrodes made of borosilicate glass had a resistance of 2.5–4 MΩ when filled with intracellular solution. Access resistance was monitored in all the recordings, and cells were included for analysis only if the access resistance was &lt; 25 MΩ. We corrected offline the potentials for −15 mV liquid junction potential. Intrinsic and bursting properties were recorded in the presence of kynurenic acid (2 mM, Sigma), the internal solution contained 67 mM potassium gluconate, 67 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM HEPES, and 1.1 mM EGTA, 4mM ATP, 6mM phosphocreatine, pH adjusted to 7.4 with KOH (290 mOsm). For EPSCs and voltage-clamp recordings, the internal solution contained 120 mM potassium gluconate, 11 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM HEPES, and 1 mM EGTA, pH adjusted to 7.4 with KOH (290 mOsm) recorded in the presence of picrotoxin (50 μM, Tocris). For EBIO recordings, 0.4 M EBIO was initially dissolved in DMSO and then diluted to 100 μM in aCSF containing kynurenic acid (2 mM) and picrotoxin (50 μM, Tocris). We only focused on studying the subset of cells in nRT that expresses <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> and exhibits rebound burst firing which is the majority cell type in nRT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>). Recordings with EBIO were done 5–10 minutes after drug application. <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> measurements were conducted as described with steady-state inactivation protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>). This protocol, which was established by the Huguenard lab, characterizes steady-state inactivation of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> by using depolarizing commands to activate near threshold (−65mV), well-clamped currents. While a reasonable voltage clamp is possible in at least some nRT cells in slices from young animals, the yield is much too low to allow us to assess the currents in our adult DS and WT slices. Instead, we show well-controlled voltage clamp of modestly sized <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub>, demonstrate that they have the prototypical slower decay that distinguishes them from relay cells. Using this protocol, we obtain an admittedly incomplete picture of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> properties. Nevertheless, we can reliably obtain inactivation slope and half-inactivation voltage, as well as amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> at our fixed test voltage (see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Paz et al., 2010</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>)).</p>
<p id="P38">For <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> recordings, apamin (100 nm final concentration) was diluted in aCSF containing the synaptic blockers kynurenic acid (2 mM, Sigma) and picrotoxin (50 μM, Tocris). Recordings for <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> measurements were done 5–10 minutes after drug application. <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> was calculated by digitally subtracting <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> using measured in aCSF with and without apamin as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Wells et al., 2016</xref>). Currents were subtracted using Clampfit 10.5 (Molecular Devices, SCR_011323).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S23">
<title>Extracellular thalamic oscillations</title>
<p id="P39">We placed horizontal slices (400 μm) containing somatosensory thalamus in an interface chamber at 34°C and superfused them at a rate of 2 mL min<sup>−1</sup> with oxygenated aCSF (same as recipe used for patch-clamp electrophysiology, except supplemented with 0.3 mM glutamine for cellular metabolic support). Extracellular multiunit activity (MUA) recordings were obtained with a linear 16-channel multi-electrode array (Neuronexus) that spanned the nRT and VB. MUA signals were amplified 10,000 times and band-pass filtered between 100 Hz and 6 kHz using the RZ5 from Tucker-Davis Technologies (TDT, SCR_006495). Position of recording array was visually checked for each recording to confirm position of electrodes in nRT and VB. We delivered electrical stimuli to the internal capsule with a pair of tungsten microelectrodes (50–100 kΩ, FHC). The stimuli were 100 μs in duration, 50 V in amplitude, and delivered once every 30 s.</p>
<p id="P40">We then used custom MATLAB software to analyze thalamic MUA recordings.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S24">
<title>Detection of Kcnn2 mRNA in brain tissue</title>
<p id="P41">DS mice and WT littermate control mice (age 3–5 months) were euthanized with Fatal Plus, and nRT were microdissected in ice-cold sucrose cutting solution. Tissue was immediately flash-frozen and then RNA was isolated using QIAGEN RNeasy kits with on-column DNase digest. Superscript First-Strand cDNA synthesis kits were used to convert RNA into cDNA. qRT-PCR experiments were performed using the following primers for mouse <italic>Kcnn2S</italic> (short transcript variant, Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_080465.2">NM_080465.2</ext-link>): F- 5′ AGT GGT CTG GAG GAA GAG GA 3′ and R- 5′ CAT TTG CAC GTT CTC CCG AA 3′ and mouse <italic>Kccn2L</italic> (long transcript variant, Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_001312905.1">NM_001312905.1</ext-link>): F-5′ TGG TTA CAG ACT GAG ACT CTT GT 3′ and R- 5′ TCC TCT TCC TCC AGA CCA CT 3′ and the mouse house-keeping gene <italic>Gapdh</italic> (Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_001289726.1">NM_001289726.1</ext-link> and Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_008084.3">NM_008084.3</ext-link>): F- 5′ GGT CGG TGT GAA CGG ATT TG 3′ and R- 5′ GCA ACA ATC TCC ACT TTG CC 3′. Reactions were performed using Sybr Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) on a 7900HT Fast Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystems) and levels of <italic>Kcnn2</italic> mRNA were determined using the ΔΔC<sub>T</sub> method.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S25">
<title>Surgical implantation of devices for simultaneous recording of seizure activity and manipulation of brain regions</title>
<p id="P42">The devices for simultaneous ECoG, MUA recordings and optical or pharmacological manipulations in freely behaving mice were all custom made in the Paz lab. In general, recordings were optimized for assessment of somatosensory subnetworks (S1 cortex and somatosensory nRT) and thus do not necessarily generalize to other nRT domains, which should be investigated in the future. For optogenetic studies, we designed devices containing multiple screws for acquisition of ECoG signal, along with local field potential (LFP) and MUA signal recoded from tungsten electrode wires that were positioned approximately 250 and 500 mm from the tip of an optic fiber (200 μm core, ThorLabs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Paz et al., 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Clemente-Perez et al., 2017</xref>).</p>
<p id="P43">Cortical screws were implanted bilaterally in S1 (−0.5 mm posterior from Bregma, ± 3.25 mm lateral), and bilaterally in V1 (−2.9 mm posterior from Bregma, ± 3.25 mm lateral). For optogenetic manipulation of VB, optrodes were implanted at −1.5 posterior from Bregma, 1.5 mm lateral, with the tips of the optical fiber and electrodes at 3.0 mm, 3.25 and 3.5 mm ventral to the cortical surface, respectively.</p>
<p id="P44">Mice were also instrumented for local infusion of drug into nRT using cannulas (Plastics One). Briefly, we made custom-built devices in which a guide cannula was attached to our devices for recording ECoG. Tungsten wires were glued to the guide cannula, so that they protruded 250 and 400 mm from the tip of the insert cannula (500 μM protrusion from tip of guide cannula). To target nRT, guide cannulas were implanted at −1.3 mm posterior from Bregma, 2 mm lateral, and 2.5 mm deep.</p>
<p id="P45">Mice were allowed to recover for at least 1 week before recording. ECoG and thalamic LFP signals were recorded using RZ5 (TDT) and sampled at 1221 Hz, with thalamic MUA signals sampled at 24 kHz. A video camera that was synchronized to the signal acquisition was used to continuously monitor the animals. Animals were briefly anesthetized with ~2% isoflurane at the start of each recording to connect for recording. Each recording trial lasted 30–180 min. To control for circadian rhythms, we housed our animals using a regular light/dark cycle, and performed recordings between roughly 11:00 AM and 6:00 PM. All the recordings were performed during wakefulness. The location of the optrodes or cannulas was validated by histology after euthanasia in mice that did not experience sudden death and whose brains we were able to recover and process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S26">
<title>ECoG spectral analysis</title>
<p id="P46">We used the continuous wavelet transformation for spectral analysis to decompose signals into both time and frequency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Sorokin et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">2017</xref>). We used a basis of Morlet wavelets from 1–128 Hz with seven octaves and 10 wavelets per octave(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Sorokin et al., 2017</xref>). Video monitoring was used to distinguish non-convulsive and convulsive seizures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S27">
<title><italic>In vivo</italic> optogenetics during free behavior</title>
<p id="P47">We simultaneously passed a fiber optic with an inline rotating joint (Doric) through a concentric channel in the electrical commutator, and connected it to the 200-μm core fiber optic in each animal’s headpiece while recording ECoG/MU. The fiber optic was connected to 450- and 532-nm wavelength laser control boxes, which were triggered externally using the RZ5 (TDT). The tip of the optical fiber rested 100–500 mm from the most ventral tungsten electrode on each optrode to allow maximal activation of the desired brain region. We used 5–35 mW of laser power, measured at the end of the optical fiber before connecting to the animals. Light was turned on by the scientist upon visual seizure detection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S28">
<title>Pharmacological manipulations during free behavior</title>
<p id="P48">All animals were habituated to the recording chamber prior to drug studies. To determine the effects of systemic EBIO administration on non-convulsive seizure frequency in DS mice, we used a randomized-block design to record half of mice on test Day 1 with vehicle (s.c. 250 μl of 10% DMSO/90% saline) and half of the mice with EBIO (s.c. 25 mg/kg, dissolved in 10% DMSO and 90% saline) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Wells et al., 2016</xref>). We then reversed the drug condition for test day 2 (which was 48 h later). Non-convulsive seizures were manually scored offline by an experienced user during the first 30 min of vehicle or EBIO application. Note, as EBIO also changed the brain state (more time spent in stage II sleep), the user could not be blinded to the experimental condition.</p>
<p id="P49">To determine the effects of local infusion of EBIO into the nRT, we implanted mice with cannulas (Plastics One) targeting the right nRT. After recovery from surgery, 800 nL of vehicle (0.25% DMSO in saline) was infused into the right nRT at a rate of 200 nL per minute using a syringe pump. ECoG and thalamic LFP/MUA were then recorded for 1 h post drug administration. EBIO (400 μM, 0.0015% DMSO in saline) was then infused into the right nRT and the ECoG, and thalamic LFP/MUA was recorded for an additional hour. Non-convulsive seizures were manually scored offline by an experienced user during the first 60 min of vehicle or EBIO application.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S29">
<title>Human Seizure Recordings</title>
<p id="P50">All procedures were approved by the Regional and Institutional Committee of Science and Research Ethics of Scientific Council of Health. Per institutional guideline, this clinical case study was exempted from IRB approval. The original video-EEG recording of three patients with DS associated with <italic>SCN1A</italic> pathogenic variant was reviewed by an experienced pediatric neurophysiologist (MRC). The international 10–20 system was used for electrode placement. From our cohort of patients with DS, we selected patients in whom long-term video-EEG recording was performed (&gt; 19 hours) and non-convulsive seizures were recorded. Atypical absences where defined as discharge of irregular high voltage spikes and slow waves accompanied by decrease awareness and at time eyelids and/or upper limb slight myoclonic jerks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S30">
<title>Computational modeling</title>
<p id="P51">A computational model of the negative feedback loop between TC neurons and thalamic reticular nucleus (nRT) neurons was built to assess the oscillatory response of thalamic slices in WT and DS mice. Excitability in TC and nRT neurons was described using the Hodgkin-Huxley formalism, based on previous modeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Paz et al., 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Destexhe et al., 1994</xref>), with some parameters fitted from present intracellular recordings. The nRT model included the leak, fast sodium, delayed rectifier potassium, low-threshold calcium (CaT), calcium-activated potassium (SK) and calcium-activated non-specific cationic (CAN) currents, and the TC model incorporated the leak, fast sodium, delayed rectifier potassium, low-threshold calcium (CaT) and hyperpolarization-activated (H) currents. Both neuron models included first-order calcium dynamics. The negative feedback loop between TC and nRT neurons was implemented with AMPA and NMDA currents at synapses from TC to nRT neurons and GABA–A and GABA–B currents at synapses from nRT to TC neurons. A noise current with zero mean was introduced in both nRT and TC neurons to account for the stochasticity observed experimentally in the thalamic circuit. The WT domain was defined, in the space of CaT and SK maximal conductances of the nRT neuron, as the parameter region yielding realistic nRT action potential firing frequencies and circuit oscillations with burst numbers and durations consistent with those obtained in slices. The DS domain was defined as the region with a similar CaT maximal conductance range but with lower SK maximal conductance, consistent with the smaller <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> found in intracellular nRT recordings in DS mice.</p>
<sec id="S31">
<title>Thalamic reticular nucleus neuron</title>
<p id="P52">The membrane potential of the nRT neuron model followed <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M7" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RT</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where the leak current was <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The action potential currents <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> were derived from [(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Traub et al., 1991</xref>)], with doubled kinetics and a leftward shift of sodium inactivation and potassium activation voltage–dependences (−10 mV and −20 mV, respectively) to qualitatively reproduce the action potentials’ properties observed experimentally in mice nRT neurons. The T–type calcium current <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was derived from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Destexhe et al., 1994</xref>), with activation and inactivation kinetics respectively slowed by factors 10 and 2, to account for voltage–clamp data observed (~200 ms inactivation at −75 mV) and reversal potential computed as <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the extracellular calcium concentration, <italic>R</italic> the gas constant, <italic>T</italic> the absolute temperature and <italic>F</italic> the Faraday constant. The SK–type calcium–activated potassium current was <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M14" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with second order activation(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Destexhe et al., 1994</xref>),(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Adelman et al., 2012</xref>) following <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M15" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M16" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M17" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The non–specific cationic CAN current followed: <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M18" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with first-order activation <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M19" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M20" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M21" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Calcium dynamics followed first-order dynamics <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M22" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>•</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CaT</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where the surface to volume ratio is <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M23" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M24" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the soma radius and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M25" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the width of a sub–membrane shell where calcium freely diffuses, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M26" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the basal intracellular calcium concentration and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M27" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the intracellular calcium time constant. Parameters were: <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>nRT</italic></sub> = 1<italic>μFcm</italic><sup>−2</sup>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M28" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.033</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M29" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M30" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>35</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M31" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M32" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Scm</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M33" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>nRT</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>80</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M34" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M35" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M36" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as detailed in legends, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M37" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>80</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M38" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Ca</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M39" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M40" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.015</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M41" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>30</mml:mn><mml:mtext>mV</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M42" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M43" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>150</mml:mn><mml:mtext>ms</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M44" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M45" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mtext>ms</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M46" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M47" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S32">
<title>TC neuron</title>
<p id="P54">The model of TC neurons was as described(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Paz et al., 2013</xref>), with: <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M48" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and parameters corresponding to the physiological condition.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S33">
<title>Synaptic architecture</title>
<p id="P55">The negative feedback loop between TC and nRT neurons was implemented as the interaction of one RTN and one TC neuron. The TC→nRT connexion comprised AMPA and NMDA components. The AMPA current was <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M49" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with glutamatergic activation kinetics following first order deactivation with time constant <italic>τ</italic><sub><italic>AMPA</italic></sub> and soft–bound increment at every TC action potential: <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M50" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>•</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <italic>δ</italic>() is the Dirac function and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M51" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents TC spike arrival times. The NMDA current was <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M52" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with a glutamatergic activation scheme similar to that of the current and where the voltage–dependence was taken from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Lacey et al., 2012</xref>). The nRT→TC connexion comprised GABA–A and GABA–B components with formalisms similar to that of AMPA currents. To model synaptic interactions between TC and nRT thalamic populations, every spike of each model neuron evoked ten spikes in the other neuron of the model, with delays uniformly distributed within 1–3 ms. Synaptic parameters were <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M53" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>AMPA</italic></sub> = 0<italic>mV</italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub><italic>AMPA</italic></sub> = 1<italic>ms</italic>, Δ<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>AMPA</italic></sub> = 0.25, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M54" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>NMDA</italic></sub> = 0<italic>mV</italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub><italic>NMDA</italic></sub> = 75<italic>ms</italic>, Δ<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>NMDA</italic></sub> = 0.1, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M55" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.45</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>GABA</italic>−<italic>A</italic></sub> = −95<italic>mV</italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub><italic>GABA</italic>−<italic>A</italic></sub> = 1<italic>ms</italic>, Δ<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>GABA</italic>−<italic>A</italic></sub> = 0.25, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M56" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>GABA</italic>−<italic>B</italic></sub> = −95<italic>mV</italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub><italic>GABA</italic>−<italic>B</italic></sub> = 75<italic>ms</italic>, Δ<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>GABA</italic>−<italic>B</italic></sub> = 0.1.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S34">
<title>Source of noise in nRT and TC neurons</title>
<p id="P56">We introduced a source of noise in nRT and TC neurons. Multiple sources of noise exist in real neurons, notably due to the stochasticity in the gating dynamics of membrane and synaptic channels. Introducing stochasticity allows network oscillations to end at one point – because of membrane voltage fluctuations – as observed experimentally (without noise, oscillations are endless in the model, once triggered). To do so, we added to nRT and TC neurons a small stochastic current mimicking noisy fluctuations in intrinsic and synaptic currents, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M57" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where time–varying conductances <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M58" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> were built as standard normally–distributed random processes, filtered with time constant <italic>τ</italic><sub><italic>Noise</italic></sub> and normalized to admit a given standard deviation <italic>σ</italic><sub><italic>Noise</italic></sub>. Note that these conductance had zero mean, so they had no net depolarizing/hyperpolarizing effect on the membrane potential of nRT and TC neurons per se and their sole influence was to introduce stochasticity. The time–varying conductances affecting nRT and TC neurons, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M59" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M60" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, were independent. Stochastic parameters were σ<sub><italic>Noise</italic></sub> = 10<sup>−3</sup><italic>mScm</italic><sup>−2</sup>, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>Noise</italic></sub> = 0<italic>mV</italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub><italic>Noise</italic></sub> = 20<italic>ms</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S35">
<title>Simulation protocols</title>
<p id="P57">In simulations mimicking intracellular recordings in nRT neurons, all synaptic conductances and the noise conductance were set to zero, the TC model was not computed and the nRT neuron was stimulated with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M61" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for 500 ms, as applied experimentally. In network simulations, the optogenetic stimulation applied to TC neurons was mimicked with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M62" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for 25 ms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S36">
<title>Definition of WT and DS domains in the <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M63" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CaT</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> parameter space</title>
<p id="P58">To define WT and DS domains, we first selected the <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M64" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> range in which the nRT neuron model produced realistic action potential firing frequencies in the range 50–230 Hz, as found experimentally. This domain corresponded to <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M65" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.3</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In this <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M66" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> range of realistic nRT spiking frequencies, the WT domain was operationally defined as <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M67" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values for which the nRT–TC network model produced oscillations ranging within 5–35 bursts and lasting within 0.5–6 s, as found experimentally. These criteria defined a domain corresponding to large <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M68" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values (~1 – 2.5<italic>mScm</italic><sup>−2</sup>), with large AHP repolarizations, as found observed in intracellular nRT recordings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The DS domain was then defined – within the <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M69" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> range of realistic nRT spiking frequencies – as models with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M70" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values smaller than those found in the WT domain, consistent with the smaller size of the <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> in intracellular nRT recordings of DS mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1H,I</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S37">
<title>Numerical simulations</title>
<p id="P59">Ordinary differential equations were solved using the forward Euler scheme with 0.01 ms time step. Simulated time was 25 s maximum and was interrupted after 300 ms in the absence of discharge. The maps for circuit simulations were obtained taking the mean of 30 repetitions of the network simulations with different noise realizations. The specific quantitative details of the results obtained obviously depended on parameter values but the behaviors observed were qualitatively very robust with regard to variations in intrinsic and synaptic parameter.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S38">
<title>QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</title>
<p id="P60">All numerical values are given as means and error bars are standard error of the mean (SEM) unless stated otherwise. Data analysis was performed with MATLAB (SCR_001622), Origin 9.0 (Microcal Software, SCR_002815), GraphPad Prism 6 (SCR_002798), and SigmaPlot (SCR_003210).</p>
<sec id="S39">
<title>Comparison of thalamic circuit oscillations in thalamic slices</title>
<p id="P61">We used custom MATLAB software to detect extracellular spikes based on taking the first derivative of the MU signal and thresholding over background. Spikes were excluded if their waveform lasted 2 ms longer. An experienced user confirmed parameter settings to optimize for all recordings. Bursts were defined as three or more spikes per burst, with the max interburst interval as 1.2 s. We quantified the number of total evoked bursts and oscillation duration recorded in the most active VB channels using on average 10–20 sweeps per recording. All data were compared using a Mann-Whitney test, with alpha = 0.05. (*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S40">
<title>Analysis of electrophysiological properties</title>
<sec id="S41">
<title>The input resistance (R<sub>in</sub>) and membrane time constant (τ<sub>m</sub>)</title>
<p id="P62">were measured from the membrane hyperpolarizations in response to low intensity current steps (−20 to −60 pA) in linear portion of the V–I plots. R<sub>in</sub> and τ<sub>m</sub> were compared with Mann-Whitney test, with α = 0.05, (ns, non-significant, p &gt; 0.05) using GraphPad Prism 6 (SCR_002798).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S42">
<title>T currents (I<sub>T</sub>)</title>
<p id="P63">Data for <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> half-maximal voltage (V50%) were taken from the Boltzmann function calculated using Origin 9.0 (Microcal Software, SCR_002815). Most data were compared using a Mann-Whitney test, with alpha = 0.05 (*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001). Number of APs on first burst measured against hyperpolarization step was compared through individual unpaired t tests not corrected for multiple comparisons, with alpha = 0.05, (*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001). Mann-Whitney tests and individual unpaired t tests were done using GraphPad Prism 6 (SCR_002798).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S43">
<title>SK currents (<italic>I<sub>SK</sub></italic>)</title>
<p id="P64">were recorded at a constant holding voltage following a hyperpolarizing step to gate <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>). Apamin subtraction was carried out by digitally subtracting averaged traces (typically 2 – 5 sweeps) obtained following bath application of 100 nM apamin. This subtraction protocol to measure <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> was adapted from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>). We assessed the quality and stability of voltage–clamp control in these recordings as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cueni et al., 2008</xref>). First, we tested whether apamin–sensitive currents, obtained by digital subtraction, remained stable for the period required to perform application of pharmacological substances via the bath or through the recording pipette (~10 min). Second, we carried out the subtraction when all recording conditions, such as input resistance, series resistance and capacitive currents remained unaltered before and after 100 nM apamin application. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S1G and S1H</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S44">
<title>What is the advantage of using a Steady-state inactivation (SSIT) protocol for quantifying I<sub>T</sub> and I<sub>SK</sub>?</title>
<p id="P65">SSIT used to measure <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> allows us to have a well-controlled voltage-clamp as shown by the fact that the decay time constants (orange lines show decay exponential fit) of the <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> do not vary depending on the voltage step used to deinactivate the <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1G</xref>). The voltage-clamp was verified before and after apamin application, and cells that showed more than 10% of variation in voltage clamp were excluded from the study. Although <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> is small with this SSIT protocol, it has a major advantage of offering a well-controlled voltage-clamp which allows a reliable quantification of <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub>, which is well-established for measuring <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> in brain slices from adult animals (see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Paz et al., 2010</xref>)). Note that the subtraction by this optimized SSIT method, with small amplitude <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub>, does not require clipping of the subtraction artifact as has been used in previous studies. Thus, the kinetics of the <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> activation can be obtained without artifact using the SSIT protocol.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S45">
<title>Analysis of cortical rhythm modulation by selective optical activation of thalamic neurons during free behavior</title>
<sec id="S46">
<title>ECoG spectral analysis</title>
<p id="P66">Spectrogram images in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> were generated for frequencies between 0 and 25 Hz using the short-time Fourier transform with 0.5 s Hamming windows and 98% overlap between segments. The power spectral density estimates were plotted as the mean values of the spectrogram at each point at 0–25 Hz during the seizure event.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S47">
<title>Optogenetic seizure interruption analysis</title>
<p id="P67">To compare the effects of light on EcoG power, we calculated relative changes in averaged band power between pre-stimulus (PreStim, 2 s before light pulse) and post-stimulus (PostStim, 2 s after end of light pulse) periods across multiple recording trials (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Average power at 1–25 Hz was calculated using a modified periodogram. The difference between groups was analyzed using a Mann-Whitney rank sum test (p &lt; 0.005).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="SM1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<label>1</label>
<media id="d36e5132" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS1517849-supplement-1.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2">
<label>2</label>
<media id="d36e5136" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS1517849-supplement-2.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S48">
<title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
<p id="P68">S.R.-M. is supported by the American Epilepsy Society and the Dravet Syndrome Foundation Postdoctoral Research Fellowship. B.H. is supported by the American Epilepsy Society Postdoctoral Research Fellowship. J.T.P. is supported by NIH/NINDS R01NS096369, the DoD, the NSF, Gladstone Institutes, the Kavli Institute for Fundamental Neuroscience, the Michael Prize, and the Jewett Foundation. A.C.-P. and F.S.C. are supported by NSF Graduate Research Fellowships. S.S.H. is supported by the ARCS Foundation and Weill Institute Foundation scholarships. O.H.J.E.R. and F.E.H. are supported by Dutch NWO-ALW VIDI 016.121.346 and ZON-MW TOPGO.L.10.066 and the Erasmus MC MRace. M.-C.C. is supported by the Belgian American Education Foundation. We thank Scott Brovarney and Juan Alcauter for help with animal husbandry and technical help with histology. We thank Jordan Sorokin and John Huguenard for sharing their MATLAB code for the analysis of evoked thalamic oscillations. We thank Meredith Calvert from the Gladstone Histology &amp; Light Microscopy Core for experimental and technical support. We thank Drs. Daniel Lowenstein and Adam Numis for their feedback on the interpretation of the human EEG and Brett Mensh for critical feedback on the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn id="FN3">
<p id="P69">SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION</p>
<p id="P70">Supplemental Information includes six figures and can be found with this article online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2018.12.018">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2018.12.018</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN5">
<p id="P71">DECLARATION OF INTERESTS</p>
<p id="P72">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="R1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adelman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maylie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Sah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Small-conductance Ca2+-activated K+ channels: form and function</article-title>. <source/>Annu. Rev. Physiol
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21942705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clawson</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Offord</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lenk</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogiwara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meisler</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parent</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Isom</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Altered cardiac electrophysiology and SUDEP in a model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>PLoS One
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e77843</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24155976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barthó</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slézia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mátyás</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faradzs-Zade</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ulbert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Acsády</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Ongoing network state controls the length of sleep spindles via inhibitory activity</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>1367</fpage>–<lpage>1379</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24945776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bazhenov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timofeev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steriade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Spiking-bursting activity in the thalamic reticular nucleus initiates sequences of spindle oscillations in thalamic networks</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurophysiol
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>1076</fpage>–<lpage>1087</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beenhakker</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Neurons that fire together also conspire together: is normal sleep circuitry hijacked to generate epilepsy?</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>612</fpage>–<lpage>632</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19524522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zachwieja</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Cacna1g is a genetic modifier of epilepsy in a mouse model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>e111</fpage>–<lpage>e115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28556246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheah</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westenbroek</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalume</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Specific deletion of NaV1.1 sodium channels in inhibitory interneurons causes seizures and premature death in a mouse model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>14646</fpage>–<lpage>14651</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22908258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Claes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Del-Favero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ceulemans</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lagae</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Broeckhoven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>De Jonghe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>De novo mutations in the sodium-channel gene SCN1A cause severe myoclonic epilepsy of infancy</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>1327</fpage>–<lpage>1332</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11359211</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Claes</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deprez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suls</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baets</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smets</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Dyck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deconinck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jordanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>De Jonghe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The SCN1A variant database: a novel research and diagnostic tool</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mutat
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>E904</fpage>–<lpage>E920</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19585586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clemente-Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Makinson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higashikubo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brovarney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wimer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dávid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fenno</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <etal></etal> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Distinct Thalamic Reticular Cell Types Differentially Modulate Normal and Pathological Cortical Rhythms</article-title>. <source/>Cell Rep
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>2130</fpage>–<lpage>2142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28591583</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crick</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Function of the thalamic reticular complex: the searchlight hypothesis</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>4586</fpage>–<lpage>4590</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6589612</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cueni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Canepari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luján</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emmenegger</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adelman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Lüthi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>T-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels, SK2 channels and SERCAs gate sleep-related oscillations in thalamic dendrites</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>692</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18488023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Dalla Bernardina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Capovilla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Chiamenti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>). <chapter-title>Myoclonic epilepsies of infancy and early childhood: nosological and prognostic approach</chapter-title> In <source/>Advances in Epileptology, <name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Penry</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, eds. (<publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>), pp. <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Deschênes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Steriade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Electrophysiology of neurons of lateral thalamic nuclei in cat: resting properties and burst discharges</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurophysiol
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1196</fpage>–<lpage>1219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6737028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Destexhe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Steriade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>A model of spindle rhythmicity in the isolated thalamic reticular nucleus</article-title>.<source/>J. Neurophysiol
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>818</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7527077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dravet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The core Dravet syndrome phenotype</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia
<volume>52</volume> (<issue>Suppl 2</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Makinson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papale</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Escayg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Preferential inactivation of Scn1a in parvalbumin interneurons increases seizure susceptibility</article-title>. <source/>Neurobiol. Dis
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22926190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Favero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sotuyo</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A Transient Developmental Window of Fast-Spiking Interneuron Dysfunction in a Mouse Model of Dravet Syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>7912</fpage>–<lpage>7927</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30104343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Claaßen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bardins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teufel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krafczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schniepp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Strupp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Effect of chlorzoxazone in patients with downbeat nystagmus: a pilot trial</article-title>. <source/>Neurology
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1152</fpage>–<lpage>1158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23975871</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ferrarelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Tononi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The thalamic reticular nucleus and schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Schizophr. Bull
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21131368</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Todorov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Dorp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van den Maagdenberg</surname><given-names>AMJM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Zeeuw</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Hoebeek</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Cerebellar ataxia by enhanced Ca(V)2.1 currents is alleviated by Ca2+-dependent K+-channel activators in Cacna1a(S218L) mutant mice</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>15533</fpage>–<lpage>15546</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23115190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gentet</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Strong, reliable and precise synaptic connections between thalamic relay cells and neurones of the nucleus reticularis in juvenile rats</article-title>. <source/>J. Physiol
<volume>546</volume>, <fpage>801</fpage>–<lpage>811</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12563005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gheyara</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ponnusamy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Djukic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Mucke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Tau reduction prevents disease in a mouse model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Ann. Neurol
<volume>76</volume>, <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25042160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>ZV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Druckmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerfen</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Maintenance of persistent activity in a frontal thalamocortical loop</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>545</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28467817</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guzzetta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Cognitive and behavioral characteristics of children with Dravet syndrome: an overview</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia
<volume>52</volume> (<issue>Suppl 2</issue>), <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Halassa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Acsády</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Thalamic Inhibition: Diverse Sources, Diverse Scales</article-title>. <source/>Trends Neurosci
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>680</fpage>–<lpage>693</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27589879</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Halassa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritt</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Selective optical drive of thalamic reticular nucleus generates thalamic bursts and cortical spindles</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21785436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Hlf is a genetic modifier of epilepsy caused by voltage-gated sodium channel mutations</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsy Res
<volume>119</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26656780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zachwieja</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Fine Mapping of a Dravet Syndrome Modifier Locus on Mouse Chromosome 5 and Candidate Gene Analysis by RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source/>PLoS Genet
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e1006398</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27768696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hedrich</surname><given-names>UBS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liautard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirschenbaum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pofahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavigne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slotta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Escayg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dihné</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal></etal> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Impaired action potential initiation in GABAergic interneurons causes hyperexcitable networks in an epileptic mouse model carrying a human Na(V)1.1 mutation</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>14874</fpage>–<lpage>14889</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25378155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holder</surname><given-names>JL</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, and <name><surname>Quach</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The spectrum of epilepsy and electroencephalographic abnormalities due to SHANK3 loss-of-function mutations</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>1651</fpage>–<lpage>1659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27554343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Houser</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>GABA neurons are the major cell type of the nucleus reticularis thalami</article-title>. <source/>Brain Res
<volume>200</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7417821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huntsman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Porcello</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Homanics</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeLorey</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Reciprocal inhibitory connections and network synchrony in the mammalian thalamus</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>283</volume>, <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9915702</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jahnsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Llinás</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Electrophysiological properties of guinea-pig thalamic neurones: an in vitro study</article-title>. <source/>J. Physiol
<volume>349</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6737292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Social deficits in the AY-9944 mouse model of atypical absence epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Behav. Brain Res
<volume>236</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22944514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalume</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westenbroek</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheah</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheuer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Sudden unexpected death in a mouse model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J. Clin. Invest
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>1798</fpage>–<lpage>1808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R37">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalume</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westenbroek</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gile</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de la Iglesia</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheuer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Sleep impairment and reduced interneuron excitability in a mouse model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Neurobiol. Dis
<volume>77</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25766678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R38">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karussis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leker</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Abramsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Cognitive dysfunction following thalamic stroke: a study of 16 cases and review of the literature</article-title>.<source/>J. Neurol. Sci
<volume>172</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10620656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R39">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kleiman-Weiner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beenhakker</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Synergistic roles of GABAA receptors and SK channels in regulating thalamocortical oscillations</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurophysiol
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19386752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R40">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lacey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Enhanced NMDA receptor-dependent thalamic excitation and network oscillations in stargazer mice</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>11067</fpage>–<lpage>11081</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22875939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R41">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Makinson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sorokin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Escayg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Regulation of Thalamic and Cortical Network Synchrony by Scn8a</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>1165</fpage>–<lpage>1179.e6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28238546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R42">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papale</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Escayg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The voltage-gated sodium channel Scn8a is a genetic modifier of severe myoclonic epilepsy of infancy</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>2892</fpage>–<lpage>2899</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R43">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogiwara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atapour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mazaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Take-uchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itohara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal></etal> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Nav1.1 localizes to axons of parvalbumin-positive inhibitory interneurons: a circuit basis for epileptic seizures in mice carrying an Scn1a gene mutation</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>5903</fpage>–<lpage>5914</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17537961</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R44">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogiwara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwasato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamagata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mazaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tamamaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hensch</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itohara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Yamakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Nav1.1 haploinsufficiency in excitatory neurons ameliorates seizure-associated sudden death in a mouse model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Hum. Mol. Genet
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>4784</fpage>–<lpage>4804</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23922229</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R45">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Papale</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Makinson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Christopher Ehlen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tufik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Escayg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Altered sleep regulation in a mouse model of SCN1A-derived genetic epilepsy with febrile seizures plus (GEFS+)</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23311867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R46">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Paxinos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <source/>Mouse Brain in Stereotaxic Coordinates (<publisher-name>Elsevier Academic Press</publisher-name>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R47">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Microcircuits and their interactions in epilepsy: is the focus out of focus?</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25710837</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R48">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Focal cortical infarcts alter intrinsic excitability and synaptic excitation in the reticular thalamic nucleus</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>5465</fpage>–<lpage>5479</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20392967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R49">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fenno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yizhar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deisseroth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A new mode of corticothalamic transmission revealed in the Gria4(−/−) model of absence epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1167</fpage>–<lpage>1173</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21857658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R50">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frechette</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delord</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deisseroth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Closed-loop optogenetic control of thalamus as a tool for interrupting seizures after cortical injury</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23143518</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R51">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pinault</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The thalamic reticular nucleus: structure, function and concept</article-title>. <source/>Brain Res. Rev
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15297152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R52">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westenbroek</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheuer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Dissecting the phenotypes of Dravet syndrome by gene deletion</article-title>. <source/>Brain
<volume>138</volume>, <fpage>2219</fpage>–<lpage>2233</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R53">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saalmann</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Kastner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The cognitive thalamus</article-title>. <source/>Front. Syst. Neurosci
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25852498</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R54">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slaght</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leresche</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deniau</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crunelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Charpier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Activity of thalamic reticular neurons during spontaneous genetically determined spike and wave discharges</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2323</fpage>–<lpage>2334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R55">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sorokin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Absence seizure susceptibility correlates with pre-ictal b oscillations</article-title>. <source/>J. Physiol. Paris
<volume>110</volume> (<issue>4 Pt A</issue>), <fpage>372</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28576554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R56">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sorokin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frechette</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abramian</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deisseroth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huguenard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Bidirectional Control of Generalized Epilepsy Networks via Rapid Real-Time Switching of Firing Mode</article-title>. <source/>Neuron
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27989462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R57">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Steriade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oakson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Deschênes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The deafferented reticular thalamic nucleus generates spindle rhythmicity</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurophysiol
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3559675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R58">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Steriade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Thalamocortical oscillations in the sleeping and aroused brain</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>262</volume>, <fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8235588</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R59">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westenbroek</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheuer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Impaired excitability of somatostatin- and parvalbumin-expressing cortical interneurons in a mouse model of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>E3139</fpage>–<lpage>E3148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25024183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R60">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Traub</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Michelson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A model of a CA3 hippocampal pyramidal neuron incorporating voltage-clamp data on intrinsic conductances</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurophysiol
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1663538</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R61">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>von Krosigk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Cellular mechanisms of a synchronized oscillation in the thalamus</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>261</volume>, <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8392750</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R62">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alviña</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Womack</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chevez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Khodakhah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Decreases in the precision of Purkinje cell pacemaking cause cerebellar dysfunction and ataxia</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16474392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R63">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Halassa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Thalamic reticular impairment underlies attention deficit in Ptchd1(Y/-) mice</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>532</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27007844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R64">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Astori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rovó</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chatton</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adelman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Lüthi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Sustaining sleep spindles through enhanced SK2-channel activity consolidates sleep and elevates arousal threshold</article-title>.<source/>J. Neurosci
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>13917</fpage>–<lpage>13928</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23035101</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R65">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yizhar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fenno</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prigge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O’Shea</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sohal</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goshen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <etal></etal> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Neocortical excitation/inhibition balance in information processing and social dysfunction</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>477</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21796121</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R66">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mantegazza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westenbroek</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalume</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spain</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheuer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Reduced sodium current in GABAergic interneurons in a mouse model of severe myoclonic epilepsy in infancy</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Neurosci
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1142</fpage>–<lpage>1149</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R67">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z-W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zak</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>MeCP2 is required for normal development of GABAergic circuits in the thalamus</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurophysiol
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>2470</fpage>–<lpage>2481</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20200124</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<title>SK Deficiency in nRT Neurons Underlies Enhanced Cellular Bursting in DS Mice</title>
<p id="P73">(A) Representative traces show that Dravet syndrome (DS) neurons (red) exhibit enhanced post-inhibitory rebound burst firing upon hyperpolarization induced by −60 pA current pulses, compared to wild-type (WT) (black). The number of APs in the rebound burst are marked above.</p>
<p id="P74">(B) Number of APs in the rebound burst (WT, n = 30 cells, 4 mice; DS, n = 43 cells, 6 mice). Data are represented as means ± SEMs, compared with parametric t test with Welch’s correction and α = 0.05, **p &lt; 0.001.</p>
<p id="P75">(C–G) T-type calcium current (<italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub>) is similar in nRT neurons from DS mice and WT littermates.</p>
<p id="P76">(C) Representative traces showing <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> from nRT cells of DS animals and WT littermates (C–F: DS, n = 26 neurons, 6 mice; WT, n = 14 neurons, 4 mice).</p>
<p id="P77">(D) <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> density, maximal amplitude divided by individual cell capacitance.</p>
<p id="P78">(E) <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> decay time constant.</p>
<p id="P79">(F) <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> half-maximal voltage (<italic>V50%</italic>) taken from Boltzmann function.</p>
<p id="P80">(G) Normalized <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> amplitude plotted as a function of the pre-pulse membrane potential best fitted with a Boltzmann function (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.99 for both fits) (DS, n = 16 cells, 6 mice; WT littermates, n = 13 cells, 4 mice).</p>
<p id="P81">(H) <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> traces obtained by digital subtraction in nRT neurons from a WT (black) mouse and a DS (red) mouse (also see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S1G and S1H</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Method Details</xref>).</p>
<p id="P82">(I) <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>SK</italic></sub> density, maximal current divided by individual cell capacitance. Data are represented as means ± SEMs, compared with the Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test. **p = 0.0085. (WT, n = 8 cells, 3 mice; DS, n = 10 cells, 3 mice).</p>
<p id="P83">(J and K) SK2 relative mRNA expression levels (encoded <italic>Kcnn2</italic>, short, J, and long, K, transcript variants) normalized to glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) mRNA, in nRT. Expression levels were calculated using the ΔΔC<sub>T</sub> method and expressed as arbitrary units. Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test, **p &lt; 0.01.</p>
<p id="P84">(L) Number of APs on the rebound burst, plotted against hyperpolarization step (mV) with vehicle or 100 μM EBIO treatment. WT, n = 6 neurons, 3 mice; DS, n = 6 neurons, 3 mice. Data are represented as means ± SEMs. Data points compared by individual unpaired t test, not corrected for multiple comparisons, *p &lt; 0.03.</p>
<p id="P85">(M) Schematic of the minimal thalamic circuit used for computational modeling, including TC<sub>VB</sub> and nRT neurons, TC<sub>VB</sub> to nRT a-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid (AMPA) and <italic>N</italic>-methyl-d-aspartate (NMDA) excitatory synapses, and nRT to TC<sub>VB</sub> GABA-A and GABA-B inhibitory synapses. Only the nRT neuron (black) is simulated (synaptic currents are absent) to obtain the results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1N and 1O</xref>.</p>
<p id="P86">(N) Voltage traces of an nRT neuron in the WT parameter domain (black trace; <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.85</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and of a neuron in the DS domain with decreased SK maximum conductance (red trace; <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.85</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), in response to a hyperpolarizing injected current <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for 500 ms.</p>
<p id="P87">(O) Map of the average number of APs in the rebound burst in the nRT neuron model as a function of <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> maximal conductance parameters. APs numbers are computed over 30 simulations with different realizations of noise in the model. The means of these average numbers of APs are indicated in the WT (white) and DS (red) domains.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1517849-f0002"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<title>SK Deficiency in nRT Neurons Underlies Intra-thalamic Circuit Hyperexcit-ability in DS Mice</title>
<p id="P88">(A) Representative evoked intra-thalamic circuit oscillations in thalamic slices from WT and DS mice. Black circles indicate stimulation artifact. Left and right boxes indicate sections of the recording that were expanded, bottom left and right, respectively. Double-sided arrow indicates the length of the evoked oscillation in DS recording. Top right inset: schematic of the intrathalamic oscillatory microcircuit between VB and nRT. Stimulation of the internal capsule (black circle and lightning bolt) leads to an interplay of activity between nRT and TC<sub>VB</sub> cells that resembles a ping-pong game causing a circuit oscillation whose strength can be assessed by VB recordings in horizontal thalamic slice preparations (see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6F</xref>).</p>
<p id="P89">(B–D) Data analyzed by the Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test,WT, n = 9 mice; DS, n = 12 mice. Data are represented as means ± SEMs.</p>
<p id="P90">(B) Duration of evoked oscillation, **p &lt; 0.01.</p>
<p id="P91">(C) Number of bursts within the evoked oscillation, *p &lt; 0.05.</p>
<p id="P92">(D) Burst frequency within the evoked oscillation, **p &lt; 0.01.</p>
<p id="P93">(E) Schematic of the full nRT-TC<sub>VB</sub> circuit used for the computational modeling of thalamic oscillations in WT and DS conditions.</p>
<p id="P94">(F) Top: representative nRT and TC<sub>VB</sub> voltage traces triggered by a stimulus (*) mimicking the electrical stimulation of the internal capsule, in the WT and DS conditions. Bottom: probability distributions of the duration of oscillations in the circuit over 1,000 simulations with different realizations of the stochastic current. The mean oscillation duration in the nRT-TC<sub>VB</sub> circuit model in the DS condition is ~5 times that in the WT condition. The maximal conductances are as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1N</xref>.</p>
<p id="P95">(G, I, and K) Maps of the duration (G), burst number(I), and frequency (K) in the nRT-TC<sub>VB</sub> circuit model, as a function of CaT and SK maximal conductances, computed over 30 simulations with different realizations of noise. The mean of these averages in the WT and DS domains (white and red boundaries, respectively) are indicated.(H, J, and L) Plots of means ± SEMs of the duration(H), burst number (J), and frequency (L) using 9 samples with randomly maximal conductances drawn from the WT domain and 12 samples with randomly maximal conductances drawn from the DS domain, with groups compared using the Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test (H, **p = 0.0062; J, *p = 0.0208; L, **p = 0.0002).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1517849-f0003"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<title>DS Mice Exhibit Non-convulsive Seizures Similar to Human Patients with DS</title>
<p id="P96">(A) Diagram of the mouse electrocorticography (ECoG) and thalamic depth electrode recording montage. ECoG was recorded from somatosensory (S1) and visual (V1) cortices, with depth electrodes implanted in the thalamus.</p>
<p id="P97">(B) Top: example of an ECoG signature of a representative non-convulsive seizure in DS mice recorded from S1 (black), along with simultaneous multiunit (MU) recordings in the thalamus—in this case, the ventrobasal thalamus (orange). Inset: magnification of ECoG poly-spikes overlaid on a slower oscillation. Bottom: spectrogram showing frequency components of the recorded seizure.</p>
<p id="P98">(C) MU recordings in the somatosensory thalamus simultaneously with ECoG show in both nRT and VB clusters of APs (“population bursts” of AP firing) phase locked with ECoG poly-spikes.</p>
<p id="P99">(D) Power spectral density of the seizure shown in (B). Peak fundamental frequency is 6–7 Hz.</p>
<p id="P100">(E) Diagram of human EEG recording montage.</p>
<p id="P101">(F) Top: EEG signature of a non-convulsive seizure in a patient with DS recorded in two different locations on the scalp. Inset: spikes are not typical spike-and-wave discharges and have a higher frequency component in addition to the slower oscillation. Bottom: spectrogram showing frequency components of the recorded seizure.</p>
<p id="P102">(G) Expanded EEG shows epileptic activity characterized by a sequence of poly-spikes overlaid on a slower oscillation (compare with C).</p>
<p id="P103">(H) Power spectral density of the seizure shown in (E). Peak fundamental frequency of the depicted seizure is ~5 Hz, but it can vary across the different cortical regions for the same seizure (see Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4</xref>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1517849-f0004"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<title>Local or Systemic EBIO Treatment Reduces Non-convulsive Seizure Frequency in DS Mice</title>
<p id="P104">(A) Diagram of targeting of the thalamus with guide cannulas and tungsten electrodes for unit recordings. Inset: depth electrodes were positioned in nRT.</p>
<p id="P105">(B) Quantification of effects of intra-nRT administration of EBIO (800 nL of 0.4 mM) on non-convulsive seizure number within 1 hr of infusion. Data are from n = 4 DS mice. *p = 0.0189, two-tailed t test.</p>
<p id="P106">(C) Diagram of systemic administration of EBIO (25 mg/kg, subcutaneously [s.c.]).</p>
<p id="P107">(D) Quantification of effects of systemic administration of EBIO (25 mg/kg, s.c.) on non-convulsive seizure number within 30 min of EBIO infusion. Data are from n = 9 DS mice. **p = 0.0039 Wilcoxon signed-rank test.</p>
<p id="P108">(E) Representative ECoG and multiunit activity (MUA) traces from one DS mouse after vehicle and EBIO treatments.</p>
<p id="P109">(F) Magnification of the recordings indicated with red line in (E). Note the lack of seizures in ECoG and switch from bursting to single spike (arrows) firing mode after EBIO injection.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1517849-f0005"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<title>Optogenetic Disruption of Thalamic Bursting Aborts Non-convulsive Seizures in DS Mice</title>
<p id="P110">(A) Diagram showing that nRT modulates cortical rhythms through the relay thalamus.</p>
<p id="P111">(B) Diagram of optogenetic targeting of the thalamus. Inset: depth electrodes were positioned in VB thalamus.</p>
<p id="P112">(C) Top: example of optogenetic seizure interruption of an ongoing non-convulsive seizure in a DS mouse. The blue bar corresponds to a brief (50 ms) pulse of blue light to activate SSFO-expressing thalamocortical neurons. Unilateral activation of SSFO in the thalamus immediately interrupts the seizure. Bottom: spectrogram showing frequency components of the recorded seizure and decrease in power after SSFO activation.</p>
<p id="P113">(D) Magnification of the seizure interruption shown in (C). Activation of SSFO switches burst firing in the thalamus to tonic firing.</p>
<p id="P114">(E) Quantification of 1–25 Hz broadband power 2 s before and after optogenetic manipulation. Data are from 32 trials across 4 mice. ****p &lt; 0.0001 Mann-Whitney test.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1517849-f0006"></graphic>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" orientation="landscape" position="float">
<caption>
<p id="P115">KEY RESOURCES TABLE</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="rows">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">REAGENT or RESOURCE</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SOURCE</th>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">IDENTIFIER</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Bacterial and Virus Strains</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">rAAV5/Camklla-eYFP</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">UNC Vector Core</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">rAAV5/Camklla-hChR2(C128S;D156A)-eYFP</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">UNC Vector Core</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">1 -EBIO (1 -Ethyl-2-benzimidazolinone)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Tocris</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Cat. # 1041</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Apamin</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Sigma</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Cat. # A1289</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Kynurenic Acid</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Sigma</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Cat. # K3375</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Picrotoxin</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Tocris</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Cat. #1128/1G</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Experimental Models: Organisms/Strains</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Mouse: <italic>Scn1a</italic><sup><italic>R1407+/−</italic></sup> C57BL6J:C3HeB/FeJ</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Ogiwara et al., 2007</xref>)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Oligonucleotides</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Forward Primer for <italic>Kcnn2S:</italic> F- 5′ AGT GGT CTG GAG GAA GAG GA 3′</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">This paper</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Custom synthesis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Reverse Primer for <italic>Kcnn2S:</italic> R- 5′ CAT TTG CAC GTT CTC CCG AA 3′</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">This paper</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Custom synthesis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Forward Primer for <italic>Kcnn2L:</italic> F-5′ TGG TTA CAG ACT GAG ACT CTT GT 3′</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">This paper</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Custom synthesis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Reverse Primer for <italic>Kcnn2L:</italic> R- 5′ TCC TCT TCC AGA CCA CT 3′</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">This paper</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Custom synthesis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Forward Primer for <italic>Gapdh:</italic> F- 5′ GGT CGG TGT GAA CGG ATT TG 3′</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">This paper</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Custom synthesis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Reverse Primer for <italic>Gapdh:</italic> R- 5′ GCA ACA ATC TCC ACT TTG CC 3′</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">This paper</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Custom synthesis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Software and Algorithms</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Clampfit 10.5</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Molecular Devices</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SCR_011323</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">MATLAB</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Mathworks</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SCR_001622</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Origin 9.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">OriginLab</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SCR_002815</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Graphpad Prism 6</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">Graphpad</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SCR_002798</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SigmaPlot</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SigmaPlot</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">SCR_003210</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<boxed-text id="BX1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Highlights</title>
</caption>
<list id="L2" list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p id="P116">Reticular thalamic neurons (nRT) are hyperexcitable in Dravet syndrome (DS)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p id="P117">This results from a potassium SK channel deficiency</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p id="P118">Boosting SK in nRT neurons treats DS non-convulsive seizures</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p id="P119">Disrupting bursting of thalamocortical neurons stops DS nonconvulsive seizures</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</boxed-text>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>