<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9500169</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">20475</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neurobiol Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neurobiol. Dis.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Neurobiology of disease</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0969-9961</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-953X</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30790616</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6588474</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2019.01.018</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1523248</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Modeling neuronopathic storage diseases with patient-derived culture
systems</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zunke</surname>
<given-names>Friederike</given-names>
</name>
<!--<email>fzunke@biochem.uni-kiel.de</email>-->
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mazzulli</surname>
<given-names>Joseph R.</given-names>
</name>
<!--<email>jmazzulli@northwestern.edu</email>-->
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute of Biochemistry,
Christian-Albrechts-Universität zu Kiel, 24118 Kiel, Germany</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Ken and Ruth Davee Department of Neurology, Northwestern
University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL 60611, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>7</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>19</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>127</volume>
<fpage>147</fpage>
<lpage>162</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.nbd.2019.01.018-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Lysosomes are organelles involved in the degradation and recycling of
macromolecules, and play a critical role in sensing metabolic information in the
cell. A class of rare metabolic diseases called lysosomal storage disorders
(LSD) are characterized by lysosomal dysfunction and the accumulation of
macromolecular substrates. The central nervous system appears to be particularly
vulnerable to lysosomal dysfunction, since many LSDs are characterized by
severe, widespread neurodegeneration with pediatric onset. Furthermore, variants
in lysosomal genes are strongly associated with some common neurodegenerative
disorders such as Parkinson’s disease (PD). To better understand disease
pathology and develop novel treatment strategies, it is critical to study the
fundamental molecular disease mechanisms in the affected cell types that harbor
endogenously expressed mutations. The discovery of methods for reprogramming of
patient-derived somatic cells into induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs), and
their differentiation into distinct neuronal and glial cell types, have provided
novel opportunities to study mechanisms of lysosomal dysfunction within the
relevant, vulnerable cell types. These models also expand our ability to develop
and test novel therapeutic targets. We discuss recently developed methods for
iPSC differentiation into distinct neuronal and glial cell types, while
addressing the need for meticulous experimental techniques and parameters that
are essential to accurately identify inherent cellular pathologies. iPSC models
for neuronopathic LSDs and their relationship to sporadic age-related
neurodegeneration are also discussed. These models should facilitate the
discovery and development of personalized therapies in the future.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>