<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9216904</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2419</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Genet.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Nature genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1061-4036</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1546-1718</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31086352</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6590703</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0409-8</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1526293</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Multi-tissue transcriptome analyses identify genetic mechanisms underlying neuropsychiatric traits</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gamazon</surname>
<given-names>Eric R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zwinderman</surname>
<given-names>Aeilko H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>Nancy J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Denys</surname>
<given-names>Damiaan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Derks</surname>
<given-names>Eske M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Division of Genetic Medicine, Department of Medicine, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, USA.</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Vanderbilt Genetics Institute, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN, USA.</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Data Science Institute, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, USA.</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Clare Hall, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK.</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>QIMR Berghofer, Translational Neurogenomics group, Brisbane, Australia.</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Author contributions</p>
<p id="P2">E.R.G.: Conception and design of study; analysis and interpretation of the data; drafting the manuscript; approval of the version of the manuscript to be published</p>
<p id="P3">A.H.Z.: Interpretation of data; approval of the version of the manuscript to be published</p>
<p id="P4">N.J.C.: Revising the manuscript critically for important intellectual content; approval of the version of the manuscript to be published</p>
<p id="P5">D.D.: Revising the manuscript critically for important intellectual content; approval of the version of the manuscript to be published</p>
<p id="P6">E.M.D.: Conception and design of study; analysis and interpretation of the data; drafting the manuscript; approval of the version of the manuscript to be published</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label><email>egamazon@uchicago.edu</email>, <email>eske.derks@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>5</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>13</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>13</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>933</fpage>
<lpage>940</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/s41588-019-0409-8-->
<permissions>
<license>
<license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<uri xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P7">The genetic architecture of psychiatric disorders is characterized by a large number of small-effect variants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> located primarily in non-coding regions, suggesting that the underlying causal effects may influence disease risk by modulating gene expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. We provide comprehensive analyses using transcriptome data from an unprecedented collection of tissues to gain pathophysiological insights into the role of the brain, neuroendocrine factors (adrenal gland) and gastrointestinal systems (colon) in psychiatric disorders. In each tissue, we perform PrediXcan analysis and identify trait-associated genes for schizophrenia (<italic>n</italic>-associations = 499; <italic>n</italic>-unique genes = 275), bipolar disorder (<italic>n</italic>-associations = 17; <italic>n</italic>-unique genes = 13), attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (<italic>n</italic>-associations = 19; <italic>n</italic>-unique genes = 12), and broad depression (<italic>n</italic>-associations = 41; <italic>n</italic>-unique genes = 31). Importantly, both PrediXcan and Summary-data-based Mendelian Randomization/HEIDI analyses propose potentially causal genes in non-brain tissues, showing the utility of these tissues for mapping psychiatric disease genetic predisposition. Our analyses further highlight the importance of joint-tissue approaches as 76% of the genes were detected only in difficult-to-acquire tissues.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary" id="ABS2">
<title>Editorial summary:</title>
<p id="P8">Multi-tissue transcriptome analyses using PrediXcan identify numerous trait-associated genes for schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, and broad depression, and highlight potentially causal genes in non-brain tissues.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p id="P9">A primary challenge in the field of psychiatric genetics is to understand the neurobiological mechanisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup> underlying genetic predisposition to disease to facilitate detection of additional disease-associated loci as well as to elucidate the precise molecular mechanisms underlying known loci. Integrative transcriptome studies promise to address the functional gap, but to date, analyses of gene expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> for psychiatric conditions have been hampered by the relative inaccessibility of the relevant tissues. Here, up to 393 individuals were assayed in 10 distinct brain regions and 3 additional non-brain tissues from the GTEx tissue panel, including a total of 889 brain samples and 633 non-brain samples. We further included 538 dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) samples from the CommonMind Consortium (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1a</xref>). We included both accessible (whole blood) and difficult-to-acquire tissues (i.e., brain, colon selected for its potential involvement in psychiatric disorders based on observed comorbidity with gastrointestinal disorders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>, and adrenal gland known to interact with the central nervous system through the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>).</p>
<p id="P10">Using the largest available genome-wide association study (GWAS) meta-analysis results of five psychiatric traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1b</xref>), we investigated gene-level psychiatric disease associations from a comprehensive PrediXcan analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> using imputation models derived from brain and non-brain transcriptomes. PrediXcan estimates the <italic>Genetically Regulated eXpression</italic> (GReX) for a gene in a given tissue for the GWAS samples and uses GReX to find genes associated with disease risk. We estimated the true positive rate (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>) (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>) for association with disease among the gene-level PrediXcan associations in each tissue and identified genes that are genome-wide significant when Bonferroni correcting for the number of genes tested across tissues (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). In subsequent analyses, we focused primarily on four out of five psychiatric traits, as we observed limited power for major depression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1a</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">e</xref>). We observed tissue- and disease-dependent levels of <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2a</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">d</xref>). The number of significant genes in each tissue (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) was determined primarily by tissue sample size (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 3</xref>; Spearman’s ρ = 0.91, <italic>P</italic> = 6.43 × 10<sup>−6</sup> for schizophrenia), showing the limitation of the number of significant genes as a metric for tissue prioritization. In contrast, <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> was not associated with tissue sample size (Spearman’s correlation ρ = 0.27, <italic>P</italic> = 0.35 for schizophrenia). Putamen basal ganglia (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M7" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.33</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) and nucleus accumbens basal ganglia (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.32</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) showed the highest <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> for schizophrenia, indeed greater than the DLPFC (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.27</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) despite the latter’s larger sample size (<italic>n</italic> = 538). Our findings suggest that the relatively large number of schizophrenia associations in DLPFC from a recent study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup> is due to relatively large sample size and provides limited evidence for greater relevance of this brain structure. For broad depression, the non-brain tissues colon (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.21</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) and whole blood (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.20</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) showed the highest estimated true positive rate, suggesting the relevance of the gastrointestinal or enteric nervous<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> and immune<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> systems for identifying genetic predispositions.</p>
<p id="P11">Gene discoveries are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 4a</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">d</xref> and reveal 275 unique genes for schizophrenia, 13 for bipolar disorder, 12 for ADHD, and 31 for broad depression. Of these, 70 disease-associated genes are not in linkage disequilibrium (LD) (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt; 0.10) with a GWAS index SNP and are considered novel discoveries from the PrediXcan analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). No genes were significantly associated with major depression, which may be due to its relatively small GWAS sample size and its large genetic and phenotypic heterogeneity. Interestingly, the schizophrenia and broad depression results revealed substantial overlap, as 17 of the 31 broad depression genes, all located within the MHC region, were also found to be significantly associated with schizophrenia. In the PrediXcan analysis, the distribution of the number of cis-variant predictors for optimal modeling (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>) of GReX for each tissue-gene pair (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>) and the number of contributing variants to the novel gene-level associations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 4a</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">d</xref>) demonstrate the importance of multi-variant models of GReX to identify trait-associated genes.</p>
<p id="P12">We replicated the significant associations for schizophrenia and broad depression using UK Biobank<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> and BioVU<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>, respectively (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>), but were unable to evaluate replication for the other two disorders due to lack of available replication datasets. Notably, we observed significantly greater replication rate for schizophrenia than expected by chance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). We identified and replicated an association between increased GReX of <italic>LRP8</italic> in hypothalamus and schizophrenia risk (<italic>P</italic> = 7.77 × 10<sup>−6</sup> in the discovery sample and <italic>P</italic> = 6.62 × 10<sup>−8</sup> in the UKB replication sample). <italic>LRP8</italic> is a key component of the RELN pathway and was previously linked to psychosis risk<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. Increased GReX for <italic>FPKP</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 2.4 × 10<sup>−4</sup>) showed replicated association with depression in BioVU, but a more systematic validation for this phenotype would require greater sample size.</p>
<p id="P13">Applying a single-SNP analysis, we also identified the target genes for expression quantitative trait loci (eQTLs) using the “best eQTL per eGene”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup> (b-eQTL, FDR &lt; 0.05) in brain and non-brain transcriptomes to gain additional insights into the role of gene regulation in conferring disease predisposition. As in the PrediXcan analysis, we observed tissue- and disease-dependent levels of <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). The substantial true positive rate for schizophrenia in anterior cingulate cortex (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M14" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.45</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, number of independent true associations <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>ta</italic></sub> = 580) suggests that b-eQTLs from this specific brain region may be used to improve the search for novel trait associations.</p>
<p id="P14">From the joint-tissue eQTL analysis (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>), which aims to improve power for eQTL discovery through joint-tissue mapping that captures heterogeneity in effect sizes between tissues while accounting for differences in sample size, non-brain b-eQTLs continued to show a substantial true positive rate of association after excluding eQTLs also found in brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). For example, 41% (i.e., 355 variants) of the whole blood b-eQTLs that are not brain eQTLs are estimated to be true associations with schizophrenia (compared to 30%; i.e., 1,836 variants prior to the filtering).</p>
<p id="P15">We aimed to improve the functional characterization of known disease-associated loci, focusing primarily on the 145 schizophrenia loci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> by considering the target genes from the single-SNP joint-tissue eQTL analysis. The 145 schizophrenia loci, in general, contained multiple genes (up to 131 genes per locus, defined as the cis-region, +/− 1 Mb, of the index SNP; average number of genes is 10; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>), complicating the search for the causal gene mechanisms and highlighting the importance of incorporating eQTL and other functional information to identify the relevant genes. We found that the 145 schizophrenia loci on average implicated 3.7 associated genes. This implies a substantial reduction in the number of proposed genes. The joint-tissue analysis implicated 290 genes at known GWAS loci to be significantly associated with schizophrenia in a tissue-specific manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p>
<p id="P16">We aimed to further reduce the number of candidate causal genes of the schizophrenia risk loci by distinguishing pleiotropic or causal genes (i.e., genetic variants influence both gene expression and disease risk) from genes that are associated indirectly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> (e.g., genes with causal eQTLs in LD with disease causal variants). We performed Summary-based Mendelian Randomization (SMR) analyses (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>) in conjunction with the Heterogeneity in Dependent Instruments (HEIDI) test using brain eQTLs from a large-scale meta-analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Despite the limitations of these methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>, they may be used as a starting point for further functional studies of proposed genes. We found that 65 genes passed the default significance threshold of 8.4 × 10<sup>−6</sup> under SMR. Nineteen of these genes showed a <italic>P</italic><sub>HEIDI</sub> ≥ 0.05 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 7a</xref>) from the subsequent HEIDI test, indicating that the null hypothesis of a single variant affecting both gene expression and disease risk could not be rejected. Of the 65 genes, 42 showed significant association in at least one tissue from the PrediXcan analysis. The extended MHC region is characterized by a disproportionately large number of OMIM genes and NHGRI catalog SNPs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>; the large number of proxy SNPs and the high gene density at this locus illustrate the challenges in fine-mapping the causal variant(s) and in finding the causal gene mechanism(s), respectively. Notably, PrediXcan analysis, which assumes multiple-variant imputation models, implicated <italic>C4A</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> to be associated with schizophrenia in seven GTEx brain tissues, colon, adrenal gland, and whole blood, but not in DLPFC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>).</p>
<p id="P17">We explored whether a non-brain tissue reveals potentially pleiotropic or causal genes and performed a secondary analysis using eQTL information from GTEx whole blood (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). Significant SMR association was observed for 37 genes, of which for seven the null hypothesis of a single variant affecting both gene expression and disease risk could not be rejected (<italic>P</italic><sub>HEIDI</sub> &gt; 0.05). Notably, all seven genes showed <italic>P</italic><sub>HEIDI</sub> &lt; 0.05 based on brain eQTLs, consistent with a model of linkage in which two distinct causal variants (for expression and disease risk) in the locus exist, implying that non-brain tissues can reveal important additional insights into the biological mechanisms of schizophrenia.</p>
<p id="P18">There is substantial sharing of eQTL SNPs (as estimated by <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M15" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>) among the tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>), with whole blood a clear outlier for the level of eQTL sharing with the other tissues. Among the brain regions, cerebellum and cerebellar hemisphere are outliers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). We compared results of the single-SNP METASOFT joint-tissue analysis across tissues and found that different tissues may propose different regulatory mechanisms within the same locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>). For example, <italic>GATA2DA</italic> shows strong tissue-specific effects in the METASOFT analysis with strong evidence for association in whole blood, while other tissues do not indicate association. In contrast, <italic>PBX4</italic> is implicated in hippocampus and cerebellum, while associations are weaker in the other brain tissues and absent in non-brain tissues.</p>
<p id="P19">We observed significant correlations in GReX of disease-associated genes for all tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref> for pairwise GReX correlations in putamen basal ganglia, which had the largest <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M16" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> for schizophrenia and showed significantly greater correlations than random GReX-derived co-expression networks in the tissue (empirical <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>), raising the possibility that they belong to a small number of genetically determined co-expression networks. Hierarchical clustering (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>) highlighted several clusters among these genes that appear to have coordinated GReX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref> for putamen basal ganglia). Underscoring the challenges of precisely mapping trait causal effects (e.g., LD contamination), these coordinated expression patterns may also highlight “convergent” function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> and pathophysiology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> for the genes and, possibly, trans-regulatory mechanisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup> (e.g., involving the genes on distinct chromosomes) in the brain underlying schizophrenia genetic predisposition. Thus, genetic susceptibility loci may act through disease-associated genes within co-expression networks to influence a limited number of core disease-related biological processes.</p>
<p id="P20">We performed Gene Ontology (GO) enrichment analysis (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>) of the PrediXcan implicated genes for schizophrenia and identified “biological processes” that are concordant between tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref>, for example, for the comparison between putamen basal ganglia and whole blood; Spearman ρ = 0.92, <italic>P</italic> &lt;2.2 × 10<sup>−16</sup>). However, we also identified biological processes specific to one tissue of a tissue pair (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5b</xref> for whole blood) and uncovered enriched biological processes (Bonferroni-adjusted <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref> in the tissue with the highest estimated <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M17" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>). These findings suggest either the tissue specificity of disease-associated genetically determined expression or that tissue-shared genetically determined expression may exert their tissue-level or pleiotropic function by implicating different processes in the different tissues.</p>
<p id="P21">Our study suggests that there is enormous value in both brain and non-brain eQTL annotations for improved discovery of novel susceptibility genes for psychiatric disorders. PrediXcan analyses across tissues revealed 331 unique disease-associated genes, 76% of which were detected only in difficult-to-acquire tissues. Furthermore, brain and non-brain tissues highlight different molecular mechanisms underlying psychiatric traits. Non-brain tissues identified 113 of the 331 (34%) of the disease-associated PrediXcan genes. Despite the challenges of distinguishing relevant pathogenic tissue(s) from tissue-shared gene regulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>, our study highlights the importance of joint-tissue analyses, in particular using non-brain tissues. Notably, our findings indicate that disease-associated genes may involve multiple variant-predictors, implying that, consistent with the recommendations of Gusev <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> and our own previous work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>, gene expression imputation may substantially extend single-eQTL-based analysis. We further showed that eQTL and transcriptome-based annotation of schizophrenia loci can substantially reduce the number of genes to be investigated in future functional studies. For example, using PrediXcan and SMR analyses and taking into account potential LD confounding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>, we proposed multiple gene mechanisms, which should be further explored by functional studies. Co-expression network analysis of schizophrenia-associated GReX revealed clustering into a limited number of genetically defined clusters. Consistent with this, GO enrichment analysis of schizophrenia-associated GReX implicated a limited number of biological processes, highlighting shared molecular mechanisms, including immune function and antigen presentation, in line with reports on the role of immune dysregulation in schizophrenia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. In conclusion, characterizing genes based on genetic regulation in brain and non-brain transcriptomes improves both the identification of novel neuropsychiatric genes and the functional elucidation of genetic risk factors of neuropsychiatric diseases.</p>
<sec id="S1" sec-type="methods" specific-use="web-only">
<title>Online Methods</title>
<p id="P22">Please see the Life Sciences Reporting Summary for additional details.</p>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Tissues and eQTL data.</title>
<p id="P23">We used GTEx v6p dataset in the analyses presented here, including the (cis) eQTLs and “best eQTL per eGene”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup> (b-eQTLs) in each of the brain regions (<italic>n</italic> = 10) and in selected non-brain tissues (whole blood, adrenal gland and colon). We present results on 889 brain RNA-seq samples from 10 brain regions and 633 non-brain samples. Up to 393 distinct individuals are included in this analysis. We used the CommonMind Consortium transcriptome data from 538 samples in dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1a</xref> for the sample size for each tissue.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>GWAS data psychiatric disorders.</title>
<p id="P24">We used genome-wide association study (GWAS) meta-analysis results of five psychiatric traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1b</xref>). These studies have been conducted in compliance with all ethical regulations. All studies have been approved by the ethical board of the relevant institution. Since each study comprises many different study cohorts, please see original publications for details.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>PrediXcan as expression-based risk score analysis.</title>
<p id="P25">Proposing a gene mechanism from a disease-associated eQTL assumes that a single-eQTL model suffices to implicate the gene. In this case, a disease-associated eGene may be viewed as a single-variant-determined gene expression phenotype that shows an association with disease. Indeed, if <italic>x</italic> is the genotype (expressed as allelic dosage) for a GWAS individual at the eQTL variant <italic>S</italic> and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M18" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> its estimated effect size on the expression of the gene <italic>g</italic> as determined by a reference eQTL resource such as GTEx, then <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M19" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the imputed eQTL-determined expression of the eGene <italic>g</italic> for the GWAS sample; the imputed (genetically determined) gene expression can be tested for association with disease risk <italic>Y</italic> using GWAS summary statistics (effect size <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M20" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and corresponding standard error <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M21" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> of <italic>S</italic> on <italic>Y</italic>).</p>
<p id="P26">Some genes, however, may require multiple variants to adequately impute the genetically determined component of the gene expression phenotype or the “<bold>G</bold>enetically <bold>R</bold>egulated <bold>eX</bold>pression” (GReX)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. Thus, we applied PrediXcan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> to the GWAS results for five psychiatric traits to discover genes with differential GReX (<italic>P</italic><sub>Bonferroni-adjusted</sub> &lt; 0.05 after adjustment for the total number of genes across all tissues tested) between patients and controls. PrediXcan implements a tissue-dependent gene expression imputation model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> (using elastic net), which is evaluated, for optimal modeling, through the 10-fold cross-validation <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> within the reference transcriptome panel (GTEx). Genes implicated by PrediXcan for a given disease may be viewed as a <italic>generalized</italic> disease-associated eGene (which is conventionally the target gene of <italic>one</italic> source eQTL variant, namely the b-eQTL). An observed association between GReX and a disease phenotype from a causal link would suggest that the causal direction of effect is from GReX to disease risk since the trait is not likely to alter the germline genetic profile. In this generalized version, we can, using GWAS summary statistics, estimate the effect size <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M22" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and corresponding standard error <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M23" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> of the imputed genetically determined component of gene expression on disease risk as follows (by noting that the imputed gene expression is <italic>a genetic risk score</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup> with weights derived from the reference transcriptome panel):
<disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math display="block" id="M24" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math display="block" id="M25" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M26" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the effect size of the <italic>j</italic>-th variant from the gene expression model (derived from the reference panel) consisting of uncorrelated <italic>m</italic> cis-variant predictors (i.e., located within +/− 1 Mb of the gene), while <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M27" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>s</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> are the effect size and the corresponding standard error of this effect size from the GWAS trait summary data. We note that, under the null hypothesis (of zero contribution <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M28" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> to trait variation from all predictors), we obtain the distribution of <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M29" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>:
<disp-formula id="FD3"><mml:math display="block" id="M30" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
which allows us to assign a <italic>P</italic>-value to the observed effect size of the imputed genetically determined component of gene expression on disease risk. When <italic>m</italic> = 1, this reduces to the special case of testing an eGene for association with phenotype.</p>
<p id="P27">In the general case in which some LD is present in the set of <italic>m</italic> cis-variant predictors for a given gene, we estimate the correlation between the “genetic risk score” generated from the gene expression prediction model and the phenotype using only GWAS summary statistics. Let <italic>X</italic> be the <italic>n</italic>-by-<italic>m</italic> standardized genotype matrix and <italic>y</italic> be the standardized phenotype <italic>n</italic>-by-1 matrix in the test GWAS. (In general, the genotype data <italic>X</italic> and phenotype data <italic>y</italic> are not publicly available.) Then the genetic risk score <italic>GRS</italic>(<italic>n</italic>) for the <italic>n</italic> GWAS individuals is given by:
<disp-formula id="FD4"><mml:math display="block" id="M31" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"> </mml:mi><mml:mo>≔</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic>β</italic> is the <italic>m</italic>-vector of model-derived effect sizes. The correlation between <italic>GRS</italic>(<italic>n</italic>) and <italic>y</italic> is thus given by the following expression:
<disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(*)</label><mml:math display="block" id="M32" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
We note that since <italic>X</italic> and <italic>y</italic> are standardized, the term <italic>X</italic><sup><italic>T</italic></sup><italic>y</italic> in the numerator of (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">*</xref>) is a correlation <italic>m</italic>-vector (equal to the trait effect size vector (because of the standardization), easily obtained using the GWAS summary statistics for the <italic>m</italic> variants). Furthermore, <italic>X</italic><sup><italic>T</italic></sup><italic>X</italic> in the denominator of (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">*</xref>) yields an <italic>m</italic>-by-<italic>m</italic> matrix (LD) matrix, which can be estimated from an ancestry-matched reference panel (such as from the 1000 Genomes project) with or without LD regularization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="P28">TWAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> and S-PrediXcan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup> have implemented approaches based on summary statistics.</p>
<p id="P29">We used the S-PrediXcan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup> implementation to test genetic associations with five psychiatric traits (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). The <italic>P</italic>-value threshold was corrected for the total number of genes tested across all tissues. Since there are two pairs of brain tissues that are replicates and therefore do not constitute independent tissues (cortex vs. frontal cortex and cerebellum vs. cerebellar hemisphere), we only corrected for one of the tissues for each replicate pair. We removed the tissue that included the lowest number of imputed genes. The <italic>P</italic>-value thresholds are slightly different across traits and are reported in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. We further used PrediXcan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> in the replication analyses of schizophrenia in UKB samples (<italic>n</italic> = 1,561 cases and 267,494 psychiatrically healthy controls) and of broad depression in the BioVU samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> (<italic>n</italic> = 3,570 cases and 14,456 controls). To evaluate replication for schizophrenia, we applied S-PrediXcan to GWAS summary statistics derived from an application of BOLT-LMM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. We explored potential sample overlap between schizophrenia GWAS data and UKB samples, using GEAR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup> and LD score regression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup> analyses. The results of these analyses did not suggest a significant amount of overlap (LD score regression covariate intercept = 0.0038 (s.e. = 0.006) and LambdaMeta = 1.54). The BioVU samples included in our analyses were of European genetic ancestry, as confirmed by principal components analysis.</p>
<p id="P30">PrediXcan software can be downloaded from the github repository (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/hakyim/PrediXcan">https://github.com/hakyim/PrediXcan</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title>Estimating the true rate of association (π<sub>1</sub>).</title>
<p id="P31">We estimated the true positive rate (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M33" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>≔</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) for association with disease among the eQTLs from the “best eQTL per eGene” (b-eQTL, FDR &lt; 0.05) set or, separately, among the gene-level results from the PrediXcan analysis in each tissue, using the method of Storey <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. The false discovery rate (FDR) at a given <italic>P</italic>-value <italic>p</italic> was estimated using the following equation:
<disp-formula id="FD6"><mml:math display="block" id="M34" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal"> </mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula>
In the case of b-eQTLs, <italic>K</italic> is the number of eQTLs used, the <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>i,D</italic></sub> is the set of <italic>P</italic>-values indexed by the eQTL SNP <italic>i</italic> for association with the disease trait <italic>D</italic>, and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M35" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the proportion of null SNPs:
<disp-formula id="FD7"><mml:math display="block" id="M36" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>
which was defined with the tuning parameter <italic>τ</italic> (selected to be 0.50, as in Storey <italic>et al</italic>.). In the case of the gene-level results from the PrediXcan analysis, the input set is that of genes tested (i.e., with imputation models).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6">
<title>Joint-tissue eQTL mapping.</title>
<p id="P32">In addition to single-tissue eQTL analysis, the joint analysis of the brain regions and the additional tissues may facilitate identification of additional eQTLs and quantification of their tissue specificity. We used METASOFT for joint-tissue eQTL analysis, across the 10 brain regions, whole blood, adrenal gland, and colon. METASOFT had been previously used in the second-phase GTEx Consortium paper<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. Joint-tissue eQTL mapping extends single-tissue eQTL mapping results by borrowing information across tissues. This approach allowed us to quantify the tissue specificity or tissue-sharedness of an eQTL-gene pair while taking into account the differential eQTL discovery power between tissues.</p>
<p id="P33">We used joint-tissue eQTL mapping to identify eQTLs in non-brain tissues that are not active in any of the brain regions. This analysis provided an approach to testing the importance of regulatory variation in non-brain tissues for psychiatric disease predisposition through the estimated true positive rate <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M37" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> for disease associations among the non-brain eQTLs that are not also regulatory in brain.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S7">
<title>SMR and HEIDI analysis of schizophrenia summary statistics.</title>
<p id="P34">We sought to further refine the set of candidate causal genes by distinguishing pleiotropy or causality (i.e., a single variant affecting both gene expression and disease risk) from a model of linkage (i.e., two distinct causal variants, for gene expression and disease risk). We applied Summary-data based Mendelian Randomization (SMR) and HEterogeneity In Dependent Instruments (HEIDI) tests<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup>, which were implemented in SMR software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/">http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/</ext-link>), to the schizophrenia GWAS results. For the input GWAS results, effect sizes were calculated as log(<italic>odds ratio</italic>) with its corresponding standard error. The top associated eQTL for the SMR test was selected using the default value of <italic>P</italic><sub>eQTL</sub> &lt; 5.0 × 10<sup>−8</sup>. For the HEIDI test, up to 20 SNPs (eQTL <italic>P</italic> &lt; 1.57 × 10<sup>−3</sup>; LD <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> with top SNP &lt; 0.9) in the cis-eQTL region (including the top cis-eQTL) were included per recommendation of the software developers.</p>
<p id="P35">The SMR analyses were based on eQTL information provided by Qi <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> who meta-analyzed GTEx-brain, CMC, and ROSMAP eQTL data (estimated effective sample size: <italic>n</italic> = 1,194). The Brain-eMeta eQTL summary data were downloaded in binary format (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/#DataResource">http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/#DataResource</ext-link>). In addition, we explored the value of a non-brain tissue by using eQTL summary data based on GTEx whole blood (version 7) for SMR analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/#DataResource">http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/#DataResource</ext-link>). SMR locus plots and plots of GWAS and eQTL effect sizes were created with R code (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/#SMRlocusplot">http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr/#SMRlocusplot</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Co-expression analysis, hierarchical clustering, and pathway analysis.</title>
<p id="P36">We hypothesized that genetically defined co-expression networks (versus networks based on directly measured gene expression, as typically done) would improve our ability to highlight novel biology underlying psychiatric disease predisposition. Using Weighted Gene Co-expression Network Analysis (WGCNA v1.61) with default settings, we performed co-expression network analysis and hierarchical clustering of the GReX levels estimated in the 1000 Genomes European samples (using gene expression imputation, as implemented in PrediXcan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>) for the disease-associated genes. In general, the availability of a reference population panel (e.g., 1000 Genomes) in a population of interest enables network analysis of the genetically determined expression traits.</p>
<p id="P37">We also applied multiscale bootstrap resampling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup> (<italic>n</italic> = 1,000 bootstrap replicates) to hierarchical clustering in order to quantify the uncertainty in the clusters, with “average” as the agglomerative method and “correlation” as distance method, generating an “Approximately Unbiased” <italic>P</italic>-value and a “Bootstrap Probability” for each cluster. This analysis allowed us to identify the clusters for which the null hypothesis of the non-existence of the cluster is rejected at α = 0.05.</p>
<p id="P38">In each tissue, we determined the significance of the set of pairwise (Spearman) correlations in GReX levels (of the 1000 Genomes European samples). We evaluated whether the resulting network was more highly correlated than expected based on 1,000 co-expression networks derived from the GReX of random sets of genes (each comprising the same number of genes as the actual network). We further explored whether some disease-associated genes may be regulatory for other such genes. The GReX correlation matrix for the disease-associated genes may be used to identify novel trans-regulatory mechanisms driving genetic susceptibility. For example, a cis eQTL (schizophrenia-associated) SNP for a gene may serve as a trans eQTL for another distal gene (that is correlated with the first).</p>
<p id="P39">Using clusterProfiler<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>, we compared the sets of “biological processes” (as defined by Gene Ontology) implicated by the disease-associated genes from each pair of tissues. We calculated the Spearman correlation for the proportion of disease-associated genes mapping to each biological process to quantify the level of concordance between tissues. For each tissue pair, we identified the biological processes present only in one tissue and with at least five genes. Furthermore, we performed a two-proportions z-test using prop.test in R and identified those processes that significantly differed between tissues (<italic>q</italic>-value &lt; 0.05) between tissues.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S9">
<title>Software for statistical analysis and visualization.</title>
<p id="P41">The software package R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>) was used for the statistical analysis. We used the libraries “ggplot2” and “corrplot” for visualization.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S10" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data Availability Statement</title>
<p id="P43">The protected data for the GTEx project (e.g., genotype and RNA-sequence data) are available via access request to dbGaP accession number phs000424.v6.p1. Processed GTEx data (e.g., gene expression and eQTLs) are available on the GTEx portal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gtexportal.org">https://gtexportal.org</ext-link>). The URLs of the summary statistics datasets of all the GWAS meta-analyses analyzed in the paper can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="SM1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<label>1</label>
<media id="d36e1927" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS1526293-supplement-1.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2">
<label>2</label>
<media id="d36e1931" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS1526293-supplement-2.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3">
<label>Sup Tables 1 - 7</label>
<media id="d36e1935" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="NIHMS1526293-supplement-Sup_Tables_1_-_7.xlsx" xlink:type="simple"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S11">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p id="P40">The Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) Project was supported by the Common Fund of the Office of the Director of the National Institutes of Health. Additional funds were provided by the NCI, NHGRI, NHLBI, NIDA, NIMH, and NINDS. Donors were enrolled at Biospecimen Source Sites funded by NCI\SAIC-Frederick, Inc. SAIC-F subcontracts to the National Disease Research Interchange (10XS170), Roswell Park Cancer Institute (10XS171), and Science Care, Inc. (X10S172). The Laboratory, Data Analysis, and Coordinating Center (LDACC) was funded through a contract (HHSN268201000029C) to The Broad Institute, Inc. Biorepository operations were funded through an SAIC-F subcontract to Van Andel Institute (10ST1035). Additional data repository and project management were provided by SAIC-F (HHSN261200800001E). The Brain Bank was supported by a supplements to University of Miami grants DA006227 &amp; DA033684 and to contract N01MH000028. Statistical Methods development grants were made to the University of Geneva (MH090941 &amp; MH101814), the University of Chicago (MH090951, MH090937, MH101820, MH101825), the University of North Carolina - Chapel Hill (MH090936 &amp; MH101819), Harvard University (MH090948), Stanford University (MH101782), Washington University St Louis (MH101810), and the University of Pennsylvania (MH101822). E.M.D. is supported by the Foundation Volksbond Rotterdam. E.R.G. is grateful to the President and Fellows of Clare Hall, University of Cambridge for providing a stimulating intellectual home and benefited from a Fellowship in the college. E.R.G. also acknowledges support from the Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam during the early stages of the study. E.R.G. and N.J.C. acknowledge support from R01MH113362. We acknowledge the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium (PGC) groups for sharing the published meta-analysis data.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p id="P44">Competing Interests Statement</p>
<p id="P45">The authors of this manuscript have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gratten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<article-title>Large-scale genomics unveils the genetic architecture of psychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source/>Nature neuroscience
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>782</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3708</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24866044</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nicolae</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Trait-associated SNPs are more likely to be eQTLs: annotation to enhance discovery from GWAS</article-title>. <source/>PLoS genetics
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e1000888</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000888</pub-id> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20369019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Schizophrenia Working Group of the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium</collab>. <article-title>Biological insights from 108 schizophrenia-associated genetic loci</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>511</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13595</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25056061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gamazon</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>The convergence of eQTL mapping, heritability estimation and polygenic modeling: emerging spectrum of risk variation in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source/>arxiv (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geschwind</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<article-title>Genetics and genomics of psychiatric disease</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>349</volume>, <fpage>1489</fpage>–<lpage>1494</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaa8954</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26404826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ozomaro</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wahlestedt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Nemeroff</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<article-title>Personalized medicine in psychiatry: problems and promises</article-title>. <source/>BMC medicine
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>132</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-11-132</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23680237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Gene expression in major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source/>Molecular psychiatry
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>444</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2015.94</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26100536</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bercik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>The intestinal microbiota affect central levels of brain-derived neurotropic factor and behavior in mice</article-title>. <source/>Gastroenterology
<volume>141</volume>, <fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>, <fpage>609 e591</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2011.04.052</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21683077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<article-title>Missing and Possible Link between Neuroendocrine Factors, Neuropsychiatric Disorders, and Microglia</article-title>. <source/>Frontiers in integrative neuroscience
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnint.2013.00053</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23874274</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies of attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source/>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>884</fpage>–<lpage>897</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2010.06.008</pub-id> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20732625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Psychiatric GWAS Consortium Bipolar Disorder Working Group</collab>. <article-title>Large-scale genome-wide association analysis of bipolar disorder identifies a new susceptibility locus near ODZ4</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.943</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21926972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Major Depressive Disorder Working Group of the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium</collab>. <article-title>A mega-analysis of genome-wide association studies for major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source/>Molecular psychiatry
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2012.21</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22472876</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pardinas</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Common schizophrenia alleles are enriched in mutation-intolerant genes and in regions under strong background selection</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0059-2</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29483656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Bipolar Disorder and Schizophrenia Working Group of the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium</collab>. <article-title>Genomic Dissection of Bipolar Disorder and Schizophrenia, Including 28 Subphenotypes</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>173</volume>, <fpage>1705</fpage>–<lpage>1715 e1716</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2018.05.046</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29906448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Genome-wide association analyses identify 44 risk variants and refine the genetic architecture of major depression</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>668</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0090-3</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29700475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Genome-wide association study of depression phenotypes in UK Biobank identifies variants in excitatory synaptic pathways</article-title>. <source/>Nature communications
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1470</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03819-3</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Demontis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Discovery of the first genome-wide significant risk loci for attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30478444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gamazon</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>A gene-based association method for mapping traits using reference transcriptome data</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1091</fpage>–<lpage>1098</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3367</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26258848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huckins</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Gene expression imputation across multiple brain regions provides insights into schizophrenia risk</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>McVey Neufeld</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<article-title>Gut-brain axis: how the microbiome influences anxiety and depression</article-title>. <source/>Trends in neurosciences
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2013.01.005</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23384445</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<article-title>The concept of depression as a dysfunction of the immune system</article-title>. <source/>Current immunology reviews
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/157339510791823835</pub-id> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21170282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sudlow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>UK biobank: an open access resource for identifying the causes of a wide range of complex diseases of middle and old age</article-title>. <source/>PLoS medicine
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e1001779</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001779</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25826379</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Systematic comparison of phenome-wide association study of electronic medical record data and genome-wide association study data</article-title>. <source/>Nature biotechnology
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1102</fpage>–<lpage>1110</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2749</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Further evidence for the association between LRP8 and schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Schizophr Res, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2017.05.002</pub-id> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<article-title>Statistical significance for genomewide studies</article-title>. <source/>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>9440</fpage>–<lpage>9445</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1530509100</pub-id> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12883005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The GTEx Consortium</collab>. <article-title>The Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) pilot analysis: multitissue gene regulation in humans</article-title>. <source/>Science
<volume>348</volume>, <fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>660</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1262110</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25954001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Opportunities and challenges for transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30926968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Identifying gene targets for brain-related traits using transcriptomic and methylomic data from blood</article-title>. <source/>Nature communications
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>2282</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04558-1</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hauberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Large-Scale Identification of Common Trait and Disease Variants Affecting Gene Expression</article-title>. <source/>American journal of human genetics
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2017.06.003</pub-id> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28686855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Schizophrenia Psychiatric Genome-Wide Association Study Consortium</collab>. <article-title>Genome-wide association study identifies five new schizophrenia loci</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>969</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.940</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21926974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Schizophrenia risk from complex variation of complement component 4</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>530</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature16549</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26814963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Spatial clustering and common regulatory elements correlate with coordinated gene expression</article-title>. <source/>PLoS computational biology
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>e1006786</fpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006786</pub-id> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30822341</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Voineagu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of autistic brain reveals convergent molecular pathology</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>474</volume>, <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10110</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21614001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Westra</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Systematic identification of trans eQTLs as putative drivers of known disease associations</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>1238</fpage>–<lpage>1243</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2756</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24013639</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gamazon</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Using an atlas of gene regulation across 44 human tissues to inform complex disease- and trait-associated variation</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>956</fpage>–<lpage>967</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0154-4</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29955180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Transcriptome-wide association study of schizophrenia and chromatin activity yields mechanistic disease insights</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29632383</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R37">
<label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mowry</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pender</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<article-title>Immune dysregulation and self-reactivity in schizophrenia: do some cases of schizophrenia have an autoimmune basis?</article-title>
<source/>Immunology and cell biology
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1711.2005.01305.x</pub-id> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15661036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R38">
<label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Witte</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ophoff</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<article-title>Genetic liability for schizophrenia predicts risk of immune disorders</article-title>. <source/>Schizophrenia research
<volume>159</volume>, <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2014.09.004</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25266548</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<ref-list>
<title>Methods-only references</title>
<ref id="R39">
<label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>International Consortium for Blood Pressure Genome-Wide Association Studies</collab>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Genetic variants in novel pathways influence blood pressure and cardiovascular disease risk</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>478</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10405</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R40">
<label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kichaev</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Pasaniuc</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<article-title>Contrasting the Genetic Architecture of 30 Complex Traits from Summary Association Data</article-title>. <source/>American journal of human genetics
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2016.05.013</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27346688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R41">
<label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gamazon</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structural architecture of SNP effects on complex traits</article-title>. <source/>American journal of human genetics
<volume>95</volume>, <fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>489</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2014.09.009</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25307299</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R42">
<label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barbeira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Integrating tissue specific mechanisms into GWAS summary results</article-title>. <source/>Biorxiv, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/045260</pub-id> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R43">
<label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Efficient Bayesian mixed-model analysis increases association power in large cohorts</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3190</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25642633</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R44">
<label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Across-cohort QC analyses of GWAS summary statistics from complex traits</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Hum Genet
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2016.106</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27552965</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R45">
<label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bulik-Sullivan</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>LD Score regression distinguishes confounding from polygenicity in genome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3211</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25642630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R46">
<label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The GTEx Consortium</collab>. <article-title>Genetic effects on gene expression across human tissues</article-title>. <source/>Nature
<volume>550</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature24277</pub-id> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29022597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R47">
<label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<etal></etal>
<article-title>Integration of summary data from GWAS and eQTL studies predicts complex trait gene targets</article-title>. <source/>Nature genetics
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>487</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3538</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27019110</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R48">
<label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<article-title>Approximately unbiased tests of regions using multistep-multiscale bootstrap resampling</article-title>. <source/>Ann Stat
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>2616</fpage>–<lpage>2641</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/009053604000000823</pub-id> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R49">
<label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>
<article-title>clusterProfiler: an R package for comparing biological themes among gene clusters</article-title>. <source/>Omics : a journal of integrative biology
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/omi.2011.0118</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455463</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1 |</label>
<caption>
<title>PrediXcan and eQTL analysis of GWAS of psychiatric traits.</title>
<p id="P46"><bold>a</bold>, Heatmap and hierarchical clustering based on true positive rate (π<sub>1</sub>) for trait associations among PrediXcan associations in each tissue. Schizophrenia and bipolar disorder were most highly enriched in putamen basal ganglia and adrenal gland, respectively. Broad depression showed relatively strong enrichment in colon. <bold>b</bold>, Significant replication of schizophrenia PrediXcan associations (Bonferroni-adjusted <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, indicated by horizontal line) was observed within the UK Biobank sample (1,561 cases; 267,494 controls). Replication <italic>P</italic>-value for a gene was from the application of S-PrediXcan to GWAS summary statistics derived from BOLT-LMM. <bold>c</bold>, Heatmap and hierarchical clustering based on true positive rate (π<sub>1</sub>) for trait associations among b-eQTL associations in each tissue. <bold>d</bold>, Non-brain eQTL enrichment was observed even after conditioning on brain eQTLs from the joint-tissue eQTL analysis. The joint-tissue analysis allowed us to quantify the tissue specificity and tissue-sharedness of an eQTL-gene pair while taking into account differential power for eQTL discovery between tissues. The <italic>x</italic>-axis shows the π<sub>1</sub> after including only those b-eQTLs active in the non-brain tissue but not regulatory in any of the 10 brain regions. The <italic>y</italic>-axis shows the π<sub>1</sub> without the filtering. Points below the diagonal line show disease and tissue pairs for which a higher true positive rate was observed after filtering the brain eQTLs. Sample sizes: schizophrenia (40,675 cases, 64,643 controls); ADHD (20,183 cases, 35,191 controls); bipolar disorder (11,974 cases, 51,792 controls); broad depression (113,769 cases, 208,811 controls).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1526293-f0001"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2 |</label>
<caption>
<title>Proposing causal variant and causal gene mechanism at known schizophrenia-associated loci (<italic>n</italic> = 145 loci; 179 index SNPs).</title>
<p id="P47"><bold>a</bold>, Distribution of number of nearby genes (defined as +/− 1 Mb of index SNPs) at known loci. <bold>b</bold>, From the joint-tissue (METASOFT) analysis, 290 genes at known loci were significantly associated with schizophrenia (40,675 cases, 64,643 controls) in a tissue-dependent manner. Significant associations (METASOFT <italic>m</italic>-value ≥ 0.90) of these 290 genes are shown as red bars, while non-significant associations are shown as white bars. The figure shows clustering of genes that are shared across tissues, but also indicates genes that have tissue-specific effects. <bold>c</bold>, LocusZoom plot of the region surrounding the <italic>C4A</italic> gene indicates that <italic>C4A</italic> is significantly associated in GTEx cerebellum but not in dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. <italic>y</italic>-axis is the schizophrenia association <italic>P</italic>-value (in log scale). The large number of SNPs and genes in the locus illustrate the challenges in fine-mapping the causal variant and in determining the gene driver(s).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1526293-f0002"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3 |</label>
<caption>
<title>Complexity of identifying the relevant gene mechanism in tissue of pathology.</title>
<p id="P48"><bold>a</bold>, There is extensive eQTL sharing among tissues, as estimated by <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>. Note that the easily accessible tissue whole blood is a clear outlier, showing the least amount of sharing with the other tissues. Among the brain regions, cerebellum and cerebellar hemisphere are outliers. Sample sizes for the tissues can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. <bold>b</bold>, Illustration of tissue-specific regulation from the METASOFT analysis. The b-eQTL of <italic>GATA2DA</italic> (rs2905432) impacts its expression only in whole blood, while the b-eQTL of <italic>PBX4</italic> (chr19_19756073_D) influences its expression in cerebellum/cerebellar hemisphere and in hippocampus, but not in the remaining tissues. These examples indicate that delineating the biological mechanisms of schizophrenia based on eQTL information requires a tissue-specific approach for at least some of the eQTL-gene associations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1526293-f0003"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 4 |</label>
<caption>
<title>Genetically determined co-expression networks of disease-associated GReX.</title>
<p id="P49"><bold>a</bold>, We observed significant correlations in GReX of disease-associated genes (Bonferroni-adjusted <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05 from S-PrediXcan analysis of schizophrenia) for all tissues. Shown here are the pairwise GReX correlations in putamen basal ganglia, which had the largest <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> for schizophrenia (40,675 cases, 64,643 controls). <bold>b</bold>, The observed GReX correlations were significantly greater (empirical <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) than expected based on 1,000 randomly generated, genetically defined co-expression networks. <bold>c</bold>, Hierarchical clustering of GReX of disease-associated genes in putamen basal ganglia was performed and identified several genetically determined clusters that appear to have coordinated expression including on distinct chromosomes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1526293-f0004"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 5 |</label>
<caption>
<title>Tissue-specific GReX, joint-tissue eQTL mapping, and tissue-specific or tissue-shared functional categories for schizophrenia.</title>
<p id="P50"><bold>a</bold>, Substantial concordance between tissues (for example, between whole blood (<italic>n</italic> = 338) and putamen basal ganglia (<italic>n</italic> = 82), Spearman ρ = 0.92, <italic>P</italic> = 3.86 × 10<sup>−164</sup>) was observed in the proportion of disease-associated GReX levels (Bonferroni-adjusted <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 from S-PrediXcan analysis) that map to a biological process (as defined by Gene Ontology). <bold>b</bold>, List of biological processes present only in whole blood and represented by five or more disease-associated GReX levels in the tissue. <bold>c</bold>, Enriched biological processes (hypergeometric test, Bonferroni-adjusted <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in putamen basal ganglia (<italic>n</italic> = 82), which had the largest <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline" id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> for schizophrenia, and the gene ratio for the genes that map to the processes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-1526293-f0005"></graphic>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table 1 |</label>
<caption>
<p id="P51">Number of gene discoveries from PrediXcan analyses and an overview of the number of significant associations in brain, difficult-to-acquire, and non-brain tissues</p>
</caption>
<table frame="box" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" span="1" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top"></th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top">Schizophrenia</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top">Bipolar disorder</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top">ADHD</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Broad depression</th>
</tr>
<tr style="border-top:solid 1px">
<th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top">Tissue<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">*</xref></th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="border-right:solid 1px" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic>
</th>
<th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">126</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Adrenal gland</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">60</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Anterior cingulate cortex BA24</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">35</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Caudate basal ganglia</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">38</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Cerebellar hemisphere</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">45</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Cerebellum</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">68</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">5</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Cortex</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">40</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Frontal cortex BA9</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">35</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Hippocampus</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">21</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Hypothalamus</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">27</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Nucleus accumbens basal ganglia</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">37</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Putamen basal ganglia</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">29</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Colon transverse</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">74</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6</td>
</tr>
<tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px">
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Whole blood</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">94</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">5</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> unique genes “total”</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">275</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">13</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> unique genes “novel PrediXcan”</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">46</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">5</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> genes “difficult-to-acquire” (%)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">242 (88)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12 (92)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12 (100)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">24 (77)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> genes “brain” (%)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">204 (74)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">7 (54)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11 (92)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">21 (66)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> genes “non-brain” (%)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">91 (33)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">7 (54)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3 (25)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12 (39)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> genes “difficult-to-acquire-only” (%)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">207 (75)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">10 (77)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11 (92)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">23 (74)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> genes “brain-only” (%)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">113 (41)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6 (46)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9 (75)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9 (29)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> genes “non-brain only” (%)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">71 (26)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6 (46)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1 (8)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">10 (32)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"><italic>n</italic> genes “whole blood” (%)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">68 (25)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3 (23)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1 (8)</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8 (26)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="TFN1">
<p id="P52"><italic>n</italic> unique genes “total” = number of unique genes that are significant in ≥1 tissue; <italic>n</italic> unique genes “novel PrediXcan” = number of unique genes that are not in LD (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt; 0.10) with a GWAS index SNP; <italic>n</italic> genes “difficult-to-acquire tissue” = number of genes that are significant in ≥1 difficult-to-acquire tissue; <italic>n</italic> genes “brain” = number of genes that are significant in ≥1 brain tissue; <italic>n</italic> genes “non-brain” = number of genes that are significant in whole blood, adrenal gland or colon; <italic>n</italic> genes “brain-only” = number of genes that are significant in ≥1 brain tissue and not significant in any non-brain tissue; <italic>n</italic> unique genes “non-brain only” = number of genes that are significant in whole blood, adrenal gland or colon, but not significant in any of the brain tissues; <italic>n</italic> unique genes “whole blood” = number of genes that are significant in whole blood.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="TFN2">
<label>*</label>
<p id="P53">Sample sizes for the tissues can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>