<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Cell</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Cell</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Molecular Cell</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1097-2765</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-4164</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Cell Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30982744</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6591016</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1097-2765(19)30222-9</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2019.03.018</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An Adversarial DNA N<sup>6</sup>-Methyladenine-Sensor Network Preserves Polycomb Silencing</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kweon</surname>
<given-names>Soo-Mi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Yibu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moon</surname>
<given-names>Eugene</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kvederaviciutė</surname>
<given-names>Kotryna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klimasauskas</surname>
<given-names>Saulius</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feldman</surname>
<given-names>Douglas E.</given-names>
</name>
<email>defeldma@usc.edu</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">∗</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, Keck School of Medicine of USC, Los Angeles, CA 90033, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Bioinformatics Service, Department of Health Sciences Libraries, Keck School of Medicine of USC, Los Angeles, CA 90033, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Institute of Biotechnology, Life Sciences Center, Vilnius University, Vilnius LT-10257, Lithuania</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author <email>defeldma@usc.edu</email></corresp>
<fn id="fn1">
<label>4</label>
<p id="ntpara0010">Lead Contact</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>20</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub">.-->
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>74</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1138</fpage>
<lpage>1147.e6</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>16</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>12</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>18</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2019 The Authors</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="abs0010">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>Adenine N6 methylation in DNA (6mA) is widespread among bacteria and phage and is detected in mammalian genomes, where its function is largely unexplored. Here we show that 6mA deposition and removal are catalyzed by the Mettl4 methyltransferase and Alkbh4 dioxygenase, respectively, and that 6mA accumulation in genic elements corresponds with transcriptional silencing. Inactivation of murine <italic>Mettl4</italic> depletes 6mA and causes sublethality and craniofacial dysmorphism in incross progeny. We identify distinct 6mA sensor domains of prokaryotic origin within the MPND deubiquitinase and ASXL1, a component of the Polycomb repressive deubiquitinase (PR-DUB) complex, both of which act to remove monoubiquitin from histone H2A (H2A-K119Ub), a repressive mark. Deposition of 6mA by Mettl4 triggers the proteolytic destruction of both sensor proteins, preserving genome-wide H2A-K119Ub levels. Expression of the bacterial 6mA methyltransferase Dam, in contrast, fails to destroy either sensor. These findings uncover a native, adversarial 6mA network architecture that preserves Polycomb silencing.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015">
<title>Graphical Abstract</title>
<fig id="undfig1" position="anchor">
<graphic xlink:href="fx1"></graphic>
</fig>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020">
<title>Highlights</title>
<p>
<list id="ulist0010" list-type="simple">
<list-item id="u0010">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0010">6mA deposition and erasure by mammalian Mettl4 and Alkbh4, respectively</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0015">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0015"><italic>Mettl4</italic>-deficient mice display craniofacial dysmorphism</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0020">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0020">6mA triggers proteolysis of its cognate sensor proteins ASXL1 and MPND</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0025">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0025">Adversarial 6mA network architecture preserves Polycomb silencing</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025">
<p>Kweon et al. reveal the molecular infrastructure of a mammalian DNA N6-methyladenine (6mA) methylation, erasure, and sensing system. Deposition of 6mA by the Mettl4 methyltransferase triggers the proteolytic destruction of its cognate sensor proteins, the histone H2A deubiquitinases ASXL1 and MPND, thus preserving Polycomb gene silencing.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>6mA</kwd>
<kwd>DNA methylation</kwd>
<kwd>TRIP12</kwd>
<kwd>ASXL1</kwd>
<kwd>MPND</kwd>
<kwd>METTL4</kwd>
<kwd>ALKBH4</kwd>
<kwd>ALKBH1</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<p id="misc0010">Published: April 11, 2019</p>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="p0030">DNA base modification systems evolved under the intense selective pressure of bacterial predation by prokaryotic viruses (phage) to discriminate self from invasive genomes and were, in turn, co-opted by phage as a counter-restriction strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bryson et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Iyer et al., 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Schlagman and Hattman, 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Weigele and Raleigh, 2016</xref>). In bacteria, enzymatically modified DNA bases also perform essential roles in DNA replication and repair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abeles et al., 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Au et al., 1992</xref>). A multitude of DNA base modifications are found in prokaryotes, yet relatively few have been detected in higher eukaryotes, with 5-methylcytosine (5mC) and its enzymatically oxidized derivatives representing well-characterized exceptions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Schübeler, 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Tahiliani et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0035">Methylation of adenine at the N6 position in DNA (6mA), among the most prevalent DNA modifications in prokaryotes, was recently detected in metazoan genomic DNA, including in vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Greer et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Koziol et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Zhang et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Zhu et al., 2018</xref>), suggesting a previously unrecognized form of gene control. Deposition of 6mA in the nematode worm <italic>C. elegans</italic> is catalyzed by DAMT-1, a member of the Ime4-like/MT-A70 clade of methyltransferases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Greer et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Iyer et al., 2016</xref>), while N6AMT1, a member of the HemK family of protein N-methyltransferases, may perform a similar role in human cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kusevic et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>). Conversely, the enzymatic removal of 6mA has been attributed to the Alkbh1 and Alkbh4 dioxygenases in mammalian cells and invertebrates, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Greer et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Xie et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Zhang et al., 2015</xref>). The function of mammalian orthologs of Alkbh4 in the oxidative demethylation of 6mA, if any, has not been addressed experimentally.</p>
<p id="p0040">6mA has been implicated in gene transactivation in the unicellular eukaryote <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> and in the invertebrates <italic>Drosophila</italic> and <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Fu et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Greer et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Zhang et al., 2015</xref>). In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, mutually reinforcing deposition of the activating histone mark H3K4me2 and 6mA defines a gene regulatory circuit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Greer et al., 2015</xref>). In contrast, 6mA is associated with epigenetic silencing in mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Xie et al., 2018</xref>). In metazoans, silenced chromatin domains are established principally through the action of Polycomb repressive complexes (PRC1 and PRC2), which catalyze conjugation of monoubiquitin to histone H2A (H2A-K119Ub) and trimethylation of histone H3 at lysine 27 (H3K27me3), respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gao et al., 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kirmizis et al., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Schuettengruber et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wang et al., 2004</xref>). Both of these marks are reversible: H3K27 demethylation is catalyzed by Kdm6 enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bosselut, 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Manna et al., 2015</xref>), while MYSM1/MPND deubiquitinases (DUBs) and the Polycomb repressive deubiquitinase (PR-DUB) complex deconjugate monoubiquitin from H2A-K119Ub (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Scheuermann et al., 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Zhu et al., 2007</xref>). High-sensitivity mass spectrometry studies have established that PR-DUB contains the core catalytic subunit BAP1, a ubiquitin hydrolase, and the regulatory components ASXL1 or ASXL2, which regulate BAP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hauri et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kloet et al., 2016</xref>). ASXL paralogs contain a central ASXH domain that stimulates BAP1 deubiquitinase activity <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Sahtoe et al., 2016</xref>). How PR-DUB composition and catalytic activity are controlled in mammalian cells is largely unknown.</p>
<p id="p0045">In this work, we uncover the components of a 6mA deposition, erasure, and sensor network in mammalian cells. We identify structurally distinct 6mA sensor domains within MPND and ASXL1 and demonstrate that native deposition of 6mA stimulates the proteolytic destruction of both sensor proteins. These observations reveal how 6mA functions antagonistically against its cognate sensors to preserve and sustain Polycomb-mediated gene silencing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec2.1">
<title>Mammalian Mettl4 and Alkbh4 Enzymes Catalyze 6mA Deposition and Erasure, Respectively</title>
<p id="p0050">Mettl4 belongs to a subclade of MT-A70 adenine methyltransferases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bujnicki et al., 2002</xref>) that is distinct from RNA-directed methyltransferases and includes both <italic>C. elegans</italic> DAMT-1 and the bacterial DNA 6mA methyltransferase M.MunI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Iyer et al., 2016</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>A and 1B). Expression of Flag-tagged <italic>E. coli</italic> 6mA methyltransferase Dam (Flag-Dam) or Mettl4 (Flag-Mettl4), but not a Mettl4 catalytic site mutant (DPPW-&gt;DRRW), in HEK293T cells promoted the accumulation of 6mA in genomic DNA, as detected by dot blot using 6mA antisera and by liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) analysis of DNA hydrolysates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>C). To evaluate the methyltransferase activity of Mettl4 <italic>in vivo</italic>, we applied CRISPR/Cas9 gene targeting in mouse zygotes to generate inactivating mutations in <italic>Mettl4</italic> and obtained pups carrying a heterozygous deletion of exon 6, which creates a translational frameshift that ablates the catalytic domain, for a predicted methyltransferase knockout (KO) allele (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S1</xref>). Quantitative LC-MS/MS analysis of genomic DNA hydrolysates prepared from strain-matched wild-type (WT) and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO embryonic stem cells (ESCs) revealed depletion of 6mA in the KO samples to undetectable levels from a mean of 8.6 ppm (relative to dA) in WT ESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>D, left panel). In agreement with previous reports of a nonredundant, essential role for the Mettl3/Mettl14 complex in mRNA adenine N6-methylation (m6A) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Dominissini et al., 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Geula et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Liu et al., 2014</xref>), inactivation of <italic>Mettl4</italic> did not significantly decrease the level of m6A in mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>D, right panel). Inactivation of <italic>Mettl4</italic> also diminished 6mA levels in spleen genomic DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>E), suggesting a role for Mettl4 in 6mA deposition during development and in adult tissues.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mettl4 and Alkbh4 Catalyze Deposition and Erasure, Respectively, of 6mA</p><p>(A) Schematic presentation of Mettl4 protein structure and linear arrangement of conserved motifs in methyltransferase domain (amino acids 257–471), showing detailed alignment to motif IV sequence logo in catalytic site of MT-A70 adenine N6-methyltransferases.</p><p>(B) Clustering of proteins within the MT-A70 family. RNA-specific methyltransferases form a tight cluster of closely related sequences, while Mettl4 and the DNA adenine N6-methyltransferases DAMT-1 (<italic>C. elegans</italic>) and M. MunI (Mycoplasma) (red circles) are positioned apart.</p><p>(C) HEK293T cells transfected with empty vector (EV) or expressing Flag-Dam or the wild-type or DPPW catalytic-site mutant (PPmut) variants of Flag-Mettl4 were harvested and proteins in whole-cell extracts resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with Flag antisera. Actin, loading control. 6mA and 5mC in the same samples were detected by dot blot of genomic DNA (n = 3 experiments), and mean 6mA levels relative to dA were quantified by LC-MS/MS analysis of genomic DNA hydrolysates (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>(D) Levels of 6mA relative to total dA in genomic DNA (left panel) and m6A relative to total adenosine (A) in mRNA (right panel), purified from WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs, as determined by quantitative LC-MS/MS. Dashed line represents limit of detection. n.d., not detected. Data are plotted as mean with SD (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>(E) Overlaid extracted LC-MS chromatograms of dA and 6mA in genomic DNA hydrolysates prepared from WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO spleens.</p><p>(F) <italic>In vitro</italic> 6mA demethylation assay. Recombinant His-Alkbh4 was purified from bacterial cell extracts (left panel). Irrelevant lanes were omitted from the gel. Human genomic DNA containing 6mA was incubated in buffer supplemented with Fe<sup>2+</sup> and 2-oxoglutarate cofactors in the absence or presence of His-Alkbh4 or vitamin C (VitC) for the indicated times. 6mA in each sample was detected by dot blot analysis (n = 3 experiments).</p><p>(G) Alkbh4 demethylates 6mA in double-stranded (ds) DNA. Single-stranded (ss) or double-stranded DNA oligonucleotide containing unmodified adenine or 6mA was incubated in the absence or presence of His-Alkbh4 for the indicated times. Following the reactions, 6mA in 10 pmol of each DNA sample was detected by dot blot analysis (n = 3 experiments).</p><p>See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0055">We then examined the activity of murine Alkbh4, which is orthologous to 6mA demethylases in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Greer et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Zhang et al., 2015</xref>). Purified, His-tagged Alkbh4 (His-Alkbh4) catalyzed the demethylation of 6mA in genomic DNA substrate in the presence of Fe<sup>2+</sup> and 2-oxoglutarate cofactors and was not measurably stimulated by the addition of ascorbic acid (Vitamin C) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>F). His-Alkbh4 also efficiently demethylated DNA duplex oligonucleotide containing 6mA base modifications within a consensus motif (5′-<underline>A</underline>GAAG<underline>A</underline>GGA-3′) identified through methylated DNA immunoprecipitation sequencing (MeDIP-seq) of genomic DNA from mouse ESCs and embryonic day (E) 9.5 embryos (strain C57BL/6x129Sv) using 6mA-specific antisera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>G and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S2</xref>). No effect of His-Alkbh4 was detected on single-stranded DNA substrate, even after prolonged incubations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>G). We conclude that Mettl4 and Alkbh4 catalyze the deposition and oxidative demethylation, respectively, of 6mA in DNA. These enzymes may act complementarily with N6AMT1 and Alkbh1 to control the genomic distribution of 6mA in different cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Xie et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Zhu et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.2">
<title>Craniofacial Dysmorphism and Embryonic Sublethality in <italic>Mettl4</italic> Knockout Progeny</title>
<p id="p0060"><italic>Mettl4</italic> and <italic>Alkbh4</italic> transcripts are expressed in mouse ESCs, as detected by reverse-transcription-quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR), with increased levels in E9.5 embryos and in some adult tissues (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>A). In ESCs, <italic>Mettl4</italic> transcripts are significantly more abundant than those encoding <italic>N6AMT1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Shen et al., 2012</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>B), implicating Mettl4 in the regulation of 6mA in ESCs. To investigate the physiological role of Mettl4 in development, we intercrossed <italic>Mettl4+/−</italic> heterozygous mice and recovered <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice at the expected Mendelian ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>A). <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice were fertile at 6 weeks of age; however, <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO incrosses produced significantly smaller litters than those obtained from strain-matched WT controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>B), and ∼6.4% of incross progeny displayed gross anatomical defects, including anophthalmia and craniofacial dysmorphism (n = 5/78 pups from 14 litters) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>B and 2C). Adult (10–12 weeks old) <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice were moribund and exhibited splenomegaly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>D and 2E) with anemia and severe leukopenia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>F), indicative of aberrant hematopoiesis. These observations implicate Mettl4 in the control of hematopoietic lineage specification and craniofacial patterning.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Embryonic Sublethality and Craniofacial Dysmorphism in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO Incross Progeny</p><p>(A) Genotypic analysis of progeny from intercrossed <italic>Mettl4</italic> ± heterozygous (Het) mice, showing expected and observed frequencies for each genotype. n.s., not significant, Chi-square test.</p><p>(B) Mating scores of strain-matched wild-type (WT) controls, intercrossed <italic>Mettl4</italic> ± heterozygotes, and incrossed <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice. Black dots indicate the numbers of pups in each litter at the day of birth or recovered by Caesarian section at E18.5. Red lines indicate the mean litter size. p value was calculated by two-tailed t test. <sup>∗∗</sup>p &lt; 0.01. The percentages of progeny that displayed craniofacial or limb dysmorphism are shown below each plot.</p><p>(C) Neonatal <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO pups from a single litter of incrossed <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO parents. White arrow indicates mandibular malformation. Scale bar, 10 mm.</p><p>(D) Representative image of spleens recovered from individual adult (10–12 weeks old) WT or <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice. Rulers show scale in cm. Separate images for WT and KO spleens were juxtaposed at the dashed line.</p><p>(E) Bar graph representation of spleen mass divided by total body mass for adult WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice (n = 6 mice per group). Error bars indicate SD <sup>∗∗</sup>p &lt; 0.01, two-tailed t test.</p><p>(F) (Left panel) Peripheral blood count of white cells (WBC) and lymphocytes (left-hand scale) and red blood cells (RBC, right-hand scale) in adult WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice. (Right panel) Hematocrit (HCT) analysis. Each point corresponds to values from an individual mouse. Brackets indicate normal range and mean values in WT mice. p values were calculated using unpaired, two-tailed t test. <sup>∗</sup>p &lt; 0.05.</p><p>See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.3">
<title>6mA Deposition Triggers Proteolysis of the Sensor Proteins ASXL1 and MPND</title>
<p id="p0065">To elucidate how 6mA is linked to gene control, we sought to identify proteins that selectively recognize this modified base. Candidate 6mA-interacting proteins in bacteria have been proposed on the basis of their recurrent association in gene operons with, or fusion to, DNA adenine N6-methyltransferases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aravind and Iyer, 2012</xref>). One such protein domain, the HB1, ASXL, restriction endonuclease HTH domain (HARE-HTH), is highly conserved and contained within the N terminus of most metazoan ASXL orthologs, including human ASXL1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>A). A second candidate 6mA sensor of prokaryotic origin, the restriction enzyme-adenine methylase-associated (RAMA) domain, is found in the related mammalian DUBs MYSM1 and MPND (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Iyer et al., 2016</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>A). In DNA pull-down assays, the standalone purified HARE-HTH and MPND RAMA domains, but not the MYSM1 RAMA domain, bound selectively to agarose resin coated with duplex DNA oligonucleotide containing 6mA in a native sequence context (5′-AAC<underline>A</underline>GAAG<underline>A</underline>GG-3′), but not to DNA containing the 5mC or 5-carboxylcytosine (5caC) modifications or to 6mA within a non-native sequence context (5′-G<underline>A</underline>TC-3′) specified by <italic>E. coli</italic> Dam (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S4</xref>). The absence of selective binding to 6mA by the MYSM1 RAMA domain suggests functional divergence of this domain across mammalian paralogs.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>6mA Deposition Triggers Proteolysis of the Sensor Proteins ASXL1 and MPND</p><p>(A) Domain structures of ASXL1, showing the positions of the HARE-HTH and PHD domains and the central proline-rich region (PRR), and the MYSM1 and MPND deubiquitinases, with the percentage amino acid identity and similarity between RAMA domains. JAMM/DUB denotes the deubiquitinase catalytic domain.</p><p>(B) <italic>In vitro</italic> DNA pull-down assays. Purified recombinant HARE-HTH and RAMA domains were incubated in the presence of untreated resin or resin coated with duplex DNA containing unmodified adenine (A) or 6mA. After extensive washing, bound protein was resolved by SDS-PAGE and detected by immunoblotting using the indicated antisera (n = 3 experiments).</p><p>(C) HEK293T cells expressing Flag-ASXL1.591 and either empty vector, Flag-Mettl4, or Flag-Dam were harvested and proteins in whole-cell extracts resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with the indicated antisera (upper panels). Dot blot analysis shows relative 6mA levels in genomic DNA recovered from the same samples (n = 3 experiments).</p><p>(D) Cells expressing Flag-RAMA, Flag-Mettl4, or Flag-Dam were harvested and proteins in whole-cell extracts resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting (upper panels). Dot blot analysis shows relative 6mA levels in genomic DNA recovered from the same samples (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>(E) Accumulation of Asxl1 and reduction of H2A-K119Ub and H3K27me3 in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO cells. Whole-cell extracts (upper panels) and purified histones (lower panels) were prepared from spleens isolated from individual WT or <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice and proteins resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>(F) Accumulation of Mpnd in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO cells. Protein extracts were prepared from spleens isolated from individual WT or <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice and resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S5</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0070">We then co-expressed in HEK293T cells Flag-Mettl4 together with a truncated form of ASXL1 (Y591X; hereafter, ASXL1.591), which is readily resolved by SDS-PAGE and is fully competent for activation of PR-DUB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Balasubramani et al., 2015</xref>), reasoning that increased deposition of 6mA might enhance the fraction of chromatin-associated ASXL1. Unexpectedly, however, expression of Flag-Mettl4 sharply diminished Flag-ASXL1.591 levels, both in whole-cell extracts and in a chromatin-enriched subcellular fraction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref>C and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S5</xref>A). Exposure of cells to the proteasome inhibitor MG132 or co-expression of Flag-Alkbh4 rescued Flag-ASXL1.591 in the presence of Flag-Mettl4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S5</xref>B and S5C), while expression of a Mettl4 catalytic site mutant failed to destabilize Flag-ASXL1.591 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>D). These observations together implicate 6mA deposition in ASXL1 proteolysis. Notably, Flag-ASXL1.591 largely escaped proteolysis in HEK293T cells co-expressing Flag-Dam, despite greater overall levels of 6mA in the genomic DNA of these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>C). The standalone MPND RAMA domain was similarly diminished by co-expression of Flag-Mettl4, but not of Flag-Dam (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>D).</p>
<p id="p0075">We found that a synthetic reporter protein containing the N-terminal region of ASXL1 (amino acids 1–115) fused upstream of firefly luciferase was also destabilized in the presence of co-expressed Flag-Mettl4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>E). Mammalian ASXL paralogs contain a short, lysine-rich segment (amino acids 2–9), adjacent to the HARE-HTH domain, that is contained in the Mettl4-sensitive reporter protein (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>F, top). Deletion of this segment (ΔN9) resulted in a gross accumulation of Flag-ASXL1.591 in HEK293T cells and blocked Mettl4-dependent proteolysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>F) but had no detectable effect on the association of ASXL1 with chromatin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>G). The ΔN9 variant of ASXL1 also strongly stabilized co-expressed Flag-HA-BAP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Sowa et al., 2009</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>H). Thus, the HARE-HTH domain, in conjunction with the adjacent, lysine-rich N terminus of ASXL1, acts as a 6mA-dependent proteolytic targeting module that regulates the stability of ASXL1 and PR-DUB catalytic subunit BAP1.</p>
<p id="p0080">Prompted by these findings, we examined the impact of Mettl4 on Polycomb repressive histone marks. Expression of Flag-Mettl4 in HEK293T cells stimulated a marked increase in H2A-K119Ub, with a more modest effect on H3K27me3, as determined by immunoblot analysis of purified histones (Figure S5I). Conversely, both H2A-K119Ub and H3K27me3 were depleted in histones purified from in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO spleens, concomitant with increased levels of Asxl1, Bap1 and Mpnd in the same tissue samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref>E and 3F). Together, these observations implicate 6mA deposition-coupled proteolysis of Asxl1 and Mpnd in the preservation of Polycomb repressive histone marks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.4">
<title>6mA Stimulates Proteolysis of ASXL1 through the E3 Ubiquitin Ligase TRIP12</title>
<p id="p0085">We reasoned that the enzymes responsible for proteolysis of ASXL1 might be detected in association with the PR-DUB complex. High-sensitivity mass spectrometry studies of BAP1 immunopurified from mammalian cell extracts identified the HECT domain ubiquitin E3 ligase TRIP12/TRIPC as a candidate-interacting protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hauri et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kloet et al., 2016</xref>). In humans, germline-inactivating mutations in <italic>TRIP12</italic> are associated with limb deformation and craniofacial dysmorphism, including a depressed nasal bridge, hypoplastic alae nasi, Cupid’s bow of the upper lip, a small lower jaw, and large ear lobes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bramswig et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>); these features strikingly overlap with those of Bohring-Opitz syndrome patients carrying germline mutant alleles of <italic>ASXL1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hoischen et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Shashi et al., 2016</xref>), suggesting overlapping functions of ASXL1 and TRIP12 in craniofacial patterning.</p>
<p id="p0090">Given these similarities, we examined the interaction of TRIP12 with ASXL1. Flag-ASXL1.591 co-immunoprecipitated with endogenous TRIP12 in HEK293T cell extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A). Importantly, expression of Flag-Mettl4 stimulated engagement of Flag-ASXL1.591 with TRIP12 while concomitantly reducing the total amount of Flag-ASXL1.591 in the lysate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A, lanes 1–3). Expression of GFP-tagged TRIP12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gudjonsson et al., 2012</xref>) also resulted in diminished levels of Flag-ASXL1.591 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A, lanes 4 and 5). Conversely, depletion of <italic>TRIP12</italic> using two independent short hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) strongly promoted accumulation of Flag-ASXL1.591 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>B) and rendered Flag-ASXL1.591 refractory to proteolysis in the presence of co-expressed Flag-Mettl4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>C). Together, these observations suggest that deposition of 6mA stimulates the engagement of ASXL1/PR-DUB with TRIP12, promoting proteolysis of ASXL1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>D).<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The E3 Ubiquitin Ligase TRIP12 Mediates Proteolysis of ASXL1</p><p>(A) Lysates prepared from HEK293T cells expressing the indicated combinations of Flag-ASXL1.591, Flag-Mettl4, or GFP-TRIP12 were immunoprecipitated using TRIP12 antisera or isotype-matched control IgG. Inputs and immunoprecipitated proteins were resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with Flag or TRIP12 antisera (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>(B) HEK293T cells expressing Flag-ASXL1.591 and either a control shRNA targeting GFP or independent shRNAs (sh1 or sh2) targeting <italic>TRIP12</italic> were lysed and protein extracts resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting. Tubulin, loading control (n = 3 experiments).</p><p>(C) Protein extracts prepared from cells expressing Flag-ASXL1.591, in the absence or presence of Flag-Mettl4 or sh1-<italic>TRIP12</italic>, were resolved by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with the indicated antisera (n = 3 experiments).</p><p>(D) Model depicting 6mA deposition by Mettl4, recruitment of ASXL1/PR-DUB to 6mA, and engagement of PR-DUB with the E3 ubiquitin ligase TRIP12. These steps are proposed to stimulate ASXL1 proteolysis, inactivating PR-DUB and thereby preserving the Polycomb repressive mark H2A-K119Ub in chromatin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.5">
<title>Mettl4-Dependent Regulation of Asxl1 and H2A-K119Ub at Defined Genic Elements</title>
<p id="p0095">To better understand the relationship between 6mA, its cognate sensor proteins, and Polycomb repressive marks, we profiled the genomic distribution of 6mA in mESCs using MeDIP-seq. Results from this approach identified 4,922 unique 6mA peaks, which overlapped significantly with 6mA base modifications identified through single-molecule real-time (SMRT) sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figures 5</xref>A and 5B; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Table S1</xref>), supporting the specificity of the 6mA peaks identified through the orthogonal MeDIP approach. A disproportionate fraction of 6mA peaks localized in intergenic regions, in line with previous observations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>A) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>). In genic regions, 6mA tag density decreased approaching the transcription start site in gene promoters, while increasing progressively toward the transcription end site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>C). In gene bodies and flanking the TSS, the highest 6mA density was detected in genes expressed at relatively low levels in WT ESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>C).<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Ectopic Asxl1 and Mpnd Correspond with Loss of Polycomb Silencing in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs</p><p>(A) Pie chart illustrating the distribution of called 6mA peaks (n = 4,922) across promoter (−2 kb to TSS), TSS downstream (0–2 kb downstream of TSS), 5′ and 3′ UTR, coding exon, intron, and intergenic regions. Red numbers indicate the fold enrichment or depletion of 6mA at each feature relative to a random distribution.</p><p>(B) Venn diagram showing overlap of 6mA peaks identified by MeDIP and called 6mA bases identified by PacBio SMRT sequencing analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>). p value, Fisher’s exact test.</p><p>(C) Normalized 6mA tag density plotted 1 kb upstream of the TSS, across the first 3 kb of a metagene, and 1 kb downstream of the TES for all genes (black), the top 10% of highly expressed genes (blue), and the bottom 10% of least expressed genes in WT ESCs (red).</p><p>(D) Venn diagrams showing the number and relative distribution of Asxl1, Bap1, O-GlcNAc, Mpnd, and H2A-K119Ub (H2A-Ub) peaks in WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs.</p><p>(E) Normalized tag density of ectopic Asxl1 peaks induced in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs (left) with heatmap representation of peaks ranked-ordered by the mean signal (right), each plotted across a window centered on the TSS.</p><p>(F) Genome browser view showing profiles of 6mA or isotype-matched control IgG in WT ESCs (top) and Asxl1, Mpnd, H2A-Ub, Bap1, and O-GlcNAc in WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs at two representative loci. Shaded vertical bars highlight regions containing ectopic Asxl1 or Mpnd and depletion of H2A-Ub in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs. RefSeq exon structures (blue) for each annotated gene are shown at the bottom.</p><p>(G) ChIP-qPCR analysis of the <italic>Rpl13</italic> and <italic>Dvl3</italic> genes in WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs. Antisera specific for Asxl1, H2A-K119Ub002C or Bap1 were used for chromatin immunoprecipitation. The mean fold enrichments normalized to isotype-matched IgG control are shown for each condition. Error bars indicate SEM (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>(H) RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>Rpl13</italic> and <italic>Dvl3</italic> transcript levels in WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs. The mean value of WT control samples is set as 1. Error bars indicate SEM (n = 2 experiments).</p><p>(I) Volcano plot presentation of transcript levels for genes expressed in WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs as determined by RNA-seq. Genes strongly up- or downregulated (FC &gt; 2.0, FDR-adjusted p &lt; 0.05) in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO cells are identified and indicated in red or green, respectively.</p><p>(J) Gene ontology analysis of differentially expressed genes induced in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO cells showing involvement in embryonic development and tissue patterning. The yellow vertical line indicates the threshold for significance.</p><p>See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0100">Inactivation of <italic>Mettl4</italic> generated a ∼5-fold increase in the number of called Asxl1 peaks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figures 5</xref>D and 5E; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S2</xref>) and a 41.3% increase in Bap1 peaks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>D) identified using stringent cutoff criteria (FDR adjusted p &lt; 0.05), in agreement with Asxl1-mediated stabilization of Bap1. In contrast, the number of called peaks and the distribution of O-linked N-acetylglucosamine (O-GlcNAc), which is attached to chromatin-associated target proteins by PR-DUB component Ogt1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hauri et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kloet et al., 2016</xref>), remained largely unchanged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>D). Thus, Ogt1 may be recruited to DNA independently of 6mA, potentially through other DNA-binding components of PR-DUB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hauri et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kloet et al., 2016</xref>). Inactivation of <italic>Mettl4</italic> also produced a ∼80% increase in the number of called Mpnd peaks relative to WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>D), further supporting a role for 6mA in destabilization of both classes of H2A DUBs. Accumulation of ectopic Asxl1 and Mpnd in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs corresponded with a 51.6% reduction in H2A-K119Ub peaks, as determined by ChIP-seq analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figures 5</xref>D and 5F) with ChIP-qPCR validation at the <italic>Rpl13</italic> and <italic>Dvl3</italic> loci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>G), and expression of both genes was accordingly induced in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs, as determined by RT-qPCR analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>H).</p>
<p id="p0105">To assess the global impact of <italic>Mettl4</italic> inactivation on gene expression, we performed RNA-seq transcriptome profiling of WT and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs and identified 198 genes that displayed significantly altered expression, with 135 upregulated and 63 downregulated genes (FC &gt; 2.0, FDR-adjusted p &lt; 0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>I). Gene ontology analysis of differentially expressed genes revealed significant involvement in tissue specification and organ morphogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>J), supporting a role for 6mA-dependent gene control in the regulation of embryonic tissue patterning.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="p0110">Here we reveal the molecular infrastructure of a mammalian-DNA 6mA methylation, erasure, and sensing system and elucidate its function in gene control. The system minimally encompasses the Mettl4 methyltransferase and Alkbh4 dioxygenase, which catalyze 6mA deposition and erasure, respectively, and two structurally distinct classes of 6mA sensor domains attached to unrelated deubiquitinases, which nonetheless remove monoubiquitin from the same substrate: H2A-K119Ub, a Polycomb repressive histone mark. Strikingly, deposition of 6mA by Mettl4 triggers the proteolytic destruction of each sensor protein, ASXL1 and MPND, thereby preserving H2A-K119Ub levels. In contrast, both sensors are largely refractory to 6mA deposited in a non-native sequence context through heterologous expression of the bacterial 6mA methyltransferase Dam in mammalian cells. Altogether, these observations reveal a native system architecture that operates through a 6mA-deposition-coupled sensor destruction mechanism to preserve Polycomb gene silencing.</p>
<p id="p0115">The methylome defined by 6mA shares several important similarities with 5mC, including reversibility through oxidative demethylation and a system output that impacts gene expression through the modulation of histone marks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">He et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kweon et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Schübeler, 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Xie et al., 2018</xref>). 5mC differentially repels or tethers methylation-selective transcription factors, effector proteins, and associated chromatin-modifying enzymes such as histone deacetylases to DNA, silencing gene transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Schübeler, 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Yin et al., 2017</xref>). 6mA, in contrast, operates through detection-triggered proteolysis and depletion of its cognate sensors. Iterative cycles of sensor engagement and destruction may greatly amplify the 6mA output space, rationalizing the significant impact of this base modification on gene control notwithstanding an exponentially (∼1,000-fold) lower abundance relative to 5mC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Schübeler, 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Smith et al., 2012</xref>). Importantly, 6mA may regulate sensor protein expression or stability through additional transcriptional or post-transcriptional mechanisms. It will also be important to determine whether 6mA can regulate chromatin states and gene expression independently of its destabilizing effects on ASXL1 and MPND.</p>
<p id="p0120">Global depletion of 6mA has been reported in aggressive tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>), raising the possibility that accumulation of ASXL1 and hyperactivation of PR-DUB drive deregulated gene expression, oncogenesis, and metastatic progression. Heterozygous nonsense alleles of <italic>ASXL1</italic>, which have been proposed to encode truncated gain-of-function proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Asada et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Balasubramani et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Guo et al., 2018</xref>), represent a prevalent class of <italic>ASXL1</italic> mutations in leukemic cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Balasubramani et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Boultwood et al., 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Dey et al., 2012</xref>). Against this backdrop, it will be interesting to determine whether inactivation of <italic>ALKBH1</italic> or <italic>ALKBH4</italic> can elevate genomic 6mA levels and thus drive the proteolytic destruction of oncogenic ASXL1 truncations. Future studies may address the feasibility and impact of 6mA modulation as an anticancer therapeutic strategy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4">
<title>STAR★Methods</title>
<sec id="sec4.1">
<title>Key Resources Table</title>
<p id="p0125">
<table-wrap id="undtbl1" position="float">
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th>REAGENT or RESOURCE</th>
<th>SOURCE</th>
<th>IDENTIFIER</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Antibodies</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti FLAG M2</td>
<td>Sigma-Aldrich</td>
<td>Cat#F3165; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0010" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_259529">AB_259529</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit polyclonal anti Histone H3K27me3</td>
<td>Active Motif</td>
<td>Cat#39155; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0015" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2561020">AB_2561020</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit polyclonal anti 6mA</td>
<td>Active Motif</td>
<td>Cat#61495</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit polyclonal anti 5mC</td>
<td>Active Motif</td>
<td>Cat#61255</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti luciferase</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-74548; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0020" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_1125118">AB_1125118</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti ASXL1</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-293204;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti HA</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-57592; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0025" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_629568">AB_629568</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit monoclonal anti Histone H2A</td>
<td>ThermoFisher</td>
<td>Cat#700158; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0030" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2532288">AB_2532288</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit monoclonal anti Histone H2A-Ub</td>
<td>Cell Signaling Technology</td>
<td>Cat#8240; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0035" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_10891618">AB_10891618</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit polyclonal anti TRIP12</td>
<td>ThermoFisher</td>
<td>Cat#PA5-38016; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0040" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2554620">AB_2554620</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti O-GlcNAc</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-59623; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0045" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_784962">AB_784962</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti S-Tag</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#71549-3; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0050" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_10806301">AB_10806301</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit polyclonal anti beta-tubulin</td>
<td>Abcam</td>
<td>Cat#ab6046; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0055" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2210370">AB_2210370</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti beta-actin</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-47778; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0060" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2714189">AB_2714189</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti His tag</td>
<td>ThermoFisher</td>
<td>Cat# MA1-135; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0065" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2536841">AB_2536841</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti GAPDH</td>
<td>Cell Signaling Technology</td>
<td>Cat#97166; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0070" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2756824">AB_2756824</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Goat anti mouse IgG-HRP</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat# sc-2005; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0075" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_631736">AB_631736</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Goat anti rabbit IgG-HRP</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-2004; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0080" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_631746">AB_631746</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Bacterial and Virus Strains</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rosetta 2(DE3)pLysS Competent Cells</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#71403</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MG132</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#M8699-1MG</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dam methyltransferase</td>
<td>New England Biolabs</td>
<td>Cat#M0222S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Power SYBR Green PCR Master Mix</td>
<td>ThermoFisher</td>
<td>Cat# 4367659</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DNA Degradase Plus</td>
<td>Zymo Research</td>
<td>Cat#E2020</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse LIF</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#ESG1106</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RNase A</td>
<td>ThermoFisher</td>
<td>Cat#12091021</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RNase H</td>
<td>New England Biolabs</td>
<td>Cat#M0297S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mpnd-RAMA-His</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MYSM1-RAMA-His</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HARE-HTH-His</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alkbh4-His</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nuclease P1</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#N8630-1VL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BioT</td>
<td>Bioland Scientific</td>
<td>Cat#B01S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ampure XP resin</td>
<td>BeckmanCoulter</td>
<td>Cat#A63880</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Protein A/G agarose</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-2003; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0085" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_10201400">AB_10201400</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Critical Commercial Assays</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Quick Genotyping DNA kit</td>
<td>Bioland Scientific</td>
<td>Cat#GT01-01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LookOut Mycoplasma PCR Detection kit</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#MP0035-1KT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DNEasy Blood and Tissue kit</td>
<td>QIAGEN</td>
<td>Cat#69506</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Quick-</italic>RNA miniprep kit</td>
<td>Zymo Research</td>
<td>Cat#R1054</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maxima First Strand cDNA Synthesis kit</td>
<td>ThermoFisher</td>
<td>Cat#K1642</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NEBNExt rRNA Depletion kit (Human/Mouse/Rat)</td>
<td>New England Biolabs</td>
<td>Cat#E6310S</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MAGnify ChIP kit</td>
<td>ThermoFisher</td>
<td>Cat#492024</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>KAPA HyperPrep kit</td>
<td>Roche</td>
<td>Cat#07962312001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>KAPA Stranded mRNA Sequencing kit</td>
<td>Roche</td>
<td>Cat#07962282001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Deposited Data</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6mA SMRT sequencing</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Wu et al., 2016</xref>
</td>
<td>GEO: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0090" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE71940">GSE71940</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>mESC RNA-seq</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Shen et al., 2012</xref>
</td>
<td>GEO: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0095" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSM723776">GSM723776</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ChIP, MeDIP, and RNA sequencing</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>GEO: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0100" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE105006">GSE105006</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mendeley dataset</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0105" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.17632/rfmf3tb5z8.1">http://doi.org/10.17632/rfmf3tb5z8.1</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Experimental Models: Cell Lines</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse Mettl4 KO ESCs</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Human HEK293T</td>
<td>ATCC</td>
<td>Cat#CRL-11268; RRID: CVCL_1926</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Experimental Models: Organisms/Strains</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse: Mettl4<sup>em6Dfel:</sup> 129/Sv <sup>∗</sup> C57BL/6N</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Oligonucleotides</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Primers for qPCR</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">Table S3</xref>
</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6mA consensus Forward: 5′-GATGCAAGCATCAGC<break></break>AAC6mAGAAG6mAGGATCTCAGGTGCAGCGC-3′</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unmethylated consensus Forward: 5′-GATGCAAGCATC<break></break>AGCAACAGAAGAGGATCTCAGGTGCAGCGC-3′</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Consensus Reverse: 5′-Biotin-GCGCTGCACCTGAGAT<break></break>CCTCTTCTGTTGCTGATGCTTGCATC-3′</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dam-methylated substrate Forward: 5′-ATAACTACACT<break></break>ATCATGCGCTGACCCACAACATCCGAAGGGATCCAG<break></break>GTTAAGTAATATAATTGCGCCTTAT-3′</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dam-methylated substrate Reverse: 5′-Biotin-ATAAGG<break></break>CGCAATTATATTACTTAACCTGGATCCCTTCGGATGTT<break></break>GTGGGTCAGCGCATGATAGTGTAGTTAT-3′</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5mC control for pull-down: 5′-biotin-GGA CCACCG GTG GTC C-3′</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5caC control for pull-down Forward: 5′-TACACTATCAT<break></break>G<underline>X</underline>GCTGACCCACAACATCCGA-3′, where X is 5caC</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5caC control for pull-down Reverse: 5′-biotin-TCGGATG<break></break>TTGTGGGTCAGCGCATGATAGTGTA-3′</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Recombinant DNA</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pcDNA3.1-HARE-HTH-luciferase</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 106427</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: p3xFlag-Alkbh4</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 105240</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: p3xFlag-Mettl4</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 86665</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pET30a-HARE-HTH</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 107164</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pET30a-Mpnd-RAMA</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 112226</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pET30a-MYSM1-RAMA</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: p3XFlag-Dam</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 121909</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: p3xFlag-RAMA</td>
<td>This study</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pCMV6-XL4 ASXL1 (p.Y591X) 3x Flag</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Balasubramani et al., 2015</xref>
</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 74261</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: Flag-HA-BAP1</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Sowa et al., 2009</xref>
</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 22539</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pX330-U6-Chimeric_BB-CBh-hSpCas9</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cong et al., 2013</xref>
</td>
<td>Addgene plasmid 42230</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pAc-GFP-TRIP12</td>
<td>Lukas lab; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gudjonsson et al., 2012</xref></td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pLKO.1-sh1-Trip12</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#TRCN0000273207</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pLKO.1-sh2-Trip12</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#TRCN0000022376</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: pLKO.1-shGFP</td>
<td>MilliporeSigma</td>
<td>Cat#SHC002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: Mettl4 CRISPR/Cas9 KO</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-429415</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plasmid: Mettl4 HDR</td>
<td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td>
<td>Cat#sc-429415-HDR</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Software and Algorithms</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MACS (v2.1.1)</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Zhang et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0110" xlink:href="http://liulab.dfci.harvard.edu/MACS/">http://liulab.dfci.harvard.edu/MACS/</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Trim Galore (v0.3.5)</td>
<td>Babraham Bioinformatics</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0115" xlink:href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/">https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bowtie (v1.2.2)</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Langmead et al., 2009</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0120" xlink:href="http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/index.shtml">http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/index.shtml</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cistrome CEAS</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Shin et al., 2009</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0125" xlink:href="https://anaconda.org/bioconda/cistrome-ceas">https://anaconda.org/bioconda/cistrome-ceas</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NGSPLOT (v2.63)</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shen et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0130" xlink:href="https://github.com/shenlab-sinai/ngsplot">https://github.com/shenlab-sinai/ngsplot</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bedtools (v2.27.0)</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0135" xlink:href="https://bedtools.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">https://bedtools.readthedocs.io/en/latest/</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cufflinks (v2.2.1)</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Trapnell et al., 2010</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0140" xlink:href="http://cole-trapnell-lab.github.io/cufflinks/">http://cole-trapnell-lab.github.io/cufflinks/</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DAVID</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Huang da et al., 2009</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0145" xlink:href="https://david.ncifcrf.gov/">https://david.ncifcrf.gov/</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.2">
<title>Contact for Reagent and Resource Sharing</title>
<p id="p0130">Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Douglas E. Feldman (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0150" xlink:href="mailto:defeldma@usc.edu">defeldma@usc.edu</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.3">
<title>Experimental Model and Subject Details</title>
<sec id="sec4.3.1">
<title>Generation of <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mice</title>
<p id="p0135">Founder mice were generated at Applied StemCell, Inc. (Milpitas, CA, USA) at an AAALAC International accredited facility (Protocol 000587). All animals were treated in accordance with guidelines established by the National Institutes of Health using a protocol approved by the USC Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (Protocol 20520).</p>
<p id="p0140">To generate the CRISPR/Cas9 guide RNA (gRNA) expression vectors targeting murine <italic>Mettl4</italic>, gRNA candidates were selected based on proximity to regions flanking exon 6 and favorable gRNA off-target profiles. Duplex oligonucleotides were ligated into BbsI-digested, phosphatase-treated pSpCas9(BB) (pX330; Addgene plasmid 42230) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cong et al., 2013</xref>) encoding human codon-optimized SpCas9 and a chimeric single guide (sg)RNA. All constructs were confirmed by DNA sequencing.</p>
<p id="p0145">For gene targeting, a mixture of Cas9 mRNA and sgRNAs targeting regions flanking exon 6 of murine <italic>Mettl4</italic> was generated by <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription of both pX330-<italic>Mettl4</italic> sgRNA constructs and microinjected into the cytoplasm of zygote-stage embryos, which were harvested from 129/Sv females mated with C57BL/6N males. The injected embryos were then implanted in CD-1 foster mice. Pups were screened for deletions in <italic>Mettl4</italic> using PCR primers flanking the targeted region. All genomic deletions were confirmed by TOPO-TA cloning of the PCR product and sequencing analysis.</p>
<p id="p0150">From a single round of microinjection, five mice were born and four contained deletions of exon 6. Three founder mice were selected for mouse line expansion and backcrossed to C57BL/6N at least three times prior to experimental analysis. For genotyping, ear tissues from founders and offspring mice were collected and DNA extraction was performed individually using the Quick Genotyping DNA kit (Bioland Scientific). PCR reactions were performed in 25 μL total volume using the following parameters: 95°C, 2 min; 35 cycles of [95°C, 15 s; 60°C, 15 s; 72°C, 30 s], 72°C, 4 min; 4°C, hold.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.3.2">
<title>Cell line generation</title>
<p id="p0155">To generate <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs, mice heterozygous for the exon 6 deletion allele were intercrossed and blastocysts were harvested at E3.5, transferred onto MEF-coated 96-well plates and cultured with 2i/LIF. Additional KO lines were generated by transfecting <italic>Mettl4</italic> heterozygous ESC with <italic>Mettl4</italic> CRISPR/Cas9 KO Plasmid and HDR vector (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) containing a puromycin resistance cassette. Established ESC clones were genotyped by PCR and confirmed by immunoblot. Male wild-type or <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO cells were then expanded in cell culture for subsequent studies. HEK293T cells, a human female embryonic kidney cell line stably expressing the SV40 large T antigen, were purchased from ATCC (CRL-3216). Both HEK293T and ESC lines were routinely authenticated by morphology check with microscope.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.3.3">
<title>Cell Culture</title>
<p id="p0160">Cells were passaged every 2-3 days and maintained at 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> in a humidified incubator. <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO and matched wild-type ESCs were cultured on gelatin-coated plates in high-glucose DMEM (ThermoFisher Scientific) containing 15% FBS (Clontech), 1x non-essential amino acids, 2 mM L-glutamine, 100 μM beta-mercaptoethanol, 1000U/mL leukemia inhibitory factor (MilliporeSigma) and 1x antibiotic-antimycotic (ThermoFisher).</p>
<p id="p0165">HEK293T cells were cultured in high-glucose DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS, 1x non-essential amino acids, and 2 mM L-glutamine, and 1x antibiotic-antimycotic. All cells were tested for absence of mycoplasma contamination using the LookOut Mycoplasma PCR Detection kit (MilliporeSigma).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.3.4">
<title>Sample collection</title>
<p id="p0170">Whole mouse spleens were collected from adult mice (10-12 weeks old) by manual dissection and immediately flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen. Mouse whole blood from was collected n EDTA tubes from 3-4 randomly selected adult female mice of each genotype.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4">
<title>Method Details</title>
<sec id="sec4.4.1">
<title>Transfection</title>
<p id="p0175">Cells cultured in 10 cm dishes or 6-well plates were transfected with purified plasmid DNA (8 μg or 1.5 μg, respectively) using BioT transfection regent (Bioland Scientific) according to the manufacturer’s protocol.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.2">
<title>Dot blot analysis</title>
<p id="p0180">Human genomic DNA was isolated from cultured HEK293T cells using the DNEasy Blood and Tissue kit (QIAGEN). Importantly, to avoid contamination with rRNA that contains m6A, samples treated overnight with RNase A (20 μg/mL) and RNase H (5 U). DNA was denatured in 0.4 M NaOH, 10mM EDTA at 95°C for 10 min, then neutralized by the addition of an equal volume of cold 2.0 M ammonium acetate (pH 7.0). Denatured DNA samples were serially diluted in TE buffer and a total of 3 μL of the diluted samples were spotted onto a nitrocellulose membrane (Biad) followed by drying under UV crosslinking for 5 min. Membranes were blocked in 2% milk and incubated with a 1:1000 dilution of 6mA antisera at 4°C overnight. After washing three times with TBST (20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% Tween-20), the membrane was incubated with the HRP-conjugated anti-rabbit IgG secondary antibody. The membrane was washed with TBST three times prior to incubation in SuperSignal West Pico (ThermoFisher) chemiluminescent substrate and imaging.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.3">
<title>Purification of recombinant proteins</title>
<p id="p0185">Plasmids encoding the His-Alkbh4, His-HARE-HTH and His-RAMA domains were transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> strain Rosetta 2 (DE3) (MilliporeSigma). Bacterial cultures were grown to an A<sub>600</sub> of 0.4-0.5, then induced with 0.1 mM IPTG for 4 h at 30°C. Bacterial pellets were resuspended in ice-cold PBS supplemented with 100mM NaCl, 1mM Imidazole, 0.2% NP-40, complete protease inhibitor cocktail, 5 mM sodium fluoride, 1 mM sodium orthovanadate, lysozyme (0.2 mg/mL) and DNase I (10 μg/mL), then sonicated in 5-6 bursts of 15 s with 1 min cooling in between bursts. Soluble proteins (5 ml) were incubated with 250 μL Profinity Nickel-charged resin (Bio-Rad) for 1 h at 4°C with gentle rotation. Resin was washed twice in lysis buffer and eluted for 30 min in elution buffer (1XPBS, 100mM NaCl, 250mM Imidazole, 5% glycerol), then pooled and dialyzed overnight at 4°C into 1XTBS containing 5% glycerol. Samples were aliquoted and stored at −80°C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.4">
<title>DNA demethylation assays</title>
<p id="p0190">Genomic DNA prepared from HEK293T cells (1.0 μg) or oligonucleotide DNA substrate (25 μM) was incubated with 2.5 μg of His-Alkbh4 in demethylation buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.6, 150 mM NaCl, 5% glycerol, 0.1 mM DTT, 1 mM 2-oxoglutarate, 200 μM (NH)<sub>4</sub>Fe(SO)<sub>4</sub>), in the absence or presence of 1 mM ascorbic acid (Vitamin C), for the indicated times at 37°C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.5">
<title>Oligonucleotide DNA pull-down assays</title>
<sec id="sec4.4.5.1">
<title>HPLC-purified DNA oligonucleotides</title>
<p id="p0195">(5′- GATGCAAGCATCAGCAAC<underline>A</underline>GAAG<underline>A</underline>GGATCTCAGGTGCAGCGC-3′, where A is 6mA or A) containing a 5′ biotin moiety attached by a 15-atom tetra-ethylene glycol (TEG) spacer arm were purchased from TriLink and IDT, respectively, dissolved to 0.15 mg/mL in annealing buffer (20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 1mM EDTA), mixed at a 1:1 molar ratio with unmodified reverse complement oligo, then denatured at 95°C for 5 min and allowed to cool gradually to room temperature. To generate Dam-methylated oligonucleotides, HPLC-purified oligonucleotide (5′-ATAACTACACTATCATGCGCTGACCCACAACATCCGAAGGGATCCAGGTTAAGTAATATAATTGCGCCTTAT-3′) containing a 5′ biotin moiety was dissolved to 0.15 mg/mL in annealing buffer (20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 1mM EDTA), mixed at a 1:1 molar ratio with unmodified reverse complement oligo, then incubated at 95°C for 5 min and allowed to cool gradually to room temperature. Duplex DNA was incubated in the presence 5 U of recombinant Dam (New England Biolabs) for 18 h at 37°C, then purified by spin column.</p>
<p id="p0200">For 5mC-modified control DNA duplexes, HPLC-purified palindromic DNA oligonucleotide (5′-GGA CCAC<underline>C</underline>G GTG GTC C −3′) containing a 5′ biotin moiety attached by a</p>
<p id="p0205">TEG spacer arm (IDT) was dissolved to 0.15 mg/mL in annealing buffer, incubated at 95°C for 5 min and allowed to cool gradually to room temperature.</p>
<p id="p0210">For 5caC- modified DNA duplexes, HPLC-purified 32-mer oligonucleotides (5′-</p>
<p id="p0215">TACACTATCATGXGCTGACCCACAACATCCGA-3′, where X is 5caC) (TriLink Technologies) was mixed with an equimolar amount of complementary oligonucleotide containing</p>
<p id="p0220">a 5′ biotin-TEG moiety, then dissolved to 0.15 mg/mL in annealing buffer, incubated at 95°C for 5 min and allowed to cool gradually to room temperature.</p>
<p id="p0225">Coupling of DNA to resin was performed essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Spruijt et al., 2013</xref>). Briefly, 1.5 μg (10 μl) of duplex oligo was coupled to 100 μL of streptavidin-agarose resin (Gold Biotechnology) in 100 μL DNA binding buffer (10mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 1M NaCl, 1mM EDTA pH 8, 0.05% NP40) for 4 h at 25°C with gentle rocking. Coupling of the DNA to the beads was verified by agarose gel electrophoresis. Resin was washed twice in 10 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 2.5% glycerol, and aliquots were stored at −20°C for subsequent use. Purified His-RAMA or His-HARE-HTH (1.0 μg) was incubated with 30 μL of uncoated control resin or DNA-coated resin in 100 μL protein binding (PB) buffer (50 mM Tris pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1.0 mM DTT, 0.25% NP-40) in the presence of 4 μg poly-dI:dC for 2 h at 4°C. Resin was recovered by centrifugation at 7,000 g for 1 min and washed three times with PB buffer, then boiled for 5 min at 95°C in 1X Laemmle Sample Buffer and resolved by SDS-PAGE for immunoblot analysis.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.6">
<title>RT-qPCR</title>
<p id="p0230">Total RNA was isolated from cultured ES cells or homogenized embryos using the <italic>Quick</italic>-RNA miniprep kit (Zymo Research) and cDNA prepared using the Maxima First Strand cDNA Synthesis kit (ThermoFisher) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. qPCR reactions were prepared with the Power SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (ThermoFisher) and cycling performed using a ViiA7 Real-Time PCR system (Applied Biosystems). Primers used for qPCR are listed in Table S3. Expression levels were normalized to <italic>Gapdh</italic> or <italic>β-actin</italic> in the same samples.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.7">
<title>LC-MS/MS analysis</title>
<p id="p0235">Genomic DNA (250 ng) purified from isogenic wild-type and <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs or adult spleens was treated with DNA Degradase Plus (Zymo Research) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. For m6A quantitation, total RNA was extracted using the <italic>Quick-</italic>RNA miniprep kit according to the manufacturer’s instructions. rRNA was removed using the NEBNExt rRNA Depletion kit (New England Biolabs). 200 ng of purified RNA was digested by P1 nuclease (2 units) in 25 μl buffer containing 25 mM NaCl and 1.0 mM of ZnCl2 for 2 h at 37 °C. Samples (20 μl) were diluted 2-fold with nuclease-free water and mixed with aqueous formic acid to 0.1% v/v, final concentration of nucleosides (50 ng/μl), and aliquots injected into a reverse phase UPLC column (Eclipse C18 2.1 × 50 mm, 1.8 um particle size, Agilent) equilibrated with buffer A (0.1% formic acid) and eluted (200 μl/min) with an increasing concentration of buffer B (methanol) with mass spectrometry detection using an Agilent 6460 QQQ triple-quadrupole tandem mass spectrometer (MS/MS) set to multiple reaction monitoring (MRM) in positive electrospray ionization mode. Replicate samples were analyzed using an Agilent Accurate Mass 6230 TOF coupled with an Agilent 1290 Liquid Chromatography system. To measure 6mA, the areas of each LC-MS measurement were determined by extraction of the accurate parent-daughter ion mass transitions of 266.1-150.0 for 6mA and 252.1-136.0 for dA from the total ion current. Quantification of the ratio 6mdA/dA was performed using the calibration curves obtained from nucleoside standards and the linear fits of the determined area ratios over the known amount were used to calculate the nucleoside contents. Quantitation of m6A was performed based on nucleoside-to-base ion transitions (282.1-150.0 for m6A and 268.1-136.0 for A) and a standard curve of pure adenine nucleoside.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.8">
<title>ChIP, MeDIP and RNA library preparation</title>
<p id="p0240">For ChIP, strain-matched wild-type or <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO mouse ES cells (C57BL/6N x 129/Sv background) were fixed in 1% paraformaldehyde for 10 min at 37°C, followed by quenching with 125 mM glycine for 5 min. Cells were lysed and processed using the MAGnify ChIP kit ThermoFisher). Lysates were sonicated using a sonic dismembrator (FisherScientific) at power setting 5 in 10 s pulses followed by 1 min on ice, for a total of 3 min sonication. Nucleoprotein complexes were immunoprecipitated the indicated antisera (2.5 μg) equivalent amounts of isotype-matched control IgG per sample. For MeDIP experiments, genomic DNA was isolated from ES cells using the DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit and sonicated for a total of 3 min as described above for ChIP samples. Samples were processed using the MAGnify ChiP kit according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Library preparations were performed using the KAPA HyperPrep kit (Roche) with 12 cycles of PCR amplification. For RNA-seq, total RNA was extracted from mouse ES cells using the Zymo <italic>Quick-</italic>RNA miniprep kit and rRNA was subtracted using the NEBNext rRNA Depletion kit. Libraries were prepared using the KAPA Stranded mRNA Sequencing kit. Amplified libraries were pooled, purified twice with 0.9X Ampure XP beads (BeckmanCoulter) and analyzed on an Illumina HiSeq2000 or NextSeq500.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.9">
<title>Sequencing data processing</title>
<p id="p0245">For ChIP-seq, MeDIP-seq and RNA-seq, raw reads were trimmed to remove adapters and low-quality reads using Trim Galore (v0.3.5). Bowtie (v1.2.2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gudjonsson et al., 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Langmead et al., 2009</xref>) was used to obtain reads mapped uniquely to the mouse genome (mm10). ChIP and DIP peak candidates were identified with MACS (v2.1.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Zhang et al., 2008</xref>) using input as the control dataset. To remove nonspecific signals, IgG samples were processed similarly and their normalized read density (RPKM) values were subtracted from modification-specific peaks. For MeDIP, the empirical FDR was estimated by exchanging the MeDIP and IgG control samples and identifying peaks in the control sample using the same set of parameters used for the MeDIP sample. Called peaks were annotated with Cistrome CEAS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Shin et al., 2009</xref>). Normalized read density plots centered on annotated elements were generated using NGSPLOT (v2.63) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shen et al., 2014</xref>). Peak overlap statistics were calculated using Bedtools (v2.27.0) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</xref>). For RNA-seq, Cufflinks (v2.2.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Trapnell et al., 2010</xref>) was used to assemble transcripts, estimate their abundances and test for differential transcript expression. All GO analyses used DAVID (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Huang da et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.10">
<title>MT-A70 sequence analysis</title>
<p id="p0250">Sequences were clustered using CLANS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Frickey and Lupas, 2004</xref>) (<italic>P</italic>-value cutoff 0.001) with sequences from PDB and UniProt. For UniProt, a subset of protein IDs (EC:2.1.1.62 (RNA MTases) and EC:2.1.1.72 (DNA MTases)) were downloaded from ExPASy (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0155" xlink:href="https://enzyme.expasy.org/">https://enzyme.expasy.org/</ext-link>). For PDB, sequences were chosen based on keyword search. For Motif identification, human METTL4 sequence was tested against pfam05063: MT-A70 using the NCBI PSSM Viewer.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.5">
<title>Quantification and Statistical Analysis</title>
<p id="p0255">No statistical methods or criteria were used to estimate sample size or to include/exclude samples. Microsoft Excel was used to process data. Statistical details such as N and error calculations are provided in the Legends.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.6" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data and Software Availability</title>
<p id="p0260">The Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) accession number for the ChIP-seq, MeDIP-seq and RNA-seq data reported in this paper is GSE105006.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list id="cebib0010">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bib1">
<element-citation id="sref1" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abeles</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brendler</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Austin</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Evidence of two levels of control of P1 oriR and host oriC replication origins by DNA adenine methylation</article-title>
<source/>J. Bacteriol.
          <volume>175</volume>
<year>1993</year>
<fpage>7801</fpage>
<lpage>7807</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8253669</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<element-citation id="sref2" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aravind</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Iyer</surname>
<given-names>L.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The HARE-HTH and associated domains: novel modules in the coordination of epigenetic DNA and protein modifications</article-title>
<source/>Cell Cycle
          <volume>11</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>119</fpage>
<lpage>131</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22186017</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<element-citation id="sref3" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asada</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goyama</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shikata</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Takeda</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fukushima</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yonezawa</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fujino</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hayashi</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kawabata</surname>
<given-names>K.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mutant ASXL1 cooperates with BAP1 to promote myeloid leukaemogenesis</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>9</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>2733</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30013160</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<element-citation id="sref4" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Au</surname>
<given-names>K.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Welsh</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Modrich</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Initiation of methyl-directed mismatch repair</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>267</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>12142</fpage>
<lpage>12148</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1601880</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<element-citation id="sref5" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Balasubramani</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Larjo</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bassein</surname>
<given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hastie</surname>
<given-names>R.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Togher</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lähdesmäki</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cancer-associated ASXL1 mutations may act as gain-of-function mutations of the ASXL1-BAP1 complex</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>7307</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26095772</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<element-citation id="sref6" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bosselut</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pleiotropic functions of H3K27Me3 demethylases in immune cell differentiation</article-title>
<source/>Trends Immunol.
          <volume>37</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>102</fpage>
<lpage>113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26796037</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<element-citation id="sref7" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boultwood</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Perry</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pellagatti</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fernandez-Mercado</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fernandez-Santamaria</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calasanz</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Larrayoz</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garcia-Delgado</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giagounidis</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Malcovati</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Frequent mutation of the polycomb-associated gene ASXL1 in the myelodysplastic syndromes and in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>
<source/>Leukemia
          <volume>24</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>1062</fpage>
<lpage>1065</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20182461</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<element-citation id="sref8" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bramswig</surname>
<given-names>N.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lüdecke</surname>
<given-names>H.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pettersson</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Albrecht</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bernier</surname>
<given-names>R.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cremer</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eichler</surname>
<given-names>E.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Falkenstein</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gerdts</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansen</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of new TRIP12 variants and detailed clinical evaluation of individuals with non-syndromic intellectual disability with or without autism</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Genet.
          <volume>136</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>192</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27848077</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<element-citation id="sref9" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bryson</surname>
<given-names>A.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherrill-Mix</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>G.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>J.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>T.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bushman</surname>
<given-names>F.D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Covalent modification of bacteriophage T4 DNA inhibits CRISPR-Cas9</article-title>
<source/>MBio
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>e00648</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26081634</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<element-citation id="sref10" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bujnicki</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feder</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radlinska</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blumenthal</surname>
<given-names>R.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure prediction and phylogenetic analysis of a functionally diverse family of proteins homologous to the MT-A70 subunit of the human mRNA:m(6)A methyltransferase</article-title>
<source/>J. Mol. Evol.
          <volume>55</volume>
<year>2002</year>
<fpage>431</fpage>
<lpage>444</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12355263</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<element-citation id="sref11" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cong</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ran</surname>
<given-names>F.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barretto</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Habib</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>P.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marraffini</surname>
<given-names>L.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Multiplex genome engineering using CRISPR/Cas systems</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>339</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>819</fpage>
<lpage>823</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287718</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<element-citation id="sref12" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dey</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seshasayee</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Noubade</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>French</surname>
<given-names>D.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chaurushiya</surname>
<given-names>M.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kirkpatrick</surname>
<given-names>D.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pham</surname>
<given-names>V.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lill</surname>
<given-names>J.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakalarski</surname>
<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Loss of the tumor suppressor BAP1 causes myeloid transformation</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>337</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>1541</fpage>
<lpage>1546</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22878500</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<element-citation id="sref13" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dominissini</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moshitch-Moshkovitz</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salmon-Divon</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ungar</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osenberg</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cesarkas</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jacob-Hirsch</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Amariglio</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kupiec</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Topology of the human and mouse m6A RNA methylomes revealed by m6A-seq</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>485</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>201</fpage>
<lpage>206</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22575960</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<element-citation id="sref14" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frickey</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lupas</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>CLANS: a Java application for visualizing protein families based on pairwise similarity</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <volume>20</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>3702</fpage>
<lpage>3704</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15284097</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib15">
<element-citation id="sref15" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>G.Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hao</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Doré</surname>
<given-names>L.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>N6-methyldeoxyadenosine marks active transcription start sites in Chlamydomonas</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>161</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>879</fpage>
<lpage>892</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25936837</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib16">
<element-citation id="sref16" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bonasio</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strino</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sawai</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parisi</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kluger</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reinberg</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>PCGF homologs, CBX proteins, and RYBP define functionally distinct PRC1 family complexes</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Cell
          <volume>45</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>344</fpage>
<lpage>356</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22325352</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib17">
<element-citation id="sref17" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geula</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moshitch-Moshkovitz</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dominissini</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mansour</surname>
<given-names>A.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kol</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salmon-Divon</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hershkovitz</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peer</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mor</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Manor</surname>
<given-names>Y.S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Stem cells. m6A mRNA methylation facilitates resolution of naïve pluripotency toward differentiation</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>347</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>1002</fpage>
<lpage>1006</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25569111</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib18">
<element-citation id="sref18" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Greer</surname>
<given-names>E.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blanco</surname>
<given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sendinc</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aristizábal-Corrales</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>C.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aravind</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DNA methylation on N6-adenine in C. elegans</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>161</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>868</fpage>
<lpage>878</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25936839</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib19">
<element-citation id="sref19" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gudjonsson</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Altmeyer</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Savic</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Toledo</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dinant</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grøfte</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bartkova</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Poulsen</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oka</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bekker-Jensen</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>TRIP12 and UBR5 suppress spreading of chromatin ubiquitylation at damaged chromosomes</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>150</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>697</fpage>
<lpage>709</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22884692</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib20">
<element-citation id="sref20" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nimer</surname>
<given-names>S.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harbour</surname>
<given-names>J.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>F.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Reduced BAP1 activity prevents ASXL1 truncation-driven myeloid malignancy in vivo</article-title>
<source/>Leukemia
          <volume>32</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>1834</fpage>
<lpage>1837</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29743720</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib21">
<element-citation id="sref21" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hauri</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Comoglio</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seimiya</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gerstung</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Glatter</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aebersold</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paro</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gstaiger</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beisel</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A high-density map for navigating the human polycomb complexome</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>17</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>583</fpage>
<lpage>595</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27705803</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib22">
<element-citation id="sref22" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Y.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>B.Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tet-mediated formation of 5-carboxylcytosine and its excision by TDG in mammalian DNA</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>333</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>1303</fpage>
<lpage>1307</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21817016</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib23">
<element-citation id="sref23" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoischen</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Bon</surname>
<given-names>B.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodríguez-Santiago</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gilissen</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vissers</surname>
<given-names>L.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Vries</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Janssen</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Lier</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hastings</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smithson</surname>
<given-names>S.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>De novo nonsense mutations in ASXL1 cause Bohring-Opitz syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <volume>43</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>729</fpage>
<lpage>731</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21706002</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib24">
<element-citation id="sref24" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huang da</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>B.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Imamichi</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stephens</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lempicki</surname>
<given-names>R.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Extracting biological meaning from large gene lists with DAVID</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Protoc. Bioinformatics
          <volume>13</volume>
<year>2009</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib25">
<element-citation id="sref25" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Iyer</surname>
<given-names>L.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tahiliani</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aravind</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prediction of novel families of enzymes involved in oxidative and other complex modifications of bases in nucleic acids</article-title>
<source/>Cell Cycle
          <volume>8</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>1698</fpage>
<lpage>1710</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19411852</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib26">
<element-citation id="sref26" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Iyer</surname>
<given-names>L.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aravind</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Adenine methylation in eukaryotes: Apprehending the complex evolutionary history and functional potential of an epigenetic modification</article-title>
<source/>BioEssays
          <volume>38</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>40</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26660621</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib27">
<element-citation id="sref27" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kirmizis</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bartley</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuzmichev</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Margueron</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reinberg</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Farnham</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Silencing of human polycomb target genes is associated with methylation of histone H3 Lys 27</article-title>
<source/>Genes Dev.
          <volume>18</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>1592</fpage>
<lpage>1605</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231737</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib28">
<element-citation id="sref28" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kloet</surname>
<given-names>S.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Makowski</surname>
<given-names>M.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baymaz</surname>
<given-names>H.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Voorthuijsen</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karemaker</surname>
<given-names>I.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Santanach</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansen</surname>
<given-names>P.W.T.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Di Croce</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vermeulen</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The dynamic interactome and genomic targets of Polycomb complexes during stem-cell differentiation</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.
          <volume>23</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>682</fpage>
<lpage>690</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27294783</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib29">
<element-citation id="sref29" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Koziol</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bradshaw</surname>
<given-names>C.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>G.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Costa</surname>
<given-names>A.S.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frezza</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gurdon</surname>
<given-names>J.B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of methylated deoxyadenosines in vertebrates reveals diversity in DNA modifications</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.
          <volume>23</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>24</fpage>
<lpage>30</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26689968</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib30">
<element-citation id="sref30" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kusevic</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kudithipudi</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeltsch</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Substrate specificity of the HEMK2 protein glutamine methyltransferase and identification of novel substrates</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>291</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>6124</fpage>
<lpage>6133</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26797129</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib31">
<element-citation id="sref31" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kweon</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aravind</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>S.Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldman</surname>
<given-names>D.E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Erasure of Tet-oxidized 5-methylcytosine by a SRAP nuclease</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>21</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>482</fpage>
<lpage>494</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29020633</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib32">
<element-citation id="sref32" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Langmead</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trapnell</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pop</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salzberg</surname>
<given-names>S.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title>
<source/>Genome Biol.
          <volume>10</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>R25</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib33">
<element-citation id="sref33" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yue</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A METTL3-METTL14 complex mediates mammalian nuclear RNA N6-adenosine methylation</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Chem. Biol.
          <volume>10</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>93</fpage>
<lpage>95</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24316715</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib34">
<element-citation id="sref34" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manna</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>J.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baugé</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cam</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shetty</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vacchio</surname>
<given-names>M.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Castro</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tran</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tessarollo</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bosselut</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Histone H3 Lysine 27 demethylases Jmjd3 and Utx are required for T-cell differentiation</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>8152</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26328764</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib35">
<element-citation id="sref35" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Quinlan</surname>
<given-names>A.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>I.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <volume>26</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>841</fpage>
<lpage>842</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib36">
<element-citation id="sref36" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sahtoe</surname>
<given-names>D.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Dijk</surname>
<given-names>W.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ekkebus</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ovaa</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sixma</surname>
<given-names>T.K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>BAP1/ASXL1 recruitment and activation for H2A deubiquitination</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>7</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>10292</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26739236</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib37">
<element-citation id="sref37" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scheuermann</surname>
<given-names>J.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Ayala Alonso</surname>
<given-names>A.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oktaba</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ly-Hartig</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGinty</surname>
<given-names>R.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fraterman</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilm</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muir</surname>
<given-names>T.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Müller</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Histone H2A deubiquitinase activity of the Polycomb repressive complex PR-DUB</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>465</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>243</fpage>
<lpage>247</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436459</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib38">
<element-citation id="sref38" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schlagman</surname>
<given-names>S.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hattman</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular cloning of a functional dam+ gene coding for phage T4 DNA adenine methylase</article-title>
<source/>Gene
          <volume>22</volume>
<year>1983</year>
<fpage>139</fpage>
<lpage>156</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6307815</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib39">
<element-citation id="sref39" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schübeler</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Function and information content of DNA methylation</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>517</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>321</fpage>
<lpage>326</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25592537</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib40">
<element-citation id="sref40" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schuettengruber</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bourbon</surname>
<given-names>H.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Di Croce</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cavalli</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome regulation by Polycomb and Trithorax: 70 years and counting</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>171</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>34</fpage>
<lpage>57</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28938122</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib41">
<element-citation id="sref41" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shashi</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pena</surname>
<given-names>L.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burton</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hempel</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schoch</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walkiewicz</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McLaughlin</surname>
<given-names>H.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stong</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<collab>Undiagnosed Diseases Network</collab>
</person-group>
<article-title>De novo truncating variants in ASXL2 are associated with a unique and recognizable clinical phenotype</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
          <volume>99</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>991</fpage>
<lpage>999</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27693232</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib42">
<element-citation id="sref42" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yue</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCleary</surname>
<given-names>D.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Edsall</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuan</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wagner</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lobanenkov</surname>
<given-names>V.V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A map of the cis-regulatory sequences in the mouse genome</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>488</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>116</fpage>
<lpage>120</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22763441</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib43">
<element-citation id="sref43" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nestler</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ngs.plot: Quick mining and visualization of next-generation sequencing data by integrating genomic databases</article-title>
<source/>BMC Genomics
          <volume>15</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>284</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24735413</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib44">
<element-citation id="sref44" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Manrai</surname>
<given-names>A.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X.S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>CEAS: cis-regulatory element annotation system</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <volume>25</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>2605</fpage>
<lpage>2606</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19689956</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib45">
<element-citation id="sref45" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>Z.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>M.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mikkelsen</surname>
<given-names>T.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gnirke</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Regev</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meissner</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A unique regulatory phase of DNA methylation in the early mammalian embryo</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>484</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>339</fpage>
<lpage>344</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22456710</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib46">
<element-citation id="sref46" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sowa</surname>
<given-names>M.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>E.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gygi</surname>
<given-names>S.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harper</surname>
<given-names>J.W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Defining the human deubiquitinating enzyme interaction landscape</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>138</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>403</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19615732</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib47">
<element-citation id="sref47" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spruijt</surname>
<given-names>C.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gnerlich</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smits</surname>
<given-names>A.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pfaffeneder</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansen</surname>
<given-names>P.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bauer</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Münzel</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wagner</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Müller</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dynamic readers for 5-(hydroxy)methylcytosine and its oxidized derivatives</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>152</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>1146</fpage>
<lpage>1159</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23434322</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib48">
<element-citation id="sref48" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tahiliani</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koh</surname>
<given-names>K.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pastor</surname>
<given-names>W.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bandukwala</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brudno</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Agarwal</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Iyer</surname>
<given-names>L.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>D.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aravind</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Conversion of 5-methylcytosine to 5-hydroxymethylcytosine in mammalian DNA by MLL partner TET1</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>324</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>930</fpage>
<lpage>935</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19372391</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib49">
<element-citation id="sref49" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trapnell</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>B.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pertea</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mortazavi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kwan</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Baren</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salzberg</surname>
<given-names>S.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wold</surname>
<given-names>B.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pachter</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Biotechnol.
          <volume>28</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>511</fpage>
<lpage>515</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib50">
<element-citation id="sref50" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erdjument-Bromage</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vidal</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tempst</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>R.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Role of histone H2A ubiquitination in Polycomb silencing</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>431</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>873</fpage>
<lpage>878</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15386022</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib51">
<element-citation id="sref51" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weigele</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raleigh</surname>
<given-names>E.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Biosynthesis and function of modified bases in bacteria and their viruses</article-title>
<source/>Chem. Rev.
          <volume>116</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>12655</fpage>
<lpage>12687</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27319741</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib52">
<element-citation id="sref52" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>T.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seetin</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Byrum</surname>
<given-names>S.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mackintosh</surname>
<given-names>S.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DNA methylation on N(6)-adenine in mammalian embryonic stem cells</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>532</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>329</fpage>
<lpage>333</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27027282</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib53">
<element-citation id="sref53" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>C.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>S.Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>N6-methyladenine DNA modification in the human genome</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Cell
          <volume>71</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>306</fpage>
<lpage>318</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017583</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib54">
<element-citation id="sref54" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>T.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gimple</surname>
<given-names>R.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prager</surname>
<given-names>B.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gorkin</surname>
<given-names>D.U.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>N6-methyladenine DNA modification in glioblastoma</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>175</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>1228</fpage>
<lpage>1243</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30392959</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib55">
<element-citation id="sref55" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morgunova</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jolma</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaasinen</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sahu</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Khund-Sayeed</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>P.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kivioja</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dave</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Impact of cytosine methylation on DNA binding specificities of human transcription factors</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>356</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>eaaj2239</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28473536</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib56">
<element-citation id="sref56" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eeckhoute</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>D.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bernstein</surname>
<given-names>B.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nusbaum</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Myers</surname>
<given-names>R.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X.S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Model-based analysis of ChIP-seq (MACS)</article-title>
<source/>Genome Biol.
          <volume>9</volume>
<year>2008</year>
<fpage>R137</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18798982</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib57">
<element-citation id="sref57" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>N6-methyladenine DNA modification in Drosophila</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>161</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>893</fpage>
<lpage>906</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25936838</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib58">
<element-citation id="sref58" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gambin</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Szafranski</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balwi</surname>
<given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alswaid</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Al-Gazali</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shamsi</surname>
<given-names>A.M.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Komara</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Haploinsufficiency of the E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase gene TRIP12 causes intellectual disability with or without autism spectrum disorders, speech delay, and dysmorphic features</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Genet.
          <volume>136</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>377</fpage>
<lpage>386</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28251352</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib59">
<element-citation id="sref59" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Puc</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ohgi</surname>
<given-names>K.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erdjument-Bromage</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tempst</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Glass</surname>
<given-names>C.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A histone H2A deubiquitinase complex coordinating histone acetylation and H1 dissociation in transcriptional regulation</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Cell
          <volume>27</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>609</fpage>
<lpage>621</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17707232</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib60">
<element-citation id="sref60" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beaulaurier</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deikus</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>T.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strahl</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hao</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gregory</surname>
<given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chess</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mapping and characterizing N6-methyladenine in eukaryotic genomes using single-molecule real-time sequencing</article-title>
<source/>Genome Res.
          <volume>28</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>1067</fpage>
<lpage>1078</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29764913</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="app2" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplemental Information</title>
<p id="p0285">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
<caption>
<title>Document S1. Figures S1–S5</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2">
<caption>
<title>Table S1. Genomic Location of 6mA Peaks in Mouse ESCs, Related to Figure 5</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3">
<caption>
<title>Table S2. Genomic Location of Ectopic Asxl1 Peaks in <italic>Mettl4</italic> KO ESCs, Related to Figure 5</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc3.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4">
<caption>
<title>Table S3. DNA Oligonucleotides, Related to STAR Methods</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc4.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5">
<caption>
<title>Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc5.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
<ack id="ack0010">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>This project is supported in part by grant IRG-16-181-57 from the <funding-source id="gs1">American Cancer Society</funding-source>, the Robert E. and May R. Wright Foundation Trust, and the James H. Zumberge Faculty Research and Innovation Fund to D.E.F., and <funding-source id="gs2">European Research Council</funding-source> grant ERC-AdG-2016/742654 to S.K. We thank Drs. Hyungjin Eoh and Jaejin Lee for assistance with mass spectrometry analysis, Tiffany Huang for mouse genotyping, and Dr. Yanhong Shi for helpful discussions.</p>
<sec id="sec5">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p id="p0270">D.E.F. conceived the project. S.-M.K. conducted experiments with cultured cells, performed biochemical assays and mouse genetics analysis, and prepared libraries for next-generation sequencing. E.M. assisted with mouse genotyping. K.K. and S.K. performed the MT-A70 informatics and clustering analysis. S.-M.K., Y.C., S.K., and D.E.F. analyzed the data. S.-M.K. and D.E.F. wrote the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6">
<title>Declaration of Interests</title>
<p id="p0275">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supplementary-material" id="app1">
<p id="p0280">Supplemental Information can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0160" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2019.03.018">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2019.03.018</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>