<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Genet Metab Rep</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Genet Metab Rep</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Molecular Genetics and Metabolism Reports</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2214-4269</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31304092</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6603334</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2214-4269(19)30051-5</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymgmr.2019.100484</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100484</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Paper</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A longitudinal study of neurocognition and behavior in patients with Hurler-Scheie syndrome heterozygous for the L238Q mutation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>Alia</given-names>
</name>
<email>ahmed306@umn.edu</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0005">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cr0005">⁎</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ou</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0010">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rudser</surname>
<given-names>Kyle</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0015">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>Elsa</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0005">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eisengart</surname>
<given-names>Julie B.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0005">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>Kelly</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0005">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Agnes</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0020">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dickson</surname>
<given-names>Patricia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0020">d</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0025">e</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Whitley</surname>
<given-names>Chester B.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0005">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="af0010">b</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Department of Pediatrics<italic>,</italic> University of Minnesota<italic>,</italic> Minneapolis<italic>,</italic> MN 55455, USA</aff>
<aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Gene Therapy Center, Department of Pediatrics, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN 55455, USA</aff>
<aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Division of Biostatistics<italic>,</italic> University of Minnesota<italic>,</italic> Minneapolis<italic>,</italic> MN <italic>55455,</italic> USA</aff>
<aff id="af0020"><label>d</label>Department of Pediatric<italic>s,</italic> Los Angeles Biomedical Research Institute at Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, Torrance, CA, USA</aff>
<aff id="af0025"><label>e</label>Department of Pediatrics, Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis, MO, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cr0005"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: 717 Delaware St. SE, 353-25, Minneapolis, MN 55414, USA. <email>ahmed306@umn.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>27</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>27</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<elocation-id>100484</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>10</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2019 The Authors</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="ab0005">
<sec>
<p>Previous research has demonstrated the mutation, c.712T&gt;A (p.L238Q) of the gene for α-L- iduronidase (IDUA) in patients with Hurler-Scheie syndrome is relatively severe when paired with a nonsense or deletion or splice-site mutation. This mutation was also found to be associated with psychiatric symptoms. This research presents longitudinal data and protein analysis to further investigate the severity and natural history of these unique patients.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Six patients heterozygous for L238Q were compared to six patients with Hurler-Scheie without the L238Q mutations. Somatic burden of disease, IQ, memory, attention, adaptive functioning and behavioral measures were given yearly over 2 to 4 years from 2009 to 2014. The impact of L238Q on the IDUA enzyme was examined using 7 bioinformatics tools and a 3D structural analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>Similar to the cross sectional study, the L238Q patients had more severe abnormalities in IQ, attention, adaptive functioning, and behavioral functioning than the comparison group. There were no major differences between the two groups in change over time; IQ for both groups was stable with some behavioral areas showing improvement. Over time, both groups declined in visual spatial memory and, attention/visual processing. They also showed increased anxiety. Structural and bioinformatics analysis of the L238Q suggest that this mutation causes a significant reduction in the IDUA enzyme's potential catalytic activity, and this mutation may be more severe than other mutations contributing to the Hurler-Scheie syndrome phenotype, presumably causing the psychiatric disease.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>L238Q patients demonstrate severe neurocognitive and neurobehavioral deficits but are relatively stable. Like the comparison group, decreasing visual spatial memory and attention and increasing anxiety suggest more intervention in life skills and emotional social supports are needed.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group id="ks0005">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>Hurler-Scheie syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>α-L-iduronidase</kwd>
<kwd>Mucopolysaccharidosis (MPS)</kwd>
<kwd>L238Q mutation</kwd>
<kwd>Neurocognition</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s0005">
<label>1</label>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="p0005">A missense mutation, L238Q, in patients with Hurler-Scheie syndrome, has been described as having a spectrum of clinical severity. In the literature, this IDUA (α-L- iduronidase) mutation has been mentioned in different levels of severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0005">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0010">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0015">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0020">[4]</xref>]. Previous cross sectional research of six heterozygous patients has documented the mutation, c.712T&gt;A (p.L238Q) of the gene for IDUA in Hurler-Scheie syndrome as relatively severe when paired with a nonsense or other severe mutation, manifested by medical, cognitive complications and also identified the mutation L238Q as uniquely associated with a neuropsychiatric phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0025">5</xref>]. Although heterozygosity of mutations of the GLB gene in Gaucher disease has been associated with Parkinson's disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0030">6</xref>], no other specific mutation of the IDUA gene has been associated with neuropsychiatric symptoms.</p>
<p id="p0010">This study extends prior cross-sectional work by investigating how this same cohort of patients has functioned over time and whether their life adjustment has been affected. These longitudinal findings are compared to a comparison group of non-L238Q patients with Hurler-Scheie. It was of particular interest to find out whether these patients showed decline in functioning over time. The primary hypothesis tested in this analysis is that while medical symptoms were likely to worsen over time as in other patients with Hurler-Scheie syndrome, their neurocognitive and neuropsychiatric status would be stable, but remain within the abnormal range.</p>
<p id="p0015">In addition, to further understand the impact of L238Q on the IDUA enzyme, a 3D structural analysis and a combination of bioinformatics tools were used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0035">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0040">8</xref>] to determine its consequences.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0010">
<label>2</label>
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="p0020">Patients were identified from MPS I participants with Hurler-Scheie syndrome in the age range of 14 to 25 years from an NIH-supported study which is a part of the Lysosomal Disease Network (LDN) (U54-NS065768). The six patients in the L238Q group were compared to 6 age-matched Hurler-Scheie patients without the L238Q mutation as a comparison group. All participants are on enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) and had DNA analysis. Specifics of their mutations can be found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0005">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap id="t0005" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mutation and medical data of L238Q and comparison group.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0060">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th></th><th>Mutation</th><th>Mutation type</th><th>Hydrocephalus</th><th>Shunt placement</th><th>Cord compression</th><th>Psychiatric problem</th><th>Sleep problem</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="8">L238Q group</td></tr><tr><td>1</td><td>L238Q/63delC</td><td>Missense/Deletion</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>L238Q/W402X</td><td>Missense/Nonsense</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>L238Q/W402X</td><td>Missense/Nonsense</td><td>present</td><td>Absent</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>L238Q/W402X</td><td>Missense/Nonsense</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Absent</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>L238Q/W402X</td><td>Missense/Nonsense</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>L238Q/Int3-2a&gt;g</td><td>Missense/Splice Site</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Present</td><td>Present</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8">  </td></tr><tr><td colspan="8">Compari-son group</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>G256R/ W402X</td><td>Missense/Nonsense</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>G265R/A327P</td><td>Missense/Missense</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Q380R/Q70X</td><td>Missense/Nonsense</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>P533R/P533R</td><td>Missense/Missense</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf0005">a</xref></td><td>Absent</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>R89W/W402X</td><td>Missense/Nonsense</td><td>Present</td><td>Absent</td><td>Present</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>W402X/Int11-7c&gt;t</td><td>Nonsense/Splice Site</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td><td>Present</td><td>Absent</td><td>Absent</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0005"><label>a</label><p id="np0005">This patient has a diagnosis of depression after his 3rd visit and was on anti-depressant thereafter.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<sec id="s0015">
<label>2.1</label>
<title>Patients</title>
<p id="p0025">Of the six patients with L238Q mutation, four were paired with a nonsense mutation, one with a deletion, and one with a splice site mutation. For the comparison group, three patients had a missense paired with nonsense, two patients with missense paired with missense, and one patient with nonsense paired with splice site mutation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0020">
<label>2.2</label>
<title>Procedures</title>
<sec id="s0025">
<label>2.2.1</label>
<title>Somatic disease burden</title>
<p id="p0030">To measure the somatic disease burden, the Physical Symptom Score (PSS<italic>)</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0045">9</xref>] was used. It quantifies severity using medical data from history and by interviewing the research participants or their caregivers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0030">
<label>2.2.2</label>
<title>Neurocognitive, adaptive, and psychological status</title>
<p id="p0035">Assessment of neurocognitive functioning, including IQ, memory, attention, adaptive skills and behavioral function, used following measures:<list id="l0005" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0005"><label>●</label><p id="p0040">WASI (Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0050">10</xref>] to obtain the Full Scale IQ (FSIQ),</p></list-item><list-item id="li0010"><label>●</label><p id="p0045">BVMT (Brief Visual Spatial Memory Test) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0055">11</xref>] to measure nonverbal memory,</p></list-item><list-item id="li0015"><label>●</label><p id="p0050">TOVA (Test of Variables of Attention) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0060">12</xref>] to assess attention,</p></list-item><list-item id="li0020"><label>●</label><p id="p0055">VABS-II (Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales, Second Edition) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0065">13</xref>] to assess adaptive functioning</p></list-item><list-item id="li0025"><label>●</label><p id="p0060">BASC-PRS and BASC–SRP (Behavior Assessment System for Children-Parent Rating Scale and Self-Report of Personality) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0070">14</xref>] to assess psychological status.</p></list-item></list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0035">
<label>2.2.3</label>
<title>DNA analysis</title>
<p id="p0065">For DNA analysis molecular diagnosis was performed by Sanger sequencing of all exomes of the IDUA gene at the Gene Therapy and Diagnostics Lab, University of Minnesota. DNA was isolated from leukocyte pellets, PCR amplified, and then sequenced with BigDye® Terminator (Life Technologies). The reactions were sequenated on an ABI 3130 Avant sequencer (Life Technologies) with subsequent analysis on Sequencer software (Gene Codes Corporation).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0040">
<label>2.2.4</label>
<title>In silico analysis of L238Q</title>
<p id="p0070">A total of 7 bioinformatics tools were used as described in a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0035">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0040">8</xref>]. These tools were listed as follows: SIFT (Sorting Intolerant From Tolerant), PolyPhen (Polymorphism Phenotyping), I-Mutant, PROVEAN (Protein Variation Effect Analyzer), PANTHER (Protein Analysis Through Evolutionary Relationships), SNPs&amp;GO (Single Nucleotide Polymorphism Database &amp; Gene Ontology) and PHD-SNP (Predictor of Human Deleterious Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms). SIFT and PROVEAN predict the consequences of a single amino acid substitution by utilizing multiple alignment information. PolyPhen predicts the impact of an amino acid substitution using straightforward physical and comparative considerations. I-Mutant can predict protein stability changes upon single amino acid substitution. PANTHER makes prediction with hidden Markov model (HMM) based statistical modeling methods and multiple sequence alignments (MAS). Both PHD-SNP and SNPs&amp;GO are support vector machine (SVM) classifiers using supervised training to predict functional impacts of amino acid substitutions.</p>
<p id="p0075">The impact of L238Q was predicted by a total of 7 bioinformatics tools using different methodologies. The associated index that indicates the confidence of prediction was given and explained as followed:<list id="l0010" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0030"><p id="p0080">SIFT: tolerated, if the index is &lt;0.05; and damaging, if the index is ≥0.05.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0035"><p id="p0085">PolyPhen: benign, if the index is &lt;0.15; probably damaging, if the index is &gt;0.85; and possibly damaging; &gt;0.15.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0040"><p id="p0090">I-Mutant: neutral, if the index is −0.5 to &lt;0.5; and large decrease, if the index is &lt; −0.5.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0045"><p id="p0095">PROVEAN: neutral, if the index is &gt; −2.5; and deleterious, if the index is &lt; −2.5.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0050"><p id="p0100">PANTHER, SNPs&amp;GO and PHD-SNP are using a probability score (0 to 1).</p></list-item></list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0045">
<label>2.2.5</label>
<title>3D Structural Analysis</title>
<p id="p0105">A 3D structural analysis was performed to reveal the impact of the L238Q on the IDUA enzyme<underline>.</underline></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s0050">
<label>2.3</label>
<title>Ethical considerations</title>
<p id="p0110">All patients and/or their legal guardians provided written informed consent to participate in the study. This study was approved by the University of Minnesota Institutional Review Board: Human Subjects Committee. The protocol was approved by each site's institutional review board or independent research ethics committee. The authors confirm independence from any of the funder of this research; the content of the article has not been influenced by any of the funder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0055">
<label>2.4</label>
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p id="p0115">Descriptive statistics were tabulated separately for L238Q and comparison Hurler-Scheie groups. These included the mean and standard deviation for continuous variables and frequency with percentages for categorical variables. Linear regression based on generalized estimating equations was used to estimate the first-order trend in neurocognition and behavioral scores over time separately for each group and compared to each other. Confidence intervals and <italic>P</italic>-values were based on robust variance estimation to account for the correlated nature of longitudinal measurements. The Holm procedure was used for statement on multiple comparisons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0075">15</xref>]. All analyses were conducted using R v3.2.4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0080">16</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s0060">
<label>3</label>
<title>Results</title>
<p id="p0120">
<list id="l0015" list-type="simple">
<list-item id="li0055">
<label>1.</label>
<p id="p0125">Mutation and medical data are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0005">Table 1</xref>.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p id="p0130"><xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref> summarizes the demographic, PSS, neurocognitive and behavioral/psychological data. Higher physical symptom scores reflect greater disease burden. IQ, BVMT, TOVA, VABS scores are reported as standard scores with a mean of 100 and standard deviation of 15; higher scores reflect better abilities. BASC scores are reported as T scores with a mean of 50 and standard deviation of 10; higher scores reflect increased psychological problems.<table-wrap id="t0010" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Patient descriptive: values are mean (SD) or N (%) where indicated. PSS and below are calculated from within individual average across visits.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0065">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Covariates</th><th>L238Q group<hr/></th><th>Comparison group<hr/></th></tr><tr><th><italic>N</italic> = 6</th><th>N = 6</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Male</td><td>3 (50%)</td><td>5 (83.3%)</td></tr><tr><td>2 Visits</td><td>0 (0.0%)</td><td>1 (16.7%)</td></tr><tr><td>3 Visits</td><td>3 (50.0%)</td><td>2 (33.3%)</td></tr><tr><td>4 Visits</td><td>3 (50.0%)</td><td>3 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td>Age (years)</td><td>17.6 (1.54)</td><td>19.2 (4.72)</td></tr><tr><td>Age at 1st treatment (years)</td><td>10.6</td><td>10.6</td></tr><tr><td>Number of years on treatment</td><td>8.3 (1.3)</td><td>9.9 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td>Physical Symptom Score (PSS)</td><td>11.2 (0.9)</td><td>10.5 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td>Number of surgeries</td><td>6.0 (1.4)</td><td>9.4 (3.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">  </td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Neuropsychological measures: standard scores 100 ± 15</td></tr><tr><td>WASI IQ</td><td>75.0 (5.06)</td><td>99.4 (13.2)</td></tr><tr><td>BVMT</td><td>63.2 (17.4)</td><td>82.5 (15.7)</td></tr><tr><td>TOVA-d prime</td><td>80.1 (11.8)</td><td>98.4 (16.2)</td></tr><tr><td>TOVA-reaction time</td><td>92.3 (20.6)</td><td>104 (16.0)</td></tr><tr><td>TOVA-variability</td><td>77.2 (18.5)</td><td>94.6 (24.8)</td></tr><tr><td>VABS-composite</td><td>69.9 (3.12)</td><td>88.7 (14.0)</td></tr><tr><td>VABS-daily living skills</td><td>68.2 (4.27)</td><td>84.9 (13.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">  </td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">BASC: T scores 50 ± 10</td></tr><tr><td>Parent report (PR); Anxiety</td><td>53.1 (8.3)</td><td>48.5 (7.5)<sup>2</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf0010">a</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Parent report (PR); depression</td><td>57.9 (12.4)</td><td>45.4 (6.6) <sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Parent report (PR); withdrawal</td><td>63.3 (12.3)</td><td>50.2 (11.5) <sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Parent report; atypicality</td><td>57.0 (12.1)</td><td>42.1 (3.0) <sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Self-report (SR); anxiety</td><td>53.5 (10.3)</td><td>49.6 (9.8)</td></tr><tr><td>Self-report (SR); depression</td><td>58.5 (14.3)</td><td>45.8 (7.0)</td></tr><tr><td>Self; atypicality</td><td>68.2 (4.27)</td><td>84.9 (13.7) <sup>1</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0010"><label>a</label><p id="np0010">Superscripts indicate number of cases with missing data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p id="p0135">There were three males in the L238Q group and five males in the comparison group. Age of first assessment was slightly earlier in L238Q group. No difference was found in age at which ERT treatment was started between the two groups, but the comparison group had a longer history of ERT treatment. The PSS average was similar between the two groups, although more surgeries occurred in the comparison group as the two oldest patients were included in that group, reflecting the increase in surgeries with age.<list id="l0020" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0060"><label>2.</label><p id="p0140">Neuropsychological and behavioral results indicated continued lower functioning in the L238Q group relative to the comparison group as seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref>. However, comparing slopes across time between the two groups suggested relative stability in functioning with the exception of a few variables described below. <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref> describes the slopes for the two groups and the comparisons between them.<table-wrap id="t0015" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Marginal slope across individuals per year in age.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0070">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Score</th><th rowspan="2">N</th><th>L238Q Group<hr/></th><th>Comparison Group<hr/></th><th>Slope L238Q vs<hr/></th><th rowspan="2">P-value</th></tr><tr><th>Slope per year (95%CI)</th><th>Slope per year (95% CI)</th><th>Comparison (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>PSS</td><td>12</td><td>0.16 (−0.09, 0.40)</td><td>0.25 (0.04, 0.46)</td><td>−0.09 (−0.42, 0.23)</td><td>0.566</td></tr><tr><td>IQ</td><td>12</td><td>0.45 (−1.15, 2.05)</td><td>1.68 (0.03, 3.33)</td><td>−1.23 (−3.53, 1.07)</td><td>0.295</td></tr><tr><td>BVMT</td><td>12</td><td>−5.32 (−9.03, −1.62)</td><td>−1.08 (−3.15, 0.98)</td><td>−4.24 (−8.48, 0.00)</td><td>0.050</td></tr><tr><td>TOVA: d prime</td><td>12</td><td>−1.47 (−4.45, 1.51)</td><td>0.48 (−0.67, 1.62)</td><td>−1.95 (−5.14, 1.25)</td><td>0.232</td></tr><tr><td>TOVA: reaction time</td><td>12</td><td>−3.99 (−9.70, 1.72)</td><td>−2.43 (−4.12, −0.74)</td><td>−1.56 (−7.52, 4.40)</td><td>0.608</td></tr><tr><td>TOVA: variability</td><td>12</td><td>−4.13 (−7.45, −0.82)</td><td>−2.76 (−4.77, −0.74)</td><td>−1.38 (−5.25, 2.50)</td><td>0.487</td></tr><tr><td>Vineland: composite</td><td>12</td><td>0.00 (−1.28, 1.28)</td><td>−0.34 (−2.92, 2.24)</td><td>0.34 (−2.54, 3.22)</td><td>0.818</td></tr><tr><td>Vineland: DLS</td><td>12</td><td>−0.45 (−2.13, 1.22)</td><td>−1.04 (−3.53, 1.46)</td><td>0.58 (−2.42, 3.59)</td><td>0.704</td></tr><tr><td>BASC PR: anxiety</td><td>10</td><td>1.59 (−0.73, 3.91)</td><td>0.22 (−1.92, 2.36)</td><td>1.37 (−1.79, 4.52)</td><td>0.395</td></tr><tr><td>BASC PR: depression</td><td>10</td><td>−1.77 (−6.16, 2.62)</td><td>−0.69 (−2.33, 0.95)</td><td>−1.08 (−5.77, 3.61)</td><td>0.652</td></tr><tr><td>BASC PR: atypicality</td><td>10</td><td>−4.69 (−7.24, −2.13)</td><td>−0.29 (−0.80, 0.23)</td><td>−4.40 (−7.01, −1.80)</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td>BASC PR: withdrawal</td><td>10</td><td>−3.63 (−5.18, −2.08)</td><td>−1.83 (−4.15, 0.48)</td><td>−1.79 (−4.58, 0.99)</td><td>0.207</td></tr><tr><td>BASC SR: anxiety</td><td>12</td><td>1.11 (−2.37, 4.58)</td><td>1.42 (0.32, 2.53)</td><td>−0.32 (−3.97, 3.33)</td><td>0.864</td></tr><tr><td>BASC SR: depression</td><td>12</td><td>−1.74 (−7.82, 4.33)</td><td>1.11 (0.35, 1.87)</td><td>−2.86 (−8.98, 3.27)</td><td>0.361</td></tr><tr><td>BASC SR: atypicality</td><td>10</td><td>−5.03 (−6.19, −3.87)</td><td>−0.92 (−3.05, 1.21)</td><td>−4.10 (−6.53, −1.68)</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></list-item></list><list id="l0025" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0065"><label>3.</label><p id="p0145">MPS-specific physical symptom score (PSS) increased with age in both groups indicating progressive somatic burden of diseases (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">Fig. 2</xref>). The difference of the marginal slopes between the two groups is not statistically significant (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>).</p></list-item></list><list id="l0030" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0070"><label>4.</label><p id="p0150">FSIQ scores increased 0.45 point in the L238Q group and 1.68 point in the comparison group, on average, per year. The difference of the marginal slopes between the two groups is not statistically significant (0.295) (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>); although the mean FSIQ was below the average range in the L238Q group and in the average range in the comparison group (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0015">Fig. 3</xref>).</p></list-item></list><list id="l0035" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0075"><label>5.</label><p id="p0155">The visual spatial memory score was almost 2 SD below average in the L238Q group and just below average for the comparison group (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0020">Fig. 4</xref>). The difference of the marginal slopes across individuals per year between the two groups was statistically significant (0.05) (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>).</p></list-item></list><list id="l0040" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0080"><label>6.</label><p id="p0160">Average attention scores were within the lower average range in TOVA-d prime (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0025">Fig. 5</xref>) and almost 1 SD below the average range for TOVA- variability in L238Q group (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0030">Fig. 6</xref>). For the comparison group all these scores in TOVA were within the average range (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref>). The differences of the marginal slopes between the two groups were not statistically significant (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>).</p></list-item></list><list id="l0045" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0085"><label>7.</label><p id="p0165">Adaptive functioning scores did not change over time but the range was almost 1.5 SD below average in the L238Q group and average in the comparison group (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0010">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0035">Fig. 7</xref>). While both groups declined in adaptive skills over time, the marginal slopes between the two groups was not statistically significant (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>).</p></list-item></list><list id="l0050" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0090"><label>8.</label><p id="p0170">On the behavioral measures, average scores on PR-anxiety increased in severity (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0040">Fig. 8</xref>) but scores on PR-depression (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0045">Fig. 9</xref>), PR-withdrawal, and PR-atypicality (e.g. stares blankly, says things that do not make sense, seems unware of those around him/her) were improved by parent-report (PR) over time. The differences of the marginal slopes of PR-anxiety, PR-depression, PR-withdrawal between the two groups were not statistically significant (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>). The difference of the marginal slopes between the two groups for PR-atypicality was statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) with both groups improving. The statistical significance of each of the parent and self-report on atypicality BASC domain is retained after accounting for multiple comparisons.</p></list-item></list><list id="l0055" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0095"><label>9.</label><p id="p0175">Average scores on SR-depression worsened in the L238Q group and were still below average (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0055">Fig. 11</xref>). Scores on SR-anxiety worsened for both groups, but especially the L238Q group (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0050">Fig. 10</xref>). SR-atypicality scores were improved by self-report (SR) over time for both groups. The difference of the marginal slopes between the two groups for SR-atypicality is statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) with more improvement in the comparison group (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item id="li0100"><label>10.</label><p id="p0180">All tools predicted L238Q to be damaging or pathogenic with the associated index shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0020">Table 4</xref>.<table-wrap id="t0020" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Prediction of L238Q by multiple bioinformatics tools.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0075">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th></th><th>SIFT</th><th>PolyPhen</th><th>I-MUTANT</th><th>PROVEN</th><th>PANTHAR</th><th>SNPs&amp;GO</th><th>PHD-SNP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Prediction</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Probably damaging</td><td>Large decrease</td><td>Deleterious</td><td>Disease</td><td>Disease</td><td>Disease</td></tr><tr><td>Associated Index</td><td>0.002</td><td>1</td><td>−2.05</td><td>−5.33</td><td>0.553</td><td>0.513</td><td>0.777</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></list-item></list></p>
<p id="p0185">L238Q leads to conversion of leucine into glutamine at position 238. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Fig. 1</xref>, the wildtype residue leucine is smaller and buried in the core of the protein; thereby the mutant residue glutamine probably will not fit. Further, this mutation will cause loss of hydrophobic interactions in the core of the protein. In addition, L238 is located in the TIM barrel domain that is important for catalytic activity and in contact with residues in another domain. The interaction between these domains could be disturbed by the mutation, which may affect the function of IDUA enzyme.<list id="l0060" list-type="simple"><list-item id="li0105"><label>11.</label><p id="p0190">The 3D structure of native IDUA protein was retrieved from the RCSB database (PDB ID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="ir0005" xlink:href="pdb:3w81">3w81</ext-link>). The mutant model of L238Q was built through the online server of SWISS-MODEL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="ir0010" xlink:href="https://swissmodel.expasy.org/interactive">https://swissmodel.expasy.org/interactive</ext-link>) using the native structure as the template. The Swiss-PDB Viewer, a free molecular graphics program was used for viewing the modeled structures. In addition, Project Have Our Protein Explained (HOPE; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="ir0015" xlink:href="http://www.cmbi.ru.nl/hope/home">http://www.cmbi.ru.nl/hope/home</ext-link>) was used to analyze the structural impact of L238Q on the whole IDUA protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0055">Fig. 11</xref>).</p></list-item></list><fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Close-up view of superimposed structure of native and mutant residues of L238Q. The main protein core is shown in white color while the wild type and mutated residues are shown in red and green color, respectively. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>PSS of L238Q vs comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>IQ of L238Q vs comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>BVMT of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>TOVA d prime of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0025">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>TOVA-Variability of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0030">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0035"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Vineland Composite of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0035">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0040"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Parent Anxiety of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0040">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0045"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Parent Depression of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0045">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0050"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Self-report of Anxiety of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0050">Fig. 10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10"></graphic></fig><fig id="f0055"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Self-Report Depression of L238Q vs Comparison.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0055">Fig. 11</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr11"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0065">
<label>4</label>
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="p0195">No biochemical or clinical guidelines have been established that reliably distinguish among the three clinical descriptions; severe Hurler syndrome, attenuated Scheie syndrome, or the intermediate Hurler-Scheie syndrome in mucopolysaccharidosis type I (MPS I). Hurler-Scheie and Scheie syndrome, are a spectrum of disorders without clearly defined diagnostic criterion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0085">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0090">18</xref>]. Genotype-phenotype associations for missense mutations are not clearly defined. Missense mutations have widely variable presentations in individuals ranging from mild to severe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0095">19</xref>]. Missense mutations can prevent any functional enzyme activity or can allow for some functional enzyme to be produced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0095">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0100">20</xref>].</p>
<p id="p0200">The missense mutation, L238Q, is associated with significant cognitive impairment and psychological impacts. L238Q mutation, when paired with nonsense, deletion or splice site mutation is more severe than most other patients with Hurler-Scheie syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0025">5</xref>]. Therefore, we examined the structure of the mutation as well as used bioinformatics tools to examine the severity of the mutation. The structural analysis suggests the L238Q mutation may have disturbing influences on the function of the IDUA enzyme. Further analysis using bioinformatics tools suggests that all tools used (SIFT, PolyPhen, I-Mutant, PROVEAN, PANTHER, SNPs&amp;GO and PHD-SNP) predicted the damaging effect of L238Q to the functional enzyme [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0035">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0040">8</xref>].</p>
<p id="p0205">This study is the first to track the longitudinal neurocognitive and neurobehavioral functioning of patients with L238Q mutations paired with a severe mutation. Given previous cross sectional findings that these patients have more impairment in cognition, memory, attention, and adaptive behavior than patients with Hurler-Scheie with other mutation types, it was crucial to clarify whether the pairing of L238Q mutations with a severe mutation could be associated with any worsening across time. We followed these patients over a 2 to 4 year period of time and the same differences were found in level of impairment between the two groups as the cross sectional study. IQ scores stayed the same in the L238Q group but slightly improved in the comparison group although not statistically significant. Stability in IQ is consistent with previous cross-sectional findings in patients with Hurler-Scheie [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0105">21</xref>].</p>
<p id="p0210">There were a few cognitive areas that did suggest some worsening, even in the face of stable IQ scores. Visual spatial memory worsened in both groups, with a marked statistically significant decrease in the L238Q group. Similarly, measures of processing speed (reaction time and variability) slightly worsened in both groups, but did not differ between groups. The d′ prime score (a measure of accuracy of response), while not statistically significant, showed a slightly worsening pattern in the L238Q patients with a slightly improving pattern in the comparison group. Poor and worsening performance on these tasks may be associated with white matter abnormalities in these patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0110">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0115">23</xref>]. Neurocognitive outcomes are functional marker that can be used to identify the disease severity in Hurler syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0120">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0125">25</xref>] and are now being used as endpoints for clinical trials of new treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0130">26</xref>].</p>
<p id="p0215">Adaptive functioning, while showing impairment in the L238Q group and normal range function in the comparison group appeared to show a slight decline over time, especially in the comparison group. The two groups were not different in their slopes. However, the finding of increasing somatic involvement as measured by the PSS over time is very likely contributing to decreasing ability to carry out activities of daily living resulting in decreased scores on the measure of adaptive functioning. Also physical disability can lead to psychological impacts and eventually decrease motivation to perform in school or daily living skills.</p>
<p id="p0220">From the medical history, three patients had shunted hydrocephalus in the L238Q group compared with one patient with hydrocephalus without shunt placement in the comparison group. Four patients had cord compressions in the L238Q group compared with two in the comparison group. All of the L238Q patients had at least one episode of depression, psychosis, or autism and they all were on psychotropic medications and all had sleep problems. None of the comparison subjects had such episodes except one, who had a diagnosis of depression after his 3rd visit and started anti-depressant medication. On ratings of behavior and psychological status, parents reported improvement in the L238Q patients in depression, level of withdrawal and atypical behaviors, but an increase in anxiety. Atypical behaviors improved significantly in the L238Q group. Parents of the comparison group reported stability in these behaviors, all within the normal range, with a slight improvement in the withdrawal score.</p>
<p id="p0225">Self-report is somewhat different with increasing anxiety and decreasing atypical behaviors in both groups, perhaps reflecting the improving awareness of the patients over time. The presence of atypical behaviors was statistically significantly improved in the L238Q group compared to the comparison group (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t0015">Table 3</xref>). A difference is seen in the self-report of depression with the L238Q group reporting slight improvement and the comparison group slight worsening (not statistically different). It should be noted that the scores on these measures of behavior are very variable, contributing to the lack of statistical significance. However, that variability may reflect the actual fluctuation in behavioral or psychological status in these children who may suffer rejection and other stresses, in addition to direct disease effects. It is possible that the increased incidence of spinal cord compression and hydrocephalus may have had an impact on the behavioral status of these patients. Previous research has found hydrocephalus also common in MPS II and MPS VI but they do not present with significant neurocognitive or psychiatric manifestations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb0135">27</xref>].</p>
<p id="p0230">With regard to limitations of this study, two of the patients in the comparison group did not have equivalent mutations (had two missense mutations). However, their data does not indicate that these two patients had different PSS, cognitive, or behavioral scores than those with other types of mutations. Finding comparable mutations is challenging in such a rare disease. Another limitation is the lack of knowledge about the polymorphism variants in IDUA gene which may have played a role in their genotype-phenotype correlation. It is mentionable that four patients from the L238Q group and two patients from the control group were eligible for and participated in a Food and Drug Administration Investigational New Drug (IND) approved clinical trial of intrathecal (IT) enzyme replacement therapy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0070">
<label>5</label>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="p0235">It can be concluded that Hurler-Scheie patients heterozygous for the L238Q mutation together with a severe mutation appear to have a greater significant central nervous system impact compared to the comparison group. The L238Q mutation is associated with a significant impact on FSIQ, memory, attention, adaptive functioning, and behavioral/psychological measurements with below average functioning. IQ appears stable but visual spatial memory and attention/processing abilities appear to decline relative to normal values in both the L238Q and in the comparison group. Somatic symptoms and adaptive functioning worsen in both groups. Depression, withdrawal, and atypicality improve, but anxiety is worsen as these patients grow older. Because the L238Q patients seem to be more severely impacted neurocognitively and vulnerable to neuropsychiatric abnormalities than other Hurler-Scheie syndrome patients, they will need even more attention to life skills, educational interventions, emotional/social supports, and efforts at improving the quality of life. Methods of early treatment need to be considered that will impact the brain in MPS I patients heterozygous for the L238Q mutation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s0075">
<title>Funding sources</title>
<p id="p0240">The <funding-source id="gts0005">Lysosomal Disease Network (LDN)</funding-source>U54-NS065768 is a part of the <funding-source id="gts0010">National Institute of Health (NIH) Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network</funding-source>, supported through collaboration between the <funding-source id="gts0015">NIH Office of Rare Diseases Research at the National Center for Advancing Translational Science</funding-source>, the <funding-source id="gts0020">National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</funding-source>, and <funding-source id="gts0025">National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</funding-source>. Dr. Li Ou is a fellow of the Lysosomal Disease Network. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH. This project was supported in part (Dr. Rudser) by the <funding-source id="gts0030">National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</funding-source>, (NCATS) <funding-source id="gts0035">National Institutes of Health</funding-source>, through <funding-source id="gts0040">University of Minnesota CTSI</funding-source> Grant Number NCATS UL1TR000114. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH or CTSI.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list id="bi0005">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bb0005">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation id="rf0005" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yogalingam</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>X.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muller</surname>
<given-names>V.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>D.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clements</surname>
<given-names>P.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kakkis</surname>
<given-names>E.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hopwood</surname>
<given-names>J.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification and molecular characterization of α-L-iduronidase mutations present in mucopolysaccharidosis type I patients undergoing enzyme replacement therapy</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Mutat.
          <volume>24</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>199</fpage>
<lpage>207</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15300847</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0010">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation id="rf0010" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chandar</surname>
<given-names>S.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mahalingam</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mucopolysaccharidosis type I: homology Modeling and docking analysis of the lysosomal enzyme, human α-L-iduronidase</article-title>
<source/>Afr. J. Pharm. Pharmacol
          <volume>6</volume>
<issue>27</issue>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>2027</fpage>
<lpage>2038</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0015">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation id="rf0015" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saito</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ohno</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maita</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sakuraba</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural and clinical implications of amino acid substitutions in α-L-iduronidase: insight into the basis of mucopolysaccharidosis type I</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Genet. Metab.
          <volume>111</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<year>2014 Feb</year>
<fpage>107</fpage>
<lpage>112</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24480078</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0020">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation id="rf0020" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bie</surname>
<given-names>Haiying</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>Jiang</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Xu</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kermode</surname>
<given-names>Allison R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goddard-Borger</surname>
<given-names>Ethan D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Withers</surname>
<given-names>Stephen G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>James</surname>
<given-names>Michael N.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Insights into mucopolysaccharidosis I from the structure and action of α-L-iduronidase</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Chem. Biol.
          <volume>9</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<year>2013 November</year>
<fpage>739</fpage>
<lpage>745</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24036510</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0025">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation id="rf0025" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>Alia</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitley</surname>
<given-names>Chester B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooksley</surname>
<given-names>Renee</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rudser</surname>
<given-names>Kyle</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cagle</surname>
<given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ali</surname>
<given-names>Nadia</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Delaney</surname>
<given-names>Kathleen</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yund</surname>
<given-names>Brianna</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>Elsa</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neurocognitive and neuropsychiatric phenotypes associated with the mutation L238Q of the α-L-iduronidase gene in Hurler-Scheie syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Genet. Metab.
          <volume>111</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<year>2014 Feb</year>
<fpage>123</fpage>
<lpage>127</lpage>
<comment>(PMCID: PMC3939822)</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24368159</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0030">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation id="rf0030" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sidransky</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nalls</surname>
<given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aasly</surname>
<given-names>J.O.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Multicenter analysis of glucocerebrosidase mutations in Parkinson's disease</article-title>
<source/>N. Engl. J. Med.
          <volume>361</volume>
<issue>17</issue>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>1651</fpage>
<lpage>1661</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19846850</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0035">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation id="rf0035" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ou</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Przybilla</surname>
<given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitley</surname>
<given-names>Chester B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Phenotype prediction for mucopolysaccharidosis type I by in silico analysis</article-title>
<source/>Orphanet J. Rare Dis.
          <volume>12</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">125</object-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0040">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation id="rf0040" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ou</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Przybilla</surname>
<given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitley</surname>
<given-names>Chester B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SAAMP 2.0: an algorithm to predict genotype-phenotype correlation of lysosomal storage diseases</article-title>
<source/>Clin. Genet.
          <volume>93</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<year>2018 May</year>
<fpage>1008</fpage>
<lpage>1014</lpage>
<comment>Clin Genet.</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29396849</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0045">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation id="rf0045" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rudser</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kunin-Batson</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Delaney</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitley</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mucopolysaccharidosis (MPS) physical symptom score: development, reliability, and validity</article-title>
<source/>J. Inherit. Metab. Dis. Rep.
          <volume>26</volume>
<year>Aug 2015</year>
<fpage>63</fpage>
<lpage>68</lpage>
<comment>(PMID: 26303610)</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0050">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation id="rf0050" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H.Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dinmore</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hildebrand</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ledbetter</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McDonald</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pike</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wolley</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence Manual</chapter-title>
<year>1999</year>
<publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0055">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation id="rf0055" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smerbeck</surname>
<given-names>A.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parrish</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>E.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoogs</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krupp</surname>
<given-names>L.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weinstock-Guttman</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benedict</surname>
<given-names>R.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Regression-based pediatric norms for the brief visuospatial memory test revised and the symbol digit modalities test</article-title>
<source/>Clin. Neuropsychol.
          <volume>25</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>402</fpage>
<lpage>412</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21391150</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0060">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation id="rf0060" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Greenberg</surname>
<given-names>L.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kindschi</surname>
<given-names>C.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dupuy</surname>
<given-names>T.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hughes</surname>
<given-names>S.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Test of Variables of Attention Continuous Performance Test</chapter-title>
<year>2007</year>
<publisher-name>The TOVA Company</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Los Alamitos, CA</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0065">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation id="rf0065" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sparrow</surname>
<given-names>S.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cicchetti</surname>
<given-names>D.V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balla</surname>
<given-names>D.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales</chapter-title>
<edition>2nd ed.</edition>
<year>2005</year>
<publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0070">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation id="rf0070" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>C.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kamphaus</surname>
<given-names>R.W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Behavior Assessment System for Children</chapter-title>
<edition>2nd ed.</edition>
<year>2004</year>
<publisher-name>American Guidance Service</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Circle Pines, MN</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0075">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation id="rf0075" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holm</surname>
<given-names>Sture</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure</article-title>
<source/>Scand. J. Statist.
          <volume>6</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<year>1979</year>
<fpage>65</fpage>
<lpage>70</lpage>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="ir0020" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/4615733">http://www.jstor.org/stable/4615733</ext-link>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0080">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation id="rf0080" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>R Core Team</surname>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>R: a Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</chapter-title>
<year>2014</year>
<publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="ir0025" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0085">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation id="rf0085" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vijay</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wraith</surname>
<given-names>J.E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Clinical presentation and follow-up of patients with the attenuated- phenotype of mucopolysaccharidosis type I</article-title>
<source/>Acta Paediatr.
          <volume>94</volume>
<year>2005</year>
<fpage>872</fpage>
<lpage>877</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16188808</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0090">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation id="rf0090" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Muenzer</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wraith</surname>
<given-names>J.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clarke</surname>
<given-names>L.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The international consensus panel on the management and treatment of mucopolysaccharidosis I</article-title>
<source/>Mucopolysaccharidosis I
          <volume>123</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>19</fpage>
<lpage>29</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0095">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation id="rf0095" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Terlato</surname>
<given-names>N.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>G.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Can mucopolysaccharidosis type I disease severity be predicted based on a patient's genotype? A comprehensive review of the literature</article-title>
<source/>Genet. Med.
          <volume>5</volume>
<year>2003</year>
<fpage>286</fpage>
<lpage>294</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12865757</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0100">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation id="rf0100" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beesley</surname>
<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meaney</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenland</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vellodi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>E.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winchester</surname>
<given-names>B.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mutational analysis of 85 mucopolysaccharidosis type I families: frequency of known mutations, identification of 17 novel mutations and in vitro expression of missense mutations</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Genet.
          <volume>109</volume>
<year>2001</year>
<fpage>503</fpage>
<lpage>511</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11735025</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0105">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation id="rf0105" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neurocognition across the spectrum of mucopolysaccharidosis type I: age, severity, and treatment</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Gen. Metab
          <volume>116</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>61</fpage>
<lpage>68</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0110">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation id="rf0110" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guler</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rudser</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Delaney</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bjoraker</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitley</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tolar</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Orchard</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Provenzale</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>An exploratory study of brain function and structure in Mucopolysaccharidosis Type I: long term observations following hematopoietic cell transplantation (HCT)</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Genet. Metab.
          <volume>107</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>116</fpage>
<lpage>121</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22867884</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0115">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation id="rf0115" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kraus</surname>
<given-names>M.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Susmaras</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caughlin</surname>
<given-names>B.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>C.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Little</surname>
<given-names>D.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>White matter integrity and cognition in chronic traumatic brain injury: a diffusion tensor imaging study</article-title>
<source/>Brain.
          <volume>130</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<year>2007 Sep 14</year>
<fpage>2508</fpage>
<lpage>2519</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17872928</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0120">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation id="rf0120" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balthazor</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Metabolic and neurodegenerative disorders</chapter-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ris</surname>
<given-names>K. Yeates</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>H.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source/>Pediatric Neuropsychology: Research, Theory and Practice
          <year>1999</year>
<publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
<fpage>171</fpage>
<lpage>205</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0125">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation id="rf0125" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>E.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lockman</surname>
<given-names>L.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balthazor</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krivit</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neuropsychological outcomes of several storage diseases with and without bone marrow transplantation</article-title>
<source/>J. Inherit. Metab. Dis.
          <volume>18</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>413</fpage>
<lpage>429</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7494400</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0130">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation id="rf0130" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Van der Lee</surname>
<given-names>J.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cognitive endpoints for therapy development for neuronopathic mucopolysaccharidoses: results of a consensus procedure</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Gen. Metab.
          <volume>121</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<year>2017 Jun</year>
<fpage>70</fpage>
<lpage>79</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bb0135">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation id="rf0135" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vedolin</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>I.V.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Komlos</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schuch</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Azevedo</surname>
<given-names>A.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vieira</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maeda</surname>
<given-names>F.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marques da Silva</surname>
<given-names>A.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giugliani</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Brain MRI in mucopolysaccharidosis, effect of aging and correlation with biochemical findings</article-title>
<source/>Neurology
          <volume>69</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<year>Aug 2007</year>
<fpage>917</fpage>
<lpage>924</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17724296</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<ack id="ac0005">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We are grateful to all of the families at the participating sites, as well as the principal investigator, Dr. Paul Harmatz at Children's Hospital and Research Center, Oakland, California. We are thankful to Kathleen Delaney and Brianna Yund for their assistance with this research. We thank Brenda Diethelm-Okita, David Erickson, and Evelyn Redtree in the Lysosomal Disease Network office at the University of Minnesota for administrative assistance, and Renee Cooksley for assistance with genotyping. We are very thankful for the support provided by the National MPS Society, Ryan Foundation for Orphan Disease Research and Center for Neurobehavioral Development (CNBD).</p>
</ack>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>