<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0370521</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">478</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am Psychol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am Psychol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The American psychologist</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0003-066X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1935-990X</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30945897</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6612428</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/amp0000436</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1013092</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Impacting Development in Infants with Tuberous Sclerosis Complex: Multidisciplinary Research Collaboration</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>Marian E.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A1">University of Southern California</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>Deborah A.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A2">University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Capal</surname>
<given-names>Jamie K.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A3">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Byars</surname>
<given-names>Anna W.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A4">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>Donna S.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A5">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Speaks</surname>
<given-names>Autism</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A6">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kissinger</surname>
<given-names>Robin</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A7">Children’s Hospital Los Angeles</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Kelley</surname>
<given-names>Sarah E.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A8">The University of Alabama at Birmingham</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hanson</surname>
<given-names>Ellen</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A9">Boston Children’s Hospital</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bing</surname>
<given-names>Nicole M.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A10">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kent</surname>
<given-names>Bridget</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A11">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Joyce Y.</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A12">University of California, Los Angeles</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Northrup</surname>
<given-names>Hope</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A13">University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bebin</surname>
<given-names>E. Martina</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A14">The University of Alabama at Birmingham</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sahin</surname>
<given-names>Mustafa</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A15">Boston Children’s Hospital</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krueger</surname>
<given-names>Darcy</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="A16">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<collab>TACERN Study Group</collab>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Author Note</p>
<p id="P2">Marian E. Williams, Department of Pediatrics, University of Southern California; Deborah A. Pearson, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston; Jamie K. Capal and Anna W. Byars, Department of Neurology, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center; Donna S. Murray, Autism Speaks and Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center; Robin Kissinger, USC University Center for Excellence in Developmental Disabilities, Children’s Hospital Los Angeles; Sarah E. O’Kelley, Department of Psychology, The University of Alabama at Birmingham; Ellen Hanson, Department of Psychiatry, Boston Children’s Hospital; Nicole M. Bing and Bridget Kent, Division of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center; Joyce Y. Wu, Division of Pediatric Neurology, University of California at Los Angeles Mattel Children’s Hospital; Hope Northrup, Department of Pediatrics, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston; E. Martina Bebin, Department of Neurology, The University of Alabama at Birmingham; Mustafa Sahin, Department of Neurology, Boston Children’s Hospital; Darcy Krueger, Department of Neurology and Rehabilitation Medicine, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center; TACERN Study Group (in addition to named authors above: Simon K. Warfield, Department of Radiology, Boston Children’s Hospital; Jurriaan M. Peters, Department of Neurology, Boston Children’s Hospital; Monisha Goyal, Department of Neurology, The University of Alabama at Birmingham; Rajna Filip-Dhima and Kira Dies, Department of Neurology, Boston Children’s Hospital; Stephanie Bruns, Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center; Benoit Scherrer, Department of Radiology, Boston Children’s Hospital; Gary Cutter, University of Alabama at Birmingham; Steven L. Roberds, Tuberous Sclerosis Alliance, Silver Spring, Maryland; Laura Mamounas, National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, National Institutes of Health).</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1">Correspondence concerning this article should be addressed to Marian E. Williams, USC University Center for Excellence in Developmental Disabilities, Children’s Hospital Los Angeles, 4650 Sunset Blvd., MS53, Los Angeles, CA, 90027. <email>mwilliams@chla.usc.edu</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>9</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>74</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>356</fpage>
<lpage>367</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1037/amp0000436-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P3">The Tuberous Sclerosis Complex Autism Center of Excellence Network (TACERN) is a six-site collaborative conducting longitudinal research on infants with tuberous sclerosis complex (TSC), focused on identifying early biomarkers for autism spectrum disorder (ASD). A multidisciplinary research team, which includes the specialties of psychology, neurology, pediatrics, medical genetics, and speech-language pathology, is working together to conduct studies on neurological status, brain structure and function, neurodevelopmental phenotype, and behavioral challenges in this population. This manuscript provides insights into the roles of the multidisciplinary multisite team and lessons learned from the collaboration, in terms of research as well as training of future researchers and clinicians. In addition, the authors detail the major findings to date, including those related to the identification and measurement of early symptoms of ASD, relationship between seizures and early development, and early biomarkers for epilepsy and developmental delay in infants and young children with TSC.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>infant</kwd>
<kwd>tuberous sclerosis complex</kwd>
<kwd>neurodevelopment</kwd>
<kwd>autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
<kwd>multidisciplinary research</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>