<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9431859</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">20937</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Prog Retin Eye Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Prog Retin Eye Res</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Progress in retinal and eye research</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1350-9462</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-1635</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31242454</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6739176</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.preteyeres.2019.06.003</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1533378</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Cholinergic Nervous System and Glaucoma: From Basic Science to Clinical Applications</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Faiq</surname>
<given-names>Muneeb A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wollstein</surname>
<given-names>Gadi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schuman</surname>
<given-names>Joel S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>Kevin C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology, New York University (NYU) School of Medicine, NYU Langone Health, New York, New York, United States</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Radiology, New York University (NYU) School of Medicine, NYU Langone Health, New York, New York, United States</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Center for Neural Science, Faculty of Arts and Science, New York University, New York, New York, United States.</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Author Statement</p>
<p id="P2">Percentage of work contributed by each author in the production of the manuscript:</p>
<p id="P3">Muneeb A. Faiq: 50%</p>
<p id="P4">Gadi Wollstein: 10%</p>
<p id="P5">Joel S. Schuman: 10%</p>
<p id="P6">Kevin C. Chan: 30%</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Kevin C. Chan, Ph.D., 222 E 41<sup>st</sup> Street, Room 460, Departments of Ophthalmology and Radiology, NYU School of Medicine, NYU Langone Health, New York University, New York, NY, USA 10017, Tel: (212) 263-7602, Fax: (212) 263-8749, <email>chuenwing.chan@fulbrightmail.org</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p id="P50"><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> The author(s) have made the following disclosure(s): J.S.S.: Royalties e Zeiss, Dublin, CA (for intellectual property licensed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary)</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>2</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>23</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>100767</fpage>
<lpage>100767</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.preteyeres.2019.06.003-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P7">The cholinergic system has a crucial role to play in visual function. Although cholinergic drugs have been a focus of attention as glaucoma medications for reducing eye pressure, little is known about the potential modality for neuronal survival and/or enhancement in visual impairments. Citicoline, a naturally occurring compound and FDA approved dietary supplement, is a nootropic agent that is recently demonstrated to be effective in ameliorating ischemic stroke, traumatic brain injury, Parkinson’s disease, Alzheimer’s disease, cerebrovascular diseases, memory disorders and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder in both humans and animal models. The mechanisms of its action appear to be multifarious including (i) preservation of cardiolipin, sphingomyelin, arachidonic acid content of phosphatidylcholine and phosphatidylethanolamine, (ii) restoration of phosphatidylcholine, (iii) stimulation of glutathione synthesis, (iv) lowering glutamate concentrations and preventing glutamate excitotoxicity, (v) rescuing mitochondrial function thereby preventing oxidative damage and onset of neuronal apoptosis, (vi) synthesis of myelin leading to improvement in neuronal membrane integrity, (vii) improving acetylcholine synthesis and thereby reducing the effects of mental stress and (viii) preventing endothelial dysfunction. Such effects have vouched for citicoline as a neuroprotective, neurorestorative and neuroregenerative agent. Retinal ganglion cells are neurons with long myelinated axons which provide a strong rationale for citicoline use in visual pathway disorders. Since glaucoma is a form of neurodegeneration involving retinal ganglion cells, citicoline may help ameliorate glaucomatous damages in multiple facets. Additionally, trans-synaptic degeneration has been identified in humans and experimental models of glaucoma suggesting the cholinergic system as a new brain target for glaucoma management and therapy.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Acetylcholine</kwd>
<kwd>Citicoline</kwd>
<kwd>Glaucoma</kwd>
<kwd>Neurodegeneration</kwd>
<kwd>Neuroprotection</kwd>
<kwd>Retinal ganglion cell</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>