<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="article-commentary" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Exp Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EXN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spexn</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Experimental Neuroscience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1179-0695</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31666796</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6798160</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1179069519880515</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1179069519880515</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-manuscript">EXN-19-0049</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Commentary</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Neurological Disease Modelling for Spinocerebellar Ataxia Using
Zebrafish</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2207-6028</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Namikawa</surname>
<given-names>Kazuhiko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1179069519880515"></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dorigo</surname>
<given-names>Alessandro</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6593-8196</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Köster</surname>
<given-names>Reinhard W</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1179069519880515">Cellular and Molecular Neurobiology, Zoological
Institute, Technische Universität Braunschweig, Braunschweig, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1179069519880515">Kazuhiko Namikawa, Cellular and Molecular
Neurobiology, Zoological Institute, Technische Universität Braunschweig,
Spielmannstr. 7, 38106 Braunschweig, Germany. Email:
<email>k.namikawa@tu-bs.de</email></corresp>
<corresp id="corresp2-1179069519880515">Reinhard W Köster, Cellular and Molecular
Neurobiology, Zoological Institute, Technische Universität Braunschweig,
Spielmannstr. 7, 38106 Braunschweig, Germany. Email:
<email>r.koester@tu-bs.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>17</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<elocation-id>1179069519880515</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>12</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>13</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="d35e113" issue="20" page="3948" related-article-type="commentary-article" vol="39" xlink:href="10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1862-18.2019"></related-article>
<abstract>
<p>The cerebellum integrates sensory information and motor actions. Increasing
experimental evidence has revealed that these functions as well as the
cerebellar cytoarchitecture are highly conserved in zebrafish compared with
mammals. However, the potential of zebrafish for modelling human cerebellar
diseases remains to be addressed. Spinocerebellar ataxias (SCAs) represent a
group of genetically inherited cerebellar diseases leading to motor
discoordination that is most often caused by affected cerebellar Purkinje cells
(PCs). Towards modelling SCAs in zebrafish we identified a small-sized
PC-specific regulatory element that was used to develop coexpression vectors
with tunable expression strength. These vectors allow for in vivo imaging of
SCA-affected PCs by high-resolution fluorescence imaging. Next, zebrafish with
SCA type 13 (SCA13) transgene expression were established, revealing that
SCA13-induced cell-autonomous PC degeneration results in eye movement deficits.
Thus, SCA13 zebrafish mimic the neuropathology of an SCA-affected brain as well
as the involved loss of motor control and hence provide a powerful approach to
unravel SCA13-induced cell biological pathogenic and cytotoxic mechanisms.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Zebrafish</kwd>
<kwd>disease modelling</kwd>
<kwd>Purkinje neurons</kwd>
<kwd>spinocerebellar degeneration</kwd>
<kwd>neurodegeneration</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>January-December 2019</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><bold>Comment on:</bold> Namikawa K, Dorigo A, Zagrebelsky M, et al. Modelling
neurodegenerative spinocerebellar ataxia type 13 in zebrafish using a Purkinje neuron
specific tunable coexpression system [published online ahead of print March 12, 2019].
<italic>J Neurosci</italic>. 2019 May 15;39(20):3948-3969. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1862-18.2019">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1862-18.2019</ext-link>. PubMed PMID: 30862666; PubMed Central
PMCID: PMC6520513. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30862666">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30862666</ext-link>.</p>
<sec id="section1-1179069519880515">
<title>Zebrafish Cerebellum as a Genetic Model for Spinocerebellar ataxia</title>
<p>The cerebellum is an essential brain compartment that controls motor coordination and
learning among other functions to allow us to move smoothly and skilfully. In
addition, mounting evidence involves the cerebellum in higher functions such as
cognition and processing of emotions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1179069519880515">1</xref></sup> The cerebellum is found in all jawed vertebrates, gnathostomes,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1179069519880515">2</xref></sup> and is highly conserved in its cytoarchitecture, connectivity, and function
as well as the underlying cellular and genetic mechanisms of differentiation and
homeostasis. In zebrafish, the cerebellum develops, differentiates, and reaches
functional maturity during embryonic and larval stages during which zebrafish are
almost transparent, making them a powerful in vivo system for bioimaging. Moreover,
as zebrafish are genetically tractable, they allow for combining molecular genetic
studies with in vivo imaging of cell biological and physiological processes making
use of the numerous available fluorescent proteins and biosensors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1179069519880515">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1179069519880515">4</xref></sup> As zebrafish are becoming an
increasingly popular model in the biomedical field, the stage is set to expand
cerebellar research in zebrafish to causal investigations of human cerebellar
diseases. Spinocerebellar ataxias (SCAs) represent a group of inherited
neurodegenerative diseases of the cerebellum that commonly lead to motor
discoordination with difficulties in walking smoothly termed ataxic gait. The SCAs
belong to a genetically heterologous group caused by more than 40 known distinct
genes used for their classification.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1179069519880515">5</xref></sup> The SCAs are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner, which prompted us to
establish a transgenic zebrafish model affected by a gain of toxicity of a
pathogenic SCA allele. As cell type, we chose Purkinje cells (PCs) as these are most
commonly affected by SCAs and represent the central neuronal population and sole
output of the cerebellum. The PCs integrate external sensory stimuli and motor
actions, which are processed into output signals relayed onto efferent neurons
usually of the motor system, explaining the difficulties in motor control upon PC
degeneration.</p>
<p>PCs in zebrafish develop fast and emerge already at 56 hours postfertilization (hpf)
with increasing cells numbers until 7 days postfertilization (dpf).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1179069519880515">6</xref></sup> By this stage, PC production reaches a plateau with a population size of
about 420 PCs,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1179069519880515">6</xref></sup> which is far less than the over 200 000 PCs estimated to populate the mouse
cerebellum. At 7 dpf, the cerebellar circuitry in zebrafish is established and PCs
like in mammals receive synaptic input from parallel fibres – the granule cell axons
– and climbing fibres – axonal connections from the inferior olive. The PC axons
form collaterals to other PCs and project either directly out of the cerebellum to
terminate on neurons of the octaval nuclei corresponding to vestibular neurons, or
they connect to nearby eurydendroid cells, which represent the equivalents to deep
cerebellar nuclei neurons in mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1179069519880515">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1179069519880515">7</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1179069519880515">Figure 1</xref>). Also, the electrophysiological
properties of PCs similar to their mammalian counterparts are established at 7 dpf,
allowing them to control visual stimuli driven eye or swimming movements like the
optokinetic response (OKR) or the optomotor reflex (OMR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1179069519880515">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1179069519880515">4</xref></sup> and being involved in motor
learning. Optogenetic silencing of PCs consequently impairs OKR and OMR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1179069519880515">3</xref></sup> reminiscent of loss of motor control in SCA patients. These findings support
the view that zebrafish PCs are well suited to model cerebellar neurodegenerative
diseases, as they will allow for continuously monitoring and thus for
interconnecting pathogenic molecular processes with anatomical, physiological, and
eventual behavioural deficits that mimic clinical signs of SCAs.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1179069519880515" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Schematics of cerebellar neurons and their circuitry in zebrafish (left) and
mouse (right). BC indicates basket cell; EC, eurydendroid cell; GC, granule
cell; GCL, granule cell layer; GoC, Golgi cell; ION, inferior olive nuclei;
MF, mossy fibre; ML, molecular layer; ON, octaval nuclei; PC, Purkinje cell;
PCL, Purkinje cell layer; SC, stellate cells; VN, vestibular nuclei.</p>
<p>Excitatory inputs from parallel fibres of granule cells and climbing fibres
from inferior olive neurons are received by dendrites of PCs in the
molecular layer. Parallel fibres also project to GABAergic inhibitory
interneurons such as Golgi cells in the granule cell layer, and stellate and
basket cells in the molecular layer, although the presence of basket cells
in the zebrafish cerebellum remains unclear. Zebrafish PC axons send
inhibitory input as collaterals to neighbouring PCs and project to
eurydendroid cells located in the PC layer, or neurons in the octaval nuclei
in the hindbrain. These correspond to excitatory neurons in the deep
cerebellar nuclei of the mammalian cerebellum, or those in the vestibular
nuclei in the brainstem. In addition, zebrafish eurydendroid cells send
efferent axons to various brain areas outside the cerebellum similar to
their deep nuclei counterparts in mammals. GABAergic interneurons such as
stellate cells provide inhibitory input to the dendrites of PCs, whereas
Golgi cells form inhibitory synapses on granule cell dendrites. The
cerebellar glomerulus is the synaptic structure consisting of granule cell
dendrites and Golgi cell axon terminals together with mossy fibre terminals,
which is also observed in zebrafish. Additional interneurons such as Lugaro
cells and unipolar brush cells exist in mammals, but have not been described
in zebrafish so far.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069519880515-fig1"></graphic>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1179069519880515">
<title>Establishment of a PC-Specific Coexpression System in Zebrafish</title>
<p>For this approach, a prerequisite is the possibility to genetically target PCs in a
cell-type-specific manner. We therefore first invested into characterizing a
regulatory element upstream of zebrafish carbonic anhydrase VIII
(<italic>ca8</italic>), which is predominantly expressed in differentiating and
mature PCs in zebrafish.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1179069519880515">6</xref></sup> By transient and stable transgenesis, we first revealed that a 7.54-kb region
upstream of the <italic>ca8</italic> transcriptional start site was able to drive
enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) expression in zebrafish PCs besides
expression in a few other tissues such as in the notochord. Subsequently, we
narrowed it down to a PC exclusive regulatory element of a size of 258 bp, which we
named <italic>ca8</italic>-derived Purkinje-cell-specific enhancer element (cpce)
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">Figure 2A</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">C</xref>). Intriguingly, this
regulatory element from zebrafish also mediates PC-specific expression in
organotypic slice cultures of the mouse cerebellum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">Figure 2D</xref>), suggesting that regulatory
mechanisms of PC-specific expression are conserved among teleosts and mammals. The
small size of the cpce further allowed for tandem orientation of several copies of
this element, resulting in PC-specific bidirectional expression vectors of different
expression strengths when 2, 4, or 8 copies of the cpce were used. The SCA-causing
pathogenic alleles can therefore be coexpressed with fluorescent protein reporters
at varying concentrations to allow for investigating dose-dependent effects and
monitoring disease progression by in vivo time-lapse imaging. Copy numbers of 4 and
more cpce elements resulted in increasing ectopic transgene expression in tectal and
retinal cells, which could be restricted to PCs again by an miRNA-mediated gene
silencing strategy. miRNA181a is predominantly expressed in tectal and retinal
cells. Incorporating the miRNA181a target site into the 3′UTR of both transgenes
eliminated successfully their expression outside of the cerebellum, while
maintaining it at high levels in PCs. This strategy can be easily adopted for other
regulatory elements with unwanted expression profiles. Finally, we established a
series of PC-specific expression vectors containing 1, 2, and 4 cpce elements,
respectively, in bidirectional orientation with different multiple cloning sites and
miRNA181a target sites inserted into the corresponding 3′UTR sequences followed by
polyA sequences where necessary (4× cpce) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">Figure 2E</xref>). This vector set will enable fast,
dose-dependent, and comparable PC-specific disease modelling in zebrafish accessible
for disease monitoring by fluorescent in vivo imaging for SCAs, but also for other
diseases affecting PCs such as various types of dystonia, ataxia telangiectasia,
Niemann-Pick disease, and autism among others, when making use of PC-specific
expression of recombinases, transcriptional activators, and repressors for
example.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1179069519880515" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Zebrafish disease modelling of SCA13 using a Purkinje-cell-specific
coexpression system. CCe indicates corpus cerebelli; Val, lateral division
of the valvula cerebelli; EGFP, enhanced green fluorescent protein; PC,
Purkinje cell.</p>
<p>(A) Schematic map of <italic>ca8</italic>-derived Purkinje-cell-specific
enhancer (cpce) and drawing of construct carrying the cpce: E1b promoter,
driving EGFP reporter expression. (B) EGFP expression is restricted to
cerebellar PCs (green) in 4 dpf stable transgenic larval fish
<italic>Tg(cpce-E1b:GFP)</italic><sup><italic>bz13</italic></sup> carrying the reporter transgene shown in (A). (C) Sagittal section of
an adult brain from <italic>Tg(cpce-E1b:GFP)</italic><sup><italic>bz13</italic></sup> fish showing immunostaining of EGFP (green) in PCs counterstained by
DAPI (blue). (D) PC expressing EGFP (green) after transfection with the
cpce-EGFP reporter plasmid in mouse cerebellar slice culture. PCs were
immunostained with anti-Calbindin antibody (blue). (E) Maps of PC-specific
coexpression vector inserts; expression is driven by 1, 2, or 4× cpce. The
vector containing 4× cpce carries insertions of 4 × miRNA181a target sites
(4 × mir181aT) immediately upstream to both polyA sequences to eliminate
ectopic expressions outside of cerebellum. Two multiple cloning sites (MCS1
and MSC2) can be used for the insertion of different genes of interest. (F)
Schematic drawing of the zebrafish <italic>Kcnc3a</italic> subunit reveals
the S1-S6 transmembrane segments homologous to those in mammals. Positively
charged arginine residues (indicated as +) located in the S4 segment,
essential for voltage sensing, are also conserved in zebrafish
<italic>Kcnc3a</italic>. The third arginine in the S4 segment is
substituted by histidine (R335H), which mimics <italic>SCA13</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> in human patients. A variable C-terminal region generated by
alternative splicing is indicated in blue. (G) Schematic drawing of a
PC-specific transgene to express <italic>Kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>wt</italic></sup>, or <italic>Kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup> together with nuclear localized H2B-EGFP and membrane targeted
Fyn-TagRFP-T reporter genes linked to a self-cleaving T2A-peptide. (H) Each
image show PCs expressing <italic>Kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>wt</italic></sup>, or <italic>Kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup> (upper, or lower rows, respectively), monitored at 4, 7, 11 dpf
zebrafish. Cerebellar PCs expressing <italic>Kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>wt</italic></sup> exhibit highly arborized dendrites in a 7-dpf old larva (I), whereas
those expressing <italic>Kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup> show degenerative changes with fragmented red labelled puncta from
dendritic or axonal structures (J).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069519880515-fig2"></graphic>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1179069519880515">
<title>Neurodegenerative Disease Modelling for Spinocerebellar Ataxia Type 13 (SCA13) in
Zebrafish</title>
<p>Using these vectors, we set out to establish a genetic model of SCA13 in zebrafish.
This neurological disease is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner leading to
cerebellar atrophy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1179069519880515">8</xref></sup> SCA13 is caused by mutations in the <italic>KCNC3</italic> allele encoding
the voltage-gated potassium channel KCNC3/Kv3.3. Its rodent homologue is expressed
in neurons with high-frequency firing rate with prominent expression in cerebellar PCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1179069519880515">9</xref></sup> It is therefore likely that cerebellar atrophy in SCA13 patients is caused by
degenerating PCs as primarily affected neuronal cell type, yet there is currently no
in vivo model of SCA13 established, which shows clear signs of neuronal degeneration
followed by loss of motor control. Hence, causal analysis of SCA13 is hampered. We
initiated SCA13 modelling in zebrafish by analysing the spatiotemporal expression of
the zebrafish <italic>KCNC3</italic> homologues <italic>kcnc3a</italic> and
<italic>kcnc3b</italic>. Although <italic>kcnc3a</italic> was strongly expressed
in larval PCs, <italic>kcnc3b</italic> expression was barely detected in this cell
type. Human, rodent, and zebrafish <italic>kcnc3</italic> alleles generate a number
of splice isoforms terminating in different C-terminal domains of the potassium
channel. Splice-isoform-specific mRNA in situ hybridization as well as
fluorescence-assisted cell sorting (FACS)-mediated single PC reverse transcription
polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) revealed that <italic>kcnc3a-X12</italic> is
expressed at highest abundance in zebrafish PCs. This splice isoform contains the
shortest C-terminus of all <italic>kcnc3a</italic> splice isoforms. We therefore
generated a <italic>kcnc3a-X12</italic> R335H zebrafish mutant allele (named
hereafter <italic>kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">Figure 2F</xref>)
mimicking a mid-age onset <italic>SCA13</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> variant causing progressive cerebellar atrophy in humans.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1179069519880515">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>By introducing either zebrafish wild type <italic>kcnc3a
(kcnc3a<sup>WT</sup>)</italic> or <italic>kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup> into PC-specific expression vectors coexpressing two fluorescent reporters,
membrane-targeted TagRFP-T and nuclear-localized EGFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">Figure 2G</xref>), transgenic zebrafish were
generated by microinjection into one-cell stage embryos. This allowed for monitoring
transgene expressing PCs in the differentiating cerebellum using in vivo confocal
microscopy. <italic>kcnc3a<sup>WT</sup></italic>-expressing PCs differentiated
indistinguishably from wild-type PCs, increased in number, and developed an
elaborated dendritic tree at 7 dpf. In contrast, <italic>kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup>-expressing PCs displayed progressively increasing signs of axonal and
dendritic fragmentation and diminished in cell numbers indicative of progressive
neuronal degeneration, which was confirmed by PC counts making use of nuclear
fluorescent protein expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">Figure 2H</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1179069519880515">J</xref>).
Moreover, when analysed for PC-mediated behaviour, larvae with PC-specific
<italic>kcnc3a<sup>WT</sup></italic> expression displayed a normal
performance of the OKR, a reflexive eye movement driven by visual stimuli.
Consistent with progressive PC degeneration larvae with <italic>kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup> expressing PCs instead were impaired in proper OKR performance, which is
reminiscent of oculomotor disturbance, a clinical hallmark of SCA patients. Taken
together, our results strongly suggest that <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> in analogy to its zebrafish homologue <italic>kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup> induces PC degeneration in a cell-autonomous manner, which appears to be the
main cause for the atrophy of the cerebellum leading to ataxic behaviour observed in
patients carrying this mutated pathogenic allele.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1179069519880515">
<title>Molecular Mechanism Underlying SCA13 Pathogenic Mutants induced PC
Degeneration</title>
<p>Although the main neuropathological features such as cerebellar atrophy and
uncoordinated motor behaviour are shared among SCA13 patients, the clinical symptoms
of SCA13 are somewhat heterogeneous as well as the age of disease onset and the
course of disease progression. This is explained by allelic heterogeneity as
currently more than 10 <italic>KCNC3</italic>-mutated alleles have been reported so
far, ranging from different missense mutations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1179069519880515">8</xref></sup> to a C-terminal deletion in the encoded potassium channel. This suggests that
the cause of SCA13 is also somewhat heterogeneous influencing the strength of
cytotoxic signals and mechanisms in PCs. Electrophysiological studies support this
hypothesis, as they indicate that different SCA13 alleles could affect the
excitability of neurons to a different extent linked to the disease phenotype.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1179069519880515">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>For example, the adult onset <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> mutant allele encodes a non-functional channel subunit mimicked by its
zebrafish counterpart <italic>kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1179069519880515">11</xref></sup> The heterotetrameric wild-type/R420H mutant channels do not result in
altering the kinetic behaviour as Kv3.3 channels. This mutant subunit as well as
another SCA13 variant <italic>R423H</italic>, however, mediate a dominant negative
effect likely by being trapped along the secretory pathway and mostly in the Golgi
together with wild-type subunits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1179069519880515">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1179069519880515">13</xref></sup> (see later), thereby
decreasing the K<sup><italic>+</italic></sup> current amplitude of the channel.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1179069519880515">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1179069519880515">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1179069519880515">14</xref></sup> Activation of voltage-gated
potassium channels belonging to the family of KCNC/Kv3 (Kv3.1-Kv3.4) depends on
unusually positively shifted membrane depolarization to around –20 mV resulting in
large K<sup><italic>+</italic></sup> currents with fast deactivation kinetics allowing neurons to repolarize
quickly to sustain high-frequency firing of action potentials.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1179069519880515">9</xref></sup> Thus, reduced K<sup><italic>+</italic></sup> currents as a consequence of a dominant negative effect of
<italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> or <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> are expected to result in decreased neuronal excitability. Indeed
fast-spiking zebrafish motoneurons expressing <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> displayed reduced amplitudes of outward currents and suppressed the
excitability of fast-spiking primary motoneurons, thereby decreasing startle
behaviour of zebrafish larvae.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1179069519880515">15</xref></sup> These altered electrophysiological properties lead to subtle changes in
distal axon branches of primary zebrafish motoneurons, when zebrafish
<italic>kcnc3a</italic><sup><italic>R335H</italic></sup> is expressed, but did not result in prominent motoneurons degeneration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1179069519880515">16</xref></sup> This is in contrast to the observed PC degeneration in our established
zebrafish SCA13 model targeting PCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1179069519880515">6</xref></sup> Therefore, cytotoxic effects of mutated <italic>kcnc3</italic> alleles are
neuronal-cell-type specific.</p>
<p>The <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> mutant allele also behaves as a dominant negative subunit, but different to
<italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup>. It affects gating properties of the channels with slower activation and
deactivation, when expressed as wild-type/mutant tetramers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1179069519880515">14</xref></sup> This may explain the more severe consequences of <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup>-associated SCA13 symptoms occurring already during infant stages.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1179069519880515">14</xref></sup> Expression of the respective homologous allele (mouse <italic>kcnc3</italic><sup><italic>R424H</italic></sup>) to <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> from mice in primary mouse PC cultures showed reduced outward current
densities and broadened action potentials similar to those observed in zebrafish
motoneurons affected by <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1179069519880515">17</xref></sup> Moreover, expression of this mouse homologous mutant allele to human
<italic>R423H</italic> in cultured PCs induced increased intracellular Ca<sup><italic>2+</italic></sup>-levels, likely triggering dendrite shrinkage, and eventually cell death,
because these effects could be partially rescued by the treatment with inhibitors of
P/Q-type voltage-gated calcium channels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1179069519880515">17</xref></sup> Together, these findings suggest that PCs unlike motoneurons are vulnerable
to the expression of dominant negative isoforms of <italic>KCNC3</italic>, and
decreased excitability caused by loss of function of <italic>KCNC3</italic> is
likely implicated in PC degeneration. Yet surprisingly, while <italic>kcnc3</italic><sup><italic>–/–</italic></sup> mutant mice show slight gait abnormalities not visible by eye, and PCs in
these mutant mice do not show signs of degeneration and cerebellar atrophy, mutant
PCs clearly display a reduced excitability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1179069519880515">18</xref></sup> resembling a dominant negative <italic>KCNC3</italic> isoform expressing
neurons. This argues for alternative cell biological mechanisms mediating
cytotoxicity in SCA13-affected PCs either acting alone or together with the altered
electrophysiological properties.</p>
<p>Further insight was provided by recent cell biological and biochemical studies
showing that <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> and <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> are aberrantly glycosylated. In addition, these channel subunits are
inefficiently transported to the plasma membrane and are retained to a large extent
in the Golgi apparatus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1179069519880515">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1179069519880515">13</xref></sup> At least in cells expressing <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup>, the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) – in addition to
<italic>KCNC3</italic> wild-type subunits – is misrouted. Because overexpression
of EGFR in <italic>Drosophila</italic> eyes could rescue <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> induced eye malformation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1179069519880515">13</xref></sup> retention of crucial signalling molecules in the secretory pathway could
represent an additional cell biological mechanism of cytotoxicity in SCA13-affected
neurons. It would be of interest if <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> affects intracellular membrane transport of EGFR as well, to reveal if this
is an allele-specific or common cell biological defect in SCA13-affected cells. The
PC-specific coexpression system established by us will allow for testing the
involvement of such mis-trafficked molecules in PC degeneration. It will further
allow for discriminating whether mis-trafficking alone or in conjunction with
altered neuronal excitability leads to progressive cytotoxicity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1179069519880515">Figure 3</xref>). In addition, recent
evidence involved another SCA13 allele <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>G592R</italic></sup> in the regulation of actin dynamics in axonal growth cones.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1179069519880515">19</xref></sup> As this research was performed on cultured cells, in vivo confirmation could
be obtained easily in zebrafish, followed by comparison to implications of
<italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> and <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> on actin regulation.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1179069519880515" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Schematic representation of SCA13-induced PC degeneration.
<italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R420H</italic></sup> and <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> variants show dominant negative effects on WT <italic>KCNC3</italic>
by being retained in the Golgi apparatus together with WT channel subunits,
thereby reducing PC excitability. A possible PC death-associated effector
activated by reduced PC excitability could be exerted via increased
intracellular Ca<sup><italic>2+</italic></sup> levels likely caused by broadening action potentials excessively
activating P/Q-type voltage-gated Ca<sup><italic>2+</italic></sup> channels (VGCC).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1179069519880515">17</xref></sup> In addition, the Golgi-retained <italic>KCNC3</italic><sup><italic>R423H</italic></sup> mutant was shown to impair EGFR trafficking,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1179069519880515">13</xref></sup> inducing loss of EGF trophic support, which may be needed for PC
survival. EGFR indicates epidermal growth factor receptors; PC, Purkinje
cell.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069519880515-fig3"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Clearly, the molecular mechanisms causing the SCA13 disease are far from being
understood, but distinct research avenues have been opened that await unravelling.
Our genetic tools and models for deciphering cell biological and physiological
causes of PC degeneration in a cell-autonomous manner directly in vivo making use of
coexpression of fluorescent reporters and biosensors will eventually enable
clarification of the pathogenic mechanisms underlying PC degeneration in SCA13.
Moreover, modelling SCA13 in zebrafish with the possibility to monitor behaviour
from single cells to the entire animal offers powerful approaches for in vivo
screening and validation of compounds towards counteracting pathogenic molecular and
physiological disease mechanisms. Thus, this little fish could make a big
splash.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p><bold>Funding:</bold>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This work was
supported in part by funding from Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft Grants
(KO1949/4-1 and 1949/7-1) to R.W.K.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> KN and RWK wrote this commentary. KN and AD prepared figures. All authors edited
the manuscript.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><bold>ORCID iDs:</bold> Kazuhiko Namikawa <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069519880515-img1.jpg"></inline-graphic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2207-6028">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2207-6028</ext-link></p>
<p>Reinhard W Köster <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1179069519880515-img1.jpg"></inline-graphic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6593-8196">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6593-8196</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1179069519880515">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cerebellar circuitry as a neuronal machine</article-title>.
<source/>Prog Neurobiol.
<year>2006</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>-<lpage>303</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2006.02.006.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16759785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1179069519880515">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pose-Mendez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Candal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Moldes</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genoarchitecture of the rostral hindbrain of a shark: basis for
understanding the emergence of the cerebellum at the agnathan-gnathostome
transition</article-title>. <source/>Brain Struct Funct.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>221</volume>:<fpage>1321</fpage>-<lpage>1335</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-014-0973-8.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25552316</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1179069519880515">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Namikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Babaryka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Köster</surname><given-names>RW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Functional regionalization of the teleost cerebellum analyzed in
vivo</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>11846</fpage>-<lpage>11851</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1403105111.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25002482</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1179069519880515">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knogler</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Portugues</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Motor context dominates output from Purkinje cell functional
regions during reflexive visuomotor behaviours</article-title>.
<source/>eLife.
<year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42138.</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1179069519880515">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klockgether</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariotti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulson</surname><given-names>HL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Spinocerebellar ataxia</article-title>. <source/>Nat Rev Dis
Primers. <year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-01910.1038/s41572-019-0074-3.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30975995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1179069519880515">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Namikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagrebelsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Modeling neurodegenerative
spinocerebellar ataxia type 13 in zebrafish using a Purkinje neuron specific
tunable coexpression system</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci.
<year>2019</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>3948</fpage>-<lpage>3969</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1862-18.2019.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30862666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1179069519880515">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Development and evolution of cerebellar neural
circuits</article-title>. <source/>Dev Growth Differ.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>389</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-169X.2012.01348.x.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22524607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1179069519880515">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaczmarek</surname><given-names>LK.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Kv3.3 potassium channels and spinocerebellar
ataxia</article-title>. <source/>J Physiol.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>594</volume>:<fpage>4677</fpage>-<lpage>4684</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP271343.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26442672</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1179069519880515">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaczmarek</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Kv3 channels: enablers of rapid firing, neurotransmitter release,
and neuronal endurance</article-title>. <source/>Physiol Rev.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1431</fpage>-<lpage>1468</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00002.2017.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28904001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1179069519880515">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Minassian</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevanin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Mutations in voltage-gated
potassium channel KCNC3 cause degenerative and developmental central nervous
system phenotypes</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet.
<year>2006</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>447</fpage>-<lpage>451</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1758.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16501573</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1179069519880515">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Papazian</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Functional effects of spinocerebellar ataxia type 13 mutations
are conserved in zebrafish Kv3.3 channels</article-title>. <source/>BMC
Neurosci. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2202-11-99.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20712895</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1179069519880515">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallego-Iradi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bickford</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Khare</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>KCNC3(R420H), a K(+) channel
mutation causative in spinocerebellar ataxia 13 displays aberrant
intracellular trafficking</article-title>. <source/>Neurobiol Dis.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2014.08.020.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25152487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1179069519880515">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khare</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nick</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A KCNC3 mutation causes a
neurodevelopmental, non-progressive SCA13 subtype associated with dominant
negative effects and aberrant EGFR trafficking</article-title>. <source/>PLoS
ONE. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:e0173565. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0173565.</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1179069519880515">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minassian</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Papazian</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Altered Kv3.3 channel gating in early-onset spinocerebellar
ataxia type 13</article-title>. <source/>J Physiol.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>590</volume>:<fpage>1599</fpage>-<lpage>1614</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.228205.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22289912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1179069519880515">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzochi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Papazian</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Spinocerebellar ataxia type 13 mutant potassium channel alters
neuronal excitability and causes locomotor deficits in
zebrafish</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>6831</fpage>-<lpage>6841</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.6572-10.2011.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21543613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1179069519880515">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagasti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Papazian</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Spinocerebellar ataxia type 13 mutation that is associated with
disease onset in infancy disrupts axonal pathfinding during neuronal
development</article-title>. <source/>Dis Model Mech.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>921</fpage>-<lpage>929</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.010157.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22736459</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1179069519880515">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Kv3.3 channels harbouring a mutation of spinocerebellar ataxia
type 13 alter excitability and induce cell death in cultured cerebellar
Purkinje cells</article-title>. <source/>J Physiol.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>592</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>247</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2013.264309.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24218544</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1179069519880515">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurlock</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Joho</surname><given-names>RH.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Purkinje-cell-restricted restoration of Kv3.3 function restores
complex spikes and rescues motor coordination in KCNC3
mutants</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>4640</fpage>-<lpage>4648</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5486-07.2008.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18448641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1179069519880515">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Kv3.3 channels bind hax-1
and Arp2/3 to assemble a stable local actin network that regulates channel
gating</article-title>. <source/>Cell.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>165</volume>:<fpage>434</fpage>-<lpage>448</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.02.009.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26997484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>