<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0367050</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6438</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharmacol Biochem Behav</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharmacol. Biochem. Behav.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Pharmacology, biochemistry, and behavior</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0091-3057</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-5177</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31103523</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6855401</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbb.2019.05.005</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1036341</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Neuroinflammation as a Risk Factor for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dunn</surname>
<given-names>Geoffrey A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nigg</surname>
<given-names>Joel T.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>Elinor L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>a</label>University of Oregon</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Oregon Health and Science University</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Oregon National Primate Research Center</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><underline>Corresponding Author:</underline> Elinor L. Sullivan, 505 NW 185th Ave., L584, Beaverton, OR 97006, <email>sullivel@ohsu.edu</email>, (503) 346-5516</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>7</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>16</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>182</volume>
<fpage>22</fpage>
<lpage>34</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.pbb.2019.05.005-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is a prevalent, persistent, and impairing pediatric-onset neurodevelopmental condition. Its high prevalence, and the enduring controversy over its widespread treatment, drive strong scientific and community interest in its etiology and mechanisms. The etiology is complex with multiple genetic and environmental factors contributing to risk. Emerging evidence for a role for neuroinflammation in ADHD pathophysiology is of great interest. While still limited, this evidence includes 1) the above-chance comorbidity of ADHD with inflammatory and autoimmune disorders, 2) initial studies indicating an association with ADHD and increased serum cytokines, 3) preliminary evidence from genetic studies demonstrating associations between polymorphisms in genes associated with inflammatory pathways and ADHD, 4) emerging evidence that early life exposure to a number of environmental risk factors may increase risk for ADHD via an inflammatory mechanism, and 5) mechanistic evidence from animal models of maternal immune activation documenting behavioral and neural outcomes consistent with ADHD. Prenatal exposure to inflammation is associated with changes in offspring brain development including reductions in cortical gray matter volume and the volume of certain cortical areas –parallel to observations associated with ADHD. Alterations in neurotransmitter systems, including the dopaminergic, serotonergic and glutamatergic systems, are observed in ADHD populations. Animal models provide strong evidence that the development and function of these neurotransmitters systems are sensitive to exposure to in utero inflammation. In summary, accumulating evidence from human studies and animal models, while still incomplete, support a potential role for neuroinflammation in the pathophysiology of ADHD. Confirmation of this association and the underlying mechanisms have become valuable targets for research. If confirmed, such a picture may be important in opening new intervention routes.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>neurodevelopmental</kwd>
<kwd>maternal immune activation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>