<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">iScience</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">iScience</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>iScience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2589-0042</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31733517</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6864320</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2589-0042(19)30445-6</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2019.10.064</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Single-Cell RNA-seq Reveals Profound Alterations in Mechanosensitive Dorsal Root Ganglion Neurons with Vitamin E Deficiency</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
<name>
<surname>Finno</surname>
<given-names>Carrie J.</given-names>
</name>
<email>cjfinno@ucdavis.edu</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">∗</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
<name>
<surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>Janel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
<name>
<surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>Mincheol</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>Seojin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
<name>
<surname>Bordbari</surname>
<given-names>Matthew H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
<name>
<surname>Durbin-Johnson</surname>
<given-names>Blythe</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
<name>
<surname>Settles</surname>
<given-names>Matthew</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
<name>
<surname>Perez-Flores</surname>
<given-names>Maria C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Jeong H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10">
<name>
<surname>Yamoah</surname>
<given-names>Ebenezer N.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Population Health and Reproduction, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of California, Davis, CA 95616, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Physiology, School of Medicine, University of Nevada, Reno, Reno, NV 89557, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Bioinformatics Core Facility, Genome Center, University of California, Davis, CA 95616, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author <email>cjfinno@ucdavis.edu</email></corresp>
<fn id="fn1">
<label>4</label>
<p id="ntpara0010">Lead Contact</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>31</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<day>22</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>31</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>720</fpage>
<lpage>735</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>22</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>16</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>28</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2019 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="abs0010">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>Ninety percent of Americans consume less than the estimated average requirements of dietary vitamin E (vitE). Severe vitE deficiency due to genetic mutations in the tocopherol transfer protein (<italic>TTPA</italic>) in humans results in ataxia with vitE deficiency (AVED), with proprioceptive deficits and somatosensory degeneration arising from dorsal root ganglia neurons (DRGNs). Single-cell RNA-sequencing of DRGNs was performed in <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice, an established model of AVED. In stark contrast to expected changes in proprioceptive neurons, <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> DRGNs showed marked upregulation of voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> channels in mechanosensitive, tyrosine-hydroxylase positive (TH+) DRGNs. The ensuing significant conductance changes resulted in reduced excitability in mechanosensitive <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> DRGNs. A highly supplemented vitE diet (600 mg dl-α-tocopheryl acetate/kg diet) prevented the cellular and molecular alterations and improved mechanosensation. VitE deficiency profoundly alters the molecular signature and functional properties of mechanosensitive TH+ DRGN, representing an intriguing shift of the prevailing paradigm from proprioception to mechanical sensation.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015">
<title>Graphical Abstract</title>
<fig id="undfig1" position="anchor">
<graphic xlink:href="fx1"></graphic>
</fig>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020">
<title>Highlights</title>
<p>
<list id="ulist0010" list-type="simple">
<list-item id="u0010">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0010">vitE deficiency alters gene expression in DRGs</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0015">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0015">Mechanosensitive TH+ DRG neurons are most affected</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0020">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0020">K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> current densities are increased in vitE-deficient TH+ DRG neurons</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0025">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0025">High-dose vitE supplementation prevents the molecular phenotype</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025">
<p>Neuroscience; Molecular Neuroscience; Transcriptomics</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
<title>Subject Areas</title>
<kwd>Neuroscience</kwd>
<kwd>Molecular Neuroscience</kwd>
<kwd>Transcriptomics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<p id="misc0010">Published: November 22, 2019</p>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="p0030">A mere 10% of the adult American population consume the estimated average requirements (EARs) of vitamin E (vitE) (∼15 mg/day α-tocopherol [α-TOH]) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Fulgoni et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Institute of Medicine, 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Maras et al., 2004</xref>). Severe vitE deficiency stemming from liver diseases, extensive intestinal resections, and the inherited disease of vitE deficiency termed “ataxia with vitE deficiency” (AVED) result in profound ataxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Muller, 2010</xref>). Prevailing functions of vitE have been ascribed to the maintenance of typical neurologic structure and function. Despite identification of vitE as an essential food nutrient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brigelius-Flohe and Traber, 1999</xref>), the molecular, cellular, and functional mechanisms of vitE remain debated. There is extensive evidence supporting the role of vitE, specifically α-tocopherol (α-TOH), as a lipid-soluble antioxidant <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Niki, 2014</xref>) and <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Choi et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">McDougall et al., 2017</xref>), and this has been suggested to be the primary functional mechanism of biologic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Traber and Atkinson, 2007</xref>). Besides this well-established role as an inhibitor of lipid peroxidation, other non-antioxidant properties of α-TOH have been identified, including transcriptional regulation and cell signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Azzi, 2018</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0035">AVED results from mutations in the α-tocopherol transfer protein gene (<italic>TTPA</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gotoda et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yokota et al., 1996</xref>). Phenotypic variability is due the location of the genetic mutation within <italic>TTPA,</italic> the amount of vitE in the daily diet, and the time of initiation and dosage of vitE supplementation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bellayou et al., 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Di Donato et al., 2010</xref>). Most patients demonstrate symptoms of AVED between 4 and 18 years of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cavalier et al., 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gotoda et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Schuelke, 1993</xref>). Patients with AVED exhibit ataxia, areflexia, decreased fine touch, and vibration discrimination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gotoda et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Schuelke, 1993</xref>). Histologic hallmarks of AVED include axonal swellings within the dorsal column medial lemniscus pathway, the sensory pathway that conveys sensations of fine touch vibration, two-point discrimination, and proprioception from the skin and joints. Of note, lesions in the gracile system of the medulla oblongata are also features of physiologic neuroaxonal aging across many species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bridge et al., 2009</xref>). Chronic vitE, specifically α-TOH, deficiency slowly accelerates brain lipid peroxidation and results in cognitive impairment in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Fukui et al., 2015</xref>) and zebrafish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">McDougall et al., 2017</xref>). These deficits can be partially restored by vitE supplementation, in the form of α-TOH. Indeed, early α-TOH supplementation in patients with AVED may suppress severe disease symptoms by unknown mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aparicio et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0040"><italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice represent an accepted model that recapitulates the phenotype of AVED, with ataxia and histologic lesions, including reduction of myelinated fibers in the gracile fasciculus and chromatolysis of neurons within the nucleus gracilis, as early as 6 months of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>). By 17 months of age, diminished dendritic branching of Purkinje neurons within the cerebellum is evident (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Ulatowski et al., 2014</xref>). The affected somatosensory tracts originate in the dorsal root ganglia (DRG), with apoptosis of DRG neurons (DRGNs) evident by 12 months of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>). Therefore, it has been suggested that the most pronounced neurologic deficit in <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice is loss of proprioception. This proprioceptive loss and associated pathology in the spinal cord and cerebellum can be prevented by supplementation of <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice at weaning with 17x the amount of dl-α-tocopheryl acetate (600 mg/kg feed) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>). These studies demonstrate that the interaction of genotype, dietary vitE concentration, and time point in postnatal development are crucial to the development of the neurologic phenotype.</p>
<p id="p0045">To investigate the underlying mechanisms of functional alterations with vitE deficiency, single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) was performed within the DRG of <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice. We hypothesized that the most profound transcriptional dysregulation with vitE deficiency would occur in large-diameter myelinated proprioceptive DRGNs. Therefore, we sought to (1) define the transcriptional dysregulation within DRGN subpopulations in <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice and (2) identify alterations in membrane electrical properties within the targeted DRGN subpopulations of <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec2.1">
<title>Single-Cell RNA-Sequencing Defines Specific DRGN Subpopulations</title>
<p id="p0050">To determine the molecular mechanisms leading to sensory deficits in vitE-deficient DRGNs, scRNA-seq was performed on neuronal cells collected from the DRG (between cervical [C1] and lumbar [L6] vertebrae) of mice in three experimental groups: (1) <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup> on a basal vitE diet (vitE+; WT), (2) <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> on vitE-deficient diet (DEF), and (3) <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> on vitE-supplemented diet (SUPP) at 6 months of age (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Table S1</xref>; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4">Methods</xref> for dietary vitE levels). We have previously identified clinicohistologic evidence of the ataxic phenotype by 6 months of age and completed whole tissue transcriptomic profiling of spinal cord and cerebellum at this time point (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>). In that study, we identified only minor differences between <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice maintained on a basal diet (i.e. 35 mg of dl-α-tocopheryl acetate/kg feed) and <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice on a vitE-deficient diet (DEF; &lt;10 mg of dl-α-tocopheryl acetate/kg feed). Instead, a highly supplemented vitE diet (SUPP; 600 mg of dl-α-tocopheryl acetate/kg feed) was required to prevent the AVED phenotype. Therefore, in the current study, we focused our comparisons on DEF vs. WT and DEF vs. SUPP mice. Contrasts included (1) WT vs. DEF, to determine gene expression changes associated with severe vitE deficiency in DRGNs; (2) SUPP vs. DEF to determine the biologic mechanisms whereby the clinicopathologic AVED phenotype is prevented; and (3) SUPP vs. WT to identify any remaining dysregulated pathways following high-dose vitE supplementation in <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice. As high-dose vitE supplementation does not restore brain α-TOH to WT concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yokota et al., 2001</xref>), we postulated that any gene dysregulation within the SUPP vs. WT group may provide insight into this phenomenon.</p>
<p id="p0055">ScRNA-seq was performed on an average of 3,614 ± 470 DRGN from two replicate mice per group, with a total of 382 million (M) reads generated (17,862 ± 2,625 reads/cell). Approximately 66.5% of reads mapped to the murine transcriptome, similar to previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>), and an average of 1,788 ± 283 genes detected per cell, with no difference between experimental groups (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S1</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0060">Unsupervised single-cell transcriptome profiling identified 14 initial subpopulations in all mice, using gene profiles as previously reported (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>A and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S2</xref>A) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Li et al., 2016</xref>). Based on further evaluation of subpopulations 0 and 2, both clusters appeared to contain peptidergic neurons and were, therefore, merged into cluster 0.2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>B). The top transcripts in each subpopulation are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S2</xref>. A t-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (t-SNE) plot identified a small number of neuronal cells that could not be classified based on previously reported gene profiles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>A). This cluster was labeled as “Unassigned.” Each DRG subpopulation set contained differentially expressed genes characteristic for that cluster. These clusters were classified as PEP1, PEP2, NP1, NP2, NP2-2, NP3, NF1, NF2, NF3, NF4-5, TH1, and TH2 as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>) and “Unassigned” for the unassigned cluster (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S2</xref>). There were no significant differences in cell count per neuronal cluster across experimental groups (p&gt; 0.05 in each subpopulation) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Table S1</xref>). A distinct population of microglial cells based on previously reported markers was not identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>A). Although previous studies have identified outliers or cells with unresolved identity, we further evaluated the “Unassigned” DRGN subpopulation using the top 15 transcripts defining this cluster (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>A, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S2</xref>). Two of the most specific transcripts representing this cluster, forkhead box protein transcription factor 2 (<italic>Foxp2</italic>) and olfactomedin 3 (<italic>Olfm3</italic>), have been previously identified in DRG, primarily in postnatal mice through P14 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jia et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Nakaya et al., 2012</xref>). However, these transcripts are also present in adult brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Ferland et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Nakaya et al., 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Saunders et al., 2018</xref>). Therefore, this subset of neurons most likely represents the small number of remaining developmental neurons undergoing axonal growth.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>An Overall Increase in the Number of Differentially Expressed Transcripts across All DRGN Subpopulations with α-TOH Deficiency</p><p>(A) A t-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (t-SNE) plot of merged datasets of the six experimental mice to define neuronal subpopulations clusters. Thirteen clusters were identified based on previously reported gene expression profiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Li et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>). The “NP2-2” subgroup contained some genes representative of the NP2 cluster but was distinct from the NP2 cluster and has been previously characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Li et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>(B) An increasing number of significantly (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt;0.05) differentially expressed transcripts (DETs) was identified in each DRGN subpopulation with increasing contrasts of vitE deficiency (i.e. SUPP vs. DEF &gt; WT vs. DEF &gt; SUPP vs. WT).</p><p>(C and D) (C) The two most commonly dysregulated transcripts across DRGN subpopulations were carbonic anhydrase 8 (<italic>Car8</italic>), which was significantly downregulated in 10/13 DRG clusters with vitE deficiency (SUPP vs. DEF), and (D) the lineage-specific transcription factor <italic>Runx3</italic>, which was significantly upregulated in 10/13 DRG clusters with vitE deficiency (SUPP vs. DEF). p values were adjusted by a false discovery rate of 0.05 and log-transformed. Significance was set at <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt;0.05, corresponding to a –log <italic>P</italic><sub>adjusted</sub>&gt;1.3 (red line). NF = neurofilament, NP = non-peptidergic, PEP = peptidergic, TH = tyrosine hydroxylase, UNKNOWN = unknown cluster, n = 2 mice per group with ~3,600 cells/mouse profiled.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.2">
<title>An Increasing Number of Dysregulated Transcripts with Increasing vitE Deficiency</title>
<p id="p0065">Within each neuronal cluster, dysregulated transcripts were identified between WT vs. DEF, SUPP vs. WT, and SUPP vs. DEF. For each cell subpopulation, at least two-fold dysregulated (i.e. up- or downregulated at <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt;0.05) transcripts were identified between vitE treatment groups (i.e. SUPP vs. DEF ≫ WT vs. DEF &gt; SUPP vs WT) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>B, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Tables S3</xref> and<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">S4</xref>). The greatest degree of dysregulation in the SUPP vs. DEF group was apparent in the NP1 and TH2 subpopulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>B).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.3">
<title>Top Dysregulated Transcripts across the Majority of DRG Subpopulations: <italic>Car8</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic></title>
<p id="p0070">When WT and SUPP were compared with the DEF groups, carbonic anhydrase 8 (<italic>Car8</italic>)<italic>,</italic> encoding for a protein that inhibits inositol trisphosphate receptor 1 (IP<sub>3</sub>R1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Zhuang et al., 2015</xref>), was significantly (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt;0.05) downregulated in 10/13 DRG clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>C). In particular, <italic>Car8</italic> was the top downregulated transcript with vitE deficiency in the four neurofilament subgroups (NF1, NF2, NF3, and NF4/5). <italic>Car8</italic> was downregulated in these subgroups even in the SUPP vs. WT contrast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>C). The lineage-specific transcription factor <italic>Runx3</italic> was significantly (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt;0.05) upregulated in 10/13 DRG clusters when comparing WT and SUPP vs. DEF groups, especially within NP3 and TH2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>D). Even within the SUPP vs. WT contrast, <italic>Runx3</italic> remained significantly upregulated in 8/13 DRG subpopulations, including NP3 and TH2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>D).</p>
<p id="p0075">As Car8 is the primary inhibitor of IP<sub>3</sub>R1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hirasawa et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hirota et al., 2003</xref>) and transcription of <italic>Car8</italic> was significantly downregulated with vitE deficiency, we postulated that IP<sub>3</sub>R1 signaling might be affected by the level α-TOH supplementation. In DEF mice, a pronounced decrease in IP<sub>3</sub>R1 was apparent in TH+ DRGNs, whereas protein levels appeared increased in SUPP mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>A). Similarly, Car8 was increased in TH+ DRGNs in the SUPP group (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>B).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.4">
<title>Profound Upregulation of Voltage-Gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> Channels in TH+ DRGNs</title>
<p id="p0080">Modulation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel activities mediate changes in neuronal plasticity and, when upregulated, promote neurodegeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chilton, 2006</xref>). Transcripts associated with both ligand-gated and voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> channels were evaluated across genotype and vitE diet groups in our scRNA-seq dataset (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S5</xref>). When comparing SUPP vs. DEF groups, of the voltage-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels expressed in DRGNs, intermediate-voltage Ca<sub>v</sub>2.3 (<italic>Cacna1e;</italic> TH1 <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 1.51 x 10<sup>−8</sup>, TH2 <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 1.29 x 10<sup>−11</sup>) channel was most notably upregulated in TH+ DRGNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>A). High-voltage-activated P-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel, <italic>Cacna1a,</italic> was not significantly altered in any DRGN subpopulation, whereas N-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel, <italic>Cacna1b,</italic> was only upregulated in the NP1 DRGN subpopulation of the SUPP vs. DEF groups (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.001) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S5</xref>). When evaluating K<sup>+</sup> channel transcripts significantly (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt; 0.05) upregulated in the SUPP vs. DEF groups, the most commonly affected DRGN subpopulations for K<sup>+</sup> voltage-gated channel transcript upregulation were TH+ (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S5</xref>). In particular, regulatory subunits of the large-conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated channel subfamily M (<italic>Kcnmb1;</italic> TH1 <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.009, TH2 <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 1.68 x 10<sup>−4</sup> and <italic>Kcnmb2;</italic> TH1 <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.017, TH2 <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 5.20 x 10<sup>−5</sup>) were upregulated in TH+ DRGNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>B). Although a few of the transcripts encoding voltage-gated K<sup>+</sup> channels were upregulated in TH+ DRGNs, most transcripts in this family were upregulated in the non-peptidergic DRGNs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S5</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Upregulation Intermediate Voltage-Gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> Channels in TH+ DRGNs with vitE Deficiency</p><p>Heatmaps, plotted by –log<italic>P</italic><sub>adjusted</sub>, comparing the degree of upregulation for R-type intermediate voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup>, <italic>Cacna1e,</italic> and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channel beta subunits channels, <italic>Kcnmb1</italic> and <italic>Kcnmb2,</italic> in DRGN subpopulations with vitE deficiency. Contrast A = SUPP vs. WT, contrast B = WT vs. DEF, contrast C = SUPP vs DEF. <italic>Cacna1e=</italic> Cav2.3 intermediate voltage-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel, <italic>Kcnmb</italic> = Potassium large conductance calcium-activated channel, subfamily M, beta.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.5">
<title>Increase in Cacna1e and Kcnmb2 with vitE Deficiency in TH+ DRG</title>
<p id="p0085">To confirm that Ca<sub>v</sub>2.3 (<italic>Cacna1e</italic>) and regulatory subunits <italic>Kcnmb1</italic> and <italic>Kcnmb2</italic> were indeed upregulated, we further evaluated mRNA and protein levels of Cacna1e and Kcnmb2. In DEF mice, there was a pronounced increase in <italic>Cacna1e</italic> and <italic>Kcnmb2</italic> in TH+ DRGNs at the level of both mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref>A, 3C, and 3E) and respective proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref>B and 3D).<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Increase in Cacna1e and Kcnmb2 with vitE Deficiency in TH+ DRG</p><p>(A–D) Green: Th, Blue: DAPI nuclei, Red: Cacna1e [(A) mRNA, (B) protein] and Kcnmb2 [(C) mRNA, (D) protein]. White box inset magnified in the last column. Fluorescent immunohistochemistry from 4-month WT, DEF, and SUPP mice, n = 1–2 per group. Scale bars represent 10 μm (TH, Cacna1e, Kcnbm2, and merge) and 3 μm (enlarged).</p><p>(E) Quantification of mRNA using RNAscope for <italic>Cacna1e</italic> and <italic>Kcnmb2</italic>. Mean ± SD, N = 8 counts per experimental group, one-way ANOVA, or Kruskal-Wallis. Scale bars represent 10 μm (TH, Cacna1e, Kcnbm2, and merge) and 3 μm (enlarged).</p><p>(F) Von Frey assay, demonstrating a significant increase in sensitivity (i.e. lower Dixon's score) in the SUPP vs. DEF mice. Mean ± SD, N = 8–22 per group, one-way ANOVA, ****p&lt; 0.0001, **p&lt; 0.01, *p&lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.6">
<title>Supplementation with High-Dose α-TOH Increased Mechanical Sensitivity in <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> Mice</title>
<p id="p0090">The von Frey filament assay was performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Martinov et al., 2013</xref>). SUPP mice had significantly increased mechanical sensitivity compared with DEF diet (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>adjusted</italic></sub> = 0.007, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>F).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.7">
<title>Altered Excitability of <italic>DEF</italic> Small-Diameter DRGNs</title>
<p id="p0095">To understand the etiology and mechanisms of DRG neuronal responses, sensory deficits, and degeneration in AVED as shown in <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yokota et al., 2001</xref>), we focused on the changes in membrane electrical properties. First, we focused on identifying small-diameter mechanosensitive DRGNs. We applied displacement-clamp at DRGN cell-bodies. Using a holding potential of −70 mV, mechanical displacement of the small-diameter DRGN cell body evoked inward currents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A, inset shows traces from WT DRGN). The mechanically activated (MA) current (I<sub>MA</sub>) had amplitudes ranging from 75 to 500 pA (<italic>n</italic> = 11; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A). The displacement-response relationships from data from WT DRGNs were fitted with a single Boltzmann function with half-maximal activation displacement (X<sub>1/2</sub>) and slope factor of 1.1 ± 0.1 μm and 0.3 ± 0.1 μm (<italic>n</italic> = 11; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A). Similar data from <italic>DEF</italic> DRGNs for X<sub>1/2</sub> and slope factor were 1.5 ± 0.1 μm and 0.4 ± 0.1 μm (n = 7). Unpaired <italic>t</italic>test comparison shows significant differences in the X<sub>1/2</sub> (p = 0.016) but not the slope factor (p = 0.51) between the WT and DEF DRGNs. The rightward shift in the displacement-response relations in the DEF DRGNs suggest a decrease in mechanical sensitivity.<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Membrane Properties of Small-Diameter Dorsal Root Ganglion Neurons (DRGNs) from WT and DEF Mice</p><p>Current-clamp recordings were performed on DRGNs 6-month-old mice. Membrane input resistance (R<sub>i</sub>) was determined by evaluating membrane voltage changes in response to negative and positive current injection. The ohmic relations were fitted with linear regression and the R<sub>i</sub> derived from the slope.</p><p>(A) Representative traces of displacement-clamp currents recorded using CsCl/NMG-based pipette solution in response to ~250-ms mechanical displacement steps of ~0.42 μm to WT small-diameter DRGN (shown as inset). DRGNs were held at −70 mV. Summary data of displacement-response relationship of mechanically activated (MA) currents (I<sub>MA</sub>) represented as the I/I<sub>max</sub> or open channel probability (P<sub>o</sub>) against displacement (X) fitted with single Boltzmann function. Data from WT DRGNs (shown in black symbols and fitted with sigmoidal curve in black) and the one-half maximum displacements (X<sub>1/2</sub>) are 1.1 ± 0.1 μm and 0.3 ± 0.1 μm (<italic>n</italic> = 11). Data from DEF DRGNs (shown in blue symbols and fitted with sigmoidal curve in blue) and the one-half maximum displacements (X<sub>1/2</sub>) are 1.5 ± 0.1 μm and 0.4 ± 0.1 μm (<italic>n</italic> = 7).</p><p>(B) Among the small-diameter neurons, there were three distinct classes: fast, medium, and slow adapting. Exemplary plots from fast-adapting DRGNs from WT mice (shown in black, mean R<sub>i</sub> in MΩ; 100 ± 6; n = 15), and in DEF (shown in blue, mean R<sub>i</sub> in MΩ; 45 ± 5; n = 17: p&lt; 0.0001). The inset is an example of data used to generate the plots. For medium-adapting neurons the R<sub>i</sub> (in MW) were as follows: WT (306 ± 23; n = 9) and DEF (162 ± 29; n = 11: p = 0.0014). For slow-adapting neurons the R<sub>i</sub> were WT (626 ± 47; n = 13) and DEF (395 ± 38; n = 11: p = 0.0012).</p><p>(C) Brief (~5 ms) stepwise positive current was injected to elicit subthreshold (shown in different color codes) and threshold depolarization (WT in black and DEF in blue). The threshold currents are indicated. The threshold voltage was determined, using a dV/dt loop plot (inset, right).</p><p>(D and E) Typical voltage response from slow-adapting DRGNs recorded from WT and DEF mice.</p><p>(F and G) Action potentials generated using varying pulse durations from fast-adapting DRGNs in WT (F) and DEF (G) mice.</p><p>(H) Plots of the relations between threshold potential and pulse duration in WT (in black) and DEF (in blue) mice. The insets show the dV/dt <italic>versus</italic> membrane potential (V) loops used to determine the thresholds.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0100">Three functional classes of neurons were then assessed based on their evoked spike frequency adaptation kinetics, defined as fast (eliciting 1–2 APs for ∼0.5-s suprathreshold current injection), medium (4–6 APs), and slow (&gt;10 APs) adapting neurons. We first compared WT with DEF DRGNs. On average, the input resistances of the three classes of neurons in WT were ∼2-fold greater than the DEF neurons. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>B and 4C summarize exemplary steady-state input resistances (R<sub>i</sub>, in MΩ), of the WT (black; 100 ± 6; n = 15), with ∼0.33 nA required to elicit an AP and DEF (blue; 45 ± 5; n =17), with ∼0.73 nA being the AP threshold for fast-adapting DRGNs. For medium-adapting neurons, the R<sub>i</sub> were WT (306 ± 23; n = 9) and DEF (162 ± 29, = 11), and for slow-adapting neurons the R<sub>i</sub> were WT (626 ± 47; n = 13) and DEF (395 ± 38; n = 11). The intrinsic membrane properties of the small-diameter DRGNs suggested that membrane excitability was reduced in DEF mice. In agreement with this assertion, DEF slow-adapting DRGNs showed profound attenuation in spike activity in response to current injection compared with WT DRGNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>D and4E). AP thresholds for fast-adapting DRGNs were determined by calculating dV/dt, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>C (right panel), and the sensitivity of neurons were tested using the indicated pulse duration. For WT DRGNs, with increasing pulse duration, the threshold voltage amplitude declined in a monotonic fashion. However, for DEF DRGNs, the threshold voltage had a biphasic response relative to pulse duration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>F–4H).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.8">
<title>Increased K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> Density in <italic>DEF</italic> Small-Diameter DRGNs</title>
<p id="p0105">The underlying conductances responsible for the reduced R<sub>i</sub> and membrane excitability in the small-diameter <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> DRGNs were examined in the voltage-clamp configuration. Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> currents were isolated under conditions where other ion channel conductances were suppressed. The rationale for focusing on these Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> conductances stemmed from the scRNAseq analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>). Whole-cell voltage-clamp of the small-diameter mechanosensitive DRGNs showed outward K<sup>+</sup> currents with transient and sustained components in both WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>A, upper panel, black) and DEF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>A, lower panel, blue) mice in response to varying voltage steps (−110 to 40 mV) from a holding potential of −90 mV in 10-mV increments. The difference-current traces plotted in dashed lines (inset) provide the profile of the enhanced outward K<sup>+</sup> current in the DEF DRGNs. This difference in currents consisted of mainly a sustained outward current. The total outward K<sup>+</sup> current density plotted as a function of voltage showed significant differences in current densities elicited at −30 to 40 mV step voltages comparing data between WT and DEF mice (n = 17; p&lt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B). To examine Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents, we suppressed outward K<sup>+</sup> currents, by substituting pipette and bath K<sup>+</sup> with NMDG<sup>+</sup> and Cs<sup>+</sup> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4">Methods</xref>). Inward Na<sup>+</sup> current contamination of Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents was suppressed using TTX (1 μM) and by partial substitution of bath Na<sup>+</sup> with NMDG. Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents were activated using −90 and −40 mV holding voltages, and varying step voltages were applied from −120 to 40 mV. Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents in DRGN consist of multiple components: low- and high-voltage-activated currents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Boland and Dingledine, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Wu and Pan, 2004</xref>). The difference-current derived by subtracting current traces generated from −40 mV and that at −90 mV holding potentials yielded mainly the transient and low-voltage activated components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figures 5</xref>C and 5D). Summary data from current-voltage relations show that the high-voltage-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents were enhanced in DEF DRGNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>E). As shown in the inset and illustrated in the current-voltage, rSNX-482 (500 nM), a Ca<sub>v</sub>2.3 (R-type) current-specific blocker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Xie et al., 2016</xref>), suppressed a component of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> current. Additionally, in three recordings from DEF DRGNs, in which rSNX-482 was applied in the bath solution, the enhanced current was attenuated, suggesting the current was conducted by Ca<sub>v</sub>2.3 channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Catterall et al., 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Xie et al., 2016</xref>).<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Increased K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> Current Density in DEF versus WT DRGNs</p><p>(A)Whole-cell onward K<sup>+</sup> currents were elicited using depolarizing steps from −110 to 40 mV (ΔV = 10 mV). The tail currents were at −40 mV. Current traces recorded from WT and DEF DRGNs are shown in black and blue, respectively. To obtain a profile of currents that are enhanced in DEF DRGNs, we determined the “difference currents” between DEF and WT neurons at −70 and 40 mV step voltages (traces are plotted with dashed lines in inset).</p><p>(B) Summary of steady-state currents was normalized to individual membrane capacitance (C<sub>m</sub>), from 6-month-old WT mice (shown with black line and symbol) and <italic>DEF</italic> (shown with gray traces). Data were generated from 14 DRGNs from each experimental group. The mean current densities (in pA/pF) in WT and DEF DRGNs at 0 mV step voltage were 26.1 ± 2.6 and 39.9 ± 2.8; n = 14, p = 0.0015.</p><p>(C and D) Inward Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents recorded from a 12-pF DRGNs in WT (in black) and DEF (in blue) mice from −90 and −40 mV holding potentials. Currents were generated using voltage steps ranging from −110 to 40 mV. The difference-current traces (−90 mV) - (−40 mV) are plotted in dashed lines as an inset.</p><p>(E) Peak Ca<sup>+</sup> current density (I)-voltage (V) relation from data amassed from 12 DRGNs in each group. The current densities generated from a holding voltage of −40 mV are plotted with WT in black and DEF in blue. The high-voltage activated component of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> current was enhanced in the DEF DRGNs. The peak current density (in pA/pF) for currents elicited from a holding potential of −40 mV for WT DRGNs was 20.1 ± 1.5 (n = 9) and for DEF DRGNs was 30.9 ± 2.5 (n = 9, p = 0.002). After application of 500 nM rSNX-482 to the DEF DRGNs the peak current density plummeted to 12.6 ± 1.2 (n = 6, p&lt; 0.0001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0110">Since high-dose vitE supplementation on DEF DRGN appeared to restore the molecular and cellular hallmarks of vitE deficiency, we examined the membrane properties of small-diameter DRGNs in SUPP mice. We examined sensitivity of SUPP DRGNs to mechanical displacements as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A. The displacement-response relationships from data from SUPP DRGNs were fitted with a single Boltzmann function (shown in green) with half-maximal activation displacement (X<sub>1/2</sub>) and slope factor of 1.09 ± 0.1 μm and 0.3 ± 0.1 μm (<italic>n</italic> = 6; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>A). We superimposed data from WT (in black) and DEF (in blue) DRGNs for comparison. A one-way ANOVA was performed to compare the X<sub>1/2</sub> and the slope factor in WT, DEF, and SUPP DRGNs displacement-response curves. There were significant differences at the p&lt; 0.05 level for the three conditions (X<sub>1/2</sub> F(2,21) = 6.088, p = 0.008). Post-hoc comparisons using the Tukey HSD test indicated that data from WT and DEF (p = 0.011) as well as DEF and SUPP (p = 0.024) are significantly different. There was no significant difference between WT and SUPP. Additionally, there were no significant differences in the slope factor in the three experimental conditions.<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Membrane Properties of Small-Diameter Dorsal Root Ganglion Neurons (DRGNs) from SUPP Mice</p><p>(A) Current-clamp recordings were performed on DRGNs 6-month-old mice supplemented with 600 mg dL-alpha-tocopheryl/kg feed. Data were assessed from DRGNs with capacitance &lt;15 pF. Membrane input resistance (R<sub>i</sub>) was determined by evaluating membrane voltage changes in response to negative and positive current injection.</p><p>(B) The ohmic relations were fitted with linear regression and the R<sub>i</sub> derived from the slope. SUPP mice fast-adapting DRGNs had a mean R<sub>i</sub> of 115 ± 9 MW (n = 11).</p><p>(C) Similar to WT DRGNs, as the pulse duration was prolonged, the threshold voltage declined.</p><p>(D) Typical voltage response from slow-adapting DRGNs recorded from SUPP mice. Compared with WT DRGNs, the slow-adapting neurons in SUPP did not recover fully despite vitE supplementation.</p><p>(E)Whole-cell onward K<sup>+</sup> currents were elicited using depolarizing steps from −130 to 30 mV (ΔV = 10 mV), from a holding potential of −90 mV. The tail currents were at −60 mV. Current traces recorded from SUPP DRGNs are shown.</p><p>(F) Summary of steady-state currents was normalized to individual membrane capacitance (C<sub>m</sub>), from 6-month-old SUPP mice. Data were generated from 15 DRGNs.</p><p>(G and H) Inward Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents recorded from a 10-pF DRGNs in SUPP mice from −90 and −40 mV holding potentials. Currents were generated using voltage steps ranging from −120 to 40 mV.</p><p>(I) The current-voltage relations generated at −90 mV and −40 mV holding potential is plotted. The I-V relations of Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents from DEF DRGNs from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>E is re-plotted in blue for comparison.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.9">
<title>Excitability of <italic>SUPP</italic> Small-Diameter DRGNs</title>
<p id="p0115">For SUPP mice, fast-adapting DRGNs had a mean R<sub>i</sub> 115 ± 9 MΩ (n = 11) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>B, shown with green symbols and line). The R<sub>i</sub> between WT (in black line), DEF (in blue line), and DRGNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>B) is replotted for comparison. There were significant differences at the p&lt; 0.05 level for the three conditions (F(2,40) = 174.7, p = 0.001). Post-hoc comparisons using the Tukey HSD test indicated that R<sub>i</sub> from WT vs. DEF (p = 0.001), WT vs. SUPP (p = 0.001), and DEF vs. SUPP (p = 0.001) are significantly different. Similar to WT DRGNs, as the pulse duration was prolonged, the threshold voltage amplitude declined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>C). However, the apparent preventative effects of vitE supplementation were not visibly seen in the slow-adapting small-diameter DRGNs. Compared with WT DRGNs, the slow-adapting neurons in SUPP did not recover fully despite vitE supplementation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>D). We examined whole-cell onward K<sup>+</sup> currents by applying depolarizing voltage steps from −130 to 30 mV (ΔV = 10 mV), from a holding potential of −90 mV in SUPP DRGNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>E). The steady-state outward K<sup>+</sup> currents normalized to individual membrane capacitance (C<sub>m</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>F) showed that vitE supplementation is sufficient to restore the outward K<sup>+</sup> current (plotted in green and compared with the mean data from WT [in black] and DEF [in blue]) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B). For example, the total outward current density elicited at 0 mV in SUPP DRGNs was 24.7 ± 2.9 pA/pF (n = 11). There were significant differences at the p&lt; 0.05 level for the three conditions; steady-state K<sup>+</sup> current elicited at 0 mV F(2,36)= 47.6, p = 0.001. Post-hoc comparisons using the Tukey HSD test indicated that WT vs. DEF (p = 0.001) and DEF vs. SUPP (p = 0.001) are significantly different. There is no significant difference between WT vs. SUPP (p = 0.58). We recorded inward Ca<sup>2+</sup> currents from ∼10-pF DRGNs in SUPP mice using −90 and −40 mV holding voltages. Currents were generated using voltage steps ranging from −120 to 40 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref>G and 6H). The current-voltage relations generated at −90 mV and −40 mV holding voltages are plotted, and the data suggest that vitE supplementation seemingly reversed the enhanced high-voltage-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> current observed in DEF DRGNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>I). Summary data from DEF DRGNs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>E (in blue) is replotted for comparison.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.10">
<title>Upregulation of Pro-apoptotic Transcripts with vitE Deficiency</title>
<p id="p0120">Based on previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>), evidence exists for increased apoptosis in the DRGNs with vitE deficiency by 1 year of age in DEF mice. In both the TH2 (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 1.13 x 10<sup>−4</sup>) and NP1 (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.01) DRGN subpopulations, apoptosis-inducing factor, mitochondrion-associated 3 (<italic>Aifm3</italic>), was upregulated with vitE deficiency (WT vs. DEF and SUPP vs. DEF; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>A). Additionally, tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily, member 21 (<italic>Tnfrsf21</italic>), which promotes apoptosis by release of cytochrome <italic>c</italic> from the mitochondria into the cytoplasm, was significantly upregulated in the NP2 (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 2 x 10<sup>−4</sup>) and TH2 (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.008) DRGN subpopulations (SUPP vs. DEF; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>A). These results suggest that molecular signatures of apoptosis, most pronounced in TH+ DRGNs, occur by 6 months of age in DEF mice.</p>
<p id="p0125">To further investigate the pathways leading to apoptosis of DRGNs with vitE deficiency by 1 year of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>), and the potential preference for TH+ DRGNs, protein expression of total and cleaved caspase 3, caspase 8, and caspase 9 was evaluated with both immunohistochemistry and Western blot analyses in 4-month-old mice. There was no evidence of total caspase 3, caspase 8, or caspase 9 activation (data not shown). However, a significant (p&lt; 0.01) increase in cleaved caspase 3 and caspase 9, localized to TH+ DRGNs, was apparent in DEF mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S4</xref>B and S4C). There was no evidence of cleaved caspase 8 activation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>D).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.11">
<title>Additional Transcript and Pathway Dysregulated with vitE Deficiency</title>
<p id="p0130">In order to determine if the altered gene expression in the DEF DRGN was modulated by the vitE binding proteins <italic>Ttpa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kono et al., 2013</xref>) and tocopherol binding protein (<italic>Tap</italic> or <italic>Sec14l2</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Zingg, 2015</xref>), we interrogated these transcripts in our dataset. <italic>Ttpa</italic> was not expressed in the DRGN dataset. <italic>Sec14l2</italic> was expressed in DRGNs but only differentially expressed between SUPP vs. DEF in the NP1 subpopulation (upregulated in DEF group; <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.004). Additionally, the scRNA-seq dataset was evaluated for genes encoding enzymes that have been previously found to directly bind to vitE, including protein kinase C (<italic>Prkca</italic>); PH domain and leucine-rich repeat protein phosphatase 2 (<italic>Phlpp2</italic>); cyclooxygenase-2 (Ptgs2); and lipoxygenases 5, 12, and 15 (<italic>Alox5, Alox12,</italic> and <italic>Alox15</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Domijan et al., 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Zingg, 2015</xref>). <italic>Ptgs2</italic>, <italic>Alox5</italic>, <italic>Alox12,</italic> and <italic>Alox15</italic> were not expressed in DRGN and, although <italic>Phlpp2</italic> was expressed, there were no differences between experimental groups in any DRGN subpopulation. <italic>Prkca</italic> was significantly downregulated in non-peptidergic DEF DRGN subpopulations (NP1, <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.01; NP2, <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.001; and NP3, <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.03) and upregulated in TH+ DRGN subpopulations (TH1, <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.03 and TH2, <italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.002) when comparing SUPP vs. DEF.</p>
<p id="p0135">With severe vitE deficiency, degenerative axons are identified within the caudal medulla oblongata and spinal cord with AVED (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Yokota et al., 2000</xref>). Therefore, we interrogated our dataset for dysregulation of transcripts associated with axonal guidance, synaptic plasticity, and myelination. When SUPP were compared with the DEF groups, upregulation of associated transcripts was identified across DRGN subpopulations, with most transcripts upregulated in TH2 DRGNs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S6</xref>). Myelin basic protein (<italic>Mbp</italic>) was upregulated in 4/13 SUPP vs. DEF DRGNs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S4</xref>) but was only downregulated in the TH2 subpopulation (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub> = 0.004).</p>
<p id="p0140">Because Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling triggers growth cone development during neurodevelopment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chilton, 2006</xref>), transcripts associated with Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding were interrogated in our scRNA-seq dataset. Most Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding transcripts were most upregulated in TH+ DRGNs with increasing vitE deficiency (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>A, contrast “C”).</p>
<p id="p0145">To further investigate the transcripts expressed among DRGN subtypes and across vitE diet groups, pathway analyses were performed using Panther Pathway overrepresentation analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0010" xlink:href="http://pantherdb.org/">http://pantherdb.org/</ext-link>). When WT and SUPP were compared with the DEF groups, the most commonly dysregulated pathways were upregulation of both the heterotrimeric G-protein signaling pathways G<sub>i</sub>α and G<sub>s</sub>α (P00026) and G<sub>q</sub>α and G<sub>o</sub>α (P00027) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S5</xref>B andS5C). Significant (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt; 0.05) upregulation of these two G-protein signaling pathways was identified in 9/13 DRG clusters (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">Table S7</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S6</xref>). For many of these analyses, G-protein coupled receptor (GPCR) pathways were also significantly (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt; 0.05) overrepresented (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">Table S7</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0150">To further investigate the potential role of enhanced G-protein signaling with vitE deficiency in specific DRGN subpopulations, specific somatosensory genes were evaluated, including G-coupled receptors (GPCRs) and the transient receptor potential vanilloid 1 (<italic>Trpv1</italic>) channel, as recently reviewed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Yudin and Rohacs, 2018</xref>). Associated transcripts were most significantly upregulated in TH+ expressing neurons in the SUPP vs. WT contrast (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>D). These results indicate a positive association between G-protein-coupled receptor transcripts and vitE deficiency, especially in TH+ DRGNs.</p>
<p id="p0155">Transcripts for GO-Slim biologic processes known to regulate mitochondrial functions were significantly (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt; 0.05) downregulated in TH+ and NP1 DRG subpopulations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">Table S7</xref>). This discovery prompted further evaluation of transcripts associated with oxidative phosphorylation. Between 30% and 50% of the transcript of mitochondrial complex I, NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase supernumerary subunits (NDUF) were significantly downregulated (<italic>P</italic><sub>FDR</sub>&lt; 0.05) in NP1 and TH2 DRG subpopulations with vitE deficiency (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>E, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S8</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="p0160">Although the antioxidant role of vitE is well established, with evidence to support protection of critical fatty acids during development of the nervous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Miller et al., 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lebold et al., 2013</xref>), the proposed non-antioxidant roles for this vitamin remain unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Gohil et al., 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Azzi, 2007</xref>). Additionally, it remains unclear why, although all central nervous system tissues are α-TOH deficient in the <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mouse model, the primary clinicopathologic lesions are localized to sensory tracts. Based on the phenotype associated with AVED (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gotoda et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yokota et al., 1996</xref>) and recapitulated in the <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mouse model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yokota et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>), we expected a profound shift in the transcriptomic profile of the proprioceptive DRGN subpopulation. Unexpectedly, we instead identified the most pronounced message alterations in NP1 and TH+ DRGNs, responsible for mechanosensation. Both NP1 and TH+ DRGNs are small to medium in diameter and unmyelinated, whereas proprioceptive DRGNs are large-diameter myelinated neurons. Intriguingly, both NP1 and TH+ subpopulations of DRGNs arise from the same developmental lineage for C-fibers, separating into distinct lineages by E16.5–17.5 in the mouse (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Olson et al., 2016</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0165">Upregulation of intermediate voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> channels in SUPP vs. DEF groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>) prioritized the TH+ DRGN subpopulation for further evaluation. Within TH+ DRGNs, Ca<sup>2+</sup> dysfunction with vitE deficiency was implicated by upregulation of the Ca<sub>v</sub>2.3 (<italic>Cacna1e</italic>) and the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channel subunit <italic>Kcnmb2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>)<italic>.</italic> These findings, in combination with decreased IP<sub>3</sub>R1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>A) and upregulation of G<sub>q</sub>-coupled receptor pathways responsible for the formation of inositol 1,4,5 triphosphate (IP<sub>3</sub>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S5</xref>B and S5C) in DEF mice, indicate that abnormal Ca<sup>2+</sup> dynamics in TH+ DRGNs may be central to the etiology of AVED. Additionally, downregulation of Car8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>C and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S3</xref>B), a major inhibitor of IP<sub>3</sub>R1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hirasawa et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hirota et al., 2003</xref>), indicated coordinated transcriptional changes that could contribute to overactive Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling in TH+ DRGNs. Consistent with this interpretation was the observation that acute vitE deficiency (4–6 months) reduced membrane excitability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>) and caspase activation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>), whereas long-term deficiency resulted in apoptosis of DRGNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>). Supplementation with high-dose α-TOH in DEF mice at weaning prevented the transcriptomic and biochemical profiles described, partially prevented the electrophysiological abnormalities of TH+ DRGNs, and significantly improved mechanical sensitivity as assessed from the displacement-response curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>A) and via the von Frey filament assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>F). As peripheral neuropathy is a clinical feature of AVED (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gotoda et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fogel and Perlman, 2007</xref>), altered Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling within mechanosensitive DRGNs could provide a mechanism for loss of peripheral sensation.</p>
<p id="p0170">Collectively, our findings are the first to link TH+ DRGNs with vitE deficiency and AVED. TH+ DRGNs constitute approximately 10%–15% of all mouse lumbar DRGNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brumovsky et al., 2006</xref>); are located in haired skin; and are responsive to brush, pressure, and pinch but not temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Li et al., 2016</xref>). In patients with AVED, loss of vibration sense and sensitivity to light touch are the frequently reported symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gotoda et al., 1995</xref>), as the dorsal column medial lemniscal neuroanatomic tract is targeted in vitE deficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yokota et al., 1996</xref>). Therefore, we postulate that these symptoms may be due to impaired excitability and abnormal Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling. Specifically, reduced membrane excitability of mechanosensitive DRGNs could account for the peripheral neuropathy associated with AVED. Supplemental α-TOH has been demonstrated to improve peripheral neuropathy in AVED patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Martinello et al., 1998</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0175">Our findings identify altered Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling in TH+ DRGNs with vitE deficiency, in particular, IP<sub>3</sub>R1 pathways. Upregulation of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding transcripts, the voltage-gated Ca<sub>v</sub>2.3 (<italic>Cacna1e</italic>) channel, and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channel subunit <italic>Kcnmb2</italic> are likely mechanistically interrelated alterations that further contribute to the neuropathology in TH+ DRGNs. First, electrophysiological recordings showed enhanced K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> current densities in small-diameter DRGNs isolated from DEF mice. Second, upregulation of GPCRs and downregulation of <italic>Car8</italic> support a role of altered GPCR/phospholipase C (PLC)/inositol triphosphate (IP<sub>3</sub>) signaling in vitE-deficient TH+ DRGNs. Reactive oxygen species can activate G<sub>q</sub>-coupled receptors, catalyzing the conversion of plasma membrane phospholipid phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PIP<sub>2</sub>) by PLC to the intracellular secondary molecules IP<sub>3</sub> and diacylglycerol (DAG) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Servitja et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Vaarmann et al., 2010</xref>). As vitE remains the most potent inhibitor of lipid peroxidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Choi et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">McDougall et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Niki, 2014</xref>), the protection afforded at the plasma membrane may affect GPCR signaling. The decrease in small-diameter DRGN membrane excitability of DEF mice may, therefore, result from altered Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling in TH+ DRGNs. In keeping with reduced excitability of DEF DRGNs, the rate of change of membrane voltage at the upstroke phase of APs (dV/dt) was shallow compared with WT neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>C), which may implicate alterations in Na<sup>+</sup> current magnitude and kinetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Han et al., 2012</xref>). Although there were no significantly dysregulated Na<sup>+</sup> channel transcripts in the TH+ DRGNs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S4</xref>), posttranslational modifications of Na<sup>+</sup> channels may have occurred. Additionally, we cannot determine from this study if the observed effects on membrane excitability are the result of the observed gene expression changes following vitE deficiency or the insufficient vitE concentrations in the DRGNs. Experiments requiring the addition of exogenous α-TOH to DRGNs from DEF mice would be required to determine if membrane excitability can be restored with the addition of vitE. Despite this inability to definitively determine causality, the clinical relevance of these findings indicate that gene expression and membrane excitability changes within the DRGN may underlie the peripheral neuropathy observed with AVED.</p>
<p id="p0180">By 12 months of age, apoptosis within most large- and small-diameter DRGNs is evident in DEF mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>). Increased TUNEL staining of DRGNs in DEF mice is not observed by 6 months of age (unpublished results). In this study, scRNA-sequencing was performed only on viable cells (see <bold><italic>Cell count/viability and RNA quality assurance</italic>)<italic>.</italic></bold> Therefore, within the 6-month DEF mice examined in this study, increased activity of cleaved caspase-3 and -9 in DEF TH+ DRGNs is likely a proximal mechanism of promoting apoptosis.</p>
<p id="p0185">Using whole tissue spinal cord homogenate, we previously identified altered nuclear receptor activation in DEF mice as they aged from weaning to 6 months (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>). With sufficient vitE, retinoid orphan-related receptor alpha (RORA)-targeted transcripts were activated in the spinal cord, whereas insufficient vitE led to the activation of liver X receptor (LXR)-targeted transcripts. This effect was not observed in whole-tissue spinal cord when simply comparing groups at 6 months of age (WT vs. DEF vs. SUPP). Similarly, we did not identify upregulation of most previously investigated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>) RORA-targeted transcripts in the DRGNs between SUPP and DEF groups at 6 months of age in this current study. Comparison of DRGNs subpopulations in WT, DEF, and SUPP experimental groups between weaning and 6 months of age requires further investigation to fully elucidate the role for RORA with vitE deficiency.</p>
<p id="p0190">Elevations in 7-oxygenated cholesterol products have been previously described in both the <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>) and atherosclerotic apolipoprotein vitE-deficient mouse models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Rosenblat and Aviram, 2002</xref>). Both 7α-hydroxycholesterol and 7-ketocholesterol are inverse agonists for the constitutively active RORA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). Therefore, we surmise that increased oxysterols suppress constitutive RORA signaling during vitE deficiency, a hypothesis that has been supported by other studies in both the <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gohil et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gohil et al., 2004</xref>) and the vitE-deficient horse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Finno et al., 2016</xref>). RORA activation is required for synaptic maintenance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Landis and Sidman, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sotelo and Changeux, 1974</xref>) and the neuroprotective effect is mediated by the antioxidant proteins glutathione peroxidase 1 and peroxiredoxin 6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Boukhtouche et al., 2006</xref>). Of note, RORA controls the expression of IP<sub>3</sub>R1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Gold et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sarachana and Hu, 2013</xref>). Therefore, the underlying molecular mechanism whereby vitE deficiency leads to AVED may involve differential nuclear receptor activation with age, leading to altered IP<sub>3</sub>R1 signaling in TH+ DRGNs, in addition to alterations in redox status at the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). Alternatively, specific oxidized polyunsaturated fatty-acid-derived lipid mediators, which are protected by vitE from oxidation and destruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Choi et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lebold et al., 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lebold and Traber, 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Ulatowski and Manor, 2013</xref>), may be involved in this protective mechanism.<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Proposed Mechanism of Action for α-TOH in TH+ DRGN</p><p>With adequate α-TOH (left), constitutive activity of the RAR-related orphan receptor alpha (RORA) transcription factor is maintained, increasing IP<sub>3</sub>R1 transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Gold et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sarachana and Hu, 2013</xref>). Although there is evidence that vitE can affect the plasma membrane structure and bind to signaling enzymes to affect their activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Zingg, 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Habermehl et al., 2005</xref>), we propose in this model that signaling through the PLC/IP<sub>3</sub>/IP<sub>3</sub>R1 axis maintains Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis. VitE can suppress PLC activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Domijan et al., 2014</xref>) and, by stimulating DAGK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Koya et al., 1997</xref>), DAG is removed and PKC inhibited, providing a protective effect. With α-TOH deficiency (right), cholesterol is oxidized and resulting oxysterols repress constitutive RORA activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wang et al., 2010</xref>), leading to decreased IP<sub>3</sub>R1 transcription. ROS activate the PLC/IP<sub>3</sub>/IP<sub>3</sub>R1 axis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Servitja et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Vaarmann et al., 2010</xref>); however, without sufficient IP<sub>3</sub>R1, [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> cannot increase. Additionally, loss of DAGK stimulation increases DAG and PKC. We propose this leads to the identified alterations in membrane excitability and activation of apoptotic pathways in DRGNs. BK= big potassium channel; DAG = diaglycerol; DAGK= diaglycerol kinase; IP<sub>3</sub> = inositol triphosphate; IP<sub>3</sub>R1 = inositol 1,4,5 triphosphate receptor 1; PIP<sub>2</sub> = phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate; PKC = protein kinase C; PLC = phospholipase C; RORA= RAR-related orphan receptor alpha; ROS = reactive oxygen species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0195">Single-cell RNA-seq generated a total of 382 million reads in our study, with an average of 3,614 DRGNs profiled per mouse (i.e. 7,228 neurons per experimental group). In the pioneer scRNA-seq study of DRG, pooled lumbar DRG were used to generate 2.76 billion reads across 622 single mouse neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>). A total of 3,574 ± 2,010 distinct genes were identified in each cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>), as compared with our study of 1,788 ± 283 genes per cell. A subsequent publication used neuron-size-based hierarchical clustering and high-coverage scRNA-seq of 203 neurons collected from lumbar DRG of five pooled male mice (10,950 ± 1,218 genes per neuron) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Li et al., 2016</xref>). Despite the overall lower depth of sequencing across genes in our study, we were able to identify the previously characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>) neuronal subpopulations within the DRG. Previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Li et al., 2016</xref>) clustered the unmyelinated TH+ neuronal population into one population. In our dataset, two distinct TH+ subgroups (TH1 and TH2) were identified across all samples. Despite highly overlapping transcriptional profiles, these subtypes were not closely enough related to merge, unlike the PEP1 subpopulation (i.e. Clusters 0 and 2). The distinct sub-clustering of TH+ subpopulations in our study warrants further investigation, as the most profound alterations with vitE deficiency in our model occurred primarily in the TH2 subpopulation. Our mice were 6 months of age, older than those used in previously reported scRNA-seq profiling studies in DRG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Li et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Usoskin et al., 2015</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0200">The von Frey filament assay is used on glabrous skin, which is innervated by both alpha and beta low-threshold mechanoreceptors, both not TH+ C-low threshold mechanoreceptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Li et al., 2011</xref>). However, it has been observed that von Frey filament can activate sensitized non-peptidergic type C nociceptive fibers (i.e. NP1 subpopulations) under certain conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pinto et al., 2019</xref>). In our study, the NP1 subpopulation, responsible for neuropathic pain, was also notably implicated with vitE deficiency. VitE has been demonstrated to act as an analgesic in rodent models of neuropathic pain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2006</xref>), although a more recent study suggests that vitC is required concurrently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lu et al., 2011</xref>). Foot withdrawal thresholds in response to mechanical stimuli were used to assess neuropathic pain followed by spinal cord ligation, with increased thresholds for 6 h after vitE injection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2006</xref>). As neurobehavioral assays through tactile stimuli cannot reliably differentiate different DRGN activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Li et al., 2011</xref>), we elected to document electrophysiological dysfunction in TH+-specific mechanosensitive DRGNs with vitE deficiency using whole-cell membrane recordings specific to small-diameter mechanosensitive DRGNs. However, further investigation into the role of vitE in NP1 nociceptive DRGNs is warranted.</p>
<p id="p0205">One of the most notable findings identified in the DEF mouse model is the complete prevention of the clinical and histologic phenotype with high-dose α-TOH supplementation at weaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yokota et al., 2001</xref>). To further support these clinical findings, we have now demonstrated complete prevention of the transcriptomic and partial rescue of the electrophysiologic dysfunction within the DRGNs at the single-cell level. VitE supplementation in <italic>Ttpa</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> mice suffices to partially restore K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> current properties in small-diameter mechanosensitive DRGNs, but it remains unclear why slow-adapting DRGNs are impervious to vitE supplementation. Of note, α-TOH concentrations in the brain of these SUPP mice are still significantly lower than those of WT mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Finno et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yokota et al., 2001</xref>), indicating that α-TTP in the brain functions in maintaining local concentration of α-TOH. Despite the lower brain α-TOH concentrations in SUPP mice compared with WT mice, the AVED clinicohistologic phenotype is completely prevented. Therefore, a minimum concentration of vitE is likely required at this critical time in postnatal development. Even more important is the fact that the phenotype is rescuable when vitE is provided at P21, a time point that is considered the end of postnatal development in the mouse. Therefore, it may be possible that synaptogenesis and axonal elongation continue into adulthood, thereby requiring sufficient vitE from 1–6 months of age in mice.</p>
<p id="p0210">Although this study focused on DRGNs, vitE has been demonstrated to have effects in other regions of the nervous system. Within the hippocampus, α-TOH induced long-term potentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Xie and Sastry, 1993</xref>), which is involved in learning and memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Thompson, 1986</xref>). The action of vitE in hippocampal CA1 neurons occurred without a significant alteration in the membrane potential and the input resistance. Rats that are fed a vitE-deficient diet for three months had impaired long-term potential induction, with a reduction in post-tetanic potentiation, suggesting that either neurotransmitter release or postsynaptic mechanisms are involved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Xie and Sastry, 1995</xref>). It remains to be determined if the postulated mechanism for the neuroprotective effect of vitE in the DRG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>) is applicable to other regions of the nervous system.</p>
<p id="p0215">In conclusion, we have identified the most profound transcriptomic, biochemical, and electrophysiologic changes in small-diameter TH+ mechanosensitive DRGNs, rather than the proprioceptive subpopulation, with vitE deficiency. Increased upregulation of voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> channels led to AP abbreviation and reduced membrane excitability in TH+ DRGNs. Concurrently, alterations in IP<sub>3</sub>R1 expression were identified, in addition to evidence of apoptosis via caspase-3- and caspase-9-mediated pathways. A highly supplemented α-TOH diet rescues the cellular and molecular alterations and represses the loss of mechanosensation found in DEF mice. The peripheral neuropathy associated with AVED likely encompasses defects in membrane properties and Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling in mechanosensitive TH+ DRGNs, providing targets for therapeutic intervention.</p>
<sec id="sec3.1">
<title>Limitations of the Study</title>
<p id="p0220">We cannot determine from this study if the observed effects on membrane excitability are the result of the observed gene expression changes following vitE deficiency or the insufficient vitE concentrations in the DRGNs. Experiments requiring the addition of exogenous α-TOH to DRGNs from DEF mice would be required to determine if membrane excitability can be restored with the addition of vitE.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="p0225">All methods can be found in the accompanying <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Transparent Methods supplemental file</xref>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list id="cebib0010">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bib1">
<element-citation id="sref1" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aparicio</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Belanger-Quintana</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Suarez</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mayo</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benitez</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Diaz</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Escobar</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ataxia with isolated vitamin E deficiency: case report and review of the literature</article-title>
<source/>J. Pediatr. Gastroenterol. Nutr.
          <volume>33</volume>
<year>2001</year>
<fpage>206</fpage>
<lpage>210</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11568526</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<element-citation id="sref2" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Azzi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular mechanism of alpha-tocopherol action</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>43</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>16</fpage>
<lpage>21</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561089</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<element-citation id="sref3" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Azzi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Many tocopherols, one vitamin E</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Aspects Med.
          <volume>61</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>92</fpage>
<lpage>103</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28624327</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<element-citation id="sref4" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bellayou</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dehbi</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bourezgui</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Slassi</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nadifi</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ataxia with vitamin E deficiency (AVED); an example of the contribution of research in molecular genetic to counselling in Morocco</article-title>
<source/>Pathol. Biol. (Paris)
          <volume>57</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>425</fpage>
<lpage>426</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19038506</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<element-citation id="sref5" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boland</surname>
<given-names>L.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dingledine</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Multiple components of both transient and sustained barium currents in a rat dorsal root ganglion cell line</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>420</volume>
<year>1990</year>
<fpage>223</fpage>
<lpage>245</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2157839</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<element-citation id="sref6" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boukhtouche</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vodjdani</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jarvis</surname>
<given-names>C.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakouche</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Staels</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mallet</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mariani</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lemaigre-Dubreuil</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brugg</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Human retinoic acid receptor-related orphan receptor alpha1 overexpression protects neurones against oxidative stress-induced apoptosis</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurochem.
          <volume>96</volume>
<year>2006</year>
<fpage>1778</fpage>
<lpage>1789</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16539693</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<element-citation id="sref7" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bridge</surname>
<given-names>K.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berg</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adalbert</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Babetto</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dias</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spillantini</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ribchester</surname>
<given-names>R.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coleman</surname>
<given-names>M.P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Late onset distal axonal swelling in YFP-H transgenic mice</article-title>
<source/>Neurobiol. Aging
          <volume>30</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>309</fpage>
<lpage>321</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17658198</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<element-citation id="sref8" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brigelius-Flohe</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin E: function and metabolism</article-title>
<source/>FASEB J.
          <volume>13</volume>
<year>1999</year>
<fpage>1145</fpage>
<lpage>1155</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10385606</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<element-citation id="sref9" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brumovsky</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Villar</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hokfelt</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tyrosine hydroxylase is expressed in a subpopulation of small dorsal root ganglion neurons in the adult mouse</article-title>
<source/>Exp. Neurol.
          <volume>200</volume>
<year>2006</year>
<fpage>153</fpage>
<lpage>165</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16516890</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<element-citation id="sref10" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Catterall</surname>
<given-names>W.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Perez-Reyes</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snutch</surname>
<given-names>T.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Striessnig</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>International Union of Pharmacology. XLVIII. Nomenclature and structure-function relationships of voltage-gated calcium channels</article-title>
<source/>Pharmacol. Rev.
          <volume>57</volume>
<year>2005</year>
<fpage>411</fpage>
<lpage>425</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16382099</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<element-citation id="sref11" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cavalier</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ouahchi</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kayden</surname>
<given-names>H.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Di Donato</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reutenauer</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mandel</surname>
<given-names>J.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koenig</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ataxia with isolated vitamin E deficiency: heterogeneity of mutations and phenotypic variability in a large number of families</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
          <volume>62</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>301</fpage>
<lpage>310</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9463307</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<element-citation id="sref12" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chilton</surname>
<given-names>J.K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular mechanisms of axon guidance</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Biol.
          <volume>292</volume>
<year>2006</year>
<fpage>13</fpage>
<lpage>24</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476423</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<element-citation id="sref13" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leonard</surname>
<given-names>S.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kasper</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McDougall</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>J.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tanguay</surname>
<given-names>R.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Novel function of vitamin E in regulation of zebrafish (Danio rerio) brain lysophospholipids discovered using lipidomics</article-title>
<source/>J. Lipid Res.
          <volume>56</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>1182</fpage>
<lpage>1190</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25855633</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<element-citation id="sref14" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Di Donato</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bianchi</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Federico</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ataxia with vitamin E deficiency: update of molecular diagnosis</article-title>
<source/>Neurol. Sci.
          <volume>31</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>511</fpage>
<lpage>515</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20464573</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib15">
<element-citation id="sref15" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Domijan</surname>
<given-names>A.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kovac</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abramov</surname>
<given-names>A.Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lipid peroxidation is essential for phospholipase C activity and the inositol-trisphosphate-related Ca(2)(+) signal</article-title>
<source/>J.Cell Sci.
          <volume>127</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>21</fpage>
<lpage>26</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24198393</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib16">
<element-citation id="sref16" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ferland</surname>
<given-names>R.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cherry</surname>
<given-names>T.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Preware</surname>
<given-names>P.O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morrisey</surname>
<given-names>E.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of Foxp2 and Foxp1 mRNA and protein in the developing and mature brain</article-title>
<source/>J. Comp. Neurol.
          <volume>460</volume>
<year>2003</year>
<fpage>266</fpage>
<lpage>279</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12687690</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib17">
<element-citation id="sref17" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Finno</surname>
<given-names>C.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bordbari</surname>
<given-names>M.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gianino</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ming-Whitfield</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Merkel</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Britton</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Durbin-Johnson</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sloma</surname>
<given-names>E.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McMackin</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>An innate immune response and altered nuclear receptor activation defines the spinal cord transcriptome during alpha-tocopherol deficiency in Ttpa-null mice</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>120</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>289</fpage>
<lpage>302</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29526809</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib18">
<element-citation id="sref18" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Finno</surname>
<given-names>C.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bordbari</surname>
<given-names>M.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Valberg</surname>
<given-names>S.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Herron</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hines</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Monsour</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bannasch</surname>
<given-names>D.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mickelson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptome profiling of equine vitamin E deficient neuroaxonal dystrophy identifies upregulation of liver X receptor target genes</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>101</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>261</fpage>
<lpage>271</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27751910</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib19">
<element-citation id="sref19" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fogel</surname>
<given-names>B.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Perlman</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Clinical features and molecular genetics of autosomal recessive cerebellar ataxias</article-title>
<source/>Lancet Neurol.
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>245</fpage>
<lpage>257</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17303531</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib20">
<element-citation id="sref20" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fukui</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shirai</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hirano</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Takatsu</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Urano</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Long-term vitamin E-deficient mice exhibit cognitive dysfunction via elevation of brain oxidation</article-title>
<source/>J. Nutr. Sci. Vitaminol. (Tokyo)
          <volume>61</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>362</fpage>
<lpage>368</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26639843</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib21">
<element-citation id="sref21" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fulgoni</surname>
<given-names>V.L.</given-names>
<suffix>3rd</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keast</surname>
<given-names>D.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bailey</surname>
<given-names>R.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dwyer</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Foods, fortificants, and supplements: where do Americans get their nutrients?</article-title>
<source/>J. Nutr.
          <volume>141</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>1847</fpage>
<lpage>1854</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21865568</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib22">
<element-citation id="sref22" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gohil</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Godzdanker</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O'Roark</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schock</surname>
<given-names>B.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaini</surname>
<given-names>R.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Packer</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Alpha-tocopherol transfer protein deficiency in mice causes multi-organ deregulation of gene networks and behavioral deficits with age</article-title>
<source/>Ann. N Y Acad. Sci.
          <volume>1031</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>109</fpage>
<lpage>126</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753139</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib23">
<element-citation id="sref23" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gohil</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schock</surname>
<given-names>B.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chakraborty</surname>
<given-names>A.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Terasawa</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raber</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Farese</surname>
<given-names>R.V.</given-names>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Packer</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Gene expression profile of oxidant stress and neurodegeneration in transgenic mice deficient in alpha-tocopherol transfer protein</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>35</volume>
<year>2003</year>
<fpage>1343</fpage>
<lpage>1354</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14642382</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib24">
<element-citation id="sref24" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gohil</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vasu</surname>
<given-names>V.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dietary alpha-tocopherol and neuromuscular health: search for optimal dose and molecular mechanisms continues!</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Nutr. Food Res.
          <volume>54</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>693</fpage>
<lpage>709</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20187127</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib25">
<element-citation id="sref25" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gold</surname>
<given-names>D.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baek</surname>
<given-names>S.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schork</surname>
<given-names>N.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rose</surname>
<given-names>D.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Larsen</surname>
<given-names>D.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sachs</surname>
<given-names>B.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hamilton</surname>
<given-names>B.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>RORalpha coordinates reciprocal signaling in cerebellar development through sonic hedgehog and calcium-dependent pathways</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>40</volume>
<year>2003</year>
<fpage>1119</fpage>
<lpage>1131</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14687547</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib26">
<element-citation id="sref26" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gotoda</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arita</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arai</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yokota</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fukuo</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yazaki</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yamada</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Adult-onset spinocerebellar dysfunction caused by a mutation in the gene for the alpha-tocopherol-transfer protein</article-title>
<source/>N. Engl. J. Med.
          <volume>333</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>1313</fpage>
<lpage>1318</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7566022</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib27">
<element-citation id="sref27" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Habermehl</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kempna</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Azzi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zingg</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Recombinant SEC14-like proteins (TAP) possess GTPase activity</article-title>
<source/>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.
          <volume>326</volume>
<year>2005</year>
<fpage>254</fpage>
<lpage>259</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15567179</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib28">
<element-citation id="sref28" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoeijmakers</surname>
<given-names>J.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gerrits</surname>
<given-names>M.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>te Morsche</surname>
<given-names>R.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lauria</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dib-Hajj</surname>
<given-names>S.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Drenth</surname>
<given-names>J.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Faber</surname>
<given-names>C.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Merkies</surname>
<given-names>I.S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Functional profiles of SCN9A variants in dorsal root ganglion neurons and superior cervical ganglion neurons correlate with autonomic symptoms in small fibre neuropathy</article-title>
<source/>Brain
          <volume>135</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>2613</fpage>
<lpage>2628</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22826602</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib29">
<element-citation id="sref29" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hirasawa</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trask</surname>
<given-names>R.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maddatu</surname>
<given-names>T.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>B.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Naggert</surname>
<given-names>J.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nishina</surname>
<given-names>P.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ikeda</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Carbonic anhydrase related protein 8 mutation results in aberrant synaptic morphology and excitatory synaptic function in the cerebellum</article-title>
<source/>Mol.Cell.Neurosci.
          <volume>35</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>161</fpage>
<lpage>170</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17376701</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib30">
<element-citation id="sref30" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hirota</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ando</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hamada</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mikoshiba</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Carbonic anhydrase-related protein is a novel binding protein for inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor type 1</article-title>
<source/>Biochem. J.
          <volume>372</volume>
<year>2003</year>
<fpage>435</fpage>
<lpage>441</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12611586</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib31">
<element-citation id="sref31" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>L.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chopp</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Szalad</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>MiR-29c/PRKCI regulates axonal growth of dorsal root ganglia neurons under hyperglycemia</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Neurobiol.
          <volume>55</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>851</fpage>
<lpage>858</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28070856</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib32">
<element-citation id="sref32" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>H.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>J.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>J.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Analgesic effect of vitamin E is mediated by reducing central sensitization in neuropathic pain</article-title>
<source/>Pain
          <volume>122</volume>
<year>2006</year>
<fpage>53</fpage>
<lpage>62</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16524661</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib33">
<element-citation id="sref33" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kono</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ohto</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hiramatsu</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Urabe</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Uchida</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Satow</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arai</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Impaired alpha-TTP-PIPs interaction underlies familial vitamin E deficiency</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>340</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>1106</fpage>
<lpage>1110</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23599266</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib34">
<element-citation id="sref34" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Koya</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>I.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ishii</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kanoh</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>G.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prevention of glomerular dysfunction in diabetic rats by treatment with d-alpha-tocopherol</article-title>
<source/>J. Am. Soc. Nephrol.
          <volume>8</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>426</fpage>
<lpage>435</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9071711</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib35">
<element-citation id="sref35" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Landis</surname>
<given-names>D.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sidman</surname>
<given-names>R.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Electron microscopic analysis of postnatal histogenesis in the cerebellar cortex of staggerer mutant mice</article-title>
<source/>J. Comp. Neurol.
          <volume>179</volume>
<year>1978</year>
<fpage>831</fpage>
<lpage>863</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">641237</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib36">
<element-citation id="sref36" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lebold</surname>
<given-names>K.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kirkwood</surname>
<given-names>J.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>A.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barton</surname>
<given-names>C.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>G.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>La Du</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jump</surname>
<given-names>D.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>J.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tanguay</surname>
<given-names>R.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Novel liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry method shows that vitamin E deficiency depletes arachidonic and docosahexaenoic acids in zebrafish (Danio rerio) embryos</article-title>
<source/>Redox Biol.
          <volume>2</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24416717</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib37">
<element-citation id="sref37" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lebold</surname>
<given-names>K.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Interactions between alpha-tocopherol, polyunsaturated fatty acids, and lipoxygenases during embryogenesis</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>66</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>13</fpage>
<lpage>19</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23920314</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib38">
<element-citation id="sref38" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>K.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>M.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Y.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>Y.Q.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Somatosensory neuron types identified by high-coverage single-cell RNA-sequencing and functional heterogeneity</article-title>
<source/>Cell Res
          <volume>26</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>967</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27481604</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib39">
<element-citation id="sref39" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rutlin</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abraira</surname>
<given-names>V.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cassidy</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kus</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jankowski</surname>
<given-names>M.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heintz</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koerber</surname>
<given-names>H.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The functional organization of cutaneous low-threshold mechanosensory neurons</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>147</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>1615</fpage>
<lpage>1627</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22196735</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib40">
<element-citation id="sref40" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kallenborn-Gerhardt</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Geisslinger</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schmidtko</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Additive antinociceptive effects of a combination of vitamin C and vitamin E after peripheral nerve injury</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>e29240</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22195029</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib41">
<element-citation id="sref41" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maras</surname>
<given-names>J.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bermudez</surname>
<given-names>O.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qiao</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakun</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boody-Alter</surname>
<given-names>E.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>K.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Intake of alpha-tocopherol is limited among US adults</article-title>
<source/>J. Am.Diet Assoc.
          <volume>104</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>567</fpage>
<lpage>575</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15054342</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib42">
<element-citation id="sref42" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martinello</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fardin</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ottina</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ricchieri</surname>
<given-names>G.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koenig</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cavalier</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trevisan</surname>
<given-names>C.P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Supplemental therapy in isolated vitamin E deficiency improves the peripheral neuropathy and prevents the progression of ataxia</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurol. Sci.
          <volume>156</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>177</fpage>
<lpage>179</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9588854</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib43">
<element-citation id="sref43" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martinov</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mack</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sykes</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chatterjea</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Measuring changes in tactile sensitivity in the hind paw of mice using an electronic von Frey apparatus</article-title>
<source/>J. Vis. Exp.
          <volume>82</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>e51212</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib44">
<element-citation id="sref44" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McDougall</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Truong</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tanguay</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin E deficiency during embryogenesis in zebrafish causes lasting metabolic and cognitive impairments despite refeeding adequate diets</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>110</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>250</fpage>
<lpage>260</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28645790</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib45">
<element-citation id="sref45" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Institute of Medicine</collab>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Dietary Reference Intakes: Vitamin C, Vitamin E, Selenium, and Carotenoids</chapter-title>
<year>2000</year>
<publisher-name>The National Academeies Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib46">
<element-citation id="sref46" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>G.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ulatowski</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Labut</surname>
<given-names>E.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lebold</surname>
<given-names>K.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Manor</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Atkinson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barton</surname>
<given-names>C.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tanguay</surname>
<given-names>R.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The alpha-tocopherol transfer protein is essential for vertebrate embryogenesis</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <volume>7</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>e47402</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23077608</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib47">
<element-citation id="sref47" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Muller</surname>
<given-names>D.P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin E and neurological function</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Nutr. Food Res.
          <volume>54</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>710</fpage>
<lpage>718</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20183831</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib48">
<element-citation id="sref48" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nakaya</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sultana</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>H.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tomarev</surname>
<given-names>S.I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Olfactomedin 1 interacts with the Nogo a receptor complex to regulate axon growth</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>287</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>37171</fpage>
<lpage>37184</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22923615</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib49">
<element-citation id="sref49" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Niki</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Role of vitamin E as a lipid-soluble peroxyl radical scavenger: in vitro and in vivo evidence</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>66</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>12</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23557727</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib50">
<element-citation id="sref50" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fleming</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The specification and wiring of mammalian cutaneous low-threshold mechanoreceptors</article-title>
<source/>Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Dev. Biol.
          <volume>5</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>404</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26992078</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib51">
<element-citation id="sref51" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pinto</surname>
<given-names>L.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Souza</surname>
<given-names>G.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kusuda</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lopes</surname>
<given-names>A.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sant'Anna</surname>
<given-names>M.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cunha</surname>
<given-names>F.Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferreira</surname>
<given-names>S.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cunha</surname>
<given-names>T.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Non-peptidergic nociceptive neurons are essential for mechanical inflammatory hypersensitivity in mice</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Neurobiol.
          <volume>56</volume>
<year>2019</year>
<fpage>5715</fpage>
<lpage>5728</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30674034</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib52">
<element-citation id="sref52" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rosenblat</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aviram</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oxysterol-induced activation of macrophage NADPH-oxidase enhances cell-mediated oxidation of LDL in the atherosclerotic apolipoprotein E deficient mouse: inhibitory role for vitamin E</article-title>
<source/>Atherosclerosis
          <volume>160</volume>
<year>2002</year>
<fpage>69</fpage>
<lpage>80</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11755924</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib53">
<element-citation id="sref53" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sarachana</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>V.W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification of transcriptional targets of RORA reveals direct regulation of multiple genes associated with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Autism
          <volume>4</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>14</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23697635</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib54">
<element-citation id="sref54" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saunders</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Macosko</surname>
<given-names>E.Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wysoker</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krienen</surname>
<given-names>F.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De Rivera</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bien</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baum</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bortolin</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S.Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular diversity and specializations among the cells of the adult mouse brain</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>174</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>1015</fpage>
<lpage>1030.e16</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30096299</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib55">
<element-citation id="sref55" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schuelke</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Ataxia with vitamin E deficiency</chapter-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Adam</surname>
<given-names>M.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ardinger</surname>
<given-names>H.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pagon</surname>
<given-names>R.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wallace</surname>
<given-names>S.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bean</surname>
<given-names>L.J.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stephens</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Amemiya</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source/>GeneReviews((R))
          <year>1993</year>
<publisher-name>University of Washington</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib56">
<element-citation id="sref56" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Servitja</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Masgrau</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pardo</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sarri</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Picatoste</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Effects of oxidative stress on phospholipid signaling in rat cultured astrocytes and brain slices</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurochem.
          <volume>75</volume>
<year>2000</year>
<fpage>788</fpage>
<lpage>794</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10899956</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib57">
<element-citation id="sref57" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sotelo</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Changeux</surname>
<given-names>J.P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Transsynaptic degeneration 'en cascade' in the cerebellar cortex of staggerer mutant mice</article-title>
<source/>Brain Res.
          <volume>67</volume>
<year>1974</year>
<fpage>519</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4470439</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib58">
<element-citation id="sref58" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>R.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The neurobiology of learning and memory</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>233</volume>
<year>1986</year>
<fpage>941</fpage>
<lpage>947</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3738519</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib59">
<element-citation id="sref59" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Traber</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Atkinson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin E, antioxidant and nothing more</article-title>
<source/>Free Radic. Biol. Med.
          <volume>43</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>4</fpage>
<lpage>15</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561088</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib60">
<element-citation id="sref60" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ulatowski</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Manor</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin E trafficking in neurologic health and disease</article-title>
<source/>Annu. Rev. Nutr.
          <volume>33</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>87</fpage>
<lpage>103</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23642196</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib61">
<element-citation id="sref61" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ulatowski</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Warrier</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sultana</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Butterfield</surname>
<given-names>D.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Manor</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin E is essential for Purkinje neuron integrity</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience
          <volume>260</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>120</fpage>
<lpage>129</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24342566</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib62">
<element-citation id="sref62" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Usoskin</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Furlan</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Islam</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abdo</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lonnerberg</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lou</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hjerling-Leffler</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haeggstrom</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kharchenko</surname>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kharchenko</surname>
<given-names>P.V.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Unbiased classification of sensory neuron types by large-scale single-cell RNA sequencing</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <volume>18</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>145</fpage>
<lpage>153</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25420068</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib63">
<element-citation id="sref63" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vaarmann</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gandhi</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abramov</surname>
<given-names>A.Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dopamine induces Ca2+ signaling in astrocytes through reactive oxygen species generated by monoamine oxidase</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>285</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>25018</fpage>
<lpage>25023</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20547771</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib64">
<element-citation id="sref64" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Solt</surname>
<given-names>L.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>T.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Helvering</surname>
<given-names>L.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Crumbley</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garcia-Ordonez</surname>
<given-names>R.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stayrook</surname>
<given-names>K.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Novick</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Modulation of retinoic acid receptor-related orphan receptor alpha and gamma activity by 7-oxygenated sterol ligands</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>285</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>5013</fpage>
<lpage>5025</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19965867</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib65">
<element-citation id="sref65" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Z.Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>H.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>High voltage-activated Ca(2+) channel currents in isolectin B(4)-positive and -negative small dorsal root ganglion neurons of rats</article-title>
<source/>Neurosci. Lett.
          <volume>368</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>96</fpage>
<lpage>101</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342142</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib66">
<element-citation id="sref66" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dolai</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gaisano</surname>
<given-names>H.Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Syntaxin-3 binds and regulates both R- and L-type calcium channels in insulin-secreting INS-1 832/13 cells</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <volume>11</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>e0147862</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26848587</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib67">
<element-citation id="sref67" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sastry</surname>
<given-names>B.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Induction of hippocampal long-term potentiation by alpha-tocopherol</article-title>
<source/>Brain Res.
          <volume>604</volume>
<year>1993</year>
<fpage>173</fpage>
<lpage>179</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8457845</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib68">
<element-citation id="sref68" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sastry</surname>
<given-names>B.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Impairment of long-term potentiation in rats fed with vitamin E-deficient diet</article-title>
<source/>Brain Res.
          <volume>681</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>196</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7552279</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib69">
<element-citation id="sref69" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yokota</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Igarashi</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Uchihara</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jishage</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tomita</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Inaba</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arita</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mizusawa</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arai</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Delayed-onset ataxia in mice lacking alpha -tocopherol transfer protein: model for neuronal degeneration caused by chronic oxidative stress</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A
          <volume>98</volume>
<year>2001</year>
<fpage>15185</fpage>
<lpage>15190</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752462</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib70">
<element-citation id="sref70" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yokota</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shiojiri</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gotoda</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arai</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Retinitis pigmentosa and ataxia caused by a mutation in the gene for the alpha-tocopherol-transfer protein</article-title>
<source/>N. Engl. J. Med.
          <volume>335</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>1770</fpage>
<lpage>1771</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8965888</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib71">
<element-citation id="sref71" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yokota</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Uchihara</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kumagai</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shiojiri</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pang</surname>
<given-names>J.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arita</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arai</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hayashi</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kiyosawa</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Okeda</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mizusawa</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Postmortem study of ataxia with retinitis pigmentosa by mutation of the alpha-tocopherol transfer protein gene</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurol. Neurosurg. Psychiatry
          <volume>68</volume>
<year>2000</year>
<fpage>521</fpage>
<lpage>525</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10727494</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib72">
<element-citation id="sref72" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yudin</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rohacs</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Inhibitory G(i/O)-coupled receptors in somatosensory neurons: potential therapeutic targets for novel analgesics</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Pain
          <volume>14</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<comment>1744806918763646</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib73">
<element-citation id="sref73" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhuang</surname>
<given-names>G.Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keeler</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bianchi</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>E.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erasso</surname>
<given-names>D.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>J.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wiltshire</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Carbonic anhydrase-8 regulates inflammatory pain by inhibiting the ITPR1-cytosolic free calcium pathway</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <volume>10</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>e0118273</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25734498</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib74">
<element-citation id="sref74" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zingg</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vitamin E: a role in signal transduction</article-title>
<source/>Annu. Rev. Nutr.
          <volume>35</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>135</fpage>
<lpage>173</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26185977</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="appsec2" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplemental Information</title>
<p id="p0250">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
<caption>
<title>Document S1. Transparent Methods, Figures S1–S6, and Tables S2, S3, S5, S6, and S8</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2">
<caption>
<title>Table S1. Metadata and Sequencing Summary Statistics on Mice Using for Single-Cell RNA-Sequencing</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3">
<caption>
<title>Table S4. Differentially Expressed Transcripts (Gene, Log-Fold Change (FC), Raw p value and Corrected p Value (P<sub>FDR</sub>)) within Each DRG Subpopulation between SUPP vs. WT (Green), WT vs. DEF (Blue), and SUPP vs. DEF (Purple) Contrasts</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc3.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4">
<caption>
<title>Table S7. Differentially Expressed Pathways within Each DRG Subpopulation between SUPP vs. WT (Green), WT vs. DEF (Blue), and SUPP vs. DEF (Purple) Contrasts</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc4.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
<ack id="ack0010">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>Support for this work was provided by the <funding-source id="gs1">National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (NIH) to C.J.F. (K01OD015134 and L40 TR001136). ENY was supported by (NIH: AG051443, DC015135, AG060504, and DC016099). Support for sequencing was provided by the <funding-source id="gs2">University of California Davis Genome Center</funding-source>. We thank Dr. Isaac Pessah for his careful review of this manuscript.</p>
<sec id="sec5">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p id="p0235">CJF and ENY were responsible for the conceptualization, funding acquisition, methodology, investigation, formal analysis, resources, and writing of the manuscript. J.P., M.K., S.P., M.H.B., M.P.F., and J.H.L. contributed to the study and analysis of results, and B.D.J. and M.S. contributed to the informatics methodology and analysis of results. All authors have reviewed the final manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6" sec-type="COI-statement">
<title>Declaration of Interests</title>
<p id="p0240">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supplementary-material" id="appsec1">
<p id="p0245">Supplemental Information can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0015" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2019.10.064">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2019.10.064</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>