<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="review-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Can J Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Can J Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpa</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Canadian Journal of Psychiatry. Revue Canadienne de Psychiatrie</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0706-7437</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1497-0015</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31530002</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6882070</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0706743719874168</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0706743719874168</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>In Review Series Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Gut Microbiome and Mental Health: What Should We Tell Our Patients?: Le microbiote Intestinal et la Santé Mentale : que Devrions-Nous dire à nos Patients?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7918-533X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Butler</surname>
<given-names>Mary I.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0706743719874168">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0706743719874168"></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mörkl</surname>
<given-names>Sabrina</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0706743719874168">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0706743719874168">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sandhu</surname>
<given-names>Kiran V.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0706743719874168">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cryan</surname>
<given-names>John F.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0706743719874168">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dinan</surname>
<given-names>Timothy G.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0706743719874168">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0706743719874168">
<label>1</label>Department of Psychiatry and APC Microbiome Institute, University College Cork, Ireland</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0706743719874168">
<label>2</label>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapeutic Medicine, Medical University of Graz, Austria</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0706743719874168">
<label>3</label>Department of Anatomy and Neuroscience and APC Microbiome Institute, University College Cork, Ireland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0706743719874168">Mary I. Butler, MD, Department of Psychiatry and APC Microbiome Institute, University College Cork, Cork, Ireland. Email: <email>mary.butler@ucc.ie</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn1-0706743719874168">
<p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>17</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>64</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>747</fpage>
<lpage>760</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Canadian Psychiatric Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The gut microbiome as a potential therapeutic target for mental illness is a hot topic in psychiatry. Trillions of bacteria reside in the human gut and have been shown to play a crucial role in gut–brain communication through an influence on neural, immune, and endocrine pathways. Patients with various psychiatric disorders including depression, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, and autism spectrum disorder have been shown to have significant differences in the composition of their gut microbiome. Enhancing beneficial bacteria in the gut, for example, through the use of probiotics, prebiotics, or dietary change, has the potential to improve mood and reduce anxiety in both healthy people and patient groups. Much attention is being given to this subject in the general media, and patients are becoming increasingly interested in the potential to treat mental illness with microbiome-based therapies. It is imperative that those working with people with mental illness are aware of the rationale and current evidence base for such treatment strategies. In this review, we provide an overview of the gut microbiome, what it is, and what it does in relation to gut–brain communication and psychological function. We describe the fundamental principles and basic techniques used in microbiome–gut–brain axis research in an accessible way for a clinician audience. We summarize the current evidence in relation to microbiome-based strategies for various psychiatric disorders and provide some practical advice that can be given to patients seeking to try a probiotic for mental health benefit.</p>
</abstract>
<trans-abstract xml:lang="fr">
<p>Le microbiote intestinal à titre de cible thérapeutique potentielle pour la maladie mentale est un sujet d’actualité en psychiatrie. Des milliards de bactéries résident dans l’intestin humain et il a été démontré qu’elles jouent un rôle essentiel dans la communication intestin-cerveau grâce à une influence sur les voies neuronales, immunes et endocriniennes. Les patients souffrant de divers troubles psychiatriques, notamment la dépression, le trouble bipolaire, la schizophrénie et le trouble du spectre de l’autisme se sont révélés avoir des différences significatives dans la composition de leur microbiote intestinal. Accroître les bactéries bénéfiques dans l’intestin, par exemple, en utilisant des probiotiques, des prébiotiques, ou un changement alimentaire, a le potentiel d’améliorer l’humeur et de réduire l’anxiété tant chez les personnes en santé que dans les groupes de patients. Ce sujet a fait l’objet d’une attention soutenue des médias généraux et les patients s’intéressent de plus en plus à la possibilité de traiter la maladie mentale à l’aide de thérapies basées sur le microbiote. Les personnes qui travaillent auprès de personnes souffrant de maladie mentale doivent absolument connaître la raison d’être et les données probantes actuelles de ces stratégies de traitement. Dans cette étude, nous présentons un aperçu du microbiote intestinal, ce qu’il est et ce qu’il fait en relation avec la communication intestin-cerveau et la fonction psychologique. Nous décrivons les principes fondamentaux et les techniques de base utilisés dans la recherche sur l’axe microbiote-intestin-cerveau de façon accessible à un auditoire clinicien. Nous résumons les données probantes actuelles relatives aux stratégies axées sur le microbiote pour divers troubles psychiatriques et prodiguons des conseils pratiques qui peuvent être transmis aux patients cherchant à essayer un probiotique pour un bénéfice de santé mentale.</p>
</trans-abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>microbiome</kwd>
<kwd>microbiota</kwd>
<kwd>biological psychiatry</kwd>
<kwd>psychobiotics</kwd>
<kwd>probiotics</kwd>
<kwd>depressive disorders</kwd>
<kwd>anxiety</kwd>
<kwd>gut–brain axis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>