<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NPJ Sci Food</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NPJ Sci Food</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>NPJ Science of Food</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2396-8370</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31815184</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6889268</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">58</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41538-019-0058-4</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A low-carbohydrate ketogenic diet induces the expression of very-low-density lipoprotein receptor in liver and affects its associated metabolic abnormalities</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5262-8057</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Okuda</surname>
<given-names>Tetsuya</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<phone>+81-11-857-8443</phone>
<email>t-okuda@aist.go.jp</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"></xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2230 7538</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.208504.b</institution-id><institution>Bio-Design Research Group, Bioproduction Research Institute, </institution><institution>National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology (AIST), </institution></institution-wrap>Tsukuba, Japan </aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>2</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>2</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<elocation-id>25</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>30</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement>
<license license-type="OpenAccess">
<license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="Par1">A low-carbohydrate ketogenic diet (LCKD) promotes the progression of hepatic steatosis in C57BL/6 wild-type mice, but improves the condition in leptin-deficient obese (<italic>ob/ob</italic>) mice. Here, we show a novel effect of LCKD associated with the conflicting effects on these mice. Gene expression microarray analyses showed that expression of the <italic>Vldlr</italic> gene, which encodes the very-low-density lipoprotein receptor (VLDLR), was induced in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice. Although the VLDLR is not normally expressed in the liver, the LCKD led to VLDLR expression in both <italic>ob/ob</italic> and wild-type mice. To clarify this effect on VLDL dynamics, we analyzed the lipid content of serum lipoproteins and found a marked decrease in VLDL-triglycerides only in LCKD-fed wild-type mice. Further analyses suggested that transport of triglycerides via VLDL from the liver to extrahepatic tissues was inhibited by LCKD-induced hepatic VLDLR expression, but rescued under conditions of leptin deficiency.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject">
<title>Subject terms</title>
<kwd>Obesity</kwd>
<kwd>Nutrition</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id>
<institution>MEXT | Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS)</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>15H02907</award-id>
<award-id>19K11810</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name>
<surname>Okuda</surname>
<given-names>Tetsuya</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
<meta-value>© The Author(s) 2019</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="Par2">Consumption of low-carbohydrate ketogenic diets (LCKDs) has been shown to have diverse beneficial effects in promoting health and alleviating pathologic conditions. For example, LCKDs exhibit antiepileptic effects,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> promote weight loss in obesity,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> and enhance control of type 2 diabetes mellitus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> LCKDs also reportedly have beneficial effects in patients with autism,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> cardiomyopathy,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> neurodegenerative diseases,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> and cancer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> The effective and safe use of LCKDs based on scientific evidence has contributed to both health promotion and disease treatment; however, the molecular mechanisms underlying the beneficial effects of LCKDs in vivo remain largely unknown.</p>
<p id="Par3">As a clinical trial demonstrated that restricting carbohydrate intake can reduce intrahepatic triglyceride levels,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> increased research attention has focused on the use of LCKDs in treating liver steatosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> However, children with epilepsy have been shown to develop liver steatosis with long-term consumption of a LCKD;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> thus, careful investigation of this effect is needed. A number of studies using rodent models have analyzed the role of LCKDs in the development of liver steatosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> Most of these studies used a common LCKD for rodents (Bio-Serv F3666),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> with subsequent development of steatosis observed in the liver of the LCKD-fed mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> However, surprisingly, we found that the F3666 diet had a dramatic preventative effect on the progression of liver steatosis in juvenile leptin-deficient obese (<italic>ob/ob</italic>) mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> We found that the underlying mechanism involves suppression of de novo triglyceride synthesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> This LCKD also suppresses de novo triglyceride synthesis in C57BL/6J (wild-type) mice that develop liver steatosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> These conflicting results suggest that the beneficial effect of the LCKD on liver steatosis in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice is regulated by an as yet unknown mechanism that is non-functional in wild-type mice.</p>
<p id="Par4">To clarify the underlying mechanism of these effects, we analyzed several molecular parameters in the liver of LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice and found a novel effect of the LCKD in up-regulating expression of the very-low-density lipoprotein receptor (VLDLR) in the liver. Although this receptor is expressed only minimally in the liver,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> LCKD feeding significantly up-regulated VLDLR expression in the liver of <italic>ob/ob</italic> and wild-type mice. Further analyses showed that VLDL-triglyceride levels were significantly lower in the serum of LCKD-fed wild-type mice. In addition, serum activity of lipoprotein lipase (LPL), which mediates triglyceride uptake from VLDL into extrahepatic tissues,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> was also down-regulated. In contrast, marked release of VLDL-triglycerides was observed in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, whereas LPL activity was maintained. These alterations in both strains were correlated with the conflicting liver steatosis phenotypes.</p>
<p id="Par5">The results of our study suggest that the transport of triglycerides via VLDL from the liver to extrahepatic tissues is inhibited by LCKD-induced hepatic VLDLR up-regulation under low LPL activity, whereas this inhibition of triglyceride transport is rescued under conditions of leptin deficiency.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="Sec3">
<title>Characterization of liver phenotypes in LCKD-fed mice</title>
<p id="Par6">Wild-type and <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice of the inbred strain C57BL/6J were used in this study and fed the Bio-Serv F3666 LCKD. F3666 is a very-low-carbohydrate, low-protein, high-fat ketogenic diet developed to induce efficient production of ketone bodies in rodents.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> In <italic>ob/ob</italic> mutant mice fed a diet of regular chow, hyperglycemia typically develops at ~10 weeks of age.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> Our initial goal was to reverse this phenotype via feeding mice the LCKD and analyze the diet’s effects on tissues at the molecular level. The mice were fed the LCKD over the period 5–12 weeks of age in the dietary experiment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> We found that the LCKD feeding effectively reversed the hyperglycemic phenotype in female <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice during this period and therefore employed these conditions in subsequent experiments.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> The average blood glucose levels during the experimental period were as follows: chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 194.30 ± 43.78 mg dl<sup>−1</sup>; LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 106.96 ± 26.41 mg dl<sup>−1</sup>; chow-fed wild-type mice, 154.08 ± 20.55 mg dl<sup>−1</sup>; and LCKD-fed wild-type mice, 114.30 ± 15.05 mg dl<sup>−1</sup>. Production of ketone bodies (β-hydroxybutyrate) was observed in both the <italic>ob/ob</italic> and wild-type mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup></p>
<p id="Par7">Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1a</xref> shows the morphology of the liver after 7 weeks of LCKD feeding. In <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, regular chow promoted significant steatosis associated with enlargement of the liver (left panel). Liver weight and total amount of triglycerides increased by more than 2-fold compared to values prior to the start of the experiment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1b</xref>). The LCKD is known to inhibit the progression of liver steatosis in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> Compared to chow-fed mice, the liver weight and total amount of triglycerides decreased by at least 70% in LCKD-fed mice (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1b</xref>). The average triglycerides (mg) to liver weight (g) ratios were as follows: chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 65.75 ± 24.7 mg g<sup>−1</sup>; and LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 48.79 ± 16.93 mg g<sup>−1</sup>. In contrast, the LCKD strongly promoted steatosis in wild-type mice. In LCKD-fed wild-type mice, the total amount of triglycerides in the liver has been shown to increase by more than 3-fold.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> Although liver weight remained unchanged in the present study, the organ became discolored as a result of excessive triglyceride accumulation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1a</xref>, right panel). The average triglycerides (mg) to liver weight (g) ratios were as follows: chow-fed wild-type mice, 19.17 ± 5.68 mg g<sup>−1</sup>; and LCKD-fed wild-type mice, 63.65 ± 16.44 mg g<sup>−1</sup>. In both strains, body weight gain and diet intake (kcal per day) were similar in the chow- and LCKD-fed groups during the experimental period.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> Although LCKD feeding improved the steatosis associated with enlargement of the liver, LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice became obese to the same degree as chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> The average final body weights were as follows: chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 53.16 ± 2.45 g; LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 52.47 ± 3.45 g; chow-fed wild-type mice, 19.16 ± 1.79 g; and LCKD-fed wild-type mice, 17.87 ± 2.02 g. The average caloric intake during the experimental period was as follows: chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 18.56 ± 0.4 kcal per day; LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, 17.27 ± 2.43 kcal per day; chow-fed wild-type mice, 10.48 ± 0.46 kcal per day; and LCKD-fed wild-type mice, 10.41 ± 1.5 kcal per day.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Effect of LCKD feeding on liver phenotypes. <bold>a</bold> Morphology of the liver after 7 weeks of feeding. <bold>b</bold> Wet weight (<italic>n</italic> = 11–13) and total triglyceride levels (<italic>n</italic> = 5–6) in the liver. <bold>c</bold> Real-time PCR analysis of expression of the <italic>Vldlr</italic> gene (<italic>n</italic> = 6). The relative expression level is shown as the ratio relative to expression of the internal standard (<italic>Eef1a1</italic>). Statistical significance was assessed using the two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic> test. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, chow-fed vs. LCKD-fed. Black squares and bars, regular chow-fed mice; gray squares and bars, LCKD-fed mice. Mean ± SD</p></caption><graphic id="d29e511" xlink:href="41538_2019_58_Fig1_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec4">
<title>LCKD effect on hepatic gene expression</title>
<p id="Par8">A gene expression microarray analysis was conducted to elucidate the molecular mechanism underlying the improvement of liver steatosis in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice. Data for all genes detected as specific signals were compared with data for mice fed the regular chow (<italic>n</italic> = 3) and deposited in the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO; accession number GSE115342). The overall features of the results have been published elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup></p>
<p id="Par9">A novel result observed in the present study was significant up-regulation of the <italic>Vldlr</italic> gene, which encodes the VLDLR. The microarray analysis revealed significant up-regulation (log<sup>2</sup> ratio [LCKD/chow] of +1.78; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) of <italic>Vldlr</italic>, which was confirmed in validation experiments using real-time PCR (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1c</xref>) with a greater number of samples (<italic>n</italic> = 6). No apparent effects on other factors associated with VLDL metabolism were observed in this experiment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec5">
<title>Effect of the LCKD on induction of VLDLR in the liver</title>
<p id="Par10">As VLDL regulates the release of triglycerides from the liver to the blood stream,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> we expected that up-regulation of <italic>Vldlr</italic> would correlate with the liver phenotype in LCKD-fed mice. Immunoblot analysis showed that VLDLR, which is not normally expressed in the liver,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> was detected in the liver of mice fed the LCKD (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). However, the induction of VLDLR expression was observed in both <italic>ob/ob</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2a</xref>) and wild-type (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2b</xref>) mice, indicating that this effect is not specific to <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice. Although individual differences were observed, further statistical analyses indicated that the effect was associated with the LCKD (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2c</xref>). The statistical analyses also revealed that the level of VLDLR expression in LCKD-fed wild-type mice was higher than that in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Immunoblot analysis of VLDLR in the liver. Representative images of immunoblotting of VLDLR in the liver of individual <italic>ob/ob</italic>
<bold>a</bold> or wild-type <bold>b</bold> mice (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Actin is shown as an internal standard. Band intensities were analyzed as previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> to determine relative levels (<bold>c</bold>, VLDLR/actin). <italic>ob/ob</italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 16–17; wild-type, <italic>n</italic> = 6. Statistical significance was assessed using the two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic> test. **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001. Black squares and bars, regular chow-fed mice; gray squares and bars, LCKD-fed mice. Mean ± SD</p></caption><graphic id="d29e639" xlink:href="41538_2019_58_Fig2_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec6">
<title>Characterization of lipid content of lipoproteins and LPL activity in serum</title>
<p id="Par11">To clarify the effect of hepatic VLDLR on lipoprotein dynamics, we subsequently analyzed the lipid content of serum lipoproteins (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>). We found that levels of VLDL-triglycerides were markedly lower in LCKD-fed wild-type mice, but unchanged in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice. In contrast, VLDL-cholesterol levels were unchanged in LCKD-fed wild-type mice, but significantly lower in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice. These results indicate that the release of VLDL from the liver to the blood stream is not impaired in either LCKD-fed mouse strain; rather, only VLDL-mediated triglyceride release is specifically inhibited in LCKD-fed wild-type mice. The increase in LDL-cholesterol levels in LCKD-fed wild-type mice also supports the normal release of VLDL from the liver in these mice. In LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, the cholesterol content of the VLDL fraction was considerably lower than the triglyceride content, indicating that triglyceride-rich VLDL was generated in these mice. Furthermore, LDL-triglyceride levels were significantly higher in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, but unchanged in LCKD-fed wild-type mice, which indicates a difference between <italic>ob/ob</italic> and wild-type mice in terms of conversion from VLDL-triglycerides to LDL-triglycerides. As this process is mediated by LPL,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> we preliminarily measured the activity of LPL in the serum and found a significant decrease only in LCKD-fed wild-type mice (Supplementary Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1</xref>). In contrast, serum LPL activity was the same in LCKD- and regular chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, indicating that the LCKD-associated decrease in serum LPL activity is specific to wild-type mice. Statistical analyses also revealed that LPL activity in chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice was lower than that in chow-fed wild-type mice (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). However, LPL activity in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice was higher than that in LCKD-fed wild-type mice (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Serum lipoprotein lipid content</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th></th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Strain</th></tr><tr><th></th><th>
<italic>ob/ob</italic>
</th><th></th><th>Wild type</th><th></th></tr><tr><th>Diet</th><th>Chow</th><th>LCKD</th><th>Chow</th><th>LCKD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5">Parameters</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"> Triglyceride (mmol l<sup>−1</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td>  Total</td><td>1.23 ± 0.22</td><td>1.47 ± 0.30</td><td>1.30 ± 0.20</td><td>0.18 ± 0.03**</td></tr><tr><td>  CM</td><td>0.31 ± 0.06</td><td>0.08 ± 0.02*</td><td>0.14 ± 0.03</td><td>0.02 ± 0.005**</td></tr><tr><td>  VLDL</td><td>0.58 ± 0.11</td><td>0.53 ± 0.14</td><td>0.97 ± 0.15</td><td>0.04 ± 0.01**</td></tr><tr><td>  LDL</td><td>0.23 ± 0.04</td><td>0.65 ± 0.17***</td><td>0.15 ± 0.02</td><td>0.10 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td>  HDL</td><td>0.08 ± 0.02</td><td>0.07 ± 0.02</td><td>0.04 ± 0.01</td><td>0.02 ± 0.002*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"> Cholesterol (mmol l<sup>−1</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td>  Total</td><td>4.08 ± 0.28</td><td>5.66 ± 0.18**</td><td>2.02 ± 0.11</td><td>5.08 ± 0.66**</td></tr><tr><td>  CM</td><td>0.05 ± 0.01</td><td>0.01 ± 0.001**</td><td>0.06 ± 0.01</td><td>0.04 ± 0.02</td></tr><tr><td>  VLDL</td><td>0.16 ± 0.03</td><td>0.09 ± 0.004***</td><td>0.44 ± 0.05</td><td>0.49 ± 0.25</td></tr><tr><td>  LDL</td><td>0.71 ± 0.06</td><td>0.81 ± 0.04</td><td>0.31 ± 0.02</td><td>1.34 ± 0.33*</td></tr><tr><td>  HDL</td><td>3.18 ± 0.24</td><td>4.66 ± 0.15**</td><td>1.21 ± 0.04</td><td>3.20 ± 0.12***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values include previously reported data for <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> Mean ± SD; <italic>n</italic> = 9 (<italic>ob/ob</italic>) or <italic>n</italic> = 6 (wild type). Statistical significance was assessed using the two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic> test, with significance defined as follows: *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, regular chow-fed vs. LCKD-fed mice</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="Par12">A novel effect of the LCKD on induction of VLDLR expression was found in the liver, where this receptor is not normally expressed. Previous studies reported that the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor α agonist fenofibrate promotes not only hepatic VLDLR expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> but also steatosis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> which is in agreement with the phenotype of the LCKD-fed wild-type mice in the present study. The induction of hepatic VLDLR expression by fenofibrate or over-expression of VLDLR decreases triglyceride-rich VLDL levels via triglyceride clearance by the liver,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> which can promote the development of liver steatosis.</p>
<p id="Par13">F3666 is a commonly used LCKD for rodents, and several recent studies have examined the effects of the low amounts of choline and protein in this diet.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> A lack of sufficient choline is associated with the development of steatosis in the liver,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> which impairs hepatic triglyceride secretion due to an absence of phosphatidylcholine synthesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> Choline supplementation can improve this pathologic condition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> The low protein content of the F3666 diet increases the expression of several genes in the liver, but this effect is attenuated by methionine supplementation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> These observations suggest that the low choline and protein content of the F3666 diet also played a role in the effects observed in our model. However, in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice in our model, the F3666 diet prevented the progression of liver steatosis observed in chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref>). Furthermore, the F3666 diet used in our study contained an abundance of choline-containing phospholipids (phosphatidylcholines and sphingomyelins, 5.8 ± 0.2 g kg<sup>−1</sup>), and serum levels of choline-containing phospholipids in F3666-fed mice were also significantly higher than the levels in chow-fed mice (Supplementary Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S2</xref>). These results indicate that choline was supplied to peripheral tissues in sufficient amounts in the mice using this study, and therefore, choline levels had a minimal effect on development of steatosis.</p>
<p id="Par14">We also observed VLDLR expression in the liver of LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, in which the hyperphagic phenotype can compensate for the low protein content of the LCKD. This result indicates that the low protein content of the diet is not associated with increased VLDLR expression. As the low protein content of the F3666 diet plays an important role in the generation of ketone bodies in rodents,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> we conclude that the low-carbohydrate and high-fat/ketogenic properties of the LCKD induce hepatic VLDLR expression.</p>
<p id="Par15">Based on the results of our present and previous studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref> illustrates the dynamics and metabolism of VLDL in LCKD-fed mice and presents a working hypothesis of how VLDLR and LPL affect VLDL-triglyceride kinetics. In LCKD-fed wild-type mice, induction of hepatic VLDLR expression and decreased serum LPL activity inhibit the transport of triglycerides by VLDL from the liver to extrahepatic tissues, ultimately promoting steatosis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3b</xref>). LCKD-induced VLDLR expression promotes triglyceride clearance from VLDL in the liver and the progression of liver steatosis. As LPL activity is necessary for the clearance of triglycerides from VLDL in peripheral tissues,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> decreased LPL activity slows triglyceride transport from the liver to peripheral tissues and promotes the development of liver steatosis. In LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, the generation of triglyceride-rich VLDL and maintained LPL activity promote the transport of triglycerides from the liver to extrahepatic tissues, ultimately leading to improvement of steatosis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3d</xref>). Maintained LPL activity promotes the clearance of triglycerides from VLDL in peripheral tissues, which can accelerate triglyceride transport from the liver to peripheral tissues and contribute to the improvement of liver steatosis. LCKD-induced VLDLR expression has a minimal effect on triglyceride-rich VLDL, which is specifically generated in the <italic>ob/ob</italic> strain. LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice became obese to the same degree as chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, in agreement with the observed effective transport of VLDL-triglycerides from the liver to extrahepatic tissues in these mice.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Schematic illustrations of VLDL dynamics and metabolism in LCKD-fed mice. Overview of VLDL dynamics and metabolism in chow-fed wild-type <bold>a</bold>, LCKD-fed wild-type mice <bold>b</bold>, chow-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice <bold>c</bold>, and LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice <bold>d</bold>. The size and number of objects are drawn to reflect the experimental results. The working hypothesis regarding the effect of hepatic VLDLR on VLDL is as follows: (i) in wild-type mice, LCKD induces hepatic VLDLR expression, which inhibits triglyceride (TG) secretion via VLDL; (ii) in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, LCKD induces hepatic VLDLR expression, whereas the VLDLR does not function for TG-rich VLDL, which is specifically generated in the <italic>ob/ob</italic> strain. Ch, cholesterol; FA, fatty acid</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1094" xlink:href="41538_2019_58_Fig3_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par16">In <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, LCKD feeding induces the production of triglyceride-rich VLDL, which has a long plasma residence time due to slow catabolism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> This property indicates that triglyceride-rich VLDL is readily delivered to extrahepatic tissues even though VLDLR expression is induced in the liver. As an absence of hepatic leptin signaling leads to elevated triglyceride levels in VLDL particles,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> the production of triglyceride-rich VLDL is likely associated with leptin deficiency in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> The maintenance of LPL activity in LCKD-fed <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice could also accelerate the release of triglycerides to extrahepatic tissues. As leptin regulates LPL production and activity in the tissues,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> maintenance of LPL activity is also likely associated with leptin deficiency in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup></p>
<p id="Par17">Based on these observations, we conclude that the transport of triglycerides via VLDL from the liver to extrahepatic tissues is inhibited by LCKD-induced hepatic VLDLR expression under conditions of low LPL activity. As this inhibition of triglyceride transport is rescued in leptin-deficient mice, regulating VLDL metabolism by hepatic VLDLR, LPL, and leptin may represent a new therapeutic strategy for preventing diet-induced liver steatosis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec8">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="Sec9">
<title>Animals and dietary studies</title>
<p id="Par18">Dietary studies using female <italic>ob/ob</italic> and wild-type mice (B6.Cg-<italic>Lep</italic><sup><italic>ob</italic></sup>/J and C57BL6J, Charles River Laboratories Japan, Yokohama, Japan) were conducted as reported previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> CE-2 (CLEA Japan, Tokyo, Japan), composed of 58.2% carbohydrate, 12.6% fat, and 29.2% protein by calories, was used as regular chow. F3666 (Bio-Serv, Frenchtown, NJ) was used as the LCKD, which is composed of 1.7% carbohydrate, 93.9% fat, and 4.4% protein by calories. Five-week-old mice were raised on either regular chow or the LCKD for 7 weeks. During this period, the blood glucose level was monitored at 3:00 p.m. on the first day of every week, and tissue samples were collected at the end of the dietary study. Blood glucose and β-hydroxybutyrate levels were determined using venous blood collected from the tail vein with a Precision Xceed Monitoring System (Abbott Laboratories, Abbott Park, IL, USA).</p>
<p id="Par19">The Committee for Experiments Involving Animals of the National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology approved all animal experiments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec10">
<title>Gene expression analysis</title>
<p id="Par20">Preparation of total RNA and gene expression analyses were conducted as reported previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> Agilent Expression Microarray analysis for gene expression profiling in tissues was conducted by Takara Bio (Shiga, Japan). The resulting microarray data were analyzed using the Aqua microarray viewer and Aqua <italic>t</italic> test (Takara Bio) and deposited in the GEO under accession number GSE115342. Relative quantification of target gene expression by real-time PCR was performed using a Light Cycler® 480 II system (Roche, Penzberg, Germany) with the following <italic>Vldlr</italic> gene-specific primers: forward, 5′-gcccgttctactcagtgtatcc-3′; reverse, 5′-gaactcatctgcactacatgttatgtt-3′ (accession number of the <italic>Vldlr</italic> gene: NM_013703, GenBank). Reactions were performed using a KAPA SYBR® FAST qPCR Kit (KAPA Biosystems, Wilmington, MA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. As it is stably expressed in the liver,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>
<italic>Eef1a1</italic> was chosen as a housekeeping gene and used as the internal reference for subsequent real-time PCR analyses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec11">
<title>Immunoblot analysis</title>
<p id="Par21">Protein extraction and immunoblot analyses were conducted according to a previously reported method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> using an anti-VLDLR antibody (AF2258; Bio-Techne, Minneapolis, MN, USA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec12">
<title>Lipoprotein analysis</title>
<p id="Par22">The triglyceride and cholesterol profiles of serum lipoproteins were determined using a high-sensitivity lipoprotein profiling system employing high-performance liquid chromatography (Skylight Biotech Inc., Akita, Japan), as reported previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec13">
<title>Measurement of LPL activity</title>
<p id="Par23">Serum LPL activity (units ml<sup>−1</sup>) was measured using an LPL Activity Assay Kit (Cell Biolabs, Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec14">
<title>Analysis of choline-containing phospholipids in the F3666 LCKD and serum</title>
<p id="Par24">The content of choline-containing phospholipids was determined using a Phosphatidylcholine Assay Kit (Phospholipids C, FUJIFILM Wako Pure Chemical Corp., Osaka, Japan) according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec15">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p id="Par25">After determination of variance using the <italic>F</italic> test, statistical significance was evaluated using the two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic> test, with statistical significance defined as follows: *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec16">
<title>Reporting summary</title>
<p id="Par26">Further information on research design is available in the <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">Nature Research Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary information</title>
<sec id="Sec17">
<p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41538_2019_58_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary figure S1, S2, S3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41538_2019_58_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Reporting summary checklist</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<sec>
<title>Supplementary information</title>
<p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41538-019-0058-4.</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>This work was supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number 15H02907 and 19K11810. We thank A. Fukui and A. Kato for technical assistance.</p>
</ack>
<notes notes-type="author-contribution">
<title>Author contributions</title>
<p>T.O. conceived, designed, performed, analyzed the experiments, and wrote the paper.</p>
</notes>
<notes notes-type="data-availability">
<title>Data availability</title>
<p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available in the GEO repository under accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115342">GSE115342</ext-link> or from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
</notes>
<notes notes-type="COI-statement">
<title>Competing interests</title>
<p id="Par27">The author declares no competing interests.</p>
</notes>
<ref-list id="Bib1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CR1">
<label>1.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gano</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rho</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ketogenic diets, mitochondria, and neurological diseases</article-title>
<source/>J. Lipid Res.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>2211</fpage>
<lpage>2228</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.R048975</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24847102</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR2">
<label>2.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shai</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Weight loss with a low-carbohydrate, Mediterranean, or low-fat diet</article-title>
<source/>N. Engl. J. Med.
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>359</volume>
<fpage>229</fpage>
<lpage>241</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0708681</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635428</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR3">
<label>3.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Westman</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tondt</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maguire</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yancy</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Implementing a low-carbohydrate, ketogenic diet to manage type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>
<source/>Expert Rev. Endocrinol. Metab.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>263</fpage>
<lpage>272</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17446651.2018.1523713</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30289048</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR4">
<label>4.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ruskin</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ketogenic diet improves core symptoms of autism in BTBR mice</article-title>
<source/>PLoS ONE
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>e65021</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065021</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23755170</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR5">
<label>5.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krebs</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lethal mitochondrial cardiomyopathy in a hypomorphic Med30 mouse mutant is ameliorated by ketogenic diet</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>19678</fpage>
<lpage>19682</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1117835108</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22106289</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR6">
<label>6.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Weber, D. D. et al. Ketogenic diet in the treatment of cancer—where do we stand? <italic>Mol. Metab</italic>. in press. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2212877819304272?via%3Dihub">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2212877819304272?via%3Dihub</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR7">
<label>7.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Browning</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Short-term weight loss and hepatic triglyceride reduction: evidence of a metabolic advantage with dietary carbohydrate restriction</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>1048</fpage>
<lpage>1052</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.110.007674</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21367948</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR8">
<label>8.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schugar</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Low-carbohydrate ketogenic diets, glucose homeostasis, and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Opin. Clin. Nutr. Metab. Care
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>374</fpage>
<lpage>380</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCO.0b013e3283547157</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22617564</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR9">
<label>9.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arslan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Is ketogenic diet treatment hepatotoxic for children with intractable epilepsy?</article-title>
<source/>Seizure
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>32</fpage>
<lpage>38</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2016.10.024</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27866088</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR10">
<label>10.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Badman</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A very low carbohydrate ketogenic diet improves glucose tolerance in <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice independently of weight loss</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab.
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>297</volume>
<fpage>E1197</fpage>
<lpage>E1204</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00357.2009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19738035</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR11">
<label>11.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jornayvaz</surname>
<given-names>FR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A high-fat, ketogenic diet causes hepatic insulin resistance in mice, despite increasing energy expenditure and preventing weight gain</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab.
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>299</volume>
<fpage>E808</fpage>
<lpage>E815</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00361.2010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20807839</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR12">
<label>12.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Garbow</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Hepatic steatosis, inflammation, and ER stress in mice maintained long term on a very low-carbohydrate ketogenic diet</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Physiol. Gastrointest. Liver Physiol.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>300</volume>
<fpage>G956</fpage>
<lpage>G967</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00539.2010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21454445</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR13">
<label>13.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Okuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morita</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A very low carbohydrate ketogenic diet prevents the progression of hepatic steatosis caused by hyperglycemia in a juvenile obese mouse model</article-title>
<source/>Nutr. Diabetes
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>e50</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nutd.2012.24</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23169538</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR14">
<label>14.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schugar</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Role of choline deficiency in the fatty liver phenotype of mice fed a low protein, very low carbohydrate ketogenic diet</article-title>
<source/>PLoS ONE
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>e74806</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074806</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24009777</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR15">
<label>15.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pissios</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Methionine and choline regulate the metabolic phenotype of a ketogenic diet</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Metab.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>306</fpage>
<lpage>313</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molmet.2013.07.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24049742</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR16">
<label>16.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Okuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morita</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A very low carbohydrate ketogenic diet increases hepatic glycosphingolipids related to regulation of insulin signaling</article-title>
<source/>J. Funct. Foods
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>70</fpage>
<lpage>74</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2015.11.040</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR17">
<label>17.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The very low-density lipoprotein (VLDL) receptor: characterization and functions as a peripheral lipoprotein receptor</article-title>
<source/>J. Atheroscler. Thromb.
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>200</fpage>
<lpage>208</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5551/jat.11.200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15356379</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR18">
<label>18.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kawano</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of hepatic triglyceride accumulation in non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>
<source/>J. Gastroenterol.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>434</fpage>
<lpage>441</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00535-013-0758-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23397118</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR19">
<label>19.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bough</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eagles</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A ketogenic diet increases the resistance to pentylenetetrazole-induced seizures in the rat</article-title>
<source/>Epilepsia
          <year>1999</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>138</fpage>
<lpage>143</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1157.1999.tb02066.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9952258</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR20">
<label>20.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coleman</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hummel</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The influence of genetic background on the expression of the obese (<italic>Ob</italic>) gene in the mouse</article-title>
<source/>Diabetologia
          <year>1973</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>287</fpage>
<lpage>293</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01221856</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4588246</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR21">
<label>21.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Okuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A low-carbohydrate ketogenic diet promotes ganglioside synthesis via the transcriptional regulation of ganglioside metabolism-related genes</article-title>
<source/>Sci. Rep.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>7627</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-43952-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31110277</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR22">
<label>22.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Upregulation of hepatic VLDLR via PPARα is required for the triglyceride-lowering effect of fenofibrate</article-title>
<source/>J. Lipid Res.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>1622</fpage>
<lpage>1633</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.M041988</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24899625</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR23">
<label>23.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor α activation induces hepatic steatosis, suggesting an adverse effect</article-title>
<source/>PLoS ONE
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e99245</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099245</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24926685</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR24">
<label>24.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tacken</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>LDL receptor deficiency unmasks altered VLDL triglyceride metabolism in VLDL receptor transgenic and knockout mice</article-title>
<source/>J. Lipid Res.
          <year>2000</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>2055</fpage>
<lpage>2062</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11108739</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR25">
<label>25.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Corbin</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zeisel</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Choline metabolism provides novel insights into nonalcoholic fatty liver disease and its progression</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Opin. Gastroenterol.
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>159</fpage>
<lpage>165</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOG.0b013e32834e7b4b</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22134222</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR26">
<label>26.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Packard</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shepherd</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lipoprotein heterogeneity and apolipoprotein B metabolism</article-title>
<source/>Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol.
          <year>1997</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>3542</fpage>
<lpage>3556</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.ATV.17.12.3542</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9437204</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR27">
<label>27.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Demant</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Packard</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>In vivo studies of VLDL metabolism and LDL heterogeneity</article-title>
<source/>Eur. Heart J.
          <year>1998</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>Suppl. H</issue>
<fpage>H7</fpage>
<lpage>H10</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9717058</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR28">
<label>28.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>FK</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A role for hepatic leptin signaling in lipid metabolism via altered very low density lipoprotein composition and liver lipase activity in mice</article-title>
<source/>Hepatology
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>543</fpage>
<lpage>554</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.26043</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22941940</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR29">
<label>29.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Positional cloning of the mouse obese gene and its human homologue</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>1994</year>
<volume>372</volume>
<fpage>425</fpage>
<lpage>432</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/372425a0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984236</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR30">
<label>30.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Donahoo</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Leptin increases skeletal muscle lipoprotein lipase and postprandial lipid metabolism in mice</article-title>
<source/>Metabolism
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>438</fpage>
<lpage>443</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2010.03.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20494377</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR31">
<label>31.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Okuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fukui</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morita</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered expression of <italic>O</italic>-GlcNAc-modified proteins in a mouse model whose glycemic status is controlled by a low carbohydrate ketogenic diet</article-title>
<source/>Glycoconj. J.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>781</fpage>
<lpage>789</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10719-013-9482-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793825</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>