<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="article-commentary" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Epilepsy Curr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Epilepsy Curr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spepi</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Epilepsy Currents</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1535-7597</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1535-7511</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31601119</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6891186</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1535759719879418</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1535759719879418</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Current Literature in Basic Science</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>When Monogenic Isn’t Monogenic—Unravelling the Oligogenic
Architecture of the Developmental and Epileptic Encephalopathies</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2311-2174</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Scheffer</surname>
<given-names>Ingrid E.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>Jianxiang</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<season>Nov-Dec</season>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>417</fpage>
<lpage>419</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work as
published without adaptation or alteration, without further permission
provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open
Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>November-December 2019</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-1535759719879418" orientation="portrait" position="float"><p>
<bold>Comprehensive Analysis of Coding Variants Highlights Genetic
Complexity in Developmental and Epileptic Encephalopathy</bold>
</p><p>Takata A, Nakashima M, Saitsu H, et al. <italic>Nat Commun</italic>.
2019;10(1):2506. doi:10.1038/s41467-019-10482-9. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/naturecommunications">www.nature.com/naturecommunications</ext-link>.</p><p>Although there are many known Mendelian genes linked to epileptic or
developmental and epileptic encephalopathy (EE/DEE), its genetic
architecture is not fully explained. Here, we address this
incompleteness by analyzing exomes of 743 EE/DEE cases and 2366
controls. We observe that damaging ultra-rare variants (dURVs) unique to
an individual are significantly overrepresented in EE/DEE, both in known
EE/DEE genes and the other non-EE/DEE genes. Importantly, enrichment of
dURVs in non-EE/DEE genes is significant, even in the subset of cases
with diagnostic dURVs (<italic>P</italic> = 0.000215), suggesting
oligogenic contribution of non-EE/DEE gene dURVs. Gene-based analysis
identifies exome-wide significant (<italic>P</italic> = 2.04 Å∼
10<sup>−6</sup>) enrichment of damaging de novo mutations in NF1, a
gene primarily linked to neurofibromatosis, in infantile spasm. Together
with accumulating evidence for roles of oligogenic or modifier variants
in severe neurodevelopmental disorders, our results highlight genetic
complexity in EE/DEE and indicate that EE/DEE is not an aggregate of
simple Mendelian disorders.</p></boxed-text>
</p>
<sec id="section1-1535759719879418">
<title>Commentary</title>
<p>Our understanding of the etiologies of the developmental and epileptic
encephalopathies (DEEs) has exploded in recent years.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1535759719879418">1</xref></sup> Developmental and epileptic encephalopathies are the most severe group of
epilepsies, typically beginning in early life. They are characterized by frequent
uncontrolled seizures, often of multiple types, and developmental delay or
intellectual disability. A key concept underpinning the term “epileptic
encephalopathy” (EE) is the presence of frequent epileptiform activity that itself
contributes to developmental slowing or regression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1535759719879418">2</xref></sup> The term was recently expanded to include “developmental” in recognition that
many of the underlying etiologies of the DEEs result in developmental impairment in
their own right, with the superimposed EE process further adversely impacting an
individual’s development.</p>
<p>Until the advent of gene discovery in the DEEs, these were considered to be acquired
in origin. Next-generation sequencing now allows us to determine a causative
pathogenic variant in around 50% of patients, with most having a de novo pathogenic
variant. To date, the majority of pathogenic variants have been found in exons,
which make up the 1% of the genome that encodes proteins. What about the remaining
50% of unsolved patients? Increasing interest in intronic regions harboring
noncoding DNA is slowly revealing previously hidden mutations, such as poison exons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1535759719879418">3</xref></sup> and repeat expansions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1535759719879418">4</xref></sup> that explain a proportion of these cases.</p>
<p>Yet the genetic architecture of the DEEs is likely to be far more complex than
finding a single pathogenic variant might suggest. Clues to this complexity come
from the broad spectrum of severity seen in most monogenic DEEs. For example, the
prototypic genetic DEE, Dravet syndrome arises due to a <italic>SCN1A</italic>
mutation in more than 80% of cases. Dravet syndrome has a broad phenotypic spectrum
with half of the patients having severe intellectual disability, a third moderate
and the remainder mild intellectual disability. Even patients with the same mutation
may look surprisingly different. Dravet syndrome is associated with a range of
comorbidities, many of which occur in only some cases, such as a crouch gait. What
factors determine these differences in patients who share the same genetic etiology?
Simple answers such as the nature or location of the <italic>SCN1A</italic> mutation
have not answered these fundamental questions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1535759719879418">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>An elegant statistical molecular study of a large DEE/EE cohort by Japanese authors
has begun to reveal some tantalizing answers using a case–control approach. Takata
and colleagues analyzed 3109 exomes, including 743 DEE/EE cases and 2366 controls.
They sequenced the 1% of the human genome called the exome that encodes proteins. In
general, each human being has 22 000 variants in their exome, where his or her DNA
nucleotide sequence differs from the general population. The challenge is to
identify whether the variant is pathogenic, benign, or of unknown significance. The
authors analyzed both common and rare variants, with a focus on ultrarare variants
(URVs), which they defined as only occurring once in their cohort and not found in
population databases such as the Exome Aggregation Consortium, gnomAD, and the
Tohoku Medical Megabank Organisation. They identified a total of 169 014 and 42 974
variants in coding and noncoding regions, respectively. They acknowledge that their
restricted analysis based on their definition of URVs would miss recurrent
pathogenic variants in their cohort or the general population, and
disease-contributing variants in the general population; however, their approach
allowed an unbiased analysis to detect enrichment of rare deleterious variants.</p>
<p>Overall, they found an excess of damaging URVs (dURVs) in patients with DEE/EEs
compared to controls, both in known DEE/EE genes and in non-DEE/EE genes. Damaging
ultra-rare variants were defined as either null (nonsense, frameshift, splice site,
and read-through; resulting in loss-of-function) or consensus-damaging missense
variants, based on their prediction as damaging by multiple in silico prediction
algorithms. Although dURVs in DEE/EE genes were 10 times more frequent in cases than
controls, 39 dURVs were identified in controls emphasizing the importance of careful
genotype–phenotype analysis in all cases. Equally, the finding of dURVs in the 18
338 non-58 known DEE/EE genes highlights potential novel genes for DEEs. Somewhat
intriguingly, the enrichment of dURVs in non-DEE/EE genes was also observed in the
116 cases with a known causative pathogenic variant in one of the 58 known DEE/EE
genes. Their gene expression data analysis of various tissues and cell types
supported the role of the non-DEE/EE gene in brain development and function.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, they found pathogenic URVs in non-DEE/EE genes that have been
reported in other neurodevelopmental phenotypes such as autism spectrum disorder,
reinforcing the known overlap in the genetic basis of neurodevelopmental disorders.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1535759719879418">6</xref></sup> They suggest these may contribute to the oligogenic architecture of a
patient’s disorder, particularly in individuals who do not have a pathogenic URV in
a known DEE/EE gene.</p>
<p>They performed gene-based burden testing and found an exome-wide significant burden
of dURVs in well-known DEE/EE genes, <italic>CDKL5, STXBP1, SCN1A, SCN2A</italic>,
and <italic>KCNQ2</italic>. They also found overlap with genes identified in the
common epilepsies studied by EPI4K, particularly the genetic generalized epilepsies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1535759719879418">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>No single gene in the non-DEE/EE genes reached exome-wide significance; however, the
most enriched gene was <italic>NF1</italic>, known to cause neurofibromatosis,
followed by <italic>TRPM5, AP5B1, DNMT3L</italic>, and <italic>ARFGEF1</italic>.
They pursued the 3 cases with dURVs in <italic>NF1</italic>; all had arisen de novo
and each patient had infantile spasms, 2 with the stigmata of neurofibromatosis.
When analysed separately, <italic>NF1</italic> surpassed the exome-wide significance
threshold in the subset of probands with infantile spasms drawn from their overall
DEE cohort.</p>
<p>They interrogated their data set for a common exonic single nucleotide polymorphism
(SNP), defined as having a minor allele frequency of greater than 1%, without
success. They rightly point out that their sample size, albeit reasonably large, is
probably not sufficient to identify common exonic SNPs of small effect or
low-frequency SNPs of intermediate effect. This will require larger cohorts,
especially if we are to focus on specific epilepsy syndromes. Sample size remains a
critical issue for all aspects of cohort studies exploring the genetic architecture
of common diseases such as epilepsy. International consortia, such as EPI25, are
bringing together larger patient groups.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1535759719879418">8</xref></sup> Their recent study of exome sequencing in 9170 patients with epilepsy showed
that there was an excess of ultrarare deleterious variation in constrained genes,
and known epilepsy genes, and a convergence of implicated genes across the DEEs,
genetic generalized epilepsies and nonacquired focal epilepsies. Although some of
the findings reflected those of Takata and colleagues, the EPI25 study highlights
the need for even larger data sets to unravel the complex genetic architecture of
the epilepsies.</p>
<p>So what does this mean? These findings suggest that these patients actually have at
least an oligogenic architecture for their DEEs, rather than being simple Mendelian
disorders. Equally though, these additional dURVs may not result in disease without
the accompanying pathogenic variant in a gene of major effect. Nevertheless, it is
likely that some patients with DEEs will have a polygenic basis. To date, this has
been too complex to unravel but, in the future, it is likely that we will be able to
drill down on those patients who may have a DEE due to 10 or even tens of genetic
variants, each of low effect, but contributing to a similarly devastating disease.
In considering the full gamut of etiologies, the impact of environmental factors on
an oligogenic or polygenic background is a challenge yet to be tackled.</p>
<p>These additional variants may be considered modifier genes likely influencing the
phenotypic picture, treatment responses, and prognosis. How do the additional dURVs
help us in the clinic? Probably not today, but in the not-too-distant future, they
may inform about efficacy and tolerability of specific antiepileptic drugs, the risk
and severity of comorbidities, risk of SUDEP, and long-term outcome.</p>
</sec>
<sig-block>
<sig>
<italic>By Ingrid E. Scheffer and Jianxiang Liao</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1535759719879418">
<p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Ingrid E. Scheffer <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1535759719879418-img1.jpg"></inline-graphic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2311-2174">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2311-2174</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1535759719879418">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McTague</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurian</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The genetic landscape of the epileptic
encephalopathies of infancy and childhood</article-title>. <source/>Lancet
Neurol.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26597089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1535759719879418">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Capovilla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>ILAE classification of the epilepsies: Position paper of the ILAE
Commission for Classification and Terminology</article-title>.
<source/>Epilepsia.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28276062</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1535759719879418">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvill</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramamurthy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Aberrant inclusion of a poison exon causes Dravet syndrome and
related <italic>SCN1A</italic>-associated genetic
epilepsies</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1022</fpage>–<lpage>1029</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30526861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1535759719879418">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Expansions of intronic TTTCA and TTTTA repeats in benign adult
familial myoclonic epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29507423</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1535759719879418">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunklaus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reavey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuberi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prognostic, clinical and demographic features in
<italic>SCN1A</italic> mutation-positive Dravet
syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Brain.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>pt
8</issue>):<fpage>2329</fpage>–<lpage>2336</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22719002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1535759719879418">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Genes with de novo mutations are shared by four neuropsychiatric
disorders discovered from NPdenovo database</article-title>. <source/>Mol
Psychiatry.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25849321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1535759719879418">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">Epi4K consortium, Epilepsy Phenome/Genome
Project</collab>. <article-title>Ultra-rare genetic variation in common
epilepsies: a case-control sequencing study</article-title>. <source/>Lancet
Neurol.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28102150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1535759719879418">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">Epi25 Collaborative</collab>.
<article-title>Ultra-rare genetic variation in the epilepsies: a whole-exome
sequencing study of 17,606 individuals</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum
Genet.
<year>2019</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.
<comment>doi:10.1016/j.ajhg.2019.05.020</comment>
<comment>Epub 2019 Jul
18</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31327507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>