<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101461858</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">35583</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Autism Res</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Autism Res</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Autism research : official journal of the International Society for Autism Research</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1939-3792</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-3806</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31433576</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6927400</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aur.2194</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1063005</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interrelationship Between Cognitive Control, Anxiety, and Restricted and Repetitive Behaviors in Children with 22q11.2 Deletion Syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Uljarević</surname>
<given-names>Mirko</given-names>
</name>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8414-4209</contrib-id>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McCabe</surname>
<given-names>Kathryn L.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Angkustsiri</surname>
<given-names>Kathleen</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Simon</surname>
<given-names>Tony J.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hardan</surname>
<given-names>Antonio Y.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Stanford University, Stanford, California (M.U., A.Y.H.); Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and Health Sciences, The University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia (M.U.); Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of California, Davis, California (K.L.M., T.J.S.); MIND (Medical Investigation of Neurodevelopmental Disorders) Institute, University of California, Davis, California (K.L.M., K.A., T.J.S.); Department of Pediatrics, University of California, Davis, Sacramento, California (K.A.)</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">Address for correspondence and reprints: Mirko Uljarević, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Stanford University, 401 Quarry Road, Stanford, CA 94305-5719. <email>mirkoulj@stanford.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN1">
<p id="P19">Conflict of Interest</p>
<p id="P20">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interests to declare.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>13</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>21</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>1737</fpage>
<lpage>1744</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/aur.2194-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Restricted and repetitive behaviors (RRB) are common in individuals with 22q11.2 microdeletion syndrome (22q11.2DS), yet the underlying mechanisms of these behaviors remain poorly characterized. In the present pilot investigation, we aimed to further our understanding of RRB in 22q11.2DS by exploring their relationship with cognitive control and anxiety as well as with sex, chronological age, and full-scale IQ. Parents of 38 children with 22q11.2DS (17 females; <italic>M</italic><sub>age</sub> = 11.15 years, <italic>SD</italic> = 2.46) completed the Social Communication Questionnaire as a measure of RRB and social and communication (SC) problems and the Behavioral Assessment System for Children-2 as a measure of anxiety and cognitive control. Higher RRB scores were significantly associated with higher anxiety levels (<italic>r</italic> = 0.44, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006), more impairments in cognitive control (<italic>r</italic> = 0.56, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and higher SC scores (<italic>r</italic> = 0.43, <italic>P</italic> = 0.011). In the first step of the hierarchical regression model, anxiety accounted for 24.5% of variance (<italic>F</italic> = 10.05, <italic>P</italic> = 0.003); cognitive control accounted for an additional 18.1% of variance (<italic>Fchange</italic> = 11.15, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in the second step; SC score accounted for only 0.8% of additional variance in the third step (<italic>Fchange</italic> = 0.40, <italic>P</italic> = 0.53). The final model explained 43.4% of variance (<italic>F</italic> = 7.42, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001), with cognitive control as a unique independent predictor of RRB score (<italic>t</italic> = 2.52, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01). The current study provides the first exploration of the cognitive control—anxiety—RRB link in individuals with 22q11.2DS and points to cognitive control as a potentially viable target for treatments aimed at reducing RRB.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary" id="ABS2">
<title>Lay Summary:</title>
<p id="P2">People with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome show high levels of repetitive behaviors, however, the previous research has not explored why people with this syndrome exhibit high rates of repetitive behaviors. Understanding the reasons for the high levels of repetitive behaviors is important given that these behaviors can be highly impairing. Our study found that repetitive behaviors were associated with impaired ability to self-regulate and high levels of anxiety. These findings need to be further replicated; however, they are important as they suggest potentially promising ways of reducing these behaviors.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>22q11.2DS</kwd>
<kwd>repetitive behaviors</kwd>
<kwd>anxiety</kwd>
<kwd>cognitive control</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>