<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="systematic-review" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Genet.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Frontiers in Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1664-8021</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31921276</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6930680</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2019.01137</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Genetics</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Systematic Review</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Childhood-Onset Schizophrenia: A Systematic Overview of Its Genetic Heterogeneity From Classical Studies to the Genomic Era</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>Arnaud</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/754390" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Drozd</surname>
<given-names>Malgorzata Marta</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/502326" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thümmler</surname>
<given-names>Susanne</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/370392" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dor</surname>
<given-names>Emmanuelle</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Capovilla</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Askenazy</surname>
<given-names>Florence</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/773987" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bardoni</surname>
<given-names>Barbara</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/95523" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup><institution>University Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, Children’s, Hospitals of NICE CHU-Lenval</institution>, <addr-line>Nice</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup><institution>CoBTek, Université Côte d’Azur</institution>, <addr-line>Nice</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup><institution>Université Côte d’Azur, CNRS UMR7275, Institut de Pharmacologie Moléculaire et Cellulaire</institution>, <addr-line>Valbonne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="aff4">
<sup>4</sup><institution>Université Côte d’Azur, INSERM, CNRS UMR7275, Institut de Pharmacologie Moléculaire et Cellulaire</institution>, <addr-line>Valbonne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="edited-by">
<p>Edited by: Elizabeth A. Thomas, The Scripps Research Institute, United States</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="edited-by">
<p>Reviewed by: Joseph Glessner, Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, United States; Guy Rouleau, McGill University, Canada; Patrick Dion, McGill University, Canada</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Arnaud Fernandez, <email xlink:href="mailto:fernandez.a@pediatrie-chulenval-nice.fr" xlink:type="simple">fernandez.a@pediatrie-chulenval-nice.fr</email>; Florence Askenazy, <email xlink:href="mailto:askenazy.f@pediatrie-chulenval-nice.fr" xlink:type="simple">askenazy.f@pediatrie-chulenval-nice.fr</email>; Barbara Bardoni, <email xlink:href="mailto:bardoni@ipmc.cnrs.fr" xlink:type="simple">bardoni@ipmc.cnrs.fr</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn002">
<p>This article was submitted to Behavioral and Psychiatric Genetics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Genetics</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="equal" id="fn003">
<p>†These authors have contributed equally to this work</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>18</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<elocation-id>1137</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>20</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>21</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2019 Fernandez, Drozd, Thümmler, Dor, Capovilla, Askenazy and Bardoni</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Fernandez, Drozd, Thümmler, Dor, Capovilla, Askenazy and Bardoni</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Childhood-onset schizophrenia (COS), a very rare and severe chronic psychiatric condition, is defined by an onset of positive symptoms (delusions, hallucinations and disorganized speech or behavior) before the age of 13. COS is associated with other neurodevelopmental disorders such as autism spectrum disorder (ASD) and attention deficit and hyperactivity disorder. Copy number variations (CNVs) represent well documented neurodevelopmental disorder risk factors and, recently, <italic>de novo</italic> single nucleotide variations (SNVs) in genes involved in brain development have also been implicated in the complex genetic architecture of COS. Here, we aim to review the genetic changes (CNVs and SNVs) reported for COS, going from previous studies to the whole genome sequencing era. We carried out a systematic review search in PubMed using the keywords “childhood(early)-onset schizophrenia(psychosis)” and “genetic(s) or gene(s) or genomic(s)” without language and date limitations. The main inclusion criteria are COS (onset before 13 years old) and all changes/variations at the DNA level (CNVs or SNVs). Thirty-six studies out of 205 met the inclusion criteria. Cytogenetic abnormalities (n = 72, including 66 CNVs) were identified in 16 autosomes and 2 sex chromosomes (X, Y), some with a higher frequency and clinical significance than others (e.g., 2p16.3, 3q29, 15q13.3, 22q11.21 deletions; 2p25.3, 3p25.3 and 16p11.2 duplications). Thirty-one single nucleotide mutations in genes principally involved in brain development and/or function have been found in 12 autosomes and one sex chromosome (X). We also describe five SNVs in X-linked genes inherited from a healthy mother, arguing for the X-linked recessive inheritance hypothesis. Moreover, <italic>ATP1A3</italic> (19q13.2) is the only gene carrying more than one SNV in more than one patient, making it a strong candidate for COS. Mutations were distributed in various chromosomes illustrating the genetic heterogeneity of COS. More than 90% of CNVs involved in COS are also involved in ASD, supporting the idea that there may be genetic overlap between these disorders. Different mutations associated with COS are probably still unknown, and pathogenesis might also be explained by the association of different genetic variations (two or more CNVs or CNVs and SNVs) as well as association with early acquired brain lesions such as infection, hypoxia, or early childhood trauma.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>childhood-onset schizophrenia</kwd>
<kwd>autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
<kwd>genetics</kwd>
<kwd>copy number variations</kwd>
<kwd>single nucleotide polymorphisms</kwd>
<kwd>exome sequencing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="3"></fig-count>
<table-count count="2"></table-count>
<equation-count count="0"></equation-count>
<ref-count count="85"></ref-count>
<page-count count="16"></page-count>
<word-count count="6451"></word-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Childhood-onset schizophrenia (COS) is a rare (&lt; 1/40,000) and severe chronic psychiatric condition that shares with adult-onset schizophrenia (AOS) positive symptoms (delusions, hallucinations, and disorganized speech or behavior), but presents an early onset (before the age of 13) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Burd and Kerbeshian, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Nicolson and Rapoport, 1999</xref>). It remains considered by many authors as an early and severe variant of AOS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Nicolson and Rapoport, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Biswas et al., 2006</xref>). In COS, neurodevelopmental abnormalities (deficits in cognition, communication, or neuromotor impairments) and premorbid dysfunction are more frequent compared with AOS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">Vourdas et al., 2003</xref>) and a clinical overlap exists with other neurodevelopmental disorders: 28% of patients with COS in the US cohort of the National Institute of Mental Health Child Psychiatry Branch met criteria for comorbid autism spectrum disorder (ASD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Rapoport et al., 2009</xref>). In addition, more than 80% of children with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder present comorbid attention deficit and hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Ross et al., 2006</xref>). Few genetic studies of COS were reported, due to the very low prevalence (&lt;1/40,000) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Burd and Kerbeshian, 1987</xref>) and to nosographic difficulties, which made it hard to obtain a consensual clinical definition of this disorder and to carry out etiological studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Maier, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Gochman et al., 2011</xref>). Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5) classification provides recent clarification in this area with schizophrenia no longer excluding the diagnosis of ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Petty et al., 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">American Psychiatric Association, 2013</xref>). Thus, clinical overlap between COS and ASD is now formally accepted. Surprisingly, DSM-5 still does not recognize the existence of COS, which therefore remains considered an adult clinical presentation (AOS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">American Psychiatric Association, 2013</xref>). Indeed, COS is a very rare complex disorder related to other neurodevelopmental disorders, and it represents a real challenge for clinical diagnosis with, to date, no objective test based on genetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Petty et al., 1984</xref>). However, a high heritability rate of COS (&gt; 80%) has been suggested in early adoption/twin studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Kallmann and Roth, 1956</xref>) and has been confirmed by familial aggregation studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Asarnow and Forsyth, 2013</xref>). To determine the etiology of COS, it is indispensable to start by reviewing the publications that have linked COS to DNA changes.</p>
<p>Macro-lesional cytogenetic abnormalities such as copy number variations (CNVs), including the 22q11.21 deletion, are more frequent in COS than in AOS [10.6% of patients with COS (DSM-III-R, onset &lt;13 years) vs. 2–5%, in AOS, p &lt; 0.0001]. These anomalies in the general population would concern only 0.86% of newborns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Recently, Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) or “high throughput sequencing” allowed, with unprecedented scalability and speed, to determine the DNA sequence of a given individual. This tool opened up new perspectives to understand complex neurodevelopmental disorders, with particular attention to <italic>de novo</italic> single nucleotide variations (SNVs) occurring in genes involved in brain development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">Veltman and Brunner, 2012</xref>). Only one study used whole exome sequencing (WES), a NGS method, in a cohort of patients with COS. This study identified 20 <italic>de novo</italic> variants in 17 COS probands (rate: 1.17) in genes previously linked to neuronal function or to psychiatric disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ambalavanan et al., 2016</xref>). These arguments (phenotypic overlap with other neurodevelopmental disorders, high heritability, disease-related CNVs, and <italic>de novo</italic> SNV rates) strongly support the neurodevelopmental and genetic bases of COS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Rapoport et al., 2012</xref>). In this context, the main aim of this study is to describe the COS genomic variation (CNVs and SNVs) in the scientific literature to identify interesting genes or genetic pathways in both clinical practice and research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We carried out a systematic review of the MEDLINE database accessible <italic>via</italic> the search engine PubMed (<uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/" xlink:type="simple">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/</uri>) with the following key words: “childhood-onset schizophrenia” or “childhood-onset psychosis” or “early-onset schizophrenia” or “early-onset psychosis” and “genetics” or “genetic” or “gene” or “genes” or “genomic” or “genomics.” Our search terms were not limited by language or date of publication and were manually reviewed. According to inclusion criteria, we considered all genomic changes occurring in COS patients (age of onset before 13). We excluded all abnormalities at RNA or protein levels (regardless the age of onset). Genomic variations were classified based on cytogenetic position (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>) and candidate gene names (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">
<bold>Table 2</bold>
</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Cytogenetic abnormalities (including copy number variations) in COS patients with their localization, length and type of inheritance.</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">CHR</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">CNV region and type (length)</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Sex, age of onset</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Neurodevelopmental disorders, Comorbidities</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Inheritance</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">coordinates (hg18-<italic>hg19</italic>)</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">SFARI</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Clinical significance</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Bibliography</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 1q21.3<break></break>(248 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr1:151,514,380-151,762,871</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1 ; 7</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">t(1;7) (p22;q22)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 9 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ASD? - ADHD? - language, intellectual and motor impairments, dysmorphia, supraventricular tachycardia</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (father)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Gordon et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">Yan et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Idol et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 2p14 (243 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr2:65,637,097-65,879,935</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 2p16.3 (115 --&gt; 112 kb) NRXN1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr2:50,023,212-50,137,825 / chr2:50,025,162-50,136,989</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 2p16.3 (38 et 40kb) NRXN1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Motoric and verbal delay, IQ 82, macrocencephalia and increase height (+3SD)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (father)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr2:51,151,955-51,190,352 / chr2:51,440,969-51,481,281</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Duong et al., 2015</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 2p25.3 (216 --&gt; 245 kb) MYT1L</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (mother)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr2:1,618,945-1,835,426 / chr2:1,591,064-1,836,375</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Lee et al., 2012</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 2p25.3 (143 --&gt; 107kb ) MYT1L</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr2:1,713,636-1,857,129 / chr2:1,720,133-1,827,317</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 2q31.2-31.3 (2,5 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">de novo or germline mosaicism in one of the parents</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr2:179,643,864-182,145,339</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 3p12.2-p12.1 (2,2 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ASD, poor motor coordination, IQ 67</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (father)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Rudd et al., 2015</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 3p21.31 (117 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr3:45,458,901-45,576,135</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 3p25.3 (120 --&gt; 134 kb) SRGAP3</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">poor peer relationships, general anxiety disorder, panic disorder, agoraphobia, and depression</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (father)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr3:9,100,744-9,220,529 / <italic>chr3: 9,111,177–9,245,155</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">Wilson et al., 2011</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 3q29 (1,58 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 5 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ASD, severe abdnormal movements and tics</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">de novo</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr3:197,161,073-198,851,029</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Sagar et al., 2013</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">5</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 5q12.3 (142 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 10 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr5:64,795,287-64,937,409</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Paternal segmental iUPD 5q32-qter (35 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 9 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">MDD, inattention,learning disability, intellectual impairments</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Seal et al., 2006</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 6p22.31 (144 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 9 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">OCD, expessive language disorder</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr6:119,596,633-119,740,850</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">7</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 7p13 (120 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr7:44,420,900-44,540,491</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 7q11.21-q11.22 (2,8 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr7:64,126,564-66,883,376</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 8p22 (1,3 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr8:13,400,795-14,679,483</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 8q11.23 (480 kb --&gt; 493 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr8:53,563,161-54,043,063 / chr8:53,550,992-54,043,684</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 8q24.3 (369 Kb) PTK2</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr8:142,025,432-142,393,948</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 9p24.2 (440 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr9:3,104,250-3,544,339</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">10</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 10p11.23 (176 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr10:28,990,284-29,166,175</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 10p13 (145 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr10:15,688,654-15,833,865</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 10q22.3 (173 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr10:81,415,378-81,588,866</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 15q11.2 (1386 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr15:18,818,086-20,203,694</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">15</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 15q11.2 (575kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (mother)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr15:20,203,​694-20,778,963</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 15q13.3 (382kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr15:30,238,780-30,620,951</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 15q13.3 (475 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (mother)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr15:30,238,780-30,713,368</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 15q13.3 (503.5 Kb) CHRNA7</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 10 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (father)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr15:32,012,361-32,515,849</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 15q13.3 (600,2 Kb) CHRNA7</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ADHD</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr15:32,019,919–32,620,127</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 15q26.2-q26.3 (687 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr15:96,246,764-96,933,404</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">16</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 16p11.2 <break></break>( 433 --&gt; 604 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">PDD-NOS, poor social and motor development</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited (father)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr16:29,652,656-30,085,308 / chr16:29,502,984-30,107,306</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Rapoport et al., 2009</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 16p11.2<break></break>( 578 --&gt; 445 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">10 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Poor social and motor development</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr16:29,657,405-30,235,818 / chr16:29,782,436-30,227,808</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 16p12.1 (449kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">father</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr16:21,498,074-21,946,841</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 16p13.11<break></break>(15 à 131 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 6 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Motor dyscoordination, langage impairments</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Father or de novo</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>chr16:1,51,32,264–1,51,47,411 (min) to 1,50,48,733-1,51,79,946 (max)</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>+</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Brownstein et al., 2016</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 16p13.11 (1,4 à 1,7 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 4 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ASD, Epilepsy, Chiari 1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">father</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>chr16:1,48,97,761–1,62,76,117 to 1,47,80,303–1,64,58,270</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 16q22.2-ter (17 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Atypical Turner, motor, language and attention impairments</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 16q22.3-q24.3 (16,7 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ASD, poor motor coordination, IQ 67</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Rudd et al., 2015</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 16q23.3<break></break>(1,5 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 9.5 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr16:80,737,839-82,208,451</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 16q24.1<break></break>(111 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;3 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr16:82,997,582-83,108,554</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">17</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 17q21.31 (384 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">father</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr17:41,321,621-41,706,070</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">18</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 18p11.31-p11.23 (510 kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr18:7,067,237-7,576,777</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 18q22.1 (768 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 10 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Asperger's disorder</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr18:61,907,915-62,675,869</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">19</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 19p12<break></break>(397 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr19:23,413,380-23,810,606</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">20</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 20p12.1<break></break>(113 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">10 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Poor social and motor development</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr20:14,921,777-15,034,862</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">22</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 22q11.2 (3Mb) PRODH DGCR6</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 9 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Language, motor and social impairments, generalized anxiety disorder, dysthymia and ADHD, craniofacial dysmorphia, hypospadias</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">de novo</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Rapoport et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Yan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">Usiskin et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Liu et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Sporn et al., 2004</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Language, motor and social impairments, craniofacial dysmorphia, celiac disease and ureteric reflux</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">de novo</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Rapoport et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">Usiskin et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Liu et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Sporn et al., 2004</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 10 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Language, motor and social impairments, craniofacial dysmorphia</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">de novo</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Craniofacial dysmorphia</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Rapoport et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Sporn et al., 2004</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 22q11.21 (3 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr22:17,092,563-20,077,678</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 22q11.21 (2,6 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr22:17,224,632-19,842,333</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 22q11.21 (2,6 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr22:17,257,787-19,855,248</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 22q11.21 (2,7 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr22:17,257,787-19,963,350</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL 22q11.21 (2,9 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr22:17,269,794-20,128,199</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP 22q13.32 (1,6 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">PDD-NOS, poor social and motor development</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chr22:47,903,228-49,557,485</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">X</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">expansion CGG (1,5 Kb) FMR1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 9 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Dysmorphia, learning and social impairments, mild MR</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">mother</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Vantalon et al., 2005</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">47, XXX</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, &lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">46,X,i(X)(q10)(22%)/45,X(78%)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, &lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mosaic Turner</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL Xq24-qter</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Atypical Turner, motor, language and attention impairments</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>*, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Kumra et al., 1998</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP Xp22.31 (342 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt;13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">not known</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chrX:8,384,117-8,726,291</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL Xp22.31 (1.68 Mb) STS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Congenital ichthyosis, microcencephalia, epilepsy. Language, motor, social, learning impairment, IQ 57, ADHD, ASD</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>chrX:6,456,036-8,139,238</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Malik et al., 2017</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP Xq28<break></break>(6 a 35 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 4 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ASD, Epilepsy, Chiari 1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>chrX:15,29,55,334–15,29,61,664 to</italic>
<italic>15,29,51,719–15,29,86,547</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>+</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Brownstein et al., 2016</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DEL Xq23-q28 (43 Mb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ASD, poor motor coordination, IQ 67</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">P</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Rudd et al., 2015</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DUP Yq11.221 (183 Kb)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 8 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Generalized anxiety disorder</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">chrY:14,441,161-14,623,937</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">+</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UCS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<p>ADHD, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder; ASD, Autism Spectrum Disorder; CNV, Copy number variation; COPD, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease; DEL, Deletion; DUP, Duplication; iUPD, Uniparental isodisomy; ID, Intellectual disability; Kb, Kilobases; Mb, Mégabases; MDD, Major Depressive Disorder; MR, Mental Retardation; OCD, Obsessive compulsive disorder; P, Pathogenic; PDD-NOS, Pervasive developmental disorder not otherwise specified; UCS, Uncertain Clinical Significance; VCF, Velocardiofacial; Y, Years; * Literature review.</p>
<p>When available, phenotypes (sex, age of onset, other neurodevelopmental disorders and comorbidities) are described.</p>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Genomic microlesions (including single nucleotide variations) in COS patients with their localization, length, and type of inheritance.</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gene name</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gene localization</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">SNV ID number/mutation (protein level)</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Population / Phenotypes</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Inheritance</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">p-value</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Bibliography</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>FAMILY BASED ASSOCIATION STUDY</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>DAOA (G72) / DAOA-AS1 (G30)</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">13q33.2</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">rs1935058, rs3916967, rs2391191</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">n=64 (53 COS trios, 11 COS dyads)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.015 to 0.5</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Addington et al., 2004</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>DTNBP1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6p22.3</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">rs11558324</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">n=92 (73 COS + PDD-NOS trios, 19 COS + PDD-NOS dyads)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.014</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Gornick et al., 2005</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>GAD1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2q31.1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">rs3749034, rs2270335, rs2241165</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">n=66 (55 COS + PDD-NOS trios, 11 COS + PDD-NOS dyads)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.005</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Addington et al., 2005</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>NRG1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8p12</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">rs35753505, rs2881272, rs327417</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">n=70 (59 COS + PDD-NOS trios, 11 COS + PDD-NOS dyads)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.009 to 0.05</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Addington et al., 2007</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>CASE CONTROL STUDY</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>BDNF</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11p13</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">val66met</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">65 patients (10.5 ± 3.7 y) vs<break></break>111 controls</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.03</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Pakhomova et al., 2010</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>COMT</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">22q11.21</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">val158met</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">83 patients (&lt;13 y) vs<break></break>208 controls</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Raznahan et al., 2011</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>TPH1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11p15.3-p14</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ala218cys</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">51 patients (&lt;16 y) vs<break></break>148 controls</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.0058</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">Sekizawa et al., 2004</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>GENES SEQUENCING (candidate genes or full exome)</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>ATP1A3</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">19q13.2</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">val129met</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 6 y, motor delay</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Smedemark-Margulies et al., 2016</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">asp801asn</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 10 y, ASD, dysmophia, motor, intellectual and learning delays. Recurent MDD</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Chaumette et al., 2018</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">glu815lys</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 12 y, motor and communication impairments, dysmophia, ASD</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ala813val</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 10 y, ASD, motor and intellectual delays</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">mother</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>FXYD1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">19q13.12</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">arg90cys</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 7 y, Asperger's disorder</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">inherited</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>FXYD6-FXYD2</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11q23.3</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">val101ala</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 13 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>FXYD6</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">11q23.3</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">gly73arg</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, onset: 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>GPR153</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1p36.31</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">arg73cys</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ambalavanan et al., 2016</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>GTF2IRD1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">7q11.23</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">arg357cys</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, onset: 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>ITGA6</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2q31.1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">glu1063del</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Female, onset: 12 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>LUZP4</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Xq23</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">arg278fs*10</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">mother</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Ambalavanan et al., 2019</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>OPHN1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Xq12</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">met461val</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">IQ 88, PDDNOS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>PCDH19</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Xq22.1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">leu1022ile</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>RPS6KA3</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Xp22.12</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">arg723his</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">IQ 64, PDDNOS</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>RYR2</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1q43</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">glu746tyr</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 8 y, PDDNOS, separation anxiety disorder, Asperger's disorder</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<italic>de novo</italic>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ambalavanan et al., 2016</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>SEZ6</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">17q11.2</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">thr229_thr231del</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 11 y</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>TTBK1</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6p21.1</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">arg258gln</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, onset: 7 y, Asperger's disorder</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<bold>UPF3B</bold>
</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Xq24</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">gln228fsX18</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male, 10 y, ADHD, PDDNOS, ASD</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">mother</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">−</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Addington et al., 2011</xref>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<p>ADHD, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder; ASD, Autism Spectrum Disorder; CNV, Copy number variation; COS, Childhood Onset Schizophrenia; DEL, Deletion; DUP, Duplication; MDD, Major Depressive Disorder; PDD-NOS, Pervasive developmental disorder not otherwise specified; SNV, Single Nucleotide Variation; Y, Years. When available, phenotypes (sex, age of onset, other neurodevelopmental disorders, and comorbidities) are described.</p>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>All CNVs were manually annotated using the University of California Santa Cruz (UCSC) Genome Browser (UCSC Mar. 2006 (NCBI36/hg18 or NCBI37/hg19) assembly; <uri xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://genome.ucsc.edu/</uri>). Regarding their type (gain or loss), their size, their genomic content, and making comparisons with external databases, we ranked each CNV as “pathogenic,” “uncertain clinical significance,” or “benign” (according to the American College of Medical Genetics standards and guidelines for interpretation and reporting of postnatal constitutional copy number variants). For each CNV, we checked on the Simons Foundation Autism Research Initiative (SFARI) Gene database (autism/genetic database, <uri xlink:href="http://sfari.org" xlink:type="simple">http://sfari.org</uri>) which CNV involved in COS was also involved in ASD. For each gene, we checked on the Phenocarta Database (<uri xlink:href="https://gemma.msl.ubc.ca/home.html" xlink:type="simple">https://gemma.msl.ubc.ca/home.html</uri>) the evidence linking genes to phenotypes of neurodevelopmental disorders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1</bold>
</xref>, Venn diagram). Phenotypes were systematically described, if available.</p>
<fig id="f1" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Venn diagram: evidence for genetic overlap in neurodevelopmental disorders (Phenocarta Database).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="fgene-10-01137-g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>The selection took place before September 2018. At this time, 36 articles (1994 to 2018) out of 205 (1982 to 2018) met the inclusion criteria. Article reviewing process, including selection and exclusion, is summarized in a PRISMA flow diagram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
<bold>Figure 2</bold>
</xref>). Two articles were added after the freezing of the inclusion process (41; 52). Mutations were identified in 21 chromosomes. The results were ranked either in ascending order of their chromosomal position for structural variants (cytogenetic abnormalities) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>) or in alphabetical order according to their gene name for genetic variants (lesions at gene level) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">
<bold>Table 2</bold>
</xref>).</p>
<fig id="f2" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p>PRISMA Flowchart diagram.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="fgene-10-01137-g002"></graphic>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s3" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3_1">
<label>I</label>
<title>Cytogenetic Abnormalities Associated With COS</title>
<p>The following cytogenetic abnormalities (n = 72, including 66 CNVs) were identified in 16 autosomes (1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, and 22) and two sex chromosomes (X and Y) of 46 patients (17–40). The results were ranked in ascending order of their chromosomal position (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>) and were summarized in a genomic map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">
<bold>Figure 3</bold>
</xref>).</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>1) CNVs</p>
<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Deletions (CNVs) from 15Kb to 43Mb: 2p16.3, 2q31.2-q31.3, 3p12.2-p12.1, 3q29, 6p22.31, 9p24.2, 10q22.3, 15q11.2, 15q13.3, 16p12.1, 16p13.11, 16q24.1, 19p12, 20p12.1, 22q11.21, Xp22.31, Xq24-ter, and Xq23-q28;</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Duplications (CNVs) from 120Kb to 17Mb: 1q21.3, 2p14, 2p25.3, 3p21.31, 3p25.3, 5q12.3, 7p13, 7q11.21-q11.22, 8p22, 8q11.23, 8q24.3, 10p11.23, 10p13, 15q11-q13, 15q13.3, 15q26.2–26.3, 16p11.2, 16p13.11, 16q22.2-ter, 16q22.3-q24.3, 16q23.3, 17q21.31, 18p11.31-p11.23, 18q22.1, 22q13.32, Xp22.31, Xq28, and Yq11.221.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</list-item>
</list>
<fig id="f3" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Genomic map of CNVs identified in COS. Circles indicate their position and color represents type of abnormality (Red circle, deletion; Blue circle, duplication).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="fgene-10-01137-g003"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Only six CNVs (9%) of our study are described in COS only: del2q31.2-q31.3 (smaller than the CNV described in ASD), del3p12.2-p12.1 (described in ASD as a duplication), delXq24-ter (larger than the CNV described in ASD), dup7p13 (described in ASD as a deletion), dup16q22.2-ter (larger than the CNV described in ASD), and dup16q22.3-q24.3 (larger than the CNV described in ASD).</p>
<p>In an on-site case series and literature review focusing on Childhood-Onset Schizophrenia Spectrum Disorders (SSDs; larger spectrum than COS), Giannitelli et al. (2018) showed that some CNVs, previously un-described in COS patients, are associated to childhood psychosis: 1q21.1 deletion, 1q21.1 duplication, Williams-Beuren region (7q11.23) duplication and 16p11.2 deletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Giannitelli et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
<p>The phenotypes of only 15 out of the 46 patients were fully described (33%). The neurodevelopmental disorders that have been presented are: motor impairments (fine or growth milestones delay, coordination disability, or tics) in 11/15 patients, language retardation in 7/15 patients, intellectual disability (IQ &lt; 70) in two patients, and ASD in five patients [(including 1 Pervasive Developmental Disorder-Not Otherwise Specified (PDD-NOS)]. Social impairment was present in six other patients with COS and ADHD in three patients. Inattention impairment was specified in only one patient. The psychiatric comorbidities that have been highlighted are: two cases with mood disorders (major depressive disorder or dysthymia) and two cases with anxiety disorders. The somatic comorbidities detected are: dysmorphia in four cases and epilepsy in two cases. Sporadic cases of hypospadias, ureteric reflux, congenital ichthyosis, Chiari type 1, or celiac disease were also described.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>2) Other DNA Lesions</p>
<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Aneuploidy</p>
<p>One case of Trisomy X (47XXX) and two cases of Turner syndrome (45X0), one atypical form (46,X,del(X)(q24-ter) and one with mosaicism 46,X,i(X)(q10)(22%)/45,X(78%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>);</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Uniparental and Segmental isoDisomy (iUSD)</p>
<p>In isodisomy, both copies of a chromosomal set are inherited from one parent (the mother or the father). An iUSD on 5q32-ter (35Mb) was described in a patient with COS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Seal et al., 2006</xref>);</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Translocation 1, 7: p22q22 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Gordon et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">Yan et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Idol et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Trinucleotide Repeat Expansions</p>
<list list-type="roman-lower">
<list-item>
<p>CGG Expansions: Although a link between Fragile X syndrome (FXS) and COS has never been reported, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Vantalon et al. (2005)</xref> described a 1.5 Kb expansion and complete methylation of the CpG island upstream of FMR1 in a 9 years-old girl with COS, dysmorphia, learning and social impairments, and mild mental retardation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Vantalon et al., 2005</xref>). This abnormality is inherited from the mother who carries an FXS premutation. Interestingly, instead of being unaffected or weakly affected as most patients carrying a premutation, the mother presents schizotypal personality. It seems that the severity of the schizophrenic spectrum disorder, which affects both mother and daughter with gradual severity, is linked to the CGG expansion degree. Effect of the hazard could not be excluded in this case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Vantalon et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>CAG/CTG Expansion: a longer repeat expansion on chromosome 18 was found in a COS cohort and in a male subclass, with a significant p-value especially for the males (0.036 and 0.002, respectively; Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney U test) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Burgess et al., 1998</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Genetic Syndromes</p>
<p>In their recent review, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Giannitelli et al. (2018)</xref> showed that some genetic syndromes, previously un-described in COS, are associated to childhood-onset SSDs: juvenile Huntington disease, Prader-Willi syndrome, Steinert myotonia, Ondine syndrome, Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome, and GLUT1 deficiency syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Giannitelli et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="s3_2">
<label>II</label>
<title>Genes Associated With COS</title>
<p>In total, 32 candidate genes have been described on 12 autosomes (1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 8, 11, 13, 15, 17, 19, and 22) and 1 sex chromosome (X) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">
<bold>Tables 1</bold>
</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">
<bold>2</bold>
</xref>) through the following studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Addington et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">Sekizawa et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Gornick et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Addington et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Addington et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Pakhomova et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Addington et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Raznahan et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Smedemark-Margulies et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Chaumette et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Ambalavanan et al., 2019</xref>):</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>1) Genetic Association Studies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">
<bold>Table 2</bold>
</xref>)</p>
<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Family-Based “Transmission Disequilibrium Test” Studies (From 2004 to 2007)</p>
<p>Transmission disequilibrium test, a family-based association test for the presence of genetic linkage between a genetic marker and a trait, was used to describe the following candidate genes: <italic>DAOA, DAOA-AS1, DTNBP1, GAD1</italic>, and <italic>NRG1</italic>. The Linkage Disequilibrium Analyses for Quantitative and Discrete Traits (QTDT) program was used to make statistical analysis (p-values).</p>
<list list-type="roman-lower">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>DAOA</italic> and <italic>DAOA-AS1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Addington et al., 2004</xref>): three Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs) are associated with COS (rs1935058, rs3916967, and rs2391191 (p = 0.5, 0.015, 0.3, respectively)). The most significant SNP (p = 0.015) is rs3916967 (genomic sequence reference: NG_012694.1:g.4133T &gt; C);</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>DTNBP1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Gornick et al., 2005</xref>): one SNP, rs11558324 (NG_009309.1:g.5154A &gt; G), is associated with COS (p = 0.014) and two two-marker haplotypes (containing rs11558324) are also associated with COS (p = 0.021, 0.008),</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>GAD 1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Addington et al., 2005</xref>): three four-marker haplotypes are associated with COS (p = 0.005);</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>NRG1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Addington et al., 2007</xref>): individual markers show association with COS (rs35753505, rs2881272, 420M9-1395 (microsatellite), and rs327417, with p-value between 0.009 and 0.05). The most significant SNP (p = 0.009) is rs327417 (NG_012005.2:g.341913G &gt; A). Further, several novel four-marker haplotypes are associated with COS (lowest p = 0.0004).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Population-Based “Case vs. Control” Studies (From 2004 to 2011)</p>
<p>A polymorphism (VAL66MET) in the <italic>BDNF</italic> (11p13) gene was associated with COS in a 65 patient cohort (10.5 ± 3.7 years old at onset) vs. 111 controls (p = 0.03; χ² test) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Pakhomova et al., 2010</xref>). A mutation (VAL158MET) in <italic>COMT</italic> (22q11.21) that increases protein activity levels in the brain accelerated adolescent cortical thinning (MRI findings) in both schizophrenia probands and their siblings (with resolution after a certain age for siblings), illustrating the influence of dopaminergic disruption on brain cortical maturation. Authors analyzed data from an 83 COS patient cohort vs. 208 healthy controls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Raznahan et al., 2011</xref>). A mutation (A218C) in the <italic>TPH1</italic> (11p15.3-p14) gene (p = 0.0058; χ² test) is described in 51 patients (early adolescent onset cohort before 16 years old) vs. 148 controls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">Sekizawa et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>2) Gene Sequencing Studies (2011 to Present)</p>
<p>Finally, five studies by DNA sequencing (candidate genes or whole exome sequencing) have allowed identifying the following 18 mutations in 11 genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Addington et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ambalavanan et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Smedemark-Margulies et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Chaumette et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Ambalavanan et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<list list-type="roman-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Six SNVs inherited from a healthy mother:</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>- Five X-linked recessive variants: <italic>LUZP4</italic> (arg278fs*10), <italic>OPHN1</italic> (met461val), <italic>PCDH19</italic> (leu1022ile), <italic>RPS6KA3</italic> (arg723his), and <italic>UPF3B</italic> gene (gln228fsX18) that also segregates in the sibling.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>- One SNV (ala813val) in <italic>ATP1A3</italic> (a boy with onset at 10 years old and co-morbid ASD).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Three SNVs inherited (missenses variants) in the FXYD gene family. <italic>FXYD1</italic> (arg90cys), <italic>FXYD6-FXYD2</italic> (val101ala), and <italic>FXYD6</italic> (gly73arg) genes. Only the patient with the mutation in FXYD1 presents a co-morbid ASD (Asperger’s disorder).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Nine <italic>de novo</italic> SNVs in the following genes: <italic>ATP1A3</italic> (val129met; asp801asn; glu815lys), <italic>GPR153</italic> (arg73cys), <italic>GTF2IRD1</italic> (arg357cys), <italic>ITGA6</italic> (glu1063del), <italic>RYR2</italic> (glu746tyr), <italic>SEZ6</italic> (thr229_thr231del), and <italic>TTBK1</italic> (arg258gln).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>The ATPase Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> transporting Alpha-3 Polypeptide (<italic>ATP1A3</italic> gene) encodes the alpha-3 catalytic subunit of the Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase transmembrane ion pump mapping at 19q12-q13.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Harley et al., 1988</xref>). The <italic>ATP1A3</italic> isoform is exclusively expressed in neurons of various brain regions, including the basal ganglia, hippocampus, and cerebellum (summary by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rosewich et al., 2012</xref>). Mutations in this gene have been associated with a spectrum of disorders depending on the domain they affect in the corresponding protein. The majority of mutations associated with rapid-onset dystonia parkinsonism, or dystonia-12 (<italic>DYT12</italic>), were located in exons 8 and 14 whereas those with alternating hemiplegia of childhood-2 (AHC2) were located in exons 17 and 18 and in general they seem to affect transmembrane and functional domains, being the most severe dysfunctions. By genetic analysis of clinical data from 155 patients with AHC2, 132 confirmed to have <italic>ATP1A3</italic> mutations. Among those with AHC2, the most frequent mutations were D801N (in 43%), E815K (in 16%) and G947R (in 11%). E815K was associated with a severe phenotype, with greater intellectual and motor disability; D801N appeared to confer a milder phenotype and G947R correlated with the most favorable prognosis. For those with epilepsy, the age at seizure onset was earlier for patients with the E815K or G947R mutations than for those with the D801N mutation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Panagiotakaki et al., 2015</xref>). In 10 patients from three unrelated families with cerebellar ataxia, areflexia, pes cavus, optic atrophy, and sensorineural hearing loss (CAPOS; 601338) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Demos et al., 2014</xref>), the same heterozygous missense mutation in the <italic>ATP1A3</italic> gene was identified (E818K; OMIM 182350.0014).</p>
<p>The G Protein-coupled Receptor 153 (<italic>GPR153</italic>) gene, located on 1p36.31, belongs to the large rhodopsin (RHO; OMIM 180380) family of GPCRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Gloriam et al., 2005</xref>) and shows a highest similarity to serotonin receptors, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Gloriam et al., 2005</xref>). Furthermore, knockdown of <italic>GPR153</italic> in mice showed reduction in food intake and increased anxiety according to the elevated plus Maze test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Sreedharan et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>The InTeGrin Alpha-6 (<italic>ITGA6</italic>) gene is located on 2q31.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Hogervorst et al., 1991</xref>). While functional absence of <italic>ITGA6</italic> has been associated with epidermolysis bullosa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Hogervorst et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Georges-Labouesse et al., 1996</xref>), a few works addressed the role of <italic>ITGA6</italic> in neurons. Alpha-6 integrin was initially reported to be involved in neural migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">Yao et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, recent data suggested that α6 and β1 integrins may play a role in mediating Schwann cell interactions with axons and promote axonal regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Chang et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
<p>The RYanodine Receptor 2 (<italic>RYR2</italic>) gene—located on chromosome 1 between q42.1 et q43—encodes a calcium channel that is located in the sarcoplasmic reticulum and is the major source of calcium required for cardiac muscle excitation-contraction coupling. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Bhuiyan et al., 2007</xref>). Ryr2-/- mice die at approximately embryonic day 10 with morphologic abnormalities in the heart tube. Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling has been associated with ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Kabir et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Stephenson et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Castagnola et al., 2018</xref>) and with other psychiatric and neurological diseases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Heyes et al., 2015</xref>). It is not surprising that <italic>RYR2</italic> was linked to ASD by genetic studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Lu and Cantor, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Soueid et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Chen et al., 2017</xref>). However, it is very interesting to underline that an SNP in this gene was associated with ASD in families with only affected males in contrast with those with affected females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Lu and Cantor, 2012</xref>) suggesting that <italic>RYR2</italic> is a sex-related genetic factor for ASD.</p>
<p>The SEiZure-related 6 (<italic>SEZ6</italic>) gene is located on the 17q11.2 chromosome. Sez6 types 1 and 2 have an N-terminal signal sequence, followed by a threonine-rich region, a Short Consensus Repeat (SCR), a CUB-like domain, a second SCR, a second CUB-like domain, three tandem SCRs, a transmembrane domain, and a cytoplasmic C-terminal tail. They differ only in the region between the last SCR and the transmembrane domain. <italic>SEZ6</italic> was predicted to be involved in neuronal maturation and plasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Miyazaki et al., 2006</xref>). Recently mutations and altered expression of this gene have been associated with Alzheimer’s and Niemann-Pick disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Causevic et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Paracchini et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
<p>The Tau TuBulin Kinase 2 (<italic>TTBK2</italic>) gene, located on 15q15.2, encodes a member of the casein kinase (CK1) group of eukaryotic protein kinases. <italic>TTBK1</italic> has been implicated in Alzheimer’s disease (OMIM 104300) and in neurofibrillary tangles formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Sato et al., 2006</xref>). Mutations in this gene also cause spinocerebellar ataxia 11 (SCA11; 604432). SCA11 is a pure progressive cerebellar ataxia that has been linked to 15q14-q21 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">Worth et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Houlden et al., 2007</xref>). In an 8-generation English family they found a one-base insertion in the <italic>TTBK2</italic> gene creating a premature stop codon and a truncation of the normal protein (OMIM 611695.0001). In a second family of Pakistani ancestry, a different mutation was found (OMIM 611695.0002). Goetz et al. (2012) concluded that <italic>TTBK2</italic> is required for removal of CP110 for the initiation of ciliogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Goetz et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>3) Candidate Genes From Cytogenetic Studies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>)</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>Interesting candidate genes deleted, duplicated, or truncated by the CNVs have also been found in cytogenetic studies (see above). These genes have brain expression and are mostly described in other neurodevelopmental or psychiatric disorders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1</bold>
</xref>). Nine genes are described as putative COS-causing genes: <italic>CHRNA7</italic> (15q13.3), <italic>DGCR6</italic> (22q11.2), <italic>FMR1</italic> (Xq27.3), <italic>MYT1L</italic> (2p25.3), <italic>NRXN1</italic> (2p16.3), <italic>PRODH</italic> (22q11.2), <italic>PTK2</italic> (8q24.3), <italic>STS</italic> (Xp22.31), and <italic>SRGAP3</italic> (3p25.3) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Yan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">Usiskin et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Liu et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Sporn et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Vantalon et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Eckstrand et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Walsh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Addington and Rapoport, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Rapoport et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">Wilson et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Lee et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Duong et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Malik et al., 2017</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s4" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>COS is a neurodevelopmental disorder with several degrees of complexity (clinical and genetic heterogeneity). Clinically, getting the diagnostic is very challenging (severe disorder, comorbidities, and association with other neurodevelopmental disorders) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Gochman et al., 2011</xref>). The clinical overlap with ASD is well documented and in our study we found a co-morbidity rate (33%) nearly equal to the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) COS cohort rate (28%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Rapoport et al., 2009</xref>). The genetic overlap with ASD is also well documented and we show that 91% of described CNVs are also described in ASD (<italic>SFARI</italic>). In the literature, we found only 20% of COS patients with co-morbid ADHD vs. 84% according to Ross et al. and we hypothesize that this trouble was under-diagnosed in schizophrenia studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Ross et al., 2006</xref>). All intellectual, motor, communication, and learning impairments are also frequently observed in COS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Ross et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Nicolson et al., 1999</xref>). Psychiatric comorbidities were rarely described (two cases of mood disorders and two cases of anxiety disorders), which was an unexpected outcome given the published literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Ross et al., 2006</xref>). Here, we highlight that only one-third of the full phenotypes associated with the mutations published in the literature are described, which constitutes a significant loss of information for researchers. Therefore, it appears fundamental to carry out preliminary work before genetic testing: perform a rigorous and homogeneous phenotypic characterization using International Classification of Disease (<italic>ICD-10</italic> and <italic>DSM-5</italic>) with standardized and internationally validated psychiatric categorical assessments and in accordance with medical history (including perinatology), biography (with significant life event and trauma), and environmental factors (such as toxic exposure).</p>
<p>COS is characterized by a complex genetic architecture with both inherited and <italic>de novo</italic> mutations distributed in almost all chromosomes. Most of the genes causing COS are unknown yet. It is interesting that, the few that have been already proposed (see before) are involved both in neurodevelopmental and neurodegenerative disorders such as Parkinson, Alzheimer, or ataxia. Moreover, schizophrenia has been shown to have complex genetic traits with high polygenic risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Ahn et al., 2016</xref>). Thus, a second hit (or more), in addition to CNV, is probably essential to explain the phenotypes. It includes <italic>de novo</italic> SNVs, other CNVs and/or environmental factors (e.g., trauma at early childhood, central nervous system infections or injuries) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Davis et al., 2016</xref>). At the interplay between genetic and environmental factors, epigenetics opens new perspectives to understand biological mechanisms of psychosis. In fact, recent findings suggest that pangenomic methylation changes during adolescence accompany conversion to psychosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Kebir et al., 2018</xref>). In clinical practice, as suggested by Szego et al. for ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">Szego and Zawati, 2016</xref>), it would seem useful to propose to COS patients genetic sequencing instead or in addition to microarrays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Anagnostou et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Soden et al., 2014</xref>) to improve genetic testing and to allow <italic>de novo</italic> SNV detection.</p>
<p>In research, the major challenge of the upcoming years will be the analysis of big data from NGS (prioritization and interpretation of DNA variations) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Richards et al., 2015</xref>) and the experimental validation of putative mutations. Sharing data with other teams around the world will be helpful to unravel the molecular pathology of COS and its underlying causes, paving the way for an early therapeutic intervention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p>AF, FA, and BB: contributed to the conceptualization of the study and drafted the first version of the manuscript. All other authors MD, ST, ED, and MC have revised first version of the manuscript critically for important intellectual content and approved the final version.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s6" sec-type="funding-information">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This study was supported by INSERM, CNRS, Université Côte d’Azur and Hôpitaux pédiatriques de Nice CHU-Lenval; ANR-11-LABX-0028-01 and ANR-15-CE16-0015 to BB; Monaco Against Autism (MONAA) Foundation to AF, MC, FA, and BB. MD is recipient of a Signalife-LabEx Program international Ph.D.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s7">
<title>Conflict of Interest</title>
<p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors are indebted to T. Maurin for discussion and to F. Aguila for artwork.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="B1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The genetics of childhood-onset schizophrenia: when madness strikes the prepubescent</article-title>. <source/>Curr. Psychiatry Rep.
<volume>11</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19302770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gornick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporn</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Polymorphisms in the 13q33.2 gene G72/G30 are associated with childhood-onset schizophrenia and psychosis not otherwise specified</article-title>. <source/>Biol. Psychiatry
<volume>55</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>976</fpage>–<lpage>980</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.01.024</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gornick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duckworth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>GAD1 (2q31.1), which encodes glutamic acid decarboxylase (GAD67), is associated with childhood-onset schizophrenia and cortical gray matter volume loss</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>10</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001599.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15505639</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gornick</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Neuregulin 1 (8p12) and childhood-onset schizophrenia: susceptibility haplotypes for diagnosis and brain developmental trajectories</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>12</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001906</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17033632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdan</surname><given-names>F. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A novel frameshift mutation in UPF3B identified in brothers affected with childhood onset schizophrenia and autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>16</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2010.59</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20479756</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anvari</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gochman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>High rate of disease-related copy number variations in childhood onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>19</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2013.59</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23689535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shugart</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Common polygenic variation and risk for childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>21</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2014.158</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25510512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambalavanan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dionne-Laporte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>De novo variants in sporadic cases of childhood onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Eur. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>24</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>944</fpage>–<lpage>948</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2015.218</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26508570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambalavanan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaumette</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Exome sequencing of sporadic childhood-onset schizophrenia suggests the contribution of X-linked genes in males</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. B Neuropsychiatr. Genet.
<volume>180</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.32683</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30378261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <source/>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (DSM-5). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Pub</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anagnostou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwaigenbaum</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szatmari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fombonne</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodbury-Smith</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Autism spectrum disorder: advances in evidence-based practice</article-title>. <source/>CMAJ
<volume>186</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.121756</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24418986</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asarnow</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsyth</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genetics of childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Child Adolesc. Psychiatr. Clin. N Am.
<volume>22</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>687</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chc.2013.06.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24012080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhuiyan</surname><given-names>Z. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tintelen</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bink-Boelkens</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiesfeld</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alders</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Expanding spectrum of human RYR2-related disease: new electrocardiographic, structural, and genetic features</article-title>. <source/>Circ.
<volume>116</volume> (<issue>14</issue>), <fpage>1569</fpage>–<lpage>1576</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.711606.</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Comparative study of neuropsychological correlates in schizophrenia with onset in childhood, adolescence and adulthood</article-title>. <source/>Eur. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
<volume>15</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>360</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00787-006-0542-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16604435</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiman</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engle</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Towne</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Angelo</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Overlapping 16p13.11 deletion and gain of copies variations associated with childhood onset psychosis include genes with mechanistic implications for autism associated pathways: two case reports</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>170A</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1165</fpage>–<lpage>1173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.a.37595</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26887912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burd</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerbeshian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>A North Dakota prevalence study of schizophrenia presenting in childhood</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
<volume>26</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-198705000-00012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3496327</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindblad</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidransky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Q. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breschel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Large CAG/CTG repeats are associated with childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>3</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4000405</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castagnola</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delhaye</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Folci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paquet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brau</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duprat</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>New Insights Into the Role of Cav2 Protein Family in Calcium Flux Deregulation in Fmr1-KO Neurons</article-title>. <source/>Front. Mol. Neurosci.
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>342</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnmol.2018.00342</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30319351</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Causevic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominko</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malnar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidatic</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cermak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pigoni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>BACE1-cleavage of Sez6 and Sez6L is elevated in Niemann-Pick type C disease mouse brains</article-title>. <source/>PloS One
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <elocation-id>e0200344</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0200344</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29979789</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Namgung</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>alpha6 and beta1 Integrin heterodimer mediates schwann cell interactions with axons and facilitates axonal regeneration after peripheral nerve injury</article-title>. <source/>Neurosci.
<volume>371</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2017.11.046</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B21">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaumette</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrafiat</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambalavanan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dionne-Laporte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Missense variants in ATP1A3 and FXYD gene family are associated with childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-018-0103-8</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B22">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Horn</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Developmental neurogenetics and multimodal neuroimaging of sex differences in autism</article-title>. <source/>Brain Imaging Behav.
<volume>11</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11682-015-9504-3.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26781567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B23">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyre</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacka</surname><given-names>F. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A review of vulnerability and risks for schizophrenia: beyond the two hit hypothesis</article-title>. <source/>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2016.03.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27073049</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demos</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Karnebeek</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>A novel recurrent mutation in ATP1A3 causes CAPOS syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Orphanet J. Rare Dis.
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1172-9-15</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24468074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B25">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeffding</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thygesen</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klitten</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Two rare deletions upstream of the NRXN1 gene (2p16.3) affecting the non-coding mRNA AK127244 segregate with diverse psychopathological phenotypes in a family</article-title>. <source/>Eur. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>58</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>650</fpage>–<lpage>653</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmg.2015.11.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26563496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B26">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckstrand</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stromberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merriman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gochman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Sex chromosome anomalies in childhood onset schizophrenia: an update</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>910</fpage>–<lpage>911</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2008.67</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18800051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B27">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georges-Labouesse</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messaddeq</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yehia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadalbert</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Meur</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Absence of integrin alpha 6 leads to epidermolysis bullosa and neonatal death in mice</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>370</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0796-370</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8673141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B28">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giannitelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Consoli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raffin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jardri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>An overview of medical risk factors for childhood psychosis: Implications for research and treatment</article-title>. <source/>Schizophr. Res.
<volume>192</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2017.05.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28526280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B29">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gloriam</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schioth</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredriksson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Nine new human Rhodopsin family G-protein coupled receptors: identification, sequence characterization and evolutionary relationship</article-title>. <source/>Biochim. Biophys. Acta
<volume>1722</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2004.12.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15777626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B30">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gochman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Childhood-onset schizophrenia: the challenge of diagnosis</article-title>. <source/>Curr. Psychiatry Rep.
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-011-0212-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21713647</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B31">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liem</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The spinocerebellar ataxia-associated gene Tau tubulin kinase 2 controls the initiation of ciliogenesis</article-title>. <source/>Cell
<volume>151</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>847</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.10.010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23141541</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B32">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnewich</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Brief report: translocation involving chromosomes 1 and 7 in a boy with childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>J. Autism Dev. Disord.
<volume>24</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02172134</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7961336</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B33">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gornick</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Dysbindin (DTNBP1, 6p22.3) is associated with childhood-onset psychosis and endophenotypes measured by the Premorbid Adjustment Scale (PAS)</article-title>. <source/>J. Autism Dev. Disord.
<volume>35</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>831</fpage>–<lpage>838</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-005-0028-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16283082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B34">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>K. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarfarazi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Localization of a human Na+,K+-ATPase alpha subunit gene to chromosome 19q12—q13.2 and linkage to the myotonic dystrophy locus</article-title>. <source/>Genomics
<volume>3</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0888-7543(88)90131-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2907504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B35">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahimene</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferron</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Genetic disruption of voltage-gated calcium channels in psychiatric and neurological disorders</article-title>. <source/>Prog. Neurobiol.
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2015.09.002.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26386135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B36">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hogervorst</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuikman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Kessel</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Molecular cloning of the human alpha 6 integrin subunit. Alternative splicing of alpha 6 mRNA and chromosomal localization of the alpha 6 and beta 4 genes</article-title>. <source/>Eur. J. Biochem.
<volume>199</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1991.tb16140.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2070796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B37">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houlden</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner-Thorpe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lashley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worth</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Mutations in TTBK2, encoding a kinase implicated in tau phosphorylation, segregate with spinocerebellar ataxia type 11</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Genet.
<volume>39</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1434</fpage>–<lpage>1436</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2007.43</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18037885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B38">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Idol</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Sequencing and analyzing the t(1;7) reciprocal translocation breakpoints associated with a case of childhood-onset schizophrenia/autistic disorder</article-title>. <source/>J. Autism Dev. Disord.
<volume>38</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>668</fpage>–<lpage>677</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-007-0435-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17879154</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B39">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>Z. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajadhyaksha</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>L-type Ca(2+) channels in mood, cognition and addiction: integrating human and rodent studies with a focus on behavioural endophenotypes</article-title>. <source/>J. Physiol.
<volume>594</volume> (<issue>20</issue>), <fpage>5823</fpage>–<lpage>5837</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP270673.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26913808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B40">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallmann</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1956</year>). <article-title>Genetic aspects of preadolescent schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Psychiatry
<volume>112</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.112.8.599</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13292546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B41">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kebir</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaumette</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Epigenetic variability in conversion to psychosis: novel findings from an innovative longitudinal methylomic analysis</article-title>. <source/>Transl. Psychiatry
<volume>8</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>93</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-018-0138-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29695761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B42">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggs</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnewich</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meck</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedwell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Brief report: association of sex chromosome anomalies with childhood-onset psychotic disorders</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
<volume>37</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-199803000-00014</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9519634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B43">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Microduplications disrupting the MYT1L gene (2p25.3) are associated with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Psychiatr. Genet.
<volume>22</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/YPG.0b013e328353ae3d</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22547139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B44">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galke</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blundell</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Genetic variation at the 22q11 PRODH2/DGCR6 locus presents an unusual pattern and increases susceptibility to schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A
<volume>99</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>3717</fpage>–<lpage>3722</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.042700699</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11891283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B45">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Allowing for sex differences increases power in a GWAS of multiplex Autism families</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>17</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2010.127.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21151189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B46">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Diagnostic classification of psychiatric disorders and familial-genetic research</article-title>. <source/>Dialogues Clin. Neurosci.
<volume>1</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22033840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B47">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amer</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alrifai</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balwi</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>X-linked ichthyosis associated with psychosis and behavioral abnormalities: a case report</article-title>. <source/>J. Med. Case Rep.
<volume>11</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>267</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13256-017-1420-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28934990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B48">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakagami</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Disturbance of cerebellar synaptic maturation in mutant mice lacking BSRPs, a novel brain-specific receptor-like protein family</article-title>. <source/>FEBS Lett.
<volume>580</volume> (<issue>17</issue>), <fpage>4057</fpage>–<lpage>4064</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2006.06.043</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16814779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B49">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Childhood-onset schizophrenia: rare but worth studying</article-title>. <source/>Biol. Psychiatry
<volume>46</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1418</fpage>–<lpage>1428</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0006-3223(99)00231-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10578456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B50">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giedd</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamburger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singaracharlu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedwell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Clinical and neurobiological correlates of cytogenetic abnormalities in childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Psychiatry
<volume>156</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1575</fpage>–<lpage>1579</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.156.10.1575</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10518169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B51">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pakhomova</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korovaitseva</surname><given-names>G. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monchakovskaia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vil’ianov</surname><given-names>V. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frolova</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasparov</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>[Molecular-genetic study of early-onset schizophrenia]</article-title>. <source/>Zh Nevrol. Psikhiatr. Im. S S Korsakova
<volume>110</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B52">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panagiotakaki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Grandis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stagnaro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinzen</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fons</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisodiya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Clinical profile of patients with ATP1A3 mutations in Alternating Hemiplegia of Childhood-a study of 155 patients</article-title>. <source/>Orphanet J. Rare Dis.
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13023-015-0335-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26410222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B53">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltrame</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeri</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fusco</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caffarra</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Exome sequencing in an Italian family with Alzheimer’s disease points to a role for seizure-related gene 6 (SEZ6) rare variant R615H</article-title>. <source/>Alzheimers Res. Ther.
<volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>106</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13195-018-0435-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30309378</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B54">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ornitz</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelman</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Autistic children who become schizophrenic</article-title>. <source/>Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
<volume>41</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1984.01790130023003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6696593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B55">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Autism spectrum disorders and childhood-onset schizophrenia: clinical and biological contributions to a relation revisited</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
<volume>48</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CHI.0b013e31818b1c63</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19218893</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B56">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Autism spectrum disorders and childhood-onset schizophrenia: clinical and biological contributions to a relation revisited</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
<volume>48</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CHI.0b013e31818b1c63</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19218893</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B57">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giedd</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Neurodevelopmental model of schizophrenia: update 2012</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>17</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1228</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2012.23</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22488257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B58">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raznahan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clasen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gochman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Catechol-o-methyl transferase (COMT) val158met polymorphism and adolescent cortical development in patients with childhood-onset schizophrenia, their non-psychotic siblings, and healthy controls</article-title>. <source/>NeuroImage
<volume>57</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1517</fpage>–<lpage>1523</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.05.032</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21620981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B59">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bick</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gastier-Foster</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Standards and guidelines for the interpretation of sequence variants: a joint consensus recommendation of the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics and the Association for Molecular Pathology</article-title>. <source/>Genet. Med.
<volume>17</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/gim.2015.30</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25741868</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B60">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosewich</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlenbusch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maschke</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altmuller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frommolt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Heterozygous de-novo mutations in ATP1A3 in patients with alternating hemiplegia of childhood: a whole-exome sequencing gene-identification study</article-title>. <source/>Lancet Neurol.
<volume>11</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>764</fpage>–<lpage>773</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(12)70182-5.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22850527</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B61">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinlein</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tregellas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>High rates of comorbidity are found in childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Schizophr. Res.
<volume>88</volume> (<issue>1–3</issue>), <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2006.07.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16916600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B62">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelsen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Epping</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreasen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wassink</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Childhood-onset schizophrenia case with 2.2 Mb deletion at chromosome 3p12.2-p12.1 and two large chromosomal abnormalities at 16q22.3-q24.3 and Xq23-q28</article-title>. <source/>Clin. Case Rep.
<volume>3</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ccr3.192</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25914809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B63">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruzzi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnoux-Palacios</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinola</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meneguzzi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Alessio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>A homozygous mutation in the integrin alpha6 gene in junctional epidermolysis bullosa with pyloric atresia</article-title>. <source/>J. Clin. Invest.
<volume>99</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>2826</fpage>–<lpage>2831</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI119474</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B64">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessman</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Co-occurrence of autism, childhood psychosis, and intellectual disability associated with a <italic>de novo</italic> 3q29 microdeletion</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. A
<volume>161A</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>845</fpage>–<lpage>849</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.a.35754</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B65">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerny</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buescher</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikezu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Tau-tubulin kinase 1 (TTBK1), a neuron-specific tau kinase candidate, is involved in tau phosphorylation and aggregation</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurochem.
<volume>98</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1573</fpage>–<lpage>1584</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2006.04059.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16923168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B66">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gornick</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Segmental uniparental isodisomy on 5q32-qter in a patient with childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>J. Med. Genet.
<volume>43</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>887</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jmg.2006.043380</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16763011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B67">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sekizawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Childhood-onset schizophrenia and tryptophan hydroxylase gene polymorphism</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. B Neuropsychiatr. Genet.
<volume>128B</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.30009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15211625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B68">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smedemark-Margulies</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tembulkar</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Towne</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A novel <italic>de novo</italic> mutation in ATP1A3 and childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Cold Spring Harb. Mol. Case Stud.
<volume>2</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <elocation-id>a001008</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/mcs.a001008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27626066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B69">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soden</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willig</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrikin</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effectiveness of exome and genome sequencing guided by acuity of illness for diagnosis of neurodevelopmental disorders</article-title>. <source/>Sci. Transl. Med.
<volume>6</volume> (<issue>265</issue>), <elocation-id>265ra168</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3010076</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B70">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soueid</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourtian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makhoul</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makoukji</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>RYR2, PTDSS1 and AREG genes are implicated in a Lebanese population-based study of copy number variation in autism</article-title>. <source/>Sci. Rep.
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>19088</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep19088</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26742492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B71">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sporn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Potocnik</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>22q11 deletion syndrome in childhood onset schizophrenia: an update</article-title>. <source/>Mol. Psychiatry
<volume>9</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001477</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14699434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B72">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sreedharan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almen</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlini</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haitina</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephansson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The G protein coupled receptor Gpr153 shares common evolutionary origin with Gpr162 and is highly expressed in central regions including the thalamus, cerebellum and the arcuate nucleus</article-title>. <source/>FEBS J.
<volume>278</volume> (<issue>24</issue>), <fpage>4881</fpage>–<lpage>4894</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2011.08388.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21981325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B73">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perfitt</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shonesy</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>A novel human CAMK2A mutation disrupts dendritic morphology and synaptic transmission, and causes ASD-related behaviors</article-title>. <source/>J. Neurosci.
<volume>37</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>2216</fpage>–<lpage>2233</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2068-16.2017.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28130356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B74">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szego</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zawati</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Whole genome sequencing as a genetic test for autism spectrum disorder: from bench to bedside and then back again</article-title>. <source/>J. Can. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
<volume>25</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27274747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B75">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usiskin</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnewich</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wudarsky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Velocardiofacial syndrome in childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
<volume>38</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1536</fpage>–<lpage>1543</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-199912000-00015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10596254</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B76">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vantalon</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Briard-Luginbuhl</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouren</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>[Fragile X syndrome and very early onset schizophrenia: a female case study]</article-title>. <source/>Arch. Pediatr.
<volume>12</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arcped.2004.11.019</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15694544</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B77">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>De novo mutations in human genetic disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat. Rev. Genet.
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3241</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22805709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B78">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vourdas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrigall</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frangou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Increased developmental deviance and premorbid dysfunction in early onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Schizophr. Res.
<volume>62</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>), <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0920-9964(02)00429-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12765738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B79">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClellan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addington</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Rare structural variants disrupt multiple genes in neurodevelopmental pathways in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Sci.
<volume>320</volume> (<issue>5875</issue>), <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1155174</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B80">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermetz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A novel microduplication in the neurodevelopmental gene SRGAP3 that segregates with psychotic illness in the family of a COS proband</article-title>. <source/>Case Rep. Genet.
<volume>2011</volume>, <fpage>585893</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/585893</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23074677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B81">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worth</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giunti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner-Thorpe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Autosomal dominant cerebellar ataxia type III: linkage in a large British family to a 7.6-cM region on chromosome 15q14-21.3</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
<volume>65</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/302495</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10417284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B82">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnewich</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenane</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Chromosome 22q11.2 interstitial deletions among childhood-onset schizophrenics and “multidimensionally impaired”</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>81</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9514586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B83">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Childhood-onset schizophrenia/autistic disorder and t(1;7) reciprocal translocation: identification of a BAC contig spanning the translocation breakpoint at 7q21</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet.
<volume>96</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>753</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1096-8628(20001204)96:6&lt;749::aid-ajmg10&gt;3.0.co;2-k</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121174</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B84">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivere</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Leukaemia hijacks a neural mechanism to invade the central nervous system</article-title>. <source/>Nat.
<volume>560</volume> (<issue>7716</issue>), <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0342-5</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B85">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gochman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadnax</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>15q13.3 duplication in two patients with childhood-onset schizophrenia</article-title>. <source/>Am. J. Med. Genet. B Neuropsychiatr. Genet.
<volume>171</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>783</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.32439.</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26968334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>