<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="case-report" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31895838</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6946260</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-19-03114</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000018695</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">18695</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>5600</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group>
<subject>Research Article</subject>
<subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ultrasonographic findings and prenatal diagnosis of Jacobsen syndrome</article-title>
<subtitle>A case report and review of the literature</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Shuang</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Ruixue</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Xinyue</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Leilei</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Yuting</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Ruizhi</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Hongguo</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>∗</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>NA.</surname>
<given-names></given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff>Center for Reproductive Medicine and Center for Prenatal Diagnosis, First Hospital, Jilin University, Changchun, China.</aff>
<author-notes id="cor1">
<corresp><label>∗</label>Correspondence: Hongguo Zhang, Center for Reproductive Medicine and Center for Prenatal Diagnosis, First Hospital, Jilin University, 71 Xinmin Street, Chaoyang District, Changchun, Jilin Province 130021, China (e-mail: <email>zhanghguo2018@163.com</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>03</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>99</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>e18695</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>13</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2020 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="medi-99-e18695.pdf" xlink:type="simple"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title>
<sec>
<title>Rationale:</title>
<p>Jacobsen syndrome (JBS) is a rare chromosomal disorder with variable phenotypic expressivity, which is usually diagnosed in infancy and childhood based on clinical examination and hematological and cytogenetic findings. Prenatal diagnosis and fetal ultrasonographic findings of JBS are rare.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Patient concerns:</title>
<p>A 38-year-old, gravida 3, para 1, pregnant woman underwent clinical ultrasound examination at 22 weeks of gestation.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Diagnoses:</title>
<p>Ultrasonographic findings indicated an interventricular septal defect, the presence of septal blood flow, dilation of the left renal pelvis, and a single umbilical artery. Amniocentesis was performed to evaluate possible genetic causes of this diagnosis by cytogenetic and single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) array analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Interventions:</title>
<p>After genetic counseling and informed consent, the couple elected to terminate the pregnancy.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Outcomes:</title>
<p>Karyotype analysis showed that the fetal karyotype was 46,XX,del(11)(q23). The SNP array revealed a 6.118 Mb duplication of 11q23.2q23.3 and a 15.03 Mb deletion of 11q23.3q25.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Lessons:</title>
<p>Ultrasonographic findings of fetal JBS, including an interventricular septal defect, dilation of the left renal pelvis, and a single umbilical artery, may be associated with a 15.03 Mb deletion of 11q23.3q25. Further cases correlating phenotype and genotype are required to predict the postnatal phenotype.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>fetus</kwd>
<kwd>Jacobsen syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>prenatal diagnosis</kwd>
<kwd>ultrasonographic findings</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
<meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec>
<label>1</label>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Jacobsen syndrome (JBS), also known as11q23 deletion syndrome, is a contiguous gene syndrome caused by partial deletion of the long arm of chromosome 11.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]</sup> JBS is a rare chromosomal disorder with variable phenotypic expressivity,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]</sup> and is usually diagnosed in infancy and childhood based on clinical examination and hematological and cytogenetic findings.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]</sup> Typical clinical features of JBS patients include multiple congenital abnormalities,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]</sup> dysmorphic features, congenital heart disease, intellectual disability,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]</sup> physical growth retardation, mental retardation, facial dysmorphism, visceral malformations,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]</sup> mild to moderate psychomotor retardation, trigonocephaly, cardiac defects,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]</sup> neonatal thrombocytopenia and persistent platelet dysfunction,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]</sup> dilation of the renal pelvis and seizures,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]</sup> combined immunodeficiency,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]</sup> or antibody deficiency.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]</sup> However, these characteristics exist variably between patients.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]</sup> This suggests that the phenotypes caused by different 11q deletions are inconsistent.</p>
<p>Since Dr Jacobsen's first report, more than 200 cases of JBS diagnosed after birth have been reported.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]</sup> However, prenatal diagnosis and fetal ultrasonographic findings are rare. We report a case of prenatal diagnosis of JBS, and describe the ultrasound findings and genetic results of a de novo duplication of chromosome 11q23.2q23.3 and deletion of chromosome 11q23.3q25. Meanwhile, this study also reviews the relationship between different 11q deletions and prenatal ultrasound findings as described in the literature.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<label>2</label>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the First Hospital, Jilin University (No. 2018-383). Patient has provided informed consent for publication of the case.</p>
<sec>
<label>2.1</label>
<title>Cytogenetic analysis</title>
<p>Fetal cells were obtained through amniocentesis after obtaining written informed consent. Then, amniocytes were collected by centrifugation, inoculated in flasks according to laboratory standards, and cultured in carbon dioxide incubators for 10 days. Chromosome analysis using G-band staining was performed as in our previous study.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]</sup> The karyotype was described according to the International System for Human Cytogenetic Nomenclature (ISCN 2013).<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]</sup> Twenty metaphases were analyzed.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<label>2.2</label>
<title>SNP array analysis</title>
<p>Genomic DNA was extracted from 10 mL of uncultured amniocytes using a QIAamp DNA Mini kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer's instructions. SNP array analysis was performed using the Human CytoScan 750K BeadChip (Affymetrix, San Diego, CA). Image data were analyzed using Chromosome Analysis Suite v3.3 software. The final results were analyzed using the Database of Chromosomal Imbalance and Phenotype in Humans using Ensembl Resources (DECIPHER), the Database of Genomic Variants (DGV), OMIM, and NCBI.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec>
<label>3</label>
<title>Case presentation</title>
<p>A 38-year-old, gravida 3, para 1, pregnant woman underwent clinical ultrasound examination at 22 weeks of gestation. Ultrasonographic findings indicated abnormalities of the single live fetus, including a single ventricle in the intracalvarium, the skull ring was completed, the width of the right ventricle was 0.89 cm and the width of the left ventricle was 0.82 cm, the biparietal diameter was 5.3 cm, the head circumference was 19.8 cm, the abdominal circumference was 16.6 cm, the femur length was 3.8 cm, and the amniotic fluid index was 13.3 cm. The main abnormal manifestations on the ultrasound images included an interventricular septal defect, the presence of septal blood flow, dilation of the left renal pelvis, and a single umbilical artery (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). After genetic counseling, the woman was offered amniocentesis for cytogenetic and single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) array analysis at 23 weeks of gestation because of advanced age in combination with these abnormal ultrasound indicators.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Prenatal ultrasound at 22 weeks of gestation showing: A: Interventricular septal defect; B: Presence of septal blood flow; C: Left renal pelvis widening; D: Single umbilical artery.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e18695-g001"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Karyotype analysis showed that the fetal karyotype was 46,XX,del(11)(q23) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The SNP array revealed a 6.118 Mb duplication of 11q23.2q23.3 and a 15.03 Mb deletion of 11q23.3q25 (11q23.2q23.3 [113790010–119907572] × 3, 11q23.3q25 [119907627–134937416] × 1) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The couple underwent cytogenetic detection. The results were both normal.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Karyotype of the fetus identified by GTG banding technique.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e18695-g002"></graphic>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p>SNP array on uncultured amniocytes depicting 11q23.2q23.3 duplication and 11q23.3q25 deletion.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e18695-g003"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Both the parents were nonconsanguineous and healthy, and their first child was healthy. The mother denied any exposure to smoking, alcohol, infectious diseases, irradiation, or teratogenic agents during this pregnancy. The chromosome aberrations of the fetus arose de novo. This case was diagnosed as JBS according to reports in the literature of JBS with del(11)(q23.3q25). After genetic counseling and informed consent, the couple elected to terminate the pregnancy.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<label>4</label>
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>JBS has an estimated occurrence of 1 in 100,000 births, with a female to male ratio of 2:1.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]</sup> Of the cases reported, 85% arose de novo and 15% may have arisen from inheritance of an unbalanced segregation of a familial balanced translocation.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]</sup> The deletion size ranged from approximately 7 to 20 Mb, and deletion of the breakpoint at 11q23.3 was found in the majority of JBS cases.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]</sup> Previous studies have shown that the fragile site in 11q23.3 is susceptible to chromosome deletion in vivo.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]</sup> The present case was a female fetus with a 15.03 Mb deletion of 11q23.3q25 and a 6.118 Mb duplication of 11q23.2q23.3.</p>
<p>For child patients who survive the neonatal period, more attention has been paid to the clinical phenotypes and the genes involved in the deleted regions.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]</sup> Patients with JBS show a wide spectrum of clinical phenotypes, and patients with the more obvious clinical features are diagnosed by the age of one.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]</sup> Previous studies have shown that 97% of JBS patients have mild to severe mental retardation; congenital heart malformations are observed in 56% of cases.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]</sup> In addition, most patients with JBS are diagnosed with either thrombocytopenia or pancytopenia. More clinical manifestations include facial dysmorphism, intellectual disability, immunodeficiency, and autism spectrum disorder.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]</sup> However, the most severe phenotypes of the patients with deletions vary between patients.</p>
<p>The present case reports prenatal diagnosis and ultrasound findings of a JBS case. Meanwhile, from a review of the literature, ultrasonographic findings of JBS were collected and are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. The ultrasound findings of the present study showed an interventricular septal defect and the presence of septal blood flow. Foley et al<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]</sup> reported fetal JBS showing hypoplastic left heart syndrome. Ye et al<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]</sup> found by animal model studies that deletion of <italic>ETS-1</italic> related to the JBS critical region can cause ventricular septal defects. These results are consistent with the high incidence of congenital heart malformation found after birth. Here, the fetus was found to have dilation of the left renal pelvis, consistent with a report by Wax et al,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]</sup> and a single umbilical artery, consistent with a report by Chen et al.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]</sup> The ultrasound findings in the published literature vary between patients. Hence, the relationship between genotype and phenotype still needs to be studied further in more cases.</p>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Prenatal diagnosis and ultrasonographic findings of Jacobsen syndrome in published literature.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="medi-99-e18695-g004"></graphic>
</table-wrap>
<p>A limitation of this study is that fetal autopsy was not performed because the couple refused consent, and so we were unable to confirm the ultrasound findings.</p>
<p>We present ultrasonographic findings of JBS in a fetus with an interventricular septal defect, dilation of the left renal pelvis, and a single umbilical artery. These abnormalities were associated with a 15.03 Mb deletion of 11q23.3q25. More cases correlating phenotype and genotype are required to predict the postnatal phenotype.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We thank Catherine Perfect, MA (Cantab), from Liwen Bianji, Edanz Editing China (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.liwenbianji.cn/ac">www.liwenbianji.cn/ac</ext-link>), for editing the English text of a draft of this manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Author contributions</title>
<p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> Ruizhi Liu.</p>
<p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Ruixue Wang, Xinyue Zhang.</p>
<p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Leilei Li, Yuting Jiang.</p>
<p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> Shuang Chen.</p>
<p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> Ruizhi Liu, Hongguo Zhang.</p>
<p>Hongguo Zhang orcid: 0000-0001-8953-863X.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="abbr">
<p>Abbreviations: DNA = deoxyribonucleic acid, EST-1 = V-ETS avian erythroblastosis virus E26 oncogene homolog 1, JBS = Jacobsen syndrome, OMIM = Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man, SNP = single nucleotide polymorphism.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>How to cite this article: Chen S, Wang R, Zhang X, Li L, Jiang Y, Liu R, Zhang H. Ultrasonographic findings and prenatal diagnosis of Jacobsen syndrome: A case report and review of the literature. <italic>Medicine</italic>. 2020;99:1(e18695).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="supported-by">
<p>This work was supported by the Special Funds of Jilin Province Development and Reform Commission, China (2017C025).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement">
<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>[1]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurcă</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Morphological and genetic abnormalities in a Jacobsen syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Rom J Morphol Embryol
<year>2017</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1531</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29556653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>[2]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afifi</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Gerzawy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Distal 11q monosomy syndrome: a report of two Egyptian sibs with normal parental karyotypes confirmed by molecular cytogenetics</article-title>. <source/>Genet Couns
<year>2008</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18564501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>[3]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valduga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannard</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Prenatal diagnosis of mosaicism for 11q terminal deletion</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Med Genet
<year>2007</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17761465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>[4]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ichimiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunishima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>11q23 deletion syndrome (Jacobsen syndrome) with severe bleeding: a case report</article-title>. <source/>J Med Case Rep
<year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29307309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>[5]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Favier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Akshoomoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Jacobsen syndrome: advances in our knowledge of phenotype and genotype</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet C Semin Med Genet
<year>2015</year>;<volume>169</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26285164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>[6]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Diagnosis and fine mapping of a deletion in distal 11q in two Chinese patients with developmental delay</article-title>. <source/>J Hum Genet
<year>2010</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>486</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20520618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>[7]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ysunza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaheen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aughton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Velopharyngeal insufficiency, submucous cleft palate and a phonological disorder as the associated clinical features which led to the diagnosis of Jacobsen syndrome. Case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source/>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol
<year>2013</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>1601</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23815883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>[8]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nalbantoğlu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Donma</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nişli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Jacobsen syndrome without thrombocytopenia: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source/>Turk J Pediatr
<year>2013</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24192682</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>[9]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossfeld</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Brain hemorrhages in Jacobsen syndrome: a retrospective review of six cases and clinical recommendations</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet A
<year>2017</year>;<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28211970</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>[10]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Pure distal 11q deletion without additional genomic imbalances in a female infant with Jacobsen syndrome and a de novo unbalanced reciprocal translocation</article-title>. <source/>Genet Couns
<year>2012</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22876581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>[11]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seppänen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koillinen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustjoki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Terminal deletion of 11q with significant late-onset combined immune deficiency</article-title>. <source/>J Clin Immunol
<year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24233263</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>[12]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blazina</surname><given-names>Š</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovrečić</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>11q terminal deletion and combined immunodeficiency (Jacobsen syndrome): case report and literature review on immunodeficiency in Jacobsen syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet A
<year>2016</year>;<volume>170</volume>:<fpage>3237</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27605496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>[13]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical feature of infertile men carrying balanced translocations involving chromosome 10: case series and a review of the literature</article-title>. <source/>Medicine (Baltimore)
<year>2018</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>e0452</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29642220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>[14]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>McGowan-Jordan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>ISCN (2013): An International System for Human Cytogenetic Nomenclature</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Basel, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Karger</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>[15]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular cytogenetic characterization of Jacobsen syndrome (11q23.3-q25 deletion) in a fetus associated with double outlet right ventricle, hypoplastic left heart syndrome and ductus venosus agenesis on prenatal ultrasound</article-title>. <source/>Taiwan J Obstet Gynecol
<year>2017</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28254208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>[16]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrotta</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossfeld</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Jacobsen syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Orphanet J Rare Dis
<year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19267933</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>[17]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dell’Aquila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical and molecular characterization of patients with distal 11q deletions</article-title>. <source/>Am J Hum Genet
<year>1995</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7887422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>[18]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Müllenbach</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossfeld</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Co-localisation of CCG repeats and chromosome deletion breakpoints in Jacobsen syndrome: evidence for a common mechanism of chromosome breakage</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<year>2000</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10767345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>[19]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akshoomoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossfeld</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evidence for autism spectrum disorder in Jacobsen syndrome: identification of a candidate gene in distal 11q</article-title>. <source/>Genet Med
<year>2015</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25058499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>[20]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossfeld</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>The 11q terminal deletion disorder: a prospective study of 110 cases</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet A
<year>2004</year>;<volume>129A</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15266616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>[21]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullarkey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Antenatal diagnosis of deletion chromosome 11(q23-qter) (Jacobsen syndrome)</article-title>. <source/>Clin Dysmorphol
<year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17551332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>[22]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coldren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Deletion of ETS-1, a gene in the Jacobsen syndrome critical region, causes ventricular septal defects and abnormal ventricular morphology in mice</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet
<year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19942620</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>[23]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wax</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Prenatal ultrasonographic findings associated with Jacobsen syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J Ultrasound Med
<year>1995</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7760474</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>[24]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Laccone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Burfeind</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Prenatal diagnosis of a large de novo terminal deletion of chromosome 11q</article-title>. <source/>Prenat Diagn
<year>2006</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16506277</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>[25]</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Nuchal thickening in Jacobsen syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol
<year>1998</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9819862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>