<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9215429</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2408</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hum Mutat</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hum. Mutat.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Human mutation</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1059-7794</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1098-1004</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31448840</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953250</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.23902</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1063692</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Xq22 deletions and correlation with distinct neurological disease traits in females: further evidence for a contiguous gene syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hijazi</surname>
<given-names>Hadia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coelho</surname>
<given-names>Fernanda S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gonzaga-Jauregui</surname>
<given-names>Claudia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bernardini</surname>
<given-names>Laura</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mar</surname>
<given-names>Soe S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manning</surname>
<given-names>Melanie A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hanson-Kahn</surname>
<given-names>Andrea</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Naidu</surname>
<given-names>SakkuBai</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Srivastava</surname>
<given-names>Siddharth</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A14">14</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>Julie R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A14">14</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Friez</surname>
<given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A14">14</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alberico</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">15</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Torres</surname>
<given-names>Barbara</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Ping</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A16">16</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cheung</surname>
<given-names>Sau Wai</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A17">17</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Xiaofei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davis-Williams</surname>
<given-names>Angelique</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">15</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jornlin</surname>
<given-names>Carly</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">15</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wight</surname>
<given-names>Patricia A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A18">18</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Patyal</surname>
<given-names>Pankaj</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A18">18</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Taube</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">15</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Poretti</surname>
<given-names>Andrea</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Ken</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A19">19</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Feng</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A20">20</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pehlivan</surname>
<given-names>Davut</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A21">21</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carvalho</surname>
<given-names>Claudia M.B.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hobson</surname>
<given-names>Grace M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">15</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN2">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lupski</surname>
<given-names>James R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A22">22</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A23">23</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A24">24</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN2">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Programa de Pós-Graduação em Genética Departmento de Biologia Geral – UFMG, Belo Horizonte, MinasGerais, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Instituto René Rachou – FIOCRUZ, Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Regeneron Genetics Center, Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Tarrytown, NY</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Cytogenetics Unit, “Casa Sollievo della Sofferenza” Foundation, San Giovanni Rotondo (FG), Italy</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Neurology, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO</aff>
<aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Stanford University School of Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, Division of Medical Genetics, Palo Alto, CA</aff>
<aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Stanford University School of Medicine, Department of Pathology, Palo Alto, CA</aff>
<aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Stanford University School of Medicine, Department of Genetics, Palo Alto, CA</aff>
<aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Lucile Packard Children’s Hospital, Department of Pediatrics, Division of Medical Genetics, Palo Alto, CA</aff>
<aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Departments of Neurology and Pediatrics, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD</aff>
<aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Department of Neurogenetics, Kennedy Krieger Institute, Baltimore, MD</aff>
<aff id="A13"><label>13</label>Department of Neurology, Boston Children’s Hospital, Boston, MA</aff>
<aff id="A14"><label>14</label>Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory, Greenwood Genetic Center, Greenwood, SC</aff>
<aff id="A15"><label>15</label>Nemours Biomedical Research, Nemours/Alfred I. duPont Hospital for Children, Wilmington, DE</aff>
<aff id="A16"><label>16</label>WuXi NextCODE, Cambridge, MA</aff>
<aff id="A17"><label>17</label>Baylor Genetics, Houston, TX</aff>
<aff id="A18"><label>18</label>Department of Physiology and Biophysics, College of Medicine, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, Little Rock, AR</aff>
<aff id="A19"><label>19</label>Department of Mental Retardation and Birth Defect Research, National Institute of Neuroscience, National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry, Kodaira, Japan</aff>
<aff id="A20"><label>20</label>Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital, State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering at School of Life Sciences, Institute of Reproduction and Development, Fudan University, Shanghai 200011, China</aff>
<aff id="A21"><label>21</label>Section of Neurology, Department of Pediatrics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX</aff>
<aff id="A22"><label>22</label>Human Genome Sequencing Center, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX</aff>
<aff id="A23"><label>23</label>Department of Pediatrics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX</aff>
<aff id="A24"><label>24</label>Texas Children’s Hospital, Houston, TX</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><bold>Corresponding authors: James R. Lupski, M.D., Ph.D., D.Sc. (hon), FAAP, FACMG, FANA, FAAAS, FAAS</bold>, Department of Molecular and Human Genetics, Baylor College of Medicine, 1 Baylor Plaza, Room 604B, Houston, TX 77030, <email>jlupski@bcm.edu</email>, Tel: (713) 798-6530, Fax: (713) 798-5073; <bold>Grace M. Hobson, PhD</bold>, Nemours Biomedical Research, Nemours/Alfred I. duPont Hospital for Children, 1600 Rockland Road, RC1, Wilmington, DE 19803, USA, Tel: +1-302-838-1771, <email>ghobson@nemours.org</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Authors’ Contributions</p>
<p id="P2">HH, CMBC, GMH, and JRL participated in the design of the study. HH performed the majority of data analyses and experiments. HH, CMBC, DP, and GH prepared the manuscript with JRL. FSC participated in the design of the study and performed some experiments and analyses. CGJ developed the HSIR computational method while at Baylor College of Medicine. LB referred a patient to this study, provided their clinical information, and performed the XCI studies on the referred case. SSM, MAM and AHK referred patients to this study and provided their clinical information. JL participated in the design of the study, performed some experiments, and together with SWC and PF facilitated anonymized sample studies and performed the XCI studies on three of the female samples. SN and SS referred a patient to this study and provided their clinical information. PP and PW performed some experiments and analyses. TA and KS performed molecular studies on one sample. JRJ and MF performed molecular studies and XCI on one samples and participated in data interpretation. JT performed in silico analyses. AP performed and interpreted MRI on one patient. XS performed the microhomeology and breakpoint-junction sequence-similarity analyses. ADW, and CJ performed molecular experiments on two samples. KI reviewed the clinical information and helped with clinical interpretation. FZ participated in the design of the study and performed some experiments. GMH provided samples and data for this study, participated in data interpretation and critically revised the manuscript. DP reviewed and analyzed the clinical information, prepared the clinical table and critically revised the manuscript. CMBC performed experiments, participated in data interpretation and critically revised the manuscript. JRL participated in data analysis and interpretation, oversaw the manuscript preparation, and critically revised the manuscript. All authors approved the final submitted version of the manuscript, and are accountable for the accuracy and integrity of the work.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN2">
<label>*</label>
<p id="P3">James R. Lupski and Grace M. Hobson should be considered joint senior authors</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3">
<p id="P64">Declarations</p>
<p id="P65">Competing Interests</p>
<p id="P66">Baylor College of Medicine (BCM) and Miraca Holdings have formed a joint venture with shared ownership and governance of the Baylor Genetics (BG), which performs clinical microarray analysis and clinical exome sequencing. CG-J is currently a full-time employee of Regeneron Pharmaceuticals Inc. and receives stock options as part of compensation. J.R.L. serves on the Scientific Advisory Board of the BG. J.R.L. has stock ownership in 23andMe, is a paid consultant for Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, and is a co-inventor on multiple United States and European patents related to molecular diagnostics for inherited neuropathies, eye diseases, and bacterial genomic fingerprinting. The Department of Molecular and Human Genetics at Baylor College of Medicine derives revenue from molecular genetic testing offered in the Baylor Genetics Laboratories. Nemours Biomedical Research derives revenue from molecular genetic testing offered in the Nemours Molecular Diagnostics Laboratory. The Greenwood Genetic Center receives revenue from diagnostic testing performed in the GGC Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory. The other authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>16</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>10</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>150</fpage>
<lpage>168</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/humu.23902-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P4">Xq22 deletions that encompass <italic>PLP1</italic> (Xq22-<italic>PLP1</italic>-DEL) are notable for variable expressivity of neurological disease traits in females ranging from a mild late-onset form of Spastic Paraplegia type 2 [MIM# 312920], sometimes associated with skewed X-inactivation, to an early-onset neurological disease trait (EONDT) of severe developmental delay, intellectual disability and behavioral abnormalities. Size and gene content of Xq22-<italic>PLP1</italic>-DEL vary and were proposed as potential molecular etiologies underlying variable expressivity in carrier females where two smallest regions of overlap (SROs) were suggested to influence disease. We ascertained a cohort of eight unrelated patients harboring Xq22-<italic>PLP1</italic>-DEL and performed high-density array Comparative Genomic Hybridization (aCGH) and breakpoint-junction sequencing. Molecular characterization of Xq22-<italic>PLP1</italic>-DEL from 17 cases (8 herein and 9 published) revealed an overrepresentation of breakpoints that reside within repeats (11/17, ~65%) and the clustering of ~47% of proximal breakpoints in a genomic instability hotspot with characteristic non-B DNA density. These findings implicate a potential role for genomic architecture in stimulating the formation of Xq22-<italic>PLP1</italic>-DEL. The correlation of Xq22-<italic>PLP1</italic>-DEL gene content with neurological disease trait in female cases enabled refinement of the associated SROs to a single genomic interval containing six genes. Our data support the hypothesis that genes contiguous to <italic>PLP1</italic> contribute to EONDT.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>BEX3</kwd>
<kwd>RAB40A</kwd>
<kwd>TCEAL4</kwd>
<kwd>TCEAL3</kwd>
<kwd>TCEAL1</kwd>
<kwd>MORF4L2</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>