<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101139309</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">30413</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Lancet. Neurology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1474-4422</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1474-4465</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31160204</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6995665</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30150-4</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1067899</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Diagnosis, epidemiology, assessment, pathophysiology, and management of fetal alcohol spectrum disorders</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wozniak</surname>
<given-names>Jeffrey R.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Riley</surname>
<given-names>Edward P.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Charness</surname>
<given-names>Michael E.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>M.D.</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">University of Minnesota (JRW); San Diego State University (EPR); VA Boston Healthcare System, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, and Boston University School of Medicine (MEC).</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="present-address" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Edward P. Riley, Center for Behavioral Teratology, SDSU, 6330 Alvarado Ct. #100, San Diego, CA 92120</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="present-address" id="FN2">
<p id="P2">Michael E. Charness, VA Boston Healthcare System, 1400 VFW Parkway, West Roxbury, MA 02132.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN3">
<p id="P3">Contributions</p>
<p id="P4">All three authors contributed equally to the conceptual development, literature review, and the drafting and revision of this paper. All three authors have given final approval of the submitted version and agree to be held accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1"><bold>Address Correspondence and Requests for Reprints</bold>: Jeffrey R. Wozniak, Ph.D., Department of Psychiatry, F282/2A West, 2450 Riverside Ave., Minneapolis, MN 55454, 612-273-9741; <email>jwozniak@umn.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN5">
<p id="P43">Declaration of interests</p>
<p id="P44"><bold>Jeffrey R. Wozniak, Ph.D.:</bold> Dr. Wozniak reports receiving grant funding from the National Institutes of Health, National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA) during the writing of this review.</p>
<p id="P45"><bold>Edward P. Riley, Ph.D.:</bold> Dr. Riley reports receiving grant funding from NIAAA during the writing of this review; he also is on the Board of Directors of the National Organization on Fetal Alcohol Syndrome (NOFAS), although he is not compensated for his board service.</p>
<p id="P46"><bold>Michael E. Charness, M.D.:</bold> Dr. Charness reports receiving grant funding from the National Institutes of Health, National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA) and the Medical Research Service of the Department of Veteran Affairs during the writing of this review. Dr. Charness also receives royalties from a chapter in UpToDate on neurological complications of alcoholism. Dr. Charness holds two US patents related to compounds that block the effects of alcohol on the L1 cell adhesion molecule and decrease the teratogenic effects of alcohol: #6,359,015 “Antagonists of alcohol inhibition of cell adhesion” and #6,977,272 B2 “Method for antagonizing inhibition effects of alcohol on cell adhesion”.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>24</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>31</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>02</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>760</fpage>
<lpage>770</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30150-4-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P5">Prenatal alcohol exposure (PAE) frequently causes neurodevelopmental disorder, yet fetal alcohol spectrum disorders (FASD) are often undiagnosed. Global prevalence rates of 0.77% for FASD and European / North American rates of 2–5% highlight the need for neurologists to engage in identification, assessment, and treatment of this preventable disorder. Diagnosis remains challenging because of limitations of self-report of drinking, lack of biomarkers, and infrequency of diagnostic dysmorphic facial features. Multiple diagnostic systems and disagreement over diagnostic criteria have slowed progress in the field. PAE impacts neurodevelopment through diverse mechanisms including oxidative injury, apoptosis, modulation of gene expression, and disruption of neuronal migration / axon pathfinding. Neuroimaging reveals abnormal brain structure, cortical development, white matter microstructure, and functional connectivity. These abnormalities modify developmental trajectories and are associated with deficits in cognition, executive function, memory, vision, hearing, motor skills, behavior, and social adaptation. Trials of promising nutritional interventions and cognitive rehabilitation are underway.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>