<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="brief-report" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Brain</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Brain</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">brainj</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Brain</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0006-8950</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-2156</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31855252</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7009479</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awz391</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">awz391</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Homozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> variant causes encephalopathy and gain-of-function in synaptic transmission</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lammertse</surname>
<given-names>Hanna C A</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="awz391-FM1"></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van Berkel</surname>
<given-names>Annemiek A</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="awz391-FM1"></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Iacomino</surname>
<given-names>Michele</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Toonen</surname>
<given-names>Ruud F</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Striano</surname>
<given-names>Pasquale</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gambardella</surname>
<given-names>Antonio</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="awz391-cor1"></xref>
<!--<email>matthijs@cncr.vu.nl</email>-->
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Verhage</surname>
<given-names>Matthijs</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="awz391-cor2"></xref>
<!--<email>a.gambardella@unicz.it</email>-->
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zara</surname>
<given-names>Federico</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="awz391-aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="awz391-aff1"><label>1</label>
<institution>Department of Clinical Genetics, Center for Neurogenomics and Cognitive Research (CNCR), University Medical Center Amsterdam</institution>, De Boelelaan 1085, 1081 HV Amsterdam, The <country country="NL">Netherlands</country></aff>
<aff id="awz391-aff2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Department of Functional Genomics, Center for Neurogenomics and Cognitive Research (CNCR), VU University Amsterdam</institution>, De Boelelaan 1085, 1081 HV Amsterdam, The <country country="NL">Netherlands</country></aff>
<aff id="awz391-aff3"><label>3</label>
<institution>Laboratory of Neurogenetics and Neuroscience, IRCCS Istituto G. Gaslini</institution>, Via Gerolamo Gaslini 5, 16147 Genova, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff>
<aff id="awz391-aff4"><label>4</label>
<institution>IRCCS Istituto “G. Gaslini”</institution>, Genova, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff>
<aff id="awz391-aff5"><label>5</label>
<institution>Department of Neurosciences, Rehabilitation, Ophthalmology, Genetics, Maternal and Child Health, University of Genova</institution>, Genova, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff>
<aff id="awz391-aff6"><label>6</label>
<institution>Institute of Neurology, University Magna Græcia</institution>, Catanzaro, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="awz391-cor1">Correspondence to: M. Verhage Department of Clinical Genetics, Center for Neurogenomics and Cognitive Research (CNCR), University Medical Center Amsterdam, De Boelelaan 1085, 1081 HV Amsterdam, The Netherlands E-mail: <email>matthijs@cncr.vu.nl</email></corresp>
<corresp id="awz391-cor2">Correspondence may also be addressed to: A. Gambardella Institute of Neurology, University Magna Græcia, Catanzaro, Italy E-mail: <email>a.gambardella@unicz.it</email></corresp>
<fn id="awz391-FM1">
<p>Hanna C.A. Lammertse and Annemiek A. van Berkel contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date iso-8601-date="2019-12-19" pub-type="epub">
<day>19</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>19</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
<volume>143</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>441</fpage>
<lpage>451</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>5</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>9</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>29</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) (2019). Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Guarantors of Brain.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="awz391.pdf"></self-uri>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>Heterozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutations are associated with severe neurodevelopmental symptoms. Lammertse <italic>et al.</italic> describe a homozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> variant that causes clinical features of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, and show that the functional consequences of this mutation are strikingly different from the heterozygous mutations.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title>
<p>Heterozygous mutations in the <italic>STXBP1</italic> gene encoding the presynaptic protein MUNC18-1 cause <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy, characterized by developmental delay, intellectual disability and epilepsy. Impaired mutant protein stability leading to reduced synaptic transmission is considered the main underlying pathogenetic mechanism. Here, we report the first two cases carrying a homozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutation, where their heterozygous siblings and mother are asymptomatic. Both cases were diagnosed with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. In Munc18-1 null mouse neurons, protein stability of the disease variant (L446F) is less dramatically affected than previously observed for heterozygous disease mutants. Neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> showed minor changes in morphology and synapse density. However, patch clamp recordings demonstrated that L446F causes a 2-fold increase in evoked synaptic transmission. Conversely, paired pulse plasticity was reduced and recovery after stimulus trains also. Spontaneous release frequency and amplitude, the readily releasable vesicle pool and the kinetics of short-term plasticity were all normal. Hence, the homozygous L446F mutation causes a gain-of-function phenotype regarding release probability and synaptic transmission while having less impact on protein levels than previously reported (heterozygous) mutations. These data show that <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutations produce divergent cellular effects, resulting in different clinical features, while sharing the overarching encephalopathic phenotype (developmental delay, intellectual disability and epilepsy).</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>
<italic>STXBP1</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>epilepsy</kwd>
<kwd>neurodevelopmental disorder</kwd>
<kwd>Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>synaptic transmission</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">Italian League against Epilepsy</named-content>
</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">Italian Ministry of Health</named-content>
</funding-source>
<award-id>RF-2016-02361949</award-id>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">Era-Net Neuron</named-content>
</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">Netherlands Scientific Organisation and De Hersenstichting</named-content>
</funding-source>
<award-id>013-17-002</award-id>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">Neuron Cofund ERA-Net SNAREopathy</named-content>
</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">Comorbidity and Synapse Biology in Clinically Overlapping Psychiatric Disorders</named-content>
</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">European Union</named-content>
<named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100000780</named-content>
</funding-source>
<award-id>667301</award-id>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">European Research Council</named-content>
<named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100010663</named-content>
</funding-source>
</award-group>
<award-group award-type="grant">
<funding-source>
<named-content content-type="funder-name">ERC</named-content>
<named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100010663</named-content>
</funding-source>
<award-id>322966</award-id>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<page-count count="11"></page-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Mutations in the <italic>STXBP1</italic> gene are associated with infantile encephalopathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B25">Saitsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), recently termed ‘<italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B30">Stamberger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Developmental delay and intellectual disability are hallmarks of <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy. Most patients experience epileptic seizures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B11">Hamdan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B9">Gburek-Augustat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Clinical heterogeneity is observed for patients carrying a <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutation, such as the severity of the developmental delay and intellectual disability, response to antiepileptic treatment and specific EEG abnormalities. This clinical heterogeneity leads to range of clinical diagnoses, including Ohtahara, and West syndromes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B30">Stamberger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p>
<p>The <italic>STXBP1</italic> gene encodes the Sec1p/Munc18 (SM) protein MUNC18-1. Mammalian MUNC18-1 organizes the protein complexes that drive secretory vesicle exocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B32">Toonen and Verhage, 2007</xref>). Synaptic transmission is critically dependent on MUNC18-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B34">Verhage <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>) and cellular MUNC18-1 levels correlate with synaptic strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B33">Toonen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>All currently reported patients with <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy carry a heterozygous mutation, ranging from full gene deletions to single point mutations occurring across the entire length of the gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B30">Stamberger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Multiple lines of evidence support the hypothesis that haploinsufficiency is the main pathogenic mechanism underlying <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy, which may explain the lack of a genotype–phenotype correlation. The probability of being loss-of-function intolerant is extremely high for <italic>STXBP1</italic> (pLI = 1), and it is therefore considered to fall in the ‘haploinsufficient’ gene category (gnomAD v2.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B14">Karczewski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy variants affect the cellular levels of the Munc18-1 protein in <italic>in vitro</italic> models of the disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B26">Saitsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B10">Guiberson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Moreover, heterozygous <italic>Stxbp1</italic> (Munc18-1 null) mice recapitulate <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy symptoms including cognitive impairments and epileptic seizures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B23">Orock <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p>
<p>Here, we present two siblings carrying a homozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutation and displaying the electroclinical features of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. The functional consequences of the mutation in a cellular model are strikingly different from heterozygous mutations modelled previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B10">Guiberson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec>
<title>Animals</title>
<p>Munc18-1 null mutant (knockout) mice were described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B34">Verhage <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Embryonic Day 18 (E18) embryos were obtained by caesarean section. Animals were housed and bred according to the Institutional and Dutch governmental guidelines.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Primary neuronal cultures</title>
<p>Neuronal cultures and rat glia islands were prepared as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B27">Santos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Cortical neurons were plated at a density of 600 000 cells/well on poly-<sc>l</sc>-ornithine/laminin coated 6-well plates for western blot analysis. Hippocampal neurons were plated at a density of 6000 cells/well on top of pregrown rat glia islands on 18 mm coverslips for immunocytochemistry and electrophysiology.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Constructs and lentiviral particles</title>
<p>Constructs encoding pSynapsin-Munc18<sup>WT</sup>-T2A-CreGFP or pSynapsin-Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>-T2A-CreGFP were subcloned into pLenti vectors, and viral particles were produced as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B21">Naldini <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Munc18-1 null neurons were infected with lentiviral particles at 0 days <italic>in vitro</italic> (DIV).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Western blot</title>
<p>HEK293T cells were infected with lentiviral particles expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> in Opti-MEM™ (Life Technologies) for 2 days. Neuronal cultures were collected at DIV 14. Western blot was executed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Protein levels were assessed using rabbit Munc18-1 (1:1000, 2701; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B4">Cijsouw <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) and mouse GFP (1:1000, eBioscience). GFP and Munc18-1 are translated in a 1:1 ratio as a result of the T2A linking sequence. GFP levels were used to normalize Munc18-1 expression levels.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Immunocytochemistry and confocal microscopy</title>
<p>Single isolated Munc18-1 null neurons expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> were fixed on DIV 14–15 with 3.7% formaldehyde. Neurons were stained as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B27">Santos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Antibodies used were chicken anti-MAP2 (1: 500; Abcam), rabbit anti-Munc18-1 (1:500; 2701; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B4">Cijsouw <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) and mouse anti-VAMP (1:1000; SySy). Images were acquired with a confocal microscope (LSM 510, Carl Zeiss) using a 40× oil immersion objective (NA = 1.3) with 0.7× zoom at 1024 × 1024 pixels and 2× averaging. Synapse morphology and protein levels were analysed using automated image analysis in MATLAB (SynD; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B28">Schmitz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and ImageJ software.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Electrophysiology</title>
<p>Single isolated Munc18-1 null neurons were in culture for DIV 14–15 prior to patch-clamp recordings. Recordings were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B20">Meijer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) and the experimenter was blinded to experimental groups. Analysis was performed using in-house written MATLAB scripts and Clampfit (Molecular Devices, v. 10.7). Size of the readily releasable pool (RRP) and the recruitment rate were estimated by a back-extrapolation procedure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 3A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B22">Neher, 2015</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analysis and graphing was performed using GraphPad Prism versions 5 and 6 and MATLAB (MathWorks Inc., v.2017a). Parametric tests were used whenever assumptions of homoscedasticity and normality were met. Otherwise, non-parametric tests were used. All statistical tests were two-tailed. An error probability level of <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05 was accepted as statistically significant. All cellular data were plotted in box-and-whisker plots with Tukey-style whiskers.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data availability</title>
<p>Data are available upon request.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec>
<title>Only homozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic><sup>L446F</sup> carriers show developmental epileptic encephalopathy</title>
<p>A family with two siblings with epilepsy and intellectual disability referred to the Neurology Unit at University Magna Graecia. The first proband (Individual 2, <xref ref-type="table" rid="awz391-T1">Table 1</xref>) was a 23-year-old female, presenting with development delay from birth, refractory epilepsy, severe intellectual disability and behavioural abnormalities. Multiple seizure types were observed, including tonic, atypical absences, ‘drop attacks’ and occasional catamenial non-convulsive status epilepticus, lasting up to several hours. Awake and sleep EEG recordings revealed a slow, disorganized background activity and high voltage, generalized 1.5–2 cycles/s spike and wave activity in addition to bursts of 10–12 Hz generalized paroxysmal fast activity during slow sleep (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>B). The 26-year-old sister (Individual 3, <xref ref-type="table" rid="awz391-T1">Table 1</xref>) displayed a highly similar neurological and electroclinical phenotype, albeit with more moderate intellectual disability. Both probands are on anti-epileptic polytherapy, achieving partial seizure control in proband 3. Their 51-year-old mother, and their 28- and 20-year-old sisters were asymptomatic and showed normal intelligence.
</p>
<table-wrap id="awz391-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Clinical features of affected sisters and direct relatives</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" span="1" valign="top"/>
<col align="center" span="1" valign="top"/>
<col align="center" span="1" valign="top"/>
<col align="center" span="1" valign="top"/>
<col align="center" span="1" valign="top"/>
<col align="center" span="1" valign="top"/>
</colgroup>
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subject</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th>
<th colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current age, years</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age at epilepsy onset, years</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of epilepsy, years</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Previous febrile seizures</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes (18 months)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type of seizures</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tonic, tonic-clonic, atypical absences, atonic seizures, episodes of non-convulsive status</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tonic, tonic-clonic, atypical absences, atonic seizures, episodes of non-convulsive status</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EEG</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5–2 Hz generalized spike-and-wave; generalized fast rhythms at 12 Hz during sleep</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5–2 Hz generalized spike-and-wave, generalized fast rhythms at 12 Hz during sleep</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brain MRI</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Some subcortical areas of increased T<sub>2</sub>-weighted signal intensity with no mass effect or contrast enhancement</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arnold-Chiari type 1 without syringomelia</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neurological exam</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kinetic and postural tremor of the arms and brisk reflexes</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kinetic and postural tremor of the arms, pes cavus</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neuropsychiatric symptoms</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe mental retardation (IQ &lt;35); moderate/severe behavioural problems with hyperactivity and aggressive behaviour</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate mental retardation (IQ 46); mild behavioural problems with hyperactivity and aggressive behaviour</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Therapy</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Valproate + felbamate + acetazolamide + levetiracetam + rufinamide</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Valproate + levetiracetam + rufinamide + clobazam (partial seizure control)</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="tblfn1">
<p>The proband is a 23-year-old female, presenting with refractory epilepsy, severe intellectual disability (IQ &lt;35), hyperactivity and aggressive behaviour. She showed developmental delay from birth and suffered from isolated febrile seizures at the age of 18 months. Tonic seizures during sleep were observed since the age of two. Afterwards, multiple seizure types occurred such as tonic, atypical absences, and ‘drop attacks’. Awake and sleep EEG recordings revealed a slow and disorganized background activity, and the classic high voltage, generalized 1.5–2 Hz spike and wave activity in addition to bursts of 10–12 Hz generalized paroxysmal fast activity during slow sleep. Moreover, she also occasionally experienced catamenial non-convulsive status epilepticus which could last up to several hours. A 3 T brain MRI study revealed non-specific subcortical areas of increased T<sub>2</sub>-weighted signal intensity. Several anti-seizure drugs were unsuccessful. She is currently on valproate, felbamate, acetazolamide, levetiracetam, and rufinamide. Her 26-year-old sister showed developmental delay and the same neurological phenotype featuring early-onset tonic, atypical absences, and ‘drop attacks’ from the age of 3 years, moderate intellectual disability (IQ = 46), hyperactivity and aggressive behaviour. Her EEG showed high-voltage, generalized 1.5–2 Hz spike and wave activity associated with bursts of generalized paroxysmal fast activity during slow sleep. A polytherapy with valproate, levetiracetam, rufinamide, and clobazam achieved a partial seizure control, with persistence of atypical absences and drop attacks, mainly during her menstrual cycle. A 3 T MRI study revealed Arnold-Chiari 1 malformation without syringomyelia. Their 51-year-old mother, and their 28- and 20-year-old sisters were asymptomatic and showed normal intelligence. NA = not available.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="awz391-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>
<bold>Identification of homozygous missense mutation MUNC18<sup>L446F</sup> in two affected patients.</bold> (<bold>A</bold>) Pedigree of the family showing the two affected (red circle) homozygous sisters (dark filled circle) for the L446F missense mutation. One sibling does not carry the mutation and another one is heterozygous, as is the mother (half-filled circle). The father was not available for analysis. (<bold>B</bold>) EEG recording from one of the two homozygous carriers. Note the bursts of generalized paroxysmal fast activity at 10–12 Hz that last for a few seconds (red box) and tend to recur at brief intervals during slow sleep. The discharges are usually followed by slow waves and generalized poly-spike and wave complexes. (<bold>C</bold>) Electropherograms of the individuals as indicated in <bold>A</bold>, showing the c.1336 C &gt; T missense mutation in Individuals 1 and 5 (heterozygous), 2 and 3 (homozygous). (<bold>D</bold>) Amino acid alignment of human MUNC18-1 protein to its homologues in <italic>Mus musculus</italic> (Munc18-1), <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (Rop) and <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Unc18). Blue box indicates the Leu446 residue, which is conserved across the indicated species. (<bold>E</bold>) Disease-associated mutations (black bars) and population variants (grey bars) are found throughout the three domains of the Munc18-1 protein. Leu446 is located in domain 3. Protein crystal structure of the Munc18-1 protein (PDB 3c98) bound to syntaxin 1 (grey) shows the Leu446 residue in red. Nearby disease-associated and population variants are indicated.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="awz391f1"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Whole-exome sequencing in the probands revealed a homozygous missense variant in exon 15 (c.1336C&gt;T, p.L446F) of <italic>STXBP1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>C and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). The mother and one sibling were heterozygous carriers of the mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>C). Protein sequence alignment showed that the Leu446 residue is evolutionary conserved from <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> to <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>D). The L446F variant is located in domain 3 of the MUNC18-1 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>E, top) in the hydrophobic core (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>E, bottom), and has not been documented before as either disease-causing or asymptomatic variant. In close proximity to L446F, multiple heterozygous disease-associated and asymptomatic mutations (gnomAD v2.1 for Ensembl gene ID ENSG00000136854; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B14">Karczewski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) are reported (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>E).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>The L-F mutation supports viability and does not have a profound effect on cellular protein levels</title>
<p>Heterozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy mutations have been reported to severely reduce Munc18-1 protein levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B26">Saitsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B10">Guiberson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). To assess the effect on protein levels, the L446F variant was expressed in HEK293 cells with wild-type or the previously characterized heterozygous disease mutation C522R as controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F2">Fig. 2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 2A</xref>). Munc18<sup>C552R</sup> levels were 90% reduced, as reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> levels showed a clear trend towards a reduction (not significant), albeit less severe than for Munc18<sup>C552R</sup>. Power analysis predicted that 10 independent samples would be required to detect a 50% reduction at <italic>P </italic>= 0.05.
</p>
<fig id="awz391-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p>
<bold>Cellular stability and morphological characterization of Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> in Munc18-1 null neurons and HEK293 cells.</bold> (<bold>A</bold>) HEK293 cells were virally infected with Munc18<sup>WT</sup>, homozygous pathogenic variant Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> and heterozygous disease variant Munc18<sup>C522R</sup>. Western blot analysis of normalized Munc18-1 levels shows that Munc18<sup>C522R</sup> presents significantly lower levels than Munc18<sup>WT</sup> [Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.508, interquartile range (IQR) = 0.340–0.727; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.187, IQR = 0.134–0.267; Munc18<sup>C522R</sup> median = 0.143, IQR = 0.085–0.199; <italic>P </italic>= 0.0006, Kruskal-Wallis test with <italic>post hoc</italic> Dunn’s multiple comparisons test]. Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> has no significant changes in levels compared to either Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and disease variant Munc18<sup>C522R</sup>. Munc18 levels were normalized to GFP levels. Relative Munc18 levels were normalized to the mean Munc18<sup>WT</sup> levels for visualization. (<bold>B</bold>) Munc18<sup>WT</sup>, homozygous disease variant Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> and heterozygous disease variant Munc18<sup>C522R</sup> were expressed in Munc18-1 null neurons through lentiviral infection. Protein levels of Munc18<sup>C522R</sup> are lower than Munc18<sup>WT</sup> (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 1.587, IQR = 1.401–2.278; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.978, IQR = 0.578–1.296; Munc18<sup>C522R</sup> median = 0.397, IQR = 0.228–0.526; <italic>P = </italic>0.0012, Kruskal-Wallis test with <italic>post hoc</italic> Dunn’s multiple comparisons test), whereas levels of Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> are not significantly different from Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and Munc18<sup>C522R</sup>. Munc18 levels were normalized to GFP levels. Relative Munc18 levels were normalized to the mean Munc18<sup>WT</sup> levels for visualization. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative images (with zoom) of Munc18-1 null neurons expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>, stained for MAP2 (dendritic marker), Munc18-1 and VAMP (synaptic marker). (<bold>D</bold>) Total dendritic length is decreased in Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> neurons (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 1243, IQR = 738–1645; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 833.4, IQR = 592.5–1254; <italic>P = </italic>0.035, Mann-Whitney U-test). (<bold>E</bold>) Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> neurons show decreased number of synapses per μm<sup>2</sup> dendrite (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.382, IQR = 0.326–0.465; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.296, IQR = 0.262–0.444; <italic>P = </italic>0.028, unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test). (<bold>F</bold>) Average synapse area is not altered between neurons expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.511, IQR = 0.480–0.577; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.519, IQR = 0.477–0.547; <italic>P = </italic>0.894, Mann-Whitney U-test). (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> neurons do not present lower Munc18-1 levels in synapses (<bold>G</bold>) (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 1276, IQR = 754.1–1789; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 893.8, IQR = 584–1376; <italic>P = </italic>0.091, Mann-Whitney U-test) or in dendrites (<bold>H</bold>) (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 654.6, IQR = 471–894; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 479.7, IQR = 353.6–641.7; <italic>P = </italic>0.094, Mann-Whitney U-test) by immunocytochemistry. The number of analysed cells and number of independent cultures tested is indicated below the graphs. *<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="awz391f2"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Munc18-1 serves an essential, cell-autonomous role in neuronal viability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B27">Santos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). We tested whether the L446F mutation compromises this role by expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup>, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> or Munc18<sup>C522R</sup> in Munc18-1 null mouse neurons. Neurons depending on Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> or Munc18<sup>C522R</sup> only, showed normal survival until 15 DIV. At DIV13–15, C522R levels were significantly lower than wild-type, whereas L446F levels again showed a trend towards reduced levels (not significantly different from wild-type and C522R) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F2">Fig. 2</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 2B</xref>). Power analysis predicted that 13 independent samples would be required to detect a 50% reduction at <italic>P </italic>= 0.05. Together, these data show that Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> supports neuronal viability as well as wild-type Munc18-1 and has a less drastic effect on cellular protein levels than previously characterized heterozygous disease variants.</p>
<p>Neuronal morphology was analysed in single isolated Munc18-1 null neurons expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F2">Fig. 2</xref>C). Dendrites of neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> were 25% shorter than wild-type neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F2">Fig. 2</xref>D) and the number of synapses per µm<sup>2</sup> dendrite was 15% lower (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F2">Fig. 2</xref>E). Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> and Munc18<sup>WT</sup> expressing neurons had similar synapse sizes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F2">Fig. 2</xref>F) and Munc18-1 levels in synapses and dendrites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F2">Fig. 2</xref>G and H). Hence, neurons that depend on Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> have slightly reduced size and synapse density.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> enhances evoked synaptic transmission and reduced paired-pulse facilitation</title>
<p>Patch-clamp electrophysiology was used to compare synaptic transmission in Munc18-1 null mutant neurons expressing either Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>. The frequency of spontaneous miniature excitatory postsynaptic current (mEPSC) events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>A and B) and their amplitude was similar between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>C). However, the postsynaptic current in response to action potential stimulation (EPSC; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>D) was approximately 2-fold larger in neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> both in amplitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>E) and charge transferred during the response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>F). The ratio between paired sets of stimuli (paired-pulse ratio, typical example shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>G) was significantly smaller for Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>-expressing neurons at most time intervals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>H).
</p>
<fig id="awz391-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p>
<bold>Patch-clamp electrophysiological characterization of Munc18-1 null neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>.</bold> (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) Spontaneous release of synaptic vesicles is not significantly altered by expression of Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>. (<bold>A</bold>) Example traces of spontaneous release of single synaptic vesicles (mEPSCs) of Munc18-1 null neurons expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>. (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) No differences are observed in spontaneous mEPSC frequency (<bold>B</bold>: Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 3.253 Hz, IQR = 0.584–7.49; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 6.473 Hz, IQR = 1.375–13.25; <italic>P = </italic>0.165, Mann-Whitney U-test) and amplitude (<bold>C</bold>: Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = −20.76 pA, IQR = −24.19–18.24; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = −21.28 pA, IQR = −24.29–18.03; <italic>P = </italic>0.943, unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test) between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>. (<bold>D</bold>–<bold>F</bold>) Evoked synaptic responses are increased in neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>. (<bold>D</bold>) Typical examples of a single evoked EPSC. Stimulus artefact has been blanked out for visualization purposes. (<bold>E</bold>) Average EPSC amplitude is significantly larger in neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> compared Munc18<sup>WT</sup> (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 3.332 nA, IQR = 2.213–5.798; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 7.716 nA, IQR = 3.838–13.81; <italic>P = </italic>0.0018, Mann-Whitney U-test) and in parallel, the average charge (<bold>F</bold>) transferred during the EPSC response is increased (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 37.36 pC, IQR = 27.65–77.65; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 117.0 pC, IQR = 43.69–164.7; <italic>P = </italic>0.0012, Mann-Whitney U-test). (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) Paired-pulse recordings at various intervals were performed to quantify release probability. (<bold>G</bold>) Example traces showing an overlay of paired-pulse recordings at several time intervals (20–50–100–200–500 ms interpulse interval) for a neuron expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>. (<bold>H</bold>) Paired-pulse ratios (calculated as the ratio of the second EPSC to the first EPSC) are significantly higher for neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> at the stimulus intervals between 0.05 and 0.5 s (0.02 s: Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.488, IQR = 0.363–0.880; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.479, IQR = 0.317–0.657, <italic>P = </italic>0.109, unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test with Welch’s correction; 0.05 s: Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.872, IQR = 0.689–1.198; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.701, IQR = 0.544–0.849, <italic>P = </italic>0.0103; 0.1 s: Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.913, IQR = 0.743–1.157; Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.732, IQR = 0.589–0.891, <italic>P = </italic>0.0045; 0.2 s: Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.873, IQR = 0.754–0.955, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.777, IQR = 0.625–0.866, <italic>P </italic>= 0.0207; 0.5 s: Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 0.833, IQR = 0.775–0.905, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 0.751, IQR = 0.614–0.839, <italic>P = </italic>0.019, Mann-Whitney U-tests). (<bold>I</bold>) Estimate of the RRP by back-extrapolation indicates no difference in RRP size between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 432.7 pC, IQR = 220.1–803.6, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 455.4 pC, IQR = 300.3–1219, <italic>P </italic>= 0.511, Mann-Whitney U-test). (<bold>J</bold>) Total charge transferred during the 40-Hz train stimulation is not significantly different between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 1488 pC, IQR = 724.4–2424, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 1296 pC, IQR = 939.0–2239, <italic>P = </italic>0.594, Mann-Whitney U-test). (<bold>K</bold>) Run-down kinetics and steady-state responses to 100 action potentials at 10 Hz are similar between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>, except for the first few pulses (<italic>inset</italic>) at which neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> display more pronounced depression compared to Munc18<sup>WT</sup>. (<bold>L</bold>) EPSC rundown in response to a stimulation of 100 action potentials at 40 Hz are also similar between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and Munc18<sup>L446F</sup>. <italic>Inset</italic>: first five pulses of the train. (<bold>M</bold>) EPSC amplitude in response to single action potential stimulations 2 and 30 s after the 10-Hz train stimulation expressed as a percentage of the amplitude of the first EPSC of the train stimulation. Neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> have a smaller EPSC response at 2 s (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 65.96%, IQR = 53.26–82.32, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 43.27%, IQR = 28.32–56.44, <italic>P = </italic>0.0003, Mann-Whitney U-test) and 30 s (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 81.15%, IQR = 62.58–100.6, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 70.29%, IQR = 53.31–77.36, <italic>P = </italic>0.021, Mann-Whitney U-test) after a 10-Hz train. (<bold>N</bold>) Recovery of the RRP was measured at 2 and 60 s after the train, respectively. After 2 s, recovery is not significantly different but shows a trend towards a reduction in Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> expressing neurons (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 84.22%, IQR = 50.45–104.0, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 63.92%, IQR = 46.39–76.59, <italic>P = </italic>0.068, Mann-Whitney U-test). Sixty seconds after 40-Hz stimulation, neurons expressing Munc18<sup>WT</sup> show full recovery whereas recovery is impaired in neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 94.90%, IQR = 83.97–107.5, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 83.93%, IQR = 73.73–91.31, <italic>P = </italic>0.0396, unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test with Welch’s correction). (<bold>O</bold>) Recruitment rate of vesicles at steady-state during 40 Hz stimulation as estimated by the back-extrapolation procedure (<bold>C</bold>) is not different between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> (Munc18<sup>WT</sup> median = 388.5 s<sup>−1</sup>, IQR = 160.7–755.8, Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> median = 377.3 s<sup>−1</sup>, IQR = 243.4–484.4, <italic>P = </italic>0.778, Mann-Whitney U-test). The number of analysed cells and number of independent cultures tested is indicated below the graphs. *<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="awz391f3"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>In addition to single stimulation, we tested evoked synaptic responses to repetitive (‘train’) stimulation. The increased response to stimulation could be due to an increase in the number of vesicles that are release-ready, which can be estimated based on a pool-depleting stimulation train at 40 Hz frequency. The estimated size of the RRP (estimated by back-extrapolation, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 3A</xref>) was similar in Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> expressing neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>I) and no difference was observed in the total charge transferred during a pool-depleting 40 Hz stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>J).</p>
<p>The difference in response amplitude observed upon single stimuli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>E and F) was again observed at the start of the train stimulations at 10 and 40 Hz. The rundown of successive responses followed a similar kinetic pattern between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> and Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> expressing neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>K and L for 10 and 40 Hz, respectively). The EPSC response to a single stimulation after high-frequency stimulation, termed ‘recovery’, was impaired in neurons expressing Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> up to 60 s after a high-frequency stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>M and N for 10 and 40 Hz, respectively). The EPSC amplitude of Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> neurons reached similar levels to Munc18<sup>WT</sup> but not the increased amplitude that was observed in naïve neurons (<italic>cf</italic>. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 3C and E</xref>).</p>
<p>The impaired recovery may be caused by a deficit in the recruitment of new synaptic vesicles into the RRP. However, the steady state vesicle recruitment, which can be estimated from the cumulative plots in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 3A</xref>, was not different between Munc18<sup>WT</sup> or Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> expressing neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F3">Fig. 3</xref>O).</p>
<p>During repetitive stimulation, many vesicles fuse without tight coupling to the action potentials because of the build-up of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the terminals and possibly mediated by distinct release machinery (‘asynchronous’ release; for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B13">Kaeser and Regehr, 2014</xref>). The relative contribution of synchronous and asynchronous components to the total charge transferred during the 40-Hz train was similar (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. 3B</xref>). Together these data show that Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> causes an increase in evoked synaptic transmission, a decrease in paired pulse plasticity and an impaired recovery following high-frequency stimulation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study identified two sisters carrying a homozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutation. Functional analysis demonstrated that L446F mutation results in a gain-of-function at the cellular level unlike heterozygous mutations so far described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B10">Guiberson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p>
<sec>
<title>The L446F mutation in <italic>STXBP1</italic>/Munc18-1 causes a gain-of-function on synaptic transmission</title>
<p>Neurons expressing Munc18-1<sup>L446F</sup> show a 2-fold increased synaptic response, indicating that twice as many synaptic vesicles fuse with the plasma membrane upon a single action potential stimulation than in neurons expressing wild-type Munc18-1. In addition, the paired-pulse ratio is reduced. This ratio is inversely proportional to the initial release probability of synaptic vesicles: a neuron with a high initial release probability releases a larger fraction of release-ready vesicles, and fewer remain for subsequent stimuli. Hence, these findings imply that Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> causes a gain-of-function on evoked synaptic transmission by increasing the initial release probability. The L446F mutation may increase the release probability of vesicles indirectly, possibly by influencing ‘superpriming’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B31">Taschenberger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) of a larger fraction of synaptic vesicles and/or by more efficiently preventing the off-pathway (de-priming) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B12">He <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B24">Prinslow <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>).</p>
<p>A gain-of-function phenotype in synaptic genetic disorders is rare, as disease-associated mutations in presynaptic genes are typically loss-of-function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B8">Fassio <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B5">Corradini <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B29">Schubert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B2">Baker <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). However, a gain-of-function phenotype was recently observed for the presynaptic protein Munc13, also resulting in a severe neurodevelopmental disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B18">Lipstein <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Homozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic>-variant L446F causes specific symptoms of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</title>
<p>
<italic>STXBP1</italic>-encephalopathy cases share two to three main clinical features (developmental delay, intellectual disability, and almost always epilepsy), but individual patients show substantial clinical heterogeneity and the primary diagnosis is diverse, including Ohtahara and West syndromes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B30">Stamberger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). To date, only two heterozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> carriers have been diagnosed as Lennox-Gastaut syndrome based on minimal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B7">Epi4K Consortium <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) or undisclosed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B3">Carvill <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) criteria. For homozygous L446F carriers described in the current study, the electroclinical phenotype is clearly pathognomonic for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B6">Cross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>): (i) multiple seizure types, including tonic, atonic and atypical absence seizures, with predominantly nocturnal tonic seizures; (ii) abnormal EEG, with interictal, diffuse, slow spike-wave complexes at &lt;3 Hz during wakefulness; and (iii) paroxysmal fast rhythms (10–20 Hz) during non-REM sleep. These features may eventually emerge in more than the two heterozygous patients described to date as a progressive aspect of STXBP1 encephalopathy. However, none of the other &gt;250 heterozygous carriers characterized to date (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awz391-F1">Fig. 1</xref>E), have had these three cardinal pathognomonic Lennox-Gastaut syndrome criteria described. Hence, the combination of these three Lennox-Gastaut syndrome symptoms may be unique for the (homozygous) L446F variant, for gain-of-function <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutations and/or for recessive mutations. Exome sequencing did not reveal additional variants that could be readily associated to the phenotype, but we cannot exclude that the other genetic factors may contribute to the clinical profile.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Loss- and gain-of-function <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutations cause shared and unique clinical features</title>
<p>Heterozygous <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy mutations are clear loss-of-function mutations in terms of protein stability and some also of synaptic transmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B10">Guiberson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B15">Kovačević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). In contrast, the Munc18<sup>L446F</sup> mutation has a less pronounced effect on protein stability, and a gain-of-function effect on synaptic transmission. Thus, at the synaptic level, homozygous and heterozygous disease mutations have opposite effects. At the clinical level, the two homozygous patients display all three main clinical <italic>STXBP1</italic> encephalopathy features (developmental delay, intellectual disability, epilepsy). Hence, opposite effects at the synaptic level lead to the same main clinical features. Different (opposite) changes in the molecular function of MUNC18-1 may ultimately lead to a similar net activity imbalance at the brain circuit level and thereby to the same clinical features. However, at the phenotypic level, the L446F homozygous mutation leads to distinct (electroclinical) symptoms, characteristic of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. These distinct symptoms may provide the first indications of underlying heterogeneity between homozygous and heterozygous disease mutations and/or between gain- and loss-of-function mutations. More detailed clinical assessments, especially of seizure types and EEG abnormalities, will be instrumental for future subclassification of <italic>STXBP1</italic> cases, to unmask differential disease mechanisms at the network level and to design rational intervention strategies.</p>
<p>Previous studies have shown that both loss- and gain-of-function heterozygous mutations produce similar epileptic encephalopathies, e.g. for mutations in <italic>KCNA2</italic>, <italic>SCN2A</italic> and <italic>SCNA8</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B17">Larsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B19">Masnada <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B36">Wolff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Recently, two homozygous cases carrying <italic>SCN2A</italic> mutations have been reported to lead to severe complex neurological phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B1">AlSaif <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B37">Yılmaz, 2019</xref>). These findings are consistent with other neurological dominant disorders, where very rare homozygous individuals share a similar phenotype with heterozygous family members, usually more severe, suggesting an additive effect on the gene product dysfunction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B35">Wexler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="awz391-B16">Labate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). However, functional analysis was not available for these variants. The situation for <italic>STXBP1</italic> mutations seems to be quite unique, displaying the same main clinical features for carriers of homozygous mutations that are recessive and of heterozygous mutations that cause haploinsufficiency. Thus, our study highlights the impact of allelic diversity and specificity in the pathogenesis and phenotypic expression of monogenic neurological disorders.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1">
<label>awz391_Supplementary_Data</label>
<media xlink:href="awz391_supplementary_data.pdf">
<caption>
<p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="ack1">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The authors thank Robbert Zalm for his help with cloning and virus production, Joke Wortel for breeding mutant mice and Joost Hoetjes genotyping of mutant mice. We thank Ingrid Saarloos for culturing of HEK293 cells, and Frank den Oudsten and Desiree Schut for preparation of glia feeder plates. The authors also thank Vincent Huson for developing MATLAB routines used for analysis of the electrophysiological data.</p>
<sec>
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This work was supported by the Italian League against Epilepsy (F.Z.), the Italian Ministry of Health (RF-2016-02361949, F.Z.); Era-Net Neuron (SNAREopathy to F.Z.), R.F.T. was supported by the Netherlands Scientific Organisation and De Hersenstichting (013-17-002), under the frame of Neuron Cofund ERA-Net SNAREopathy; COSYN (Comorbidity and Synapse Biology in Clinically Overlapping Psychiatric Disorders; Horizon 2020 Program of the European Union under RIA grant agreement 667301 to M.V.); a European Research Council (ERC) advanced grant (322966) of the European Union (to M.V.).</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Competing interests</title>
<p>The authors report no competing interests.</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<ref-list id="ref1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="awz391-B1">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>AlSaif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Umair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alfadhel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biallelic <italic>SCN2A</italic> gene mutation causing early infantile epileptic encephalopathy: case report and review</article-title>. <source/>J Cent Nerv Syst Dis<year>2019</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>117957351984993</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B2">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grozeva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Kogelenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Identification of a human synaptotagmin-1 mutation that perturbs synaptic vesicle cycling</article-title>. <source/>J Clin Invest<year>2015</year>; <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>1670</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25705886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B3">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvill</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heavin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yendle</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Roak</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Targeted resequencing in epileptic encephalopathies identifies de novo mutations in CHD2 and SYNGAP1</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet<year>2013</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>825</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23708187</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B4">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cijsouw</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broeke</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broek</surname><given-names>JAC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schut</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Munc18-1 redistributes in nerve terminals in an activity- and PKC-dependent manner</article-title>. <source/>J Cell Biol<year>2014</year>; <volume>204</volume>: <fpage>759</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24590174</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B5">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corradini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donzelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welzl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martucci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>epileptiform activity and cognitive deficits in SNAP-25+/− mice are normalized by antiepileptic drugs</article-title>. <source/>Cereb Cortex<year>2014</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B6">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Auvin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falip</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Striano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arzimanoglou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Expert opinion on the management of Lennox–Gastaut Syndrome: treatment algorithms and practical considerations</article-title>. <source/>Front Neurol<year>2017</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29085326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B7">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">Epi4K Consortium<name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berkovic</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cossette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delanty</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dlugos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>De novo mutations in epileptic encephalopathies</article-title>. <source/>Nature<year>2013</year>; <volume>501</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23934111</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B8">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fassio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Congia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onofri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>SYN1 loss-of-function mutations in autism and partial epilepsy cause impaired synaptic function</article-title>. <source/>Hum Mol Genet<year>2011</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B9">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gburek-Augustat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beck-Woedl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tzschach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoening</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riess</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Epilepsy is not a mandatory feature of STXBP1 associated ataxia-tremor-retardation syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Paediatr Neurol<year>2016</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27184330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B10">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guiberson</surname><given-names>NGL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abramov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kharel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carnazza</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wragg</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Mechanism-based rescue of Munc18-1 dysfunction in varied encephalopathies by chemical chaperones</article-title>. <source/>Nat Commun<year>2018</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>3986</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266908</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B11">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamdan</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrzeniecka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lortie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mottron</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanasse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Intellectual disability without epilepsy associated with STXBP1 disruption</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Hum Genet<year>2011</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21364700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B12">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wierda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Westen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broeke</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toonen</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelisse</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Munc13-1 and Munc18-1 together prevent NSF-dependent de-priming of synaptic vesicles</article-title>. <source/>Nat Commun<year>2017</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>15915</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28635948</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B13">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaeser</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Regehr</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular mechanisms for synchronous, asynchronous, and spontaneous neurotransmitter release</article-title>. <source/>Annu Rev Physiol<year>2014</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24274737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B14">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karczewski</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francioli</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alföldi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Variation across 141, 456 human exomes and genomes reveals the spectrum of loss-of-function intolerance across human protein-coding genes</article-title>. <source/>bioRxiv<year>2019</year>; <fpage>531210</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B15">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovačević</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maroteaux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schut</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pitsch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Protein instability, haploinsufficiency, and cortical hyper-excitability underlie STXBP1 encephalopathy</article-title>. <source/>Brain<year>2018</year>; <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>1350</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29538625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B16">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tarantino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mumoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gagliardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Homozygous c.649dupC mutation in <italic>PRRT2</italic> worsens the BFIS/PKD phenotype with mental retardation, episodic ataxia, and absences</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia<year>2012</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>e196</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23126439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B17">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carvill</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kluger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmiedel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barisic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The phenotypic spectrum of SCN8A encephalopathy</article-title>. <source/>Neurology<year>2015</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25568300</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B18">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipstein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhoeven-Duif</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michelassi</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calloway</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hasselt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pienkowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Synaptic UNC13A protein variant causes increased neurotransmission and dyskinetic movement disorder</article-title>. <source/>J Clin Invest<year>2017</year>; <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>1005</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28192369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B19">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masnada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedrich</surname><given-names>UBS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiwar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Clinical spectrum and genotype–phenotype associations of KCNA2-related encephalopathies</article-title>. <source/>Brain<year>2017</year>; <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>2337</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29050392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cijsouw</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toonen</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic effects of Munc18-1 alternative splicing in excitatory hippocampal neurons</article-title>. <source/>PLoS One<year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B21">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naldini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blomer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ory</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>In vivo gene delivery and stable transduction of nondividing cells by a lentiviral vector</article-title>. <source/>Science (80-)<year>1996</year>; <volume>272</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B22">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Merits and limitations of vesicle pool models in view of heterogeneous populations of synaptic vesicles</article-title>. <source/>Neuron<year>2015</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>1131</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402599</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B23">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Munc18-1 haploinsufficiency impairs learning and memory by reduced synaptic vesicular release in a model of Ohtahara syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Mol Cell Neurosci<year>2018</year>; <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29217410</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prinslow</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stepien</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y-Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rizo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Multiple factors maintain assembled trans-SNARE complexes in the presence of NSF and alpha-SNAP</article-title>. <source/>Elife<year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B25">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tohyama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>De novo mutations in the gene encoding STXBP1 (MUNC18-1) cause early infantile epileptic encephalopathy</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet<year>2008</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>782</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B26">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orii</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoshino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>STXBP1 mutations in early infantile epileptic encephalopathy with suppression-burst pattern</article-title>. <source/>Epilepsia<year>2010</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>2397</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20887364</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B27">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wierda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broeke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toonen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Early Golgi abnormalities and neurodegeneration upon loss of presynaptic proteins Munc18-1, Syntaxin-1, or SNAP-25</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci<year>2016</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>4525</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B28">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hjorth</surname><given-names>JJJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joemai</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wijntjes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eijgenraam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bruijn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Automated analysis of neuronal morphology, synapse number and synaptic recruitment</article-title>. <source/>J Neurosci Methods<year>2011</year>; <volume>195</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B29">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siekierska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huneau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Mutations in STX1B, encoding a presynaptic protein, cause fever-associated epilepsy syndromes</article-title>. <source/>Nat Genet<year>2014</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1327</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25362483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B30">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamberger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikanorova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Accorsi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Angriman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benkel-herrenbrueck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Capovilla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>STXBP1 encephalopathy: a neurodevelopmental disorder including epilepsy</article-title>. <source/>Neurology<year>2016</year>; <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B31">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taschenberger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woehler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Superpriming of synaptic vesicles as a common basis for intersynapse variability and modulation of synaptic strength</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci<year>2016</year>; <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>E4548</fpage>–<lpage>E4557</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27432975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B32">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toonen</surname><given-names>RFG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Munc18-1 in secretion: lonely Munc joins SNARE team and takes control</article-title>. <source/>Trends Neurosci<year>2007</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17956762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B33">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toonen</surname><given-names>RFG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wierda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sons</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wit</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelisse</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brussaard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Munc18-1 expression levels control synapse recovery by regulating readily releasable pool size</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci<year>2006</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B34">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verhage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plomp</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brussaard</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heeroma</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Synaptic assembly of the brain in the absence of neurotransmitter secretion</article-title>. <source/>Science (80-)<year>2000</year>; <volume>287</volume>: <fpage>864</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B35">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wexler</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanzi</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Starosta-Rubinstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penney</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Homozygotes for Huntington’s disease</article-title>. <source/>Nature<year>1987</year>; <volume>326</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2881213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B36">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johannesen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedrich</surname><given-names>UBS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masnada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubboli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genetic and phenotypic heterogeneity suggest therapeutic implications in SCN2A-related disorders</article-title>. <source/>Brain<year>2017</year>; <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>1316</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28379373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="awz391-B37">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yılmaz</surname><given-names>HÖ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Homozygous SCN2A gene mutation causing early infantile epileptic encephalopathy: the second case in literature</article-title>. <source/>Med Sci Discov<year>2019</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<glossary>
<def-list>
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<def-item>
<term>EPSC = </term>
<def>
<p>excitatory postsynaptic current</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term>RRP = </term>
<def>
<p>readily releasable pool</p>
</def>
</def-item>
</def-list>
</glossary>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>