<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">2984726R</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">1011</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochem J</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biochem. J.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Biochemical journal</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0264-6021</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1470-8728</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27555610</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7014977</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BCJ20160585</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1068737</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Plasma metabolic profile delineates roles for neurodegeneration, pro-inflammatory damage and mitochondrial dysfunction in the <italic>FMR1</italic> premutation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giulivi</surname>
<given-names>Cecilia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Napoli</surname>
<given-names>Eleonora</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tassone</surname>
<given-names>Flora</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Halmai</surname>
<given-names>Julian</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hagerman</surname>
<given-names>Randi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Molecular Biosciences, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of California Davis, CA 95616,</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Medical Investigation of Neurodevelopmental Disorders (MIND) Institute, University of California Davis, CA 95817,</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Pediatrics University of California Davis Medical Center, Sacramento CA 95817,</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, School of Medicine, University of California Davis, CA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Author contribution statement</p>
<p id="P2">C. Giulivi conceptualized and designed the study, wrote the manuscript, and approved the final manuscript as submitted; E. Napoli separated the plasma from all blood samples, contributed to the writing of the manuscript, revised and approved the final version as submitted; F. Tassone provided the CGG repeat sizing, revised the manuscript and approved the final manuscript as submitted; J. Halmal helped with the collection and classification of nutritional supplements and medications, revised and approved the manuscript as submitted; R. Hagerman carried out clinical assessment of the subjects, wrote clinical findings, revised the manuscript and approved the final manuscript as submitted.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Dr. Cecilia Giulivi, Department of Molecular Biosciences, University of California, 1089 Veterinary Medicine Dr., VetMed 3B #3009, Davis, CA 95616, <email>cgiulivi@ucdavis.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3">
<p id="P46">Declaration of interest</p>
<p id="P47">The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. R. Hagerman has received funding from Novartis, Roche/Genentech, Alcobra, Zynerba, and Neuren for treatment trials in fragile X syndrome, autism and Down syndrome. She has also consulted with Novartis and Roche/Genentech regarding treatment for fragile X syndrome. The other authors have no financial disclosures relevant to this article.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>27</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>23</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>01</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>12</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>473</volume>
<issue>21</issue>
<fpage>3871</fpage>
<lpage>3888</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1042/BCJ20160585-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P3">Carriers of premutation CGG expansions in the fragile X mental retardation 1 (<italic>FMR1</italic>) gene are at higher risk of developing a late-onset neurodegenerative disorder named Fragile X-tremor ataxia syndrome (FXTAS). Given that mitochondrial dysfunction has been identified in fibroblasts, PBMC and brain samples from carriers as well as in animal models of the premutation and that mitochondria are at the center of intermediary metabolism, the aim of this study was to provide a complete view of the metabolic pattern by uncovering plasma metabolic perturbations in premutation carriers. To this end, metabolic profiles were evaluated in plasma from 23 premutation individuals and 16 age- and sex-matched controls. Among the affected pathways, mitochondrial dysfunction was associated with a Warburg-like shift with increases in lactate levels and altered Krebs’ intermediates, neurotransmitters, markers of neurodegeneration, and increases in oxidative stress-mediated damage to biomolecules. The number of CGG repeats correlated with a subset of plasma metabolites, which are implicated in mitochondrial disorders but also in other neurological diseases such as Parkinson’s, Alzheimer’s and Huntington’s diseases. For the first time, the identified pathways shed light on disease mechanisms contributing to morbidity of the premutation, with the potential of assessing metabolites in longitudinal studies as indicators of morbidity or disease progression, especially at the early pre-clinical stages.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary" id="ABS2">
<title>Summary statement</title>
<p id="P4">Our study defines the potential use of plasma metabolic profiling to monitor brain pathophysiology in carriers of a 50–200 CGG expansion (premutation) in the 5’UTR fragile X mental retardation 1 (<italic>FMR1</italic>) gene before the onset of the neurodegenerative disorder FXTAS.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Fragile X</kwd>
<kwd>metabolomics</kwd>
<kwd>mitochondrial dysfunction</kwd>
<kwd>neurodegeneration</kwd>
<kwd>trinucleotide repeat disease</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>