<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Mol Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Mol. Neurosci</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Molecular Neuroscience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0895-8696</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1559-1166</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31838722</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7018782</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1456</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12031-019-01456-z</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Identification of De Novo JAK2 and MAPK7 Mutations Related to Autism Spectrum Disorder Using Whole-Exome Sequencing in a Chinese Child and Adolescent Trio-Based Sample</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jiao</surname>
<given-names>Jian</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Manxue</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Pingyuan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Yan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Xiao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Jia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Chan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Situ</surname>
<given-names>Mingjing</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Hui</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>Lei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Kuifang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Yi</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>huangyu@scu.edu.cn</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412901.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1770 1022</institution-id><institution>Mental Health Center, </institution><institution>West China Hospital of Sichuan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chengdu, China </aff>
<aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13291.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0807 1581</institution-id><institution>Psychiatric Laboratory, State Key Laboratory of Biotherapy, West China Hospital, </institution><institution>Sichuan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chengdu, Sichuan China </aff>
<aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412901.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1770 1022</institution-id><institution>Brain Research Center, </institution><institution>West China Hospital of Sichuan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chengdu, China </aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>14</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>70</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>219</fpage>
<lpage>229</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>4</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement>
<license license-type="OpenAccess">
<license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="Par1">Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a neurodevelopmental disorder with high phenotypic and genetic heterogeneity. Whole-exome sequencing studies have shown that de novo single-nucleotide variations (SNVs) play an important role in sporadic ASD. The present study aimed to search for de novo SNVs using whole-exome sequencing in 59 unrelated Chinese ASD sporadic trios, and found 24 genes (including five reported ASD candidate genes <italic>CACNA1D</italic>, <italic>ACHE</italic>, <italic>YY1</italic>, <italic>TTN</italic>, and <italic>FBXO11</italic>) with de novo harmful SNVs. Five genes (<italic>CACNA1D</italic>, <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>ACHE</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and <italic>PRKAG2</italic>) classified as “medium-confidence” genes were found to be related to ASD using the Phenolyzer gene analysis tool, which predicts the correlation between the candidate genes and the ASD phenotype. De novo SNVs in <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and <italic>PRKAG2</italic> were first found in ASD. Both <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> were involved in the regulation of the MAPK signaling pathway. Gene co-expression and inter-gene interaction networks were constructed and gene expression data in different brain regions were further extracted, revealing that <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> genes were associated with certain previously reported ASD genes and played an important role in early brain development. The findings of this study suggest that the aforementioned five reported ASD genes and <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> may be related to ASD susceptibility. Further investigations of expression studies in cellular and animal models are needed to explore the mechanism underlying the involvement of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> in ASD.</p>
<sec>
<title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
<p>The online version of this article (10.1007/s12031-019-01456-z) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group xml:lang="en">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>Autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
<kwd>De novo single-nucleotide variations</kwd>
<kwd>
<italic>JAK2</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>
<italic>MAPK7</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>Whole-exome sequencing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
<meta-value>© Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2020</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="Sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="Par2">Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a lifelong neurodevelopmental condition with a prevalence of 1–2% of the general population (Lai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2014</xref>; Lord et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2018</xref>). According to the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition</italic> (DSM-V), the ASD category includes autistic disorder, Asperger’s disorder, pervasive developmental disorders not otherwise specified, and childhood disintegrative disorder (Lord et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2018</xref>). The core symptoms of this disease are persistent deficits in social communication and restricted, repetitive sensory-motor behaviors (Lord et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2018</xref>). A substantial portion of individuals with ASD require lifelong support, thus constituting a huge burden for both families and society (Lavelle et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2014</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par3">Various pieces of evidence have indicated that genetics plays an important role in the etiological mechanism of ASD. Consistency rates in monozygotic twins, dizygotic twins, and siblings of 30–99%, 0–65%, and 3–30%, respectively, have been found, with an estimated overall heritability of 0.7–0.8 (Bailey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1995</xref>; Rosenberg et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2009</xref>; Hallmayer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2011</xref>; Colvert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2015</xref>). Early genetic studies focused on identifying multiple genetic lineages to support genetic linkage analysis aimed at identifying chromosomal regions commonly inherited by patients with the disease. However, only two loci (one in chromosome 20p13 and the other in chromosome 7q35) reached statistical significance across the genome and could be replicated in different studies (Alarcon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2002</xref>; Weiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2009</xref>; Werling et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2014</xref>). Based on this, quantitative phenotypes (language delay and social responsiveness) were found to be related to <italic>CNTNAP2</italic> on chromosome 7q35 (Alarcon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2002</xref>; Chiocchetti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2015</xref>). However, this method was less efficient in complex diseases due to the combined effects of many genetic and environmental factors (Sener et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2016</xref>). The genome-wide association study (GWAS), as a powerful data-driven approach for identifying common variants with low penetrance, permits an unbiased and comprehensive scan for susceptibility genes and has greater statistical power than the linkage study (Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>). This method was used to assess the contribution of common variants to ASD, revealing that they accounted for 40–60% of the total deficits (Gaugler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2014</xref>). As this method requires a large sample size, only <italic>CDH9</italic> and <italic>CDH10</italic> on 5p14.1 and <italic>MACROD2</italic> on 20p12.1 reached genome-wide significance (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2009</xref>; Anney et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2010</xref>; Ramaswami et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2018</xref>). However, these results have not been replicated in other studies. Many small-scale chromosomal abnormalities have been found by array comparative genomic hybridization and microarray techniques, confirming that the copy number variation (CNV) is closely related to ASD. Based on this, de novo CNVs, such as duplication of 7q11.23 and microdeletion of 16p11.2, were found to be recurrent in patients with ASD (Sanders et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2011</xref>; Blumenthal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>). Nevertheless, many genes with CNVs located at noncoding regions and the sizes of de novo CNVs exhibited large differences, which involved excessive heterogeneity, making it difficult to determine the role of a specific gene in the disease.</p>
<p id="Par4">Relative to the noncoding region, the exon region represents less than 1% of the human genome but contains 85% of known disease-causing genetic variants (Sener et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2016</xref>). High-throughput sequencing technology has made it possible to detect de novo or rare point mutations in the coding region in genes. Whole-exome sequencing (WES) technology is used to identify the variations in all coding regions of genes, and to some extent it overcomes the research deficiencies mentioned earlier (Sener et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2016</xref>). Another advantage is that specific genes with genetic variations can be discovered in sporadic cases, and the relevant biological pathways can be further studied (Sener et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2016</xref>). Since 2011, WES has led to the identification of many new susceptibility genes with de novo single-nucleotide variations (SNVs), which play an important role in sporadic cases of ASD. It has been estimated that 400–1000 genes may be related to ASD (Geschwind et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2015</xref>). Despite its high heritability, ASD is genetically complex, and the underlying genetic architecture is still not well understood (Schaaf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011</xref>; Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>). Notably, one study found that only 13% of de novo missense mutations in the coding region of genes contributed to 12% of diagnoses (Iossifov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2014</xref>), implying that more than 80% of de novo missense mutations were not true ASD pathogenic mutations and may not be related to the ASD phenotype. Therefore, the selection of de novo missense mutations has become a problem requiring further investigation. Relevant software programs (e.g., SIFT [Sorting Intolerant From Tolerant], MutationTaster) have been used to assess the harmfulness and conservation of gene mutation sites (Thongnak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2018</xref>). Other software tools, such as RVIS [Residual Variation Intolerance Score] (Ronemus et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2014</xref>) and TADA [Transmission And De novo Association] (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2016</xref>), which prioritize the list of genes depending on the impact of mutations and assess the tolerance of genes to genetic mutations, have also been used. However, the relationship between genes and phenotypes has not been analyzed or predicted. Moreover, although several studies have conducted WES in ASD on relatively large sample sizes and performed functional verification at the cellular level based on the de novo SNVs found in the special genes (Sadybekov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2017</xref>; Wen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>), few studies have reported on a multiple-expression level, such as multigene co-expression, inter-gene interaction, or gene expression analysis in the brain region, to verify the role of de novo SNVs in the phenotypes of ASD. Therefore, in the present study, WES was conducted in 59 family trios with a child with ASD; de novo SNVs were selected using comprehensive bioinformatics and multiple-expression analysis to confirm the results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec2">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="Sec3">
<title>Patient Recruitment and Demographic Characteristics</title>
<p id="Par5">The patients were recruited from the second outpatient department of the West China Mental Health Center of Sichuan University, special education schools, and nursery and primary schools in Chengdu city, in addition to online recruitment. A child psychiatrist used the DSM-V criteria to make a preliminary clinical diagnosis in the children, and the patients with ASD were then diagnosed independently by two well-trained child psychiatrists using the Autism Diagnostic Interview-Revised (ADIR) (Lord et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1994</xref>) and Autism Diagnostic Observational Schedule (ADOS) (Lord et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1989</xref>). Any patient who had definite somatic or hereditary disease, including congenital heart disease, Rett syndrome, Down syndrome, fragile X syndrome, phenylketonuria, or epilepsy, was excluded. Parents who had no other relatives diagnosed with ASD within three family generations signed informed consent for genetic testing. Eventually, a total of 59 ASD trios participated in this study (probands: male/female = 57:2, ADIR: 40.05 ± 16.26, ADOS: 18.31 ± 4.79, intelligence quotient: 84.11 ± 23.65, age: 8.71 ± 3.05). The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of the West China Hospital and was conducted in accordance with the ethical guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec4">
<title>Whole-Exome Sequencing</title>
<p id="Par6">Blood was obtained from all members of the 59 trios using an ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) anticoagulation tube, and genomic DNA was extracted from the whole blood. DNA degradation and suspected RNA/protein contamination were verified by electrophoresis in 1% agarose gel. The DNA sample concentration and purity were further precisely quantified using the Qubit dsDNA HS Assay Kit in the Qubit 3.0 Fluorometer (Life Technologies/Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The exome sequences were efficiently enriched from 0.4-μg genomic DNA, which was required for library generation using the Agilent SureSelect Human All Exon V6 liquid capture system (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA USA), according to the manufacturer’s protocol. The DNA library was sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 4000 system (Illumina, Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) for paired-end 150 bp reads.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec5">
<title>Data Processing and Variant Calling</title>
<p id="Par7">Quality control was followed by filtering reads with adapter contamination (&gt;10 nucleotides not aligned to the adapter, allowing ≤10% mismatches) and discarding a paired read if &gt;10% of bases were uncertain in either read so as to guarantee a meaningful downstream analysis. Paired reads in which any of the single reads had more than 50% low-quality (Phred quality &lt;5) nucleotides were also discarded. Valid sequencing data were mapped to the reference genome (GRCh37/hg19) using the Burrows-Wheeler Aligner (BWA) software to obtain the original mapping result in the BAM format. Subsequently, SAMtool and Picard (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://broadinstitute.github.io/picard/">http://broadinstitute.github.io/picard/</ext-link>), which are software programs using internationally accepted filtering criteria, were respectively used to sort bam files and perform duplicate marking to generate the final bam file. These duplicate reads were uninformative and not considered as evidence for variants. The Picard was employed to mark these duplicates so that they could be ignored in the following analysis. After this process, SAMtools, mpileup, and bcftools were used for variant calling and identification of SNVs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec6">
<title>Functional Annotation and Filter</title>
<p id="Par8">To further examine the association between genetic variation and disease, ANNOVAR [ANNOtate VARiation] (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2010</xref>) was used to functionally annotate variations that were obtained in the previous steps. The variant position, variant type, conservative prediction, and other information were obtained from several databases, including dbSNP [Single Nucleotide Polymorphism Database] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/</ext-link>), the International Genome Sample Resource from the 1000 Genomes Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.1000genomes.org/">http://www.1000genomes.org/</ext-link>), ExAC [Exome Aggregation Consortium] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://exac.broadinstitute.org/">http://exac.broadinstitute.org/</ext-link>), HGMD [Human Gene Mutation Database] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hgmd.cf.ac.uk/ac/index.php/">http://www.hgmd.cf.ac.uk/ac/index.php/</ext-link>), and CADD [Combined Annotation-Dependent Depletion] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cadd.gs.washington.edu/">https://cadd.gs.washington.edu/</ext-link>). As this study was focused on the exonic variants, gene transcript annotation databases, including Consensus Coding Sequence Project (CDS), RefSeq [NCBI Reference Sequence Database], Ensembl, and the University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) Genome Browser, were also applied for annotation to determine the amino acid alteration. Variants obtained from previous steps were then filtered with the minor allele frequency &gt; 1% in the 1000 Genomes databases (1000 Genomes Project Consortium). Only rare SNVs occurring in exons or in canonical splice sites (splicing junction 10 bp) were further analyzed to investigate the amino acid changes. Harmful mutations in all nonsynonymous SNVs were retained using the SIFT (Ng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2003</xref>), MutationTaster (Schwarz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2010</xref>), and gerp++gt2 (Davydov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2010</xref>) software to categorize the detrimental mutation types.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec7">
<title>Primers and Sanger Sequencing Validation</title>
<p id="Par9">As WES is performed by fragment sequencing, the sequencing error rate is relatively high (Ku et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2012</xref>), and it is important to further validate the identified de novo variants using Sanger sequencing. As nonsynonymous and harmful variants of genes are likely to be associated with true ASD candidate genes (Hnoonual et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2016</xref>; Miryounesi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>), the gene harmful mutation sites were verified using Sanger sequencing. These mutation sites were as follows: <italic>ACHE</italic> (c.G1165A: p. E389K); <italic>TMUB2</italic> (c.G112A: p. V38I); <italic>YY1</italic> (c.G961A: p.G321S); <italic>AOC1</italic> (c.C1687T: p. R563C); <italic>PRAG1</italic> (c.C2783T: p. S928F); <italic>KIF15</italic> (c.T796A: p. L266I; c.G832A: p. E278K); <italic>JAK2</italic> (c.G649C: p. V217L); <italic>MAPK</italic> (c.C709T: p.R237C); <italic>RNF31</italic> (c.C1624T: p. R542C); <italic>CACNA1D</italic> (c.C4127T: p. T1376M); <italic>C1GALT1</italic> (c.T620C: p. M207T); <italic>QSER1</italic> (c.C2788G: p. L930V); <italic>CELSR3</italic> (c.C1865T: p. A622V); <italic>ZNF276</italic> (c.G584T: p. C195F); <italic>VPS9D1</italic> (c.G742C: p. D248H); <italic>ADGRL3</italic> (c.T4075C: p. F1359L); <italic>WDR63</italic> (c.C764T: p. T255M); <italic>PRKAG2</italic> (c.C221T: p. P74L); <italic>MCMDC2</italic> (c.T1532C: p. L511P); <italic>AASDH</italic> (c.G638T: p. R213L); <italic>TTN</italic> (c.G26999A: p. R9000H); <italic>FBXO11</italic> (c.G2335A: p. A779T); <italic>HIST1H2AG</italic> (c.G245C: p. R82P); ZNF512 (c.C1069T: p. P357); <italic>HIPK1</italic> (c.G81C: p. E27D); and <italic>EXTL3</italic> (c.G1504A: p. D502N). Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assays and Sanger sequencing were performed. The primers used in this study are listed in Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">1</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec8">
<title>Selection of SNVs/Genes</title>
<p id="Par10">The criteria for SNV/gene selection included the combination of the strength of the association between gene and phenotype and the involvement of genes in neural synaptic formation and brain development. Genes containing de novo harmful mutations with the strongest association with ASD phenotype were screened out using the Phenolyzer (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2015</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phenolyzer.wglab.org/">http://phenolyzer.wglab.org/</ext-link>), which integrates information from disease, gene–disease, and gene–gene relational databases to analyze the correlation between the mutant gene and the disease phenotype. When entering a disease name (such as “autism spectrum disorder”) in the “Diseases/Phenotypes,” the Phenolyzer generates a confidence score based on the correspondence of each gene to the disease name by determining all the genes that have a reported association with the disease (seed genes) in query-precompiled databases (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2015</xref>). Then, “gene selection” is clicked, and the candidate genes, which carry the nonsynonymous and harmful variants (see above in “Primers” and “Sanger sequencing validation”) obtained from WES sequencing in the pop-up box, are entered. The seed genes are then expanded to the candidate genes based on several types of gene–gene relationship logic to include related genes, such as displaying protein–protein interactions, gene families, transcriptional regulation, or regulation by another gene (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2015</xref>). Finally, all the information is integrated to generate a score for the candidate genes, with the weights trained from a logistic regression model (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phenolyzer.wglab.org/FAQ.php">http://phenolyzer.wglab.org/FAQ.php</ext-link>). The negative intercept, meaning the genes not associated with the ASD phenotype, was deducted to ensure that the final gene score was positive. The scores were renormalized to the final prioritized gene list. The software workflow can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phenolyzer.wglab.org/FAQ.php">http://phenolyzer.wglab.org/FAQ.php</ext-link>. The association between genes and phenotypes were defined based on the Phenolyzer score for the gene: low confidence (&lt;0.1), medium confidence (0.1 ≤ Phenolyzer score &lt; 0.5), and high confidence (≥0.5) (Fang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2017</xref>). The higher the score, the stronger the association between genes and phenotypes. Genes strongly associated with the phenotypes are the focus of further research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec9">
<title>Pathway Enrichment and the Expression of Genes in the Brain</title>
<p id="Par11">To exclude genes not expressed in the brain, the PubMed Gene database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/</ext-link>), which contains information about the expression of genes in different tissues and disease information related to the gene, was used. The genes expressed in the brain with a gene-phenotype score &gt; 0.1 as defined by the Phenolyzer are the targeted genes, as these genes are the most closely associated with the ASD phenotype. As the function of ASD-related genes is focused mostly on neurodevelopment and synapse formation (De Rubeis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>; Hammerschlag et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2019</xref>), the STRING database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://string-db.org/">https://string-db.org/</ext-link>), a system for predicting protein interactions to extract pathway information and functional information, was used to further explore whether the genes with a gene-phenotype score &gt; 0.1 were involved in the neural synaptic formation and developmental pathway. In addition, expression data for genes associated with neural-synaptic formation and developmental pathways in different brain regions and developmental stages were extracted using the HBT [Human Brain Transcriptome] database, which contains transcriptome data and associated metadata for the developing and adult human brain.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec10">
<title>Building the Network of Gene Co-Expression and Genetic Interaction</title>
<p id="Par12">The functional association and co-expression relationship between candidate genes found in this study and previously reported ASD genes were investigated by performing gene co-expression and gene interaction analysis. Again, the network of gene co-expression was built using spatially and temporally rich transcriptome data extracted from the BrainSpan database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.brainspan.org/">http://www.brainspan.org/</ext-link>), which is a database of gene expression in specific brain regions obtained from RNA sequencing and exon microarray techniques. Pearson correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic>) were then used to represent the index of the gene co-expression level. To avoid missing genes that were reported, all the genes in the “Human Gene Module” in SFARI Gene (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gene.sfari.org/">https://gene.sfari.org/</ext-link>) and in “Human Gene” in AutDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://autism.mindspec.org/">http://autism.mindspec.org/</ext-link>) (Basu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2009</xref>) were used. Both are centers of susceptibility genes implicated in ASD, providing an up-to-date and annotated list of ASD candidate genes in the form of a reference data set for interrogating molecular mechanisms underlying the disorder (Basu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2009</xref>). The reported ASD genes exhibited strong co-expression correlation coefficients (absolute <italic>r</italic> ≥ 0.6) with candidate genes extracted in this study. The data set used to explore the association between candidate genes and previously reported ASD genes was obtained from GeneMANIA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genemania.org/">http://genemania.org/</ext-link>) (Warde-Farley et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2010</xref>) using the Cytoscape program plugin (Smoot et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2011</xref>), which is a web interface that can display an interactive functional association network between genes and data sets, to create a genetic interaction network. In addition, a number of nodes (representing genes) and edges (representing the interaction of two genes) between the candidate genes and previously reported ASD genes were calculated using GeneMANIA. Both networks were drawn and visualized by employing the Cytoscape program (overall experimental procedure and gene screening steps in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Overall experimental procedure and gene screening steps</p></caption><graphic id="MO1" xlink:href="12031_2019_1456_Fig1_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec11">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="Sec12">
<title>Detection of De Novo Mutations</title>
<p id="Par13">Each sample had approximately 9.71–22.42 Gb of cleaned sequencing data obtained after removing the adapters and low-quality bases (Data S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">1</xref>). Overall, each person had more than 99.77% of reads aligned to the reference genome (GRCh37/hg19), and after the removal of PCR duplications, at least 54% effective reads were obtained from the target regions. More than 99.7% of target regions had at least tenfold coverage, and more than 99.4% and 79.6% of the target regions had 20- and 50-fold coverage, respectively.</p>
<p id="Par14">A total of 76 de novo SNVs (56 missense mutations, 10 unknown mutations, 5 non-frameshift deletions, 3 frameshift deletions, 1 stop-gain mutation, and 1 synonymous mutation) were found in 42 probands (Data S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">2</xref>). Using the software (SIFT, MutationTaster, and gerp++gt2) to analyze the harmfulness and conservation of the mutation site, it was found that only 27 de novo SNVs were possible pathogenic sites left in the 26 genes. PCR and Sanger sequencing were further conducted for validation and found that the mutation site in the <italic>WDR63</italic> gene was false positive and, therefore, was excluded. Finally, 26 de novo harmful SNVs in 25 gene coding regions of 19 probands were retained (listed in Data S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">3</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec13">
<title>Analysis and Identification of the De Novo Gene Mutations in ASD</title>
<p id="Par15">Twenty-four of the 25 genes were found to be expressed in the brain, the exception being the <italic>AOC1</italic> gene. Of these 24, only 17 genes were shown by Phenolyzer analysis to be associated with the ASD phenotypes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). The other seven genes (<italic>TMUB2</italic>, <italic>PRAG1</italic>, <italic>QSER1</italic>, <italic>VPS9D1</italic>, <italic>ADGRL3</italic>, <italic>MCMDC2</italic>, and <italic>AASDH</italic>) were excluded because of the negative intercept, which means that these genes may not be associated with the ASD phenotype. Analysis using the SFARI and AutDB database further showed that these seven genes were also not previously reported in ASD. A search of PubMed Gene (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/</ext-link>) additionally showed that none of these seven genes were reported in any other mental disorders. However, five (<italic>CACNA1D</italic>, <italic>ACHE</italic>, <italic>YY1</italic>, <italic>TTN</italic>, and <italic>FBXO11</italic>) of the remaining 17 genes listed in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref> were found in the SFARI and AutDB databases, and their mutation sites had never been reported (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>). Five genes (<italic>CACNA1D</italic>, <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>ACHE</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and <italic>PRKAG2</italic>) were classified as medium-confidence genes, which meant that these genes were strongly associated with the disease phenotypes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). Using the STRING database for function enrichment, the molecular function of all five gene products was found to be ion-binding. The <italic>ACHE</italic>, <italic>CACNA1D</italic>, and <italic>JAK2</italic> genes were also found to take part in the formation of a cholinergic synapse, while the <italic>CACNA1D</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> genes were involved in the regulation of the MAPK signaling pathway (Data S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM3">4</xref>). The <italic>JAK2</italic> gene was further found through PubMed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/3717">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/3717</ext-link>) to participate in the MAPK cascade process, which played an important role in the MAPK signaling pathway. All five genes were clearly predicted to be functionally deleterious by these prediction tools (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>). However, de novo SNVs in <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> were first discovered in ASD, and both these genes are involved in the regulation of the MAPK signaling pathway. <italic>JAK2</italic> (c. G649C: p. V217 L), located in the FERM domain of the gene (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3a and b</xref>), was found in proband A15. <italic>MAPK7</italic> (c.C709T: p. R237C), located in the protein kinase domain of the gene (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3c and d</xref>), was found in proband A16.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Prioritizing candidate genes using the Phenolyzer. The genes tagged with the boxes were ASD-related genes found in the SFARI Gene database and the AutDB. The first column is the gene score, ranging from 0 to 1; the greater the score, the stronger the association with the disease. HI represents the haploinsufficiency score. The score range is 0–1; the larger the score, the greater the possibility of haploinsufficiency. RVIS represents the Residual Variation Intolerance Score. This is used to describe gene tolerance, ranging from 0 to 1; the greater the score, the worse the tolerance</p></caption><graphic id="MO2" xlink:href="12031_2019_1456_Fig2_HTML"></graphic></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of seven de novo SNVs detected by trio-based WES of ASD, with five of those genes having been reported in ASD before</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Family</th><th>Chrom <sup>†</sup></th><th>Gene</th><th>Func <sup>‡</sup></th><th>ExonicFunc<sup>§</sup></th><th>Mutation</th><th>AAChang</th><th>SIFT</th><th>MutationTaster</th><th>gerp++gt2</th><th>Reported (genes/sites)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A 1</td><td>7</td><td><italic>ACHE</italic></td><td>Exonic</td><td>Missense SNV</td><td>c.G1165A</td><td>p. E389K</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Conserved</td><td>Yes/No</td></tr><tr><td>A18</td><td>3</td><td><italic>CACNA1D</italic></td><td>Exonic</td><td>Missense SNV</td><td>c.C4127T</td><td>p. T1376 M</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Conserved</td><td>Yes/No</td></tr><tr><td>A49</td><td>2</td><td><italic>TTN</italic></td><td>Exonic</td><td>Missense SNV</td><td>c.G26999A</td><td>p. R9000H</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Conserved</td><td>Yes/No</td></tr><tr><td>A51</td><td>2</td><td><italic>FBXO11</italic></td><td>Exonic</td><td>Missense SNV</td><td>c.G2335A</td><td>p. A779T</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Conserved</td><td>Yes/No</td></tr><tr><td>A4</td><td>14</td><td><italic>YY1</italic></td><td>Exonic</td><td>Missense SNV</td><td>c.G961A</td><td>p. G321S</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Conserved</td><td>Yes/No</td></tr><tr><td>A15</td><td>9</td><td><italic>JAK2</italic></td><td>Exonic</td><td>Missense SNV</td><td>c.G649C</td><td>p. V217 L</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Conserved</td><td>No/No</td></tr><tr><td>A16</td><td>17</td><td><italic>MAPK7</italic></td><td>Exonic</td><td>Missense SNV</td><td>c.C709T</td><td>p. R237C</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Conserved</td><td>No/No</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Using hg19 as the human reference genome</p><p>Chrom <sup>†</sup>: Chromosome. Func <sup>‡</sup>: Comment on the area where the mutation site is located; the exonic should include the coding exonic portion, UTR3, and UTR5, but the ANNOVAR comment indicates that the exonic represents only the coding exonic portion. ExonicFunc <sup>§</sup>: SNV variant type of exon region</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>De novo mutations (DNM) and relative positions in <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic>. <bold>a</bold> The DNM of <italic>JAK2</italic> (c. G649C: p. V217L) was confirmed by Sanger sequencing in A15. <bold>b</bold> Schematic representation of the <italic>JAK2</italic> protein. <bold>c</bold> The DNM of <italic>MAPK7</italic> (c.C709T: p. R237C) was confirmed by Sanger sequencing in A16. <bold>d</bold> Schematic representation of the <italic>MAPK7</italic> protein. Black represents amino acid changes caused by mutations in these two gene loci in patients with ASD</p></caption><graphic id="MO3" xlink:href="12031_2019_1456_Fig3_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec14">
<title>Expression Profile of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> in the Human Brain</title>
<p id="Par16">Using the HBT database, expression data were extracted for genes in different brain regions and developmental stages and indicated that <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> were widely expressed in all human brain regions in different developmental stages. It is worth noting that both <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAKP7</italic> demonstrated distinct peak-level expression during the middle and late stages of pregnancy (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">1</xref>). More importantly, the <italic>JAK2</italic> gene reached its highest level of expression in the cerebellar cortex (CBC) and remained relatively stable in the later trajectory of life. The expression of <italic>MAPK7</italic> gradually reduced after birth, while the changes in the expression level were nearly the same in different brain regions (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec15">
<title>Co-Expression and Genetic Interaction Network Analyses of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic></title>
<p id="Par17">The relationship between the <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> genes and the previously reported ASD candidate genes was explored using the BrainSpan database to extract gene co-expression data. <italic>JAK2</italic> was co-expressed with 53 previously reported ASD candidate genes, including six high-confidence genes (achieving genome-wide statistical significance with independent replication) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>) and eight strong-confidence genes (achieving genome-wide statistical significance with independent replication, but with standards slightly relaxed from those for high-confidence genes); the gene scoring process can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gene.sfari.org/about-gene-scoring/criteria/">https://gene.sfari.org/about-gene-scoring/criteria/</ext-link>. <italic>MAPK7</italic> was co-expressed with 183 previously reported ASD candidate genes, including 10 high-confidence genes and 32 strong-confidence genes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>). Moreover, nine previously reported ASD candidate genes, including one high-confidence gene (<italic>NAA15</italic>) and three strong-confidence genes (<italic>MED13, SPAST,</italic> and <italic>PHF3</italic>), simultaneously appeared in the co-expression network of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic>, indicating the presence of functional interactions between them.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Gene co-expression network analysis of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic>. Pearson correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic>) were used to represent the gene co-expression levels between each pair of genes. The orange-red circles represent high-confidence candidate genes in the SFARI Gene database and genes (evidence score: 5 stars) in the AutDb database. The blue circles represent strong-confidence candidate genes in the SFARI database and genes (evidence score: 4 stars) in the AutDb database. The green circles represent the remaining genes in the two gene databases</p></caption><graphic id="MO4" xlink:href="12031_2019_1456_Fig4_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par18">Using the GeneMANIA database to extract data on inter-gene interaction between <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and the previously reported ASD candidate genes, <italic>JAK2</italic> was found to have an interaction relationship with five previously reported ASD candidate genes (<italic>DDX1</italic>, <italic>BRD4</italic>, <italic>GNB1L</italic>, <italic>BRCA2</italic>, and <italic>OXTR</italic>), while <italic>MAPK7</italic> was observed to interact with three previously reported ASD candidate genes (<italic>DLX1</italic>, <italic>DMXL2</italic>, and <italic>CX3CR1</italic>) (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>). All eight of these previously reported ASD candidate genes were nominated as normal-confidence candidate genes in the SFARI Gene database, indicating that they were validated in independent replication but did not achieve genome-wide statistical significance.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec16">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="Par19">In this study, WES was performed among 59 sporadic trios, and 24 genes with de novo harmful SNVs were found to be expressed in the brain. The Phenolyzer (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2015</xref>), a software tool that reveals hidden associations between genotypes and phenotypes, was used to validate the correlation between the originally known genes with de novo SNVs and the disease phenotype by combining prior biological knowledge and phenotype information from different databases (Disease Ontology, Online Mendelian In Man, GWAS Catalog and Human Protein Relation Database, etc.). Five genes (<italic>CACNA1D</italic>, <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>ACHE</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and <italic>PRKAG2</italic>) were found to be “medium-confidence” genes related to ASD. De novo SNVs in <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and <italic>PRKAG2</italic> were first found in ASD. Both <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> were involved in the regulation of the MAPK signaling pathway, which took part in the neural-synaptic formation and brain development. This study involved multiple verification steps, including gene co-expression, inter-gene interaction analysis, and early gene expression profile in the brain, to further validate the association between <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> mutations and ASD susceptibility. This study was novel in illustrating the important role of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> in the etiology of ASD in the same sample at the gene–gene interaction level and gene expression levels.</p>
<p id="Par20">Through gene co-expression and inter-gene interaction network analysis, many previously reported ASD genes were found to be in the <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> co-expression and interaction networks, several of which co-existed in the co-expression network of both genes. Among the genes co-existing in the co-expression network, one (<italic>NAA15</italic>) and three genes (<italic>MED13</italic>, <italic>SPAST</italic>, <italic>PHF3</italic>) were listed as “high-confidence” and “strong-confidence” genes, respectively, in the SFARI Gene database. Multiple different mutation sites in these genes have been reported by various studies in patients with ASD, suggesting that <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> may act as a functional link between these co-expressing genes. However, due to significant genetic heterogeneity, only several previously reported ASD candidate genes (<italic>DDX1</italic>, <italic>BRD4</italic>, <italic>GNB1L</italic>, <italic>BRCA2</italic>, <italic>OXTR</italic> and <italic>DLX1</italic>, <italic>DMXL2</italic>, and <italic>CX3CR1</italic>) were found to exist in the <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> gene interaction networks. These results indicate that <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> may interact with the aforementioned genes at the functional level of the protein. Therefore, the interaction between <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and the known ASD-related genes provide further evidence that ASD is caused by these genetic variants.</p>
<p id="Par21">Previous studies have shown that enlarged head circumference is a ubiquitous phenomenon in children with ASD, which is due to an increased rate of brain growth before the age of 2 years (Hazlett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2011</xref>). Moreover, dynamic macrostructural and microstructural changes from the mid-fetal stage to 2 years after birth are also closely related to ASD (Ouyang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2019</xref>), indicating that neurodevelopmental conditions and dysplasia in the fetal and infant stages play a crucial role in the pathogenesis of ASD. Using HBT software, this study found that both <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> genes were expressed in multiple developmental stages in different brain regions and reached the peak of their expression in the mid–late embryonic stage, which is the crucial developmental period of the brain with ASD. Furthermore, the <italic>JAK2</italic> gene was found to have the highest expression level in the CBC, playing a central role in cognitive and emotional processing, which are key deficits in autism and other neuropsychiatric disorders (Menashe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2013</xref>; Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2014</xref>). The degrees of variation in expression levels in different brain regions are similar for <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and the peak expression levels of this gene appear in the mid-embryo phase, which involves a rapid increase in the volume of the cortical plate and the surface of the human brain (Clouchoux et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2012</xref>; Andescavage et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2017</xref>). The changes in cortical thickness, especially the volume gain of the gray matter during brain development associated with language development, social cognition, and behavioral control, are driven by a lack of typical age-related increase in cortical thickness and play an important role in early childhood autism (Smith et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2016</xref>). The findings of this study indicate that <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> play a role in early brain development, and their mutations may result in minor structural deficits, eventually causing ASD-related symptoms.</p>
<p id="Par22">Chromosome fragment abnormalities are closely related to ASD, including 7q abnormalities (Alarcon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2002</xref>) and 9p24.1 microdeletion (Kantojärvi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2010</xref>). In proband A16, the only nonsynonymous and harmful mutation was <italic>MAPK7</italic> (c.C709T: p. R237C), located in the protein kinase domain of the gene (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3c and d</xref>). <italic>MAPK7</italic> is located in chromosome 17p11.2, where a 3.7-Mb duplication exists, which is considered the cause of Potocki-Lupski syndrome (PTLS; MIM #610883), a disease having approximately 70–90% comorbidity with ASD (Lacaria et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2012</xref>). <italic>RAI1</italic> is one of the important pathogenic genes in this region (Abad et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>). Rare de novo mutations in the <italic>RAI1</italic> gene have been found to be closely related to ASD (Abad et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>), and animal models showed that the haploinsufficiency of this gene was associated with social abnormalities in mice (Rao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2017</xref>). As illustrated in this study, <italic>MAPK7</italic> had a co-expression relationship with <italic>RAI1</italic>. It is speculated that <italic>MAPK7</italic> may participate in the etiology of ASD. This gene also takes part in the MAPK signaling pathway. In the nervous system, the brain-derived neurotrophic factor stimulates neural differentiation and survival of human umbilical cord blood mesenchymal stem cells via the MAPK signaling pathway (Lim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>). Many genes in this pathway are involved in the pathogenesis of many psychiatric disorders, such as ASD (Wen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2016</xref>), attention deficit and hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), bipolar disorder, and schizophrenia (Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2018</xref>). Moreover, the protein encoded by <italic>MAPK7</italic> is a member of the MAPK family involved in a wide variety of cellular processes, such as proliferation, differentiation, transcription regulation, and brain development (Pearson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2001</xref>), and abnormalities in these processes can lead to the development of ASD symptoms (Nagy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2017</xref>; Courchesne et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2019</xref>). Previous evidence also indicated rare mutations in the <italic>MAPK</italic> gene family participating in ASD, such as <italic>MAPK3</italic> (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2017</xref>) and <italic>MAPK1</italic> knockout mice showing ASD-like behavior (Satoh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2011</xref>). Together with these results of de novo SNVs in <italic>MAPK7</italic>, it may be inferred from this study that mutations in the MAPK family may involve the genes that affect multiple cellular processes, resulting in the inability of cells to develop and mature normally, leading to the onset of ASD.</p>
<p id="Par23"><italic>JAK2</italic> is located in chromosome 9p24.1 where deletions have been found in patients with ASD in earlier studies (Kantojärvi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2010</xref>). The nonsynonymous and harmful de novo SNV of <italic>JAK2</italic> (c. G649C: p. V217L) found in this study was located in the FERM domain of the gene (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3a and b</xref>), which encodes the cytoskeletal-associated proteins that constitute a link between the membrane and the cytoskeleton involved in the signal transduction pathways. Evidence from functional studies suggest that <italic>JAK2</italic> is involved in the JAK-STAT cascade, a process that includes the development, maintenance, and survival of central nervous system glial cells and neurons as well as enhanced brain-derived neurotrophic factor expression (Kaur et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2005</xref>; Kazim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2015</xref>). Previous studies have demonstrated that JAK-STAT activation signals play a crucial role in ASD immune dysfunction (Ahmad et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2017</xref>), and it was found to participate in the MAPK cascade process (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/3717">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/3717</ext-link>) in the MAPK signaling pathway. Furthermore, it was found that abnormal synaptic functions, especially in the basal forebrain cholinergic dysfunction, may lead to ASD (Garber et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2007</xref>). Along with the findings using the STRING database, the present study also found that <italic>JAK2</italic> participated in the cholinergic synapse. Therefore, <italic>JAK2</italic> may be involved in the genetic etiological mechanism of ASD.</p>
<p id="Par24">This study had several limitations. First, no association analysis was performed in an independent case–control sample on these two de novo SNVs. However, multiple verification methods, including Phenolyzer software, which combines many different databases to integrate all known information in order to more accurately analyze the correlation between the mutant gene and the disease phenotype, were used to overcome the limitations of the sample size. Second, the study did not validate the newly discovered ASD candidate genes at the expression level. However, with the use of the STRING, BrainSpan, GeneMANIA, and HBT databases to extract the co-expressed and inter-gene interaction data, as well as gene expression profile data in the brain, the link between <italic>JAK2</italic>, <italic>MAPK7</italic>, and ASD was verified at multiple levels of gene interaction and expression using the most advanced databases. Future studies on gene expression in cells and animal models are still needed to explore the precise function of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> in ASD.</p>
<p id="Par25">This study found the de novo SNVs of <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> genes in the MAPK signaling pathway to be related to ASD from different perspectives, including relationships between genes and phenotypes, gene co-expression, gene interaction network analysis, and gene expression in early brain development. The results suggest that <italic>JAK2</italic> and <italic>MAPK7</italic> genes in the MAPK signaling pathway may play an important role in the etiology of ASD through interaction with other ASD-related genes and eventually lead to the abnormal development of the ASD brain. This information may shed new light on the genetic etiology and therapeutic drugs in ASD. Further genetic and functional studies are needed to elucidate the precise molecular mechanisms involved in the joint action of multiple genes.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
<sec id="Sec17">
<p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12031_2019_1456_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>ESM 1</label><caption><p>(DOCX 317 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12031_2019_1456_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><label>ESM 2</label><caption><p>(XLSX 99 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12031_2019_1456_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><label>ESM 3</label><caption><p>(XLSX 11 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p>
<bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
</p>
<p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ack>
<p>The authors are grateful to the participants and their families for their contribution to the study.</p>
</ack>
<notes notes-type="funding-information">
<title>Funding Information</title>
<p>This study was supported financially by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant number: 81371495), the Key Research Project of the Ministry of Science and Technology China (grant number: 2016YFC1306104), and the Key Project from Sichuan Provincial Science and Technology Department (grant number: 2017SZ0135).</p>
</notes>
<notes>
<title>Compliance with Ethical Standards</title>
<notes notes-type="COI-statement">
<title>Conflict of Interest</title>
<p id="Par26">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
</notes>
</notes>
<ref-list id="Bib1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CR1">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abad</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cook</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Srivastava</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A rare de novo RAI1 gene mutation affecting BDNF-enhancer-driven transcription activity associated with autism and atypical Smith-Magenis syndrome presentation</article-title>
<source/>Biology
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR2">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nadeem</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ansari</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Attia</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Upregulation of IL-9 and JAK-STAT signaling pathway in children with autism</article-title>
<source/>Prog Neuro-Psychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>472</fpage>
<lpage>480</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR3">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alarcon</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cantor</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gilliam</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Geschwind</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Evidence for a language quantitative trait locus on chromosome 7q in multiplex autism families</article-title>
<source/>Am J Hum Genet
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>60</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741194</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR4">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Andescavage</surname>
<given-names>NN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>du Plessis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCarter</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Limperopoulos</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Complex trajectories of brain development in the healthy human fetus</article-title>
<source/>Cereb Cortex
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>5274</fpage>
<lpage>5283</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27799276</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR5">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anney</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klei</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pinto</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hallmayer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A genome-wide scan for common alleles affecting risk for autism</article-title>
<source/>Hum Mol Genet
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>4072</fpage>
<lpage>4082</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20663923</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR6">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bailey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Le Couteur</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gottesman</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rutter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autism as a strongly genetic disorder: evidence from a British twin study</article-title>
<source/>Psychol Med
          <year>1995</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>63</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7792363</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR7">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Basu</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kollu</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Banerjee-Basu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>AutDB: a gene reference resource for autism research</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>D832</fpage>
<lpage>D836</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015121</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR8">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blumenthal</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ragavendran</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erdin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Talkowski</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptional consequences of 16p11.2 deletion and duplication in mouse cortex and multiplex autism families</article-title>
<source/>Am J Hum Genet
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>870</fpage>
<lpage>883</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24906019</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR9">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chiocchetti</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kopp</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Waltes</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Freitag</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Variants of the CNTNAP2 5′ promoter as risk factors for autism spectrum disorders: a genetic and functional approach</article-title>
<source/>Mol Psychiatry
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>839</fpage>
<lpage>849</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25224256</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR10">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clouchoux</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kudelski</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gholipour</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Limperopoulos</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Quantitative in vivo MRI measurement of cortical development in the fetus</article-title>
<source/>Brain Struct Funct
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>217</volume>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>139</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21562906</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR11">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Colvert</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tick</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McEwen</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bolton</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Heritability of autism spectrum disorder in a UK population-based twin sample</article-title>
<source/>JAMA Psychiat
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>415</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR12">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Courchesne</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pramparo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gazestani</surname>
<given-names>VH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>NE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The ASD living biology: from cell proliferation to clinical phenotype</article-title>
<source/>Mol Psychiatry
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>88</fpage>
<lpage>107</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29934544</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR13">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davydov</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goode</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sirota</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Batzoglou</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identifying a high fraction of the human genome to be under selective constraint using GERP++</article-title>
<source/>PLoS Comput Biol
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>e1001025</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21152010</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR14">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>De Rubeis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldberg</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buxbaum</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic, transcriptional and chromatin genes disrupted in autism</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>515</volume>
<fpage>209</fpage>
<lpage>215</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25363760</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR15">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lyon</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Whole genome sequencing of one complex pedigree illustrates challenges with genomic medicine</article-title>
<source/>BMC Med Genet
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>10</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR16">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Garber</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neuroscience. Autism’s cause may reside in abnormalities at the synapse</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>317</volume>
<fpage>190</fpage>
<lpage>191</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626859</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR17">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gaugler</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klei</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sanders</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buxbaum</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Most genetic risk for autism resides with common variation</article-title>
<source/>Nat Genet
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>881</fpage>
<lpage>885</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038753</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR18">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geschwind</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>State</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Gene hunting in autism spectrum disorder: on the path to precision medicine</article-title>
<source/>Lancet Neurol
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>1109</fpage>
<lpage>1120</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25891009</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR19">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hallmayer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cleveland</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torres</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Risch</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetic heritability and shared environmental factors among twin pairs with autism</article-title>
<source/>Arch Gen Psychiatry
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>1095</fpage>
<lpage>1102</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21727249</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR20">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hammerschlag AR, de Leeuw CA, Middeldorp CM, Polderman TJC et al (2019) Synaptic and brain-expressed gene sets relate to the shared genetic risk across five psychiatric disorders. Psychol Med 1-11</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR21">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hazlett</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Poe</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gerig</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Piven</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Early brain overgrowth in autism associated with an increase in cortical surface area before age 2 years</article-title>
<source/>Arch Gen Psychiatry
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>467</fpage>
<lpage>476</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21536976</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR22">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hnoonual</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sripo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Limprasert</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Whole-exome sequencing identifies a novel heterozygous missense variant of the EN2 gene in two unrelated patients with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Psychiatr Genet
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>297</fpage>
<lpage>301</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27755371</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR23">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Iossifov</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Roak</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sanders</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wigler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The contribution of de novo coding mutations to autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>515</volume>
<fpage>216</fpage>
<lpage>221</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25363768</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR24">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kantojärvi K, Onkamo P, Vanhala R, Järvelä I et al (2010) Analysis of 9p24 and 11p12-13 regions in autism spectrum disorders: rs1340513 in the JMJD2C gene is associated with ASDs in Finnish sample. Psychiatr Genet 1</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR25">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Monroe</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Halvorsen</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Inducers of oxidative stress block ciliary neurotrophic factor activation of Jak/STAT signaling in neurons</article-title>
<source/>J Neurochem
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>1521</fpage>
<lpage>1530</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15748169</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR26">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kazim</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cardenas-Aguayo</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arif</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Iqbal</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sera from children with autism induce autistic features which can be rescued with a CNTF small peptide mimetic in rats</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>e0118627</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25769033</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR27">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ku</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soong</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Exome versus transcriptome sequencing in identifying coding region variants</article-title>
<source/>Expert Rev Mol Diagn
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>241</fpage>
<lpage>251</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22468815</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR28">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lacaria</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spencer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paylor</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lupski</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Enriched rearing improves behavioral responses of an animal model for CNV-based autistic-like traits</article-title>
<source/>Hum Mol Genet
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>3083</fpage>
<lpage>3096</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492990</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR29">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lombardo</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baron-Cohen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autism</article-title>
<source/>Lancet
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>383</volume>
<fpage>896</fpage>
<lpage>910</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074734</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR30">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lavelle</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weinstein</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Newhouse</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prosser</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Economic burden of childhood autism spectrum disorders</article-title>
<source/>Pediatrics
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>133</volume>
<fpage>e520</fpage>
<lpage>e529</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24515505</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR31">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genes with de novo mutations are shared by four neuropsychiatric disorders discovered from NPdenovo database</article-title>
<source/>Mol Psychiatry
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>290</fpage>
<lpage>297</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25849321</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR32">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oh</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeun</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Brain-derived neurotrophic factor stimulates the neural differentiation of human umbilical cord blood-derived mesenchymal stem cells and survival of differentiated cells through MAPK/ERK and PI3K/Akt-dependent signaling pathways</article-title>
<source/>J Neurosci Res
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>86</volume>
<fpage>2168</fpage>
<lpage>2178</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438930</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR33">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Takumi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genomic and genetic aspects of autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Biochem Biophys Res Commun
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>452</volume>
<fpage>244</fpage>
<lpage>253</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25173933</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR34">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lord</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Elsabbagh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baird</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Veenstra-Vanderweele</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Lancet
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>392</volume>
<fpage>508</fpage>
<lpage>520</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30078460</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR35">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lord</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rutter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goode</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schopler</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autism diagnostic observation schedule: a standardized observation of communicative and social behavior</article-title>
<source/>J Autism Dev Disord
          <year>1989</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2745388</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR36">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lord</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rutter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Le Couteur</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autism diagnostic interview-revised: a revised version of a diagnostic interview for caregivers of individuals with possible pervasive developmental disorders</article-title>
<source/>J Autism Dev Disord
          <year>1994</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>659</fpage>
<lpage>685</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7814313</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR37">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Menashe</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grange</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Larsen</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Banerjee-Basu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mitra</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Co-expression profiling of autism genes in the mouse brain</article-title>
<source/>PLoS Comput Biol
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e1003128</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23935468</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR38">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Miryounesi M, S Bahari, S Salehpour, N Alipour, S Ghafouri-Fard et al (2019) ELMO domain containing 1 (ELMOD1) gene mutation is associated with mental retardation and autism spectrum disorder. J Mol Neurosci</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR39">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nagy</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kobolak</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berzsenyi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roman</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered neurite morphology and cholinergic function of induced pluripotent stem cell-derived neurons from a patient with Kleefstra syndrome and autism</article-title>
<source/>Transl Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>e1179</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28742076</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR40">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>SIFT: predicting amino acid changes that affect protein function</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>3812</fpage>
<lpage>3814</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824425</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR41">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ouyang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dubois</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mukherjee</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Delineation of early brain development from fetuses to infants with diffusion MRI and beyond</article-title>
<source/>Neuroimage
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>185</volume>
<fpage>836</fpage>
<lpage>850</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29655938</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR42">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>MAPK3 at the autism-linked human 16p11.2 locus influences precise synaptic target selection at Drosophila larval neuromuscular junctions</article-title>
<source/>Mol Cells
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>151</fpage>
<lpage>161</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28196412</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR43">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beers</surname>
<given-names>GT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cobb</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mitogen-activated protein (MAP) kinase pathways: regulation and physiological functions</article-title>
<source/>Endocr Rev
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>153</fpage>
<lpage>183</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11294822</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR44">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ramaswami</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Geschwind</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetics of autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Handb Clin Neurol
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>147</volume>
<fpage>321</fpage>
<lpage>329</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29325621</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR45">
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rao NR, C Abad, IC Perez, K Walz et al (2017) Rai1 haploinsufficiency is associated with social abnormalities in mice. Biology (Basel) 6</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR46">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ronemus</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Iossifov</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Levy</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wigler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The role of de novo mutations in the genetics of autism spectrum disorders</article-title>
<source/>Nat Rev Immunol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>133</fpage>
<lpage>141</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR47">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Law</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yenokyan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Law</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Characteristics and concordance of autism spectrum disorders among 277 twin pairs</article-title>
<source/>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>163</volume>
<fpage>907</fpage>
<lpage>914</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805709</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR48">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sadybekov</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arnesano</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katritch</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Herring</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>An autism spectrum disorder-related de novo mutation hotspot discovered in the GEF1 domain of trio</article-title>
<source/>Nat Commun
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>601</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28928363</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR49">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sanders</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ercan-Sencicek</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hus</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>State</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Multiple recurrent de novo CNVs, including duplications of the 7q11.23 Williams syndrome region, are strongly associated with autism</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>863</fpage>
<lpage>885</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21658581</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR50">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Satoh</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nakata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kazama</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>ERK2 contributes to the control of social behaviors in mice</article-title>
<source/>J Neurosci
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>11953</fpage>
<lpage>11967</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21849556</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR51">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schaaf</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zoghbi</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Solving the autism puzzle a few pieces at a time</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>806</fpage>
<lpage>808</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21658575</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR52">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schwarz</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodelsperger</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schuelke</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seelow</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>MutationTaster evaluates disease-causing potential of sequence alterations</article-title>
<source/>Nat Methods
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>575</fpage>
<lpage>576</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20676075</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR53">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sener</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Canatan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ozkul</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Recent advances in autism spectrum disorders: applications of whole exome sequencing technology</article-title>
<source/>Psychiat Invest
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>255</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR54">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thurm</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenstein</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raznahan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cortical thickness change in autism during early childhood</article-title>
<source/>Hum Brain Mapp
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>2616</fpage>
<lpage>2629</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27061356</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR55">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smoot</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ono</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ruscheinski</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ideker</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cytoscape 2.8: new features for data integration and network visualization</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>431</fpage>
<lpage>432</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21149340</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR56">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thongnak</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hnoonual</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tangviriyapaiboon</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sukasem</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Whole-exome sequencing identifies one de novo variant in the FGD6 gene in a Thai family with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Int J Genomics
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>2018</volume>
<fpage>8231547</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29888248</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR57">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hakonarson</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Common genetic variants on 5p14.1 associate with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>459</volume>
<fpage>528</fpage>
<lpage>533</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19404256</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR58">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hakonarson</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>e164</fpage>
<lpage>e164</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601685</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR59">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kloth</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Badura</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The cerebellum, sensitive periods, and autism</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>518</fpage>
<lpage>532</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25102558</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR60">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Warde-Farley</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Donaldson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Comes</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The GeneMANIA prediction server: biological network integration for gene prioritization and predicting gene function</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>W214</fpage>
<lpage>W220</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576703</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR61">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weiss</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arking</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peltonen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A genome-wide linkage and association scan reveals novel loci for autism</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>461</volume>
<fpage>802</fpage>
<lpage>808</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812673</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR62">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alshikho</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Herbert</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pathway network analyses for autism reveal multisystem involvement, major overlaps with other diseases and convergence upon MAPK and calcium signaling</article-title>
<source/>PLoS One
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>e0153329</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27055244</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR63">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>GZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qiu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of autism-related MECP2 mutations by whole-exome sequencing and functional validation</article-title>
<source/>Mol Autism
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>43</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28785396</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR64">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Werling</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lowe</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cantor</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Geschwind</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Replication of linkage at chromosome 20p13 and identification of suggestive sex-differential risk loci for autism spectrum disorder</article-title>
<source/>Mol Autism
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>13</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24533643</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR65">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Phenolyzer: phenotype-based prioritization of candidate genes for human diseases</article-title>
<source/>Nat Methods
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>841</fpage>
<lpage>843</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26192085</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR66">
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A large-scale integrative analysis of GWAS and common meQTLs across whole life course identifies genes, pathways and tissue/cell types for three major psychiatric disorders</article-title>
<source/>Neurosci Biobehav Rev
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>347</fpage>
<lpage>352</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30339835</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>