<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="case-report" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Paul Pediatr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev Paul Pediatr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rpp</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Revista Paulista de Pediatria</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0103-0582</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1984-0462</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Sociedade de Pediatria de São Paulo</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32074227</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7025451</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1984-0462/2020/38/2018294</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="other">00607</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>PREPUBERTAL GYNECOMASTIA: A RARE MANIFESTATION OF MYOTONIC DYSTROPHY
TYPE 1</article-title>
<trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
<trans-title>GINECOMASTIA PRÉ-PÚBERE: UMA MANIFESTAÇÃO RARA DA DISTROFIA
MIOTÔNICA TIPO 1</trans-title>
</trans-title-group>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4028-651X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Miranda</surname>
<given-names>Patrícia Sofia Ferreira</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5956-0940</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>Ester Preciosa Maio Nunes</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0372-7841</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Barreto</surname>
<given-names>Joana Serra Caetano Baltazar</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4888-0396</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Henriques</surname>
<given-names>Margarida Maria Videira</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4138-8622</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Mirante</surname>
<given-names>Maria Alice Santos Cordeiro</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2908-7504</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Ramos</surname>
<given-names>Lina Maria Jesus Ferreira Cardoso</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1">
<label>a</label>Centro Hospitalar de Leiria, Portugal.</aff>
<aff id="aff2">
<label>b</label>Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de Coimbra, Portugal.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. E-mail:
<email>pati_m16@hotmail.com</email> (P.S.F. Miranda).</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2">
<p>The authors declare no conflict of interests.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<elocation-id>e2018294</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>05</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="online">
<day>07</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<title>ABSTRACT</title>
<sec>
<title>Objective:</title>
<p> To present a case of bilateral gynecomastia in a prepubertal boy with autism
spectrum disorder, diagnosed with myotonic dystrophy type 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Case description:</title>
<p> A 12-year-old boy with autism spectrum disorder presented at a follow-up
visit with bilateral breast growth. There was a family history of
gynecomastia, cataracts at a young age, puberty delay, and myotonic
dystrophy type 1. The physical examination showed that he had bilateral
gynecomastia with external genitalia Tanner stage 1. Neurologic examination
was regular, without demonstrable myotonia. The analytical study revealed
increased estradiol levels and estradiol/testosterone ratio. After excluding
endocrine diseases, the molecular study of the dystrophia myotonica protein
kinase gene confirmed the diagnosis of myotonic dystrophy type 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Comments:</title>
<p> A diagnosis of prepubertal gynecomastia should include an investigation for
possible underlying diseases. This case report highlights the importance of
considering the diagnosis of myotonic dystrophy type 1 in the presence of
endocrine and neurodevelopmental manifestations.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
<title>RESUMO</title>
<sec>
<title>Objetivo:</title>
<p> Apresentar o caso de um adolescente pré-púbere com ginecomastia bilateral e
transtorno do espectro autista, diagnosticado com distrofia miotônica tipo
1.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Descrição do caso:</title>
<p> Adolescente do sexo masculino de 12 anos, com transtorno do espectro
autista, observado em consulta de seguimento por crescimento mamário
bilateral. O paciente tinha antecedentes familiares de ginecomastia,
catarata em idade jovem, atraso pubertário e distrofia miotônica tipo 1. À
observação física, apresentava ginecomastia bilateral estádio 1 de Tanner. O
exame neurológico era normal, sem miotonia aparente. O estudo analítico
mostrou níveis elevados de estradiol e da relação estradiol/testosterona.
Após exclusão de causas endócrinas, o estudo molecular do gene DMPK
confirmou o diagnóstico de distrofia miotônica tipo 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Comentários:</title>
<p> Perante um quadro de ginecomastia pré-púbere, deve-se excluir doenças
subjacentes. Este caso reforça a importância de considerar o diagnóstico de
distrofia miotônica tipo 1 na presença de manifestações endócrinas e do
neurodesenvolvimento.</p>
</sec>
</trans-abstract>
<kwd-group>
<title>Keywords:</title>
<kwd>Gynecomastia</kwd>
<kwd>Myotonic dystrophy</kwd>
<kwd>Steinert disease</kwd>
<kwd>Aromatase</kwd>
<kwd>Adolescent</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group xml:lang="pt">
<title>Palavras-chave:</title>
<kwd>Ginecomastia</kwd>
<kwd>Distrofia miotônica</kwd>
<kwd>Doença de Steinert</kwd>
<kwd>Aromatase</kwd>
<kwd>Adolescente.</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4"></fig-count>
<table-count count="0"></table-count>
<equation-count count="0"></equation-count>
<ref-count count="16"></ref-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="intro">
<title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>True gynecomastia is diagnosed by the presence of a palpable fibroglandular mass that
measures at least 0.5 cm in diameter and is located concentrically beneath the
nipple-areolar complex.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> It is highly prevalent and often benign during the neonatal period, puberty,
and in males over 50 years-old.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>Pubertal gynecomastia is a common and usually physiological disease, and spontaneous
regression occurs within one to three years.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> The prevalence of pubertal gynecomastia ranges from 3.9 to 64.6% and,
typically, it appears at least six months after the onset of male secondary sex
characteristics, with the peak of incidence at Tanner stages 3-4 and testicular
volume of 5 to 10 mL.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>On the other hand, prepubertal gynecomastia is characterized by the presence of
breast tissue without other secondary sexual characteristics. It is rare and
comprises 5% of gynecomastia referrals.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref> Generally, it is considered a pathological sign of a possible
endocrinopathy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>Pathological gynecomastia is thought to be caused by the imbalance between estrogen
related to androgen action at the breast tissue.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> Elevated serum estrogen levels may be the result of endogenous abnormal
production, such as neoplasms secreting estrogen or precursors (e.g. Leydig or
Sertoli cell tumors, hCG-producing tumors, and adrenocortical tumors), exogenous
administration or, more commonly, increased extragonadal conversion of androgens to
estrogens through tissue aromatase.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> Inversely, imbalance can also be caused by a decrease in serum androgen
levels seen in primary (e.g. Klinefelter’s syndrome) or secondary hypogonadism,
impaired androgen biosynthesis caused by enzymatic deficiency or medications and
androgen receptor malfunction.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>Several medical conditions may be associated with pathological gynecomastia, such as
hyperprolactinemia, hyperthyroidism, chronic diseases leading to malnutrition (e.g.
cystic fibrosis, ulcerative colitis, liver disease, chronic renal failure, acquired
immunodeficiency syndromes),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> and myotonic dystrophy type 1.</p>
<p>The authors present a case report of bilateral gynecomastia in a prepubertal boy with
autism spectrum disorder. Molecular study of the dystrophia myotonica protein kinase
(DMPK) gene confirmed the diagnosis of myotonic dystrophy type 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="cases">
<title>CASE DESCRIPTION</title>
<p>A 12-year-old boy with autism spectrum disorder presented at a surveillance consult
with bilateral breast growth, which was noticed on the last few months. He did not
mention other symptoms, such as headache, vomiting, and polyuria polydipsia. Growth
was unremarkable, with height on the 75<sup>th</sup> centile and weight on the
75-90<sup>th</sup> centile. His mother denied he had been exposed to
medications, herbal medicine drugs, or estrogen-containing creams.</p>
<p>The family history showed that his parents were non-consanguineous. He had a
first-degree cousin from his father’s family with gynecomastia since adolescence and
other first-degree cousin from his father’s family with a recent diagnosis of
myotonic dystrophy type 1. His father had cataracts diagnosed at 49 years-old and a
history of puberty delay. The cousin’s diagnosis led to family genetic study, and
his father and older brother were waiting for their results. His mother was healthy
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<p>
<fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Genogram.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1984-0462-rpp-38-e2018294-gf1"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p>On physical examination, he had an eunuchoid phenotype and bilateral gynecomastia
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). Testicular volume was 2 mL
bilaterally, with no palpable nodules, penis length was 5 cm (-2 standard deviation
according to age), and there were sparse long, slightly pigmented curled pubic hairs
at the base of his penis (external genitalia at Tanner stage 1 and pubic hair at
Tanner stage 2). There was no tachycardia or tremor and nonpalpable thyroid. Body
mass index was 18.8 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (50<sup>th</sup> to 75<sup>th</sup> centile).
There were no other relevant findings. Neurologic examination was regular, without
demonstrable myotonia.</p>
<p>
<fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Gynecomastia (Tanner stage 3).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1984-0462-rpp-38-e2018294-gf2"></graphic></fig>
</p>
<p>Analytical evaluation showed total testosterone=0.13 ng/mL (reference value=0.24±0.01
for male and Tanner stage 1), estradiol=49 pg/mL (reference value=4.6±5.8),
estradiol/testosterone ratio=400 (reference value &lt;10), LH=0.19 UI/L, and FSH
1.02=UI/L, prolactin=8.6 ng/mL (reference value=2.6-13.1), b-hCG=0.3 mUI/mL
(reference value=0-3), TSH=2.33 uUI/mL (reference value=2.0±1.8), and free
thyroxine=13 pmol/L (reference value=16.6±3.6). Complete blood count, kidney
function, liver profile, and muscle enzyme levels were normal.</p>
<p>The presence of autism spectrum disorder in association with gynecomastia caused the
consideration of genetic diseases. Karyotype was 46, XY normal and molecular genetic
testing of FMR1 gene excluded X-Fragile syndrome. Molecular genetic testing of DMPK
gene confirmed the diagnosis of myotonic dystrophy type 1. His father and brother
were also diagnosed with the same condition.</p>
<p>Pubertal development was observed, and gynecomastia remained stable during the
follow-up. On the last consult, at 14 years-old, he presented bilateral gynecomastia
classified as Tanner stage 3, testicular volume of 8 mL on the left, and 6 mL on the
right and pubic hair at Tanner stage 4. Analytical evaluation showed: total
testosterone of 1.82 ng/mL (reference value=0.68±0.02 for male and Tanner stage 2),
estradiol of 15 pg/mL (reference value=7.3±3.7), LH=3.7 UI/L, and FSH=6.9 UI/L.
Electromyography was regular.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="discussion">
<title>DISCUSSION</title>
<p>Prepubertal gynecomastia, especially if unilateral, is extremely rare<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref> and should prompt an immediate evaluation for pathological causes and
possible endocrine disorders.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>In our case report, gynecomastia occurred in a 12-year-old boy with external
genitalia at Tanner stage 1 (testicular volume of 2 mL bilaterally) and, therefore,
prepubertal. After exclusion of exogenous estrogen and drug intake by clinical
history, we focused on possible endocrine and systemic non-endocrine diseases,
especially those that could be part of a syndrome that occurs with autism spectrum
disorder.</p>
<p>The analytical study revealed an increase in estradiol levels and in
estradiol/testosterone ratio. Tumoral abnormal production of estradiol was unlikely,
given the inexistence of palpable testicular masses and regular b-hCG value. Normal
prolactin levels excluded hyperprolactinemia, and regular levels of hepatic, renal
and thyroid function excluded other chronic diseases.</p>
<p>The presence of an autism spectrum disorder caused the consideration of genetic
diseases, namely Klinefelter syndrome and myotonic dystrophy type 1. In Klinefelter
syndrome, serum-free testosterone levels are low-normal or frankly low, whereas
serum estradiol levels are normal or elevated. The resulting increase in the
circulating estrogen/androgen ratio leads to gynecomastia.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> However, normal karyotype excluded the diagnosis of Klinefelter
syndrome.</p>
<p>According to family history, molecular study of the DMPK gene was carried out,
confirming the diagnosis of myotonic dystrophy type 1. It or Steinert’s disease is
an autosomal, dominantly inherited disorder caused by the expansion of an unstable
trinucleotide CTG repeated sequence in the 3’ untranslated region of the DMPK gene
on chromosome 19q13.3.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>The myotonic dystrophy type 1 is a multisystemic disease and the second most common
form of muscular dystrophy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref> Several hypotheses have been proposed to explain the pathogenesis of this
multisystemic disorder, which seems to involve the RNA transcribed from the expanded
allele.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref> The pathogenic mechanisms involve protein sequestration, stimulation of
signaling pathways, disruption of alternative splicing, mRNA translation and,
possibly, mRNA stability, causing a wide clinical spectrum.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>Gynecomastia is a known manifestation of myotonic dystrophy type 1, even though it is
uncommon (&lt;10%) and rarely a presentation form of the disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> Usually, it is seen in older male individuals, associated with
hypergonadotropic hypogonadism<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> and in the context of infertility screening. However, in our case report,
the boy was at the peripubertal period, with slight increase of FSH, which may mean
the beginning of hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis activation, with doseable
estradiol, but without testosterone production. This could have led to imbalance in
estradiol/testosterone ratio, with subsequent breast enlargement.</p>
<p>Imbalance in estradiol/testosterone ratio, nevertheless, could be also explained by
low levels of adrenal androgen production, seen in peripubertal period, which can
serve as precursors for peripheral conversion to estrogens.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> Onset of gynecomastia of our case report occurred around the adrenarche
period (seven to 14 years), favoring this contributing mechanism. The beginning of
pubarche reflects the activity of adrenal gland, which leads to the production of
androgens. Aromatase is a key player in estrogen synthesis and converts androgen to
estrogen.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> In case of increase of aromatization activity, androgens are converted into
estrogens that cause breast enlargement. In hypothesis, there could have been an
increase of aromatization activity resulting from “gains-of-function” of the mutant
RNA, causing breast enlargement at a prepubertal age. On follow-up, pubertal
development was observed, and gynecomastia remained stable.</p>
<p>Myotonic dystrophy type 1 is a disease with high morbidity, which may be associated
with early death (at the fifth decade of life), mainly due to cardiorespiratory
failure (70%).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref> There is currently no cure, but proactive management is likely to
significantly reduce morbidity and mortality.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>Follow-up includes regular monitoring of cardiac function to screen conduction
disturbances and tachyarrhythmias,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref> screening of other endocrine dysfunction by regular analytical evaluation,
and regular ophthalmologic assessment for cataract detection. At each consultation,
it is important to question about muscle symptoms, namely myotonia and muscle
weakness, gastrointestinal symptoms (swallowing difficulties, postprandial
vomiting/bloating/nausea and weight loss), and bladder dysfunction (incontinence,
frequency and urgency).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
</p>
<p>We presented the case of a prepubertal adolescent with autism spectrum disorder and
bilateral gynecomastia, who was diagnosed with myotonic dystrophy type 1 without
other symptoms or anomalies in the observation, namely in muscle strength and
relaxation. Analytically, there was an increased estradiol/testosterone ratio. As
compared to the adult form of disease, endocrinopathy has been rarely documented in
childhood myotonic dystrophy type 1 patients,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref> and we are not aware of another case similar to ours described in the
literature.</p>
<p>Prepubertal gynecomastia must ensure the investigation for possible underlying
diseases. Myotonic dystrophy type 1 in childhood manifested by autistic disorder and
gynecomastia is rare, especially in the absence of muscular symptoms. This case
highlights the importance of considering the diagnosis of myotonic dystrophy type 1
in the presence of endocrine and neurodevelopmental manifestations.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<title>Funding</title>
<fn fn-type="supported-by" id="fn1">
<p>This study did not receive funding.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="B1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Geffner</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Gynecomastia in prepubertal and pubertal men</article-title>
<source/>Curr Opin Pediatr
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>465</fpage>
<lpage>470</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOP.0b013e328305e415</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18622206</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoevenaren</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schott</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Otten</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kroese-Deutman</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prepubertal unilateral gynecomastia: a report of two
cases</article-title>
<source/>Eur J Plast Surg
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>395</fpage>
<lpage>398</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00238-010-0469-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21966096</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dermirbilek</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bacak</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baran</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Avci</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baran</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keleş</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prepubertal unilateral gynecomastia: report of 2
cases</article-title>
<source/>J Clin Res Pediatr Endocrinol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>250</fpage>
<lpage>253</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4274/Jcrpe.1477</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25541897</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Einav-Bachar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Phillip</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aurbach-Klipper</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lazar</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prepubertal gynecomastia: aetiology, course and
outcome</article-title>
<source/>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)
          <year>2004</year>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>55</fpage>
<lpage>60</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2004.02059.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15212645</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordt</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>DiVasta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Gynecomastia in adolescents</article-title>
<source/>Curr Opin Pediatr
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>375</fpage>
<lpage>382</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOP.0b013e328306a07c</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18622190</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dursun</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dur</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Șahin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kırmızıbekmez</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karabulut</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yörük</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A rare cause of prepubertal gynecomastia: Sertoli cell
tumor</article-title>
<source/>Case Rep Pediatr
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>2015</volume>
<fpage>439239</fpage>
<lpage>439239</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/439239</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26366315</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ferraro</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Francesco</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Romano</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grandone</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>D’Andrea</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giudice</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Clinical and surgical management of unilateral prepubertal
gynecomastia</article-title>
<source/>Int J Surg Case Rep
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>1158</fpage>
<lpage>1161</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijscr.2014.11.040</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25437663</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Becker</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source/>Principles and practice of endocrinology and metabolism
          <edition>3</edition>
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia (USA)</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
<year>2001</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shozu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fukami</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ogata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Understanding the pathological manifestations of aromatase excess
syndrome: lessons for clinical diagnosis</article-title>
<source/>Expert Rev Endocrinol Metab
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>397</fpage>
<lpage>409</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/17446651.2014.926810</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25264451</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ørngreen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arlien-Søborg</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Duno</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hertz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vissing</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Endocrine function in 97 patients with myotonic dystrophy type
1</article-title>
<source/>J Neurol
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>259</volume>
<fpage>912</fpage>
<lpage>920</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-011-6277-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22349862</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Echenne</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bassez</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Congenital and infantile myotonic dystrophy</article-title>
<source/>Handbook Clin Neurol
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>113</volume>
<fpage>1387</fpage>
<lpage>1393</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-59565-2.00009-5</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ekstrom</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hung</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Parent-reported multi-national study of the impact of congenital
and childhood onset myotonic dystrophy</article-title>
<source/>Dev Med Child Neurol
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>698</fpage>
<lpage>705</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.12948</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26510705</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shieh</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Muscular dystrophies and other genetic myopathies</article-title>
<source/>Neurol Clin
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>1009</fpage>
<lpage>1029</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ncl.2013.04.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24176421</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pathogenic mechanisms of myotonic dystrophy</article-title>
<source/>Biochem Soc Trans
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>1281</fpage>
<lpage>1286</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST0371281</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19909263</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Turner</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hilton-Jones</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Myotonic dystrophy: diagnosis, management and new
therapies</article-title>
<source/>Curr Opin Neurol
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>599</fpage>
<lpage>606</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WCO.0000000000000128</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25121518</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Turner</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hilton-Jones</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The myotonic dystrophies: diagnosis and
management</article-title>
<source/>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>358</fpage>
<lpage>367</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.2008.158261</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20176601</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>