<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0213264</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">1117</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biol Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biol. Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Biological psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0006-3223</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-2402</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31272685</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7053436</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2019.04.029</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1548822</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Habituation Learning is a Widely Affected Mechanism in Drosophila Models of Intellectual Disability and Autism Spectrum Disorders</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fenckova</surname>
<given-names>Michaela</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blok</surname>
<given-names>Laura E.R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asztalos</surname>
<given-names>Lenke</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>David P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cizek</surname>
<given-names>Pavel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Singgih</surname>
<given-names>Euginia L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Glennon</surname>
<given-names>Jeffrey C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>IntHout</surname>
<given-names>Joanna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zweier</surname>
<given-names>Christiane</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eichler</surname>
<given-names>Evan E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>von Reyn</surname>
<given-names>Catherine R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bernier</surname>
<given-names>Raphael A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asztalos</surname>
<given-names>Zoltan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schenck</surname>
<given-names>Annette</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Human Genetics, Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour, Radboud university medical center, 6525 GA, Nijmegen, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Aktogen Ltd., Department of Genetics, University of Cambridge, CB2 3EH, Cambridge, United Kingdom. Current address: Unit 1 Highlode Industrial Estate, Stocking Fen Road, Ramsey, Huntingdon Cambridgeshire PE26 2RB, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Aktogen Hungary Ltd., Bay Zoltán Nonprofit Ltd. for Applied Research, Institute for Biotechnology (BAY-BIO), H-6726, Szeged, Hungary</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>School of Biomedical Engineering, Science and Health Systems, Drexel University, 3141 Chestnut Street, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA</aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Centre for Molecular and Biomolecular Informatics, Radboud Institute for Molecular Life Sciences, Radboud university medical center, Nijmegen, 6525 GA, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Cognitive Neuroscience, Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour, Radboud university medical center, 6525 EN, Nijmegen, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department for Health Evidence, Radboud university medical center, 6525 EZ, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Institute of Human Genetics, Friedrich-Alexander-Universität Erlangen-Nürnberg, 91054, Erlangen, Germany</aff>
<aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Genome Sciences, University of Washington School of Medicine, Seattle, WA 98195, USA</aff>
<aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98195, USA</aff>
<aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Department of Neurobiology and Anatomy, Drexel School of Medicine, 2900 W. Queen Lane, Philadelphia, PA 19129, USA</aff>
<aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98105, USA</aff>
<aff id="A13"><label>13</label>Institute of Biochemistry, Biological Research Centre, Hungarian Academy of Sciences, H-6726, Szeged, Hungary</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Annette Schenck, Radboudumc, Dept. of Human Genetics, Geert Grooteplein 10, 6525 GA, Nijmegen, The Netherlands, <email>Annette.Schenck@radboudumc.nl</email>, Tel: +31243610868</corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
<p id="P34">Financial disclosures:</p>
<p id="P35">In the past 3 years, J.C.G. has acted as a consultant to Boehringer Ingelheim GmbH but is not an employee, stock- or share-holder of this company. E.E.E. is on the scientific advisory board (SAB) of DNAnexus, Inc.. Z.A. is a director and shareholder of Aktogen Ltd.. L.A. is a director of Aktogen Ltd.. The commercial light-off jump habituation system was purchased from Aktogen Ltd.. Aktogen Ltd. provided training of the personnel and ~ 150 experiments from the initial screen were performed at Aktogen Ltd. by M.F. and L.A.. All other authors report no biomedical financial interests or potential conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>24</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>09</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>15</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>03</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>86</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>294</fpage>
<lpage>305</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2019.04.029-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<sec id="S1">
<title>Background:</title>
<p id="P1">Although habituation is one of the most ancient and fundamental forms of learning, its regulators and relevance for human disease are poorly understood.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p id="P2">We manipulated the orthologs of 286 genes implicated in intellectual disability (ID) with or without comorbid autism spectrum disorder (ASD) specifically in <italic>Drosophila</italic> neurons, and tested these models in light-off jump habituation. We dissected neuronal substrates underlying the identified habituation deficits and integrated genotype-phenotype annotations, gene ontologies and interaction networks to determine the clinical features and molecular processes that are associated with habituation deficits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Results:</title>
<p id="P3">We identified more than 100 genes required for habituation learning. For the vast majority of these, 93 genes, a role in habituation learning was previously unknown. These genes characterize ID disorders with macrocephaly/overgrowth and comorbid ASD. Moreover, ASD individuals from the Simons Simplex Collection (SSC) carrying damaging <italic>de novo</italic> mutations in these genes exhibit increased aberrant behaviors associated with inappropriate, stereotypic speech. At the molecular level, ID genes required for normal habituation are enriched in synaptic function and converge on Ras-MAPK signaling. Both increased Ras-MAPK signaling in GABAergic and decreased Ras-MAPK signaling in cholinergic neurons specifically inhibit the adaptive habituation response.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p id="P4">Our work supports the relevance of habituation learning to autism, identifies an unprecedented number of novel habituation players, supports an emerging role for inhibitory neurons in habituation and reveals an opposing, circuit-level-based mechanism for Ras-MAPK signaling. This establishes habituation as a possible, widely applicable functional readout and target for pharmacologic intervention in ID/ASD.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Habituation learning</kwd>
<kwd>Intellectual Disability</kwd>
<kwd>Autism Spectrum Disorder</kwd>
<kwd>
<italic>Drosophila</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>Ras-MAPK</kwd>
<kwd>GABAergic neurons</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>