<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101139309</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">30413</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Lancet. Neurology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1474-4422</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1474-4465</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30981321</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7055532</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30033-X</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1565473</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Clinical application of next-generation sequencing to the practice of neurology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rexach</surname>
<given-names>Jessica</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Hane</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martinez-Agosto</surname>
<given-names>Julian A</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Németh</surname>
<given-names>Andrea H</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fogel</surname>
<given-names>Brent L</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1">Program in Neurogenetics, Department of Neurology (J Rexach MD, B L Fogel MD), Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine (H Lee PhD), Department of Human Genetics (H Lee, J A Martinez-Agosto MD, B L Fogel), Division of Medical Genetics, Department of Pediatrics (J A Martinez-Agosto), and Clinical Neurogenomics Research Center, Department of Neurology (B L Fogel), David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles, CA, USA; Nuffield Department of Clinical Neurosciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK (A H Németh PhD); and Oxford Centre for Genomic Medicine, Oxford University Hospitals National Health Service Foundation Trust, Oxford, UK (A H Németh)</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
<p id="P1">Contributors</p>
<p id="P2">JR, HL, JAM-A, AHN, and BLF wrote the manuscript and all authors were responsible for its review and critique.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="CR1">Correspondence to: Dr Brent L Fogel, University of California at Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA <email>bfogel@ucla.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3">
<p id="P35">Declaration of interests</p>
<p id="P36">We declare no competing interests.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>24</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>01</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>492</fpage>
<lpage>503</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30033-X-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P3">Next-generation sequencing technologies allow for rapid and inexpensive large-scale genomic analysis, creating unprecedented opportunities to integrate genomic data into the clinical diagnosis and management of neurological disorders. However, the scale and complexity of these data make them difficult to interpret and require the use of sophisticated bioinformatics applied to extensive datasets, including whole exome and genome sequences. Detailed analysis of genetic data has shown that accurate phenotype information is essential for correct interpretation of genetic variants and might necessitate re-evaluation of the patient in some cases. A multidisciplinary approach that incorporates bioinformatics, clinical evaluation, and human genetics can help to address these challenges. However, despite numerous studies that show the efficacy of next-generation sequencing in establishing molecular diagnoses, pathogenic mutations are generally identified in fewer than half of all patients with genetic neurological disorders, exposing considerable gaps in the understanding of the human genome and providing opportunities to focus research on improving the usefulness of genomics in clinical practice. Looking forward, the emergence of precision health in neurological care will increasingly apply genomic data analysis to pharmacogenetics, preventive medicine, and patient-targeted therapies.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>