<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Translational Psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2158-3188</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32184385</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7078234</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">777</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-020-0777-y</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Further confirmation of <italic>netrin 1 receptor</italic> (<italic>DCC</italic>) as a depression risk gene <italic>via</italic> integrations of multi-omics data</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Hui-Juan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>Na</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6162-1335</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Xin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Chu-Yi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7229-1519</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>Bao-Liang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Shu-Fang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Jing</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>Bin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Lu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>Qiu-Fang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Wei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>Hong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>Xiao</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>xiaoxiao2@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8197-6552</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Ming</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>limingkiz@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Yi</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>psylee@163.com</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1792 7072</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419010.d</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Animal Models and Human Disease Mechanisms of the Chinese Academy of Sciences and Yunnan Province, </institution><institution>Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Kunming, Yunnan China </aff>
<aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Kunming College of Life Science, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, Yunnan China </aff>
<aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0368 7223</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.33199.31</institution-id><institution>Affiliated Wuhan Mental Health Center, Tongji Medical College, </institution><institution>Huazhong University of Science and Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, Hubei China </aff>
<aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 9015</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.503241.1</institution-id><institution>Research Center for Psychological and Health Sciences, </institution><institution>China University of Geosciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, Hubei China </aff>
<aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0198 0694</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.263761.7</institution-id><institution>Suzhou Guangji Hospital, </institution><institution>The Affiliated Guangji Hospital of Soochow University, </institution></institution-wrap>Suzhou, Jiangsu China </aff>
<aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.415444.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Blood Transfusion, </institution><institution>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Kunming Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kunming, Yunnan China </aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>17</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>17</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<elocation-id>98</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>26</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>21</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>3</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement>
<license license-type="OpenAccess">
<license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="Par1">Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) of major depression and its relevant biological phenotypes have been extensively conducted in large samples, and transcriptome-wide analyses in the tissues of brain regions relevant to pathogenesis of depression, e.g., dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC), have also been widely performed recently. Integrating these multi-omics data will enable unveiling of depression risk genes and even underlying pathological mechanisms. Here, we employ summary data-based Mendelian randomization (SMR) and integrative risk gene selector (iRIGS) approaches to integrate multi-omics data from GWAS, DLPFC expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) analyses and enhancer-promoter physical link studies to prioritize high-confidence risk genes for depression, followed by independent replications across distinct populations. These integrative analyses identify multiple high-confidence depression risk genes, and numerous lines of evidence supporting pivotal roles of the <italic>netrin 1 receptor</italic> (<italic>DCC</italic>) gene in this illness across different populations. Our subsequent explorative analyses further suggest that <italic>DCC</italic> significantly predicts neuroticism, well-being spectrum, cognitive function and putamen structure in general populations. Gene expression correlation and pathway analyses in DLPFC further show that <italic>DCC</italic> potentially participates in the biological processes and pathways underlying synaptic plasticity, axon guidance, circadian entrainment, as well as learning and long-term potentiation. These results are in agreement with the recent findings of this gene in neurodevelopment and psychiatric disorders, and we thus further confirm that <italic>DCC</italic> is an important susceptibility gene for depression, and might be a potential target for new antidepressants.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject">
<title>Subject terms</title>
<kwd>Depression</kwd>
<kwd>Comparative genomics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id>
<institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (National Science Foundation of China)</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>81722019</award-id>
<award-id>81771439</award-id>
<award-id>81871067</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name>
<surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>Hong</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Ming</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source>
<institution>Hubei Province health and family planning scientific research project (WJ2015Q033 to N.Q.)</institution>
</funding-source>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<funding-group>
<award-group>
<funding-source>
<institution>Xiao Xiao was supported by the Chinese Academy of Sciences Western Light Program, and Youth Innovation Promotion Association, CAS.</institution>
</funding-source>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
<meta-value>© The Author(s) 2020</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="Par2">A primary current challenge in the psychiatry field is to dissect the underlying neurobiological basis of common mental illnesses such as major depression, which is said to be one of the ten most disabling conditions in the world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Given the substantial heritability of major depression (~37%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, the application of human genetic approaches is believed to both promote the understanding of its biological mechanisms and benefit discovery and development of effective clinical treatment strategies. Indeed, recent genome-wide association studies (GWAS) of depressive subjects and healthy controls have identified multiple statistically robust loci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, providing numerous candidates for in-depth exploration of its pathological mechanisms. Notably, there is growing consensus on such “in-depth functional exploration” of psychiatric disease-related loci, and several critical steps have been raised: (1) probe the risk genes from risk locus; (2) depict (novel or refined) disease mechanisms based on the risk genes; (3) assess the druggability of the risk gene product itself or a proximate pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. This research regimen has been widely applied in recent years, however, the fact that majority of the disease risk loci identified by GWAS reside in the noncoding genomic regions has significantly hampered the accomplishments in elucidating their biological and pathological impacts. Fortunately, accumulating studies have found that noncoding variations of complex diseases tend to be associated with mRNA expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, and analyzing the expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) effects of the risk alleles in relevant tissues is therefore a plausible strategy to probe the risk genes from risk locus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. In line with this, several integrative analyses using GWAS and brain eQTL data have revealed susceptibility genes and potential biological mechanisms for psychiatric disorders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par3">For depression, recent genome-wide linkage disequilibrium (LD) score regression analyses have shown strong genetic correlations between this illness and multiple quantifiable behavioral phenotypes (e.g., emotional traits and cognitive functions)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. In addition, accumulating clinical and basic data derived from depression patients and inbred model mice have demonstrated that depression is associated with multiple levels of abnormalities of brain areas engaged in emotional and cognitive processes (e.g., dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) and hippocampus), including aberrant structure and function as well as neuronal atrophy and synaptic loss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The observation that some antidepressants likely exert effects via blocking or reversing these aberrations further confirmed that such phenotypes might play pivotal roles in depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Therefore, translating genetic findings of depression may provide valuable insights into its pathological mechanisms and even facilitate therapeutic development, however, such translational approach requires thorough integrations of the data obtained from multiple perspectives including genomics, neuroscience, pharmacology, and biochemical<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par4">In the present study, with an aim to identify risk genes and relevant mechanisms of depression, we have employed summary data-based Mendelian randomization (SMR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and Bayesian integrative risk gene selector (iRIGS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> to integrate omics data from GWAS, DLPFC eQTL, and genome-scale chromosome conformation capture (Hi-C). Multiple depression risk genes are identified after combined investigation of integrative results, among which the <italic>netrin 1 receptor</italic> (<italic>DCC</italic>) gene is prioritized as a high-confidence candidate. Risk alleles correlated with brain <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA levels show robust link with the onset of depression. We also find that <italic>DCC</italic> associating variants significantly predict depression relevant biological phenotypes, suggesting participation of this gene in the biological processes of depression pathogenesis. These results further confirm the previous functional analyses of <italic>DCC</italic> supporting the hypothesis that it is an authentic and important risk gene for depression.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods and materials</title>
<p id="Par5">All the protocols and methods used in this study were approved by the institutional review board of the Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences.</p>
<sec id="Sec3">
<title>Depression GWAS data</title>
<sec id="Sec4">
<title>European GWAS data</title>
<p id="Par6">Depression GWAS data was retrieved from that Howard et al. meta-analyses of UK Biobank, PGC2, and 23andMe GWAS datasets (a total of 246,363 cases and 561,190 controls)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. There were originally 102 independent loci identified as showing genome-wide significant associations with depression in Europeans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Due to the restrictions on data share policy of 23andMe sample, the authors publicly deposited the genome-wide statistics combining UK Biobank and PGC2 GWAS datasets (170,756 cases and 329,443 controls) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://datashare.is.ed.ac.uk/handle/10283/3203">https://datashare.is.ed.ac.uk/handle/10283/3203</ext-link>), which was utilized for the current analyses. Detailed information of sample characteristics, genotyping method, and statistical analyses of each GWAS dataset can be found in the original studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec5">
<title>Chinese GWAS data</title>
<p id="Par7">Data of the GWAS of major depression in Han Chinese conducted by the CONVERGE Consortium was collected for the current study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. A total of 5303 patients and 5337 non-psychiatric controls after quality control were included. Data was accessed via the public sharing portal at 10.6084/m9.figshare.3840696. Details of the samples, genotyping method and statistical analyses can be found in the initial report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec6">
<title>SMR integrative analyses</title>
<p id="Par8">Mendelian randomization (MR) analyses utilize a genetic variation as the instrumental variable to examine causative effects of defined exposure variables (e.g., gene expression) on an outcome (e.g., illness)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. It is thus plausible to use MR analysis to identify the risk or even causal genes of complex illnesses through integrating the eQTL data. However, one potential handicap of MR analyses is that this method requires a large cohort of individuals with simultaneously available data on their phenotype, genotype and gene expression profiles, which is usually difficult to recruit. As a possible solution, Zhu et al. have developed a novel alternative method called summary data-based Mendelian randomization (SMR), which requires summary level statistical data from independent GWAS and eQTL datasets for the integration and prioritization of genes whose expression levels are relevant to the illness due to pleiotropic effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Based on SMR, the authors further developed a multi-SNP-based SMR test (--smr-multi) that considers multiple SNPs at a cis-eQTL locus in the SMR test<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, and this method is applied in this study. We respectively integrated the brain eQTL datasets from BrainSeq Phase 2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, CommonMind<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, and PsychENCODE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> with the European depression GWAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> to perform the SMR analyses. Details of the data and relevant procedure conducted are discussed below.</p>
<p id="Par9">The BrainSeq Phase 2 is a RiboZero RNA-seq eQTL database of human brain tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Data obtained from the DLPFC tissues of 397 individuals older than 13 were included, and gene-level expression eQTL was calculated based on the formula: log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) ~SNP + diagnosis + sex + SNP PCs + expression PCs. The authors identified 1,577,964 eQTL associations at a false discovery rate (FDR) ≤ 1% between 945,693 genetic variants and 13,510 genes, and the eQTL summary data were downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/libd-brainseq2/SupplementaryTable15_eQTL.tar.gz">https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/libd-brainseq2/SupplementaryTable15_eQTL.tar.gz</ext-link>, and then transformed into SMR binary (BESD) file using SMR (version 1.02) for subsequent analyses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par10">The CommonMind dataset contains polyA<sup>+</sup> RNA-seq eQTL data of DLPFC tissues collected from 467 European donors (age &gt; 17 years old)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. The mRNA levels of genes were normalized using log (CPM) (read counts per million per reads) and adjusted for diagnosis, sex, institution, AOD, PMI, RIN, RIN2, clustered LIB, and 20 SVs. The expression levels were then quantified using a linear eQTL analysis on the imputed genotype dosages based on the formula: adjusted gene expression ~SNP + 5 ancestry vectors + diagnosis. This dataset identified 3,725,946 significant cis-eQTL at a FDR ≤ 5% between 16,089 genes and 2,072,425 SNPs. We downloaded the eQTL summary data from Synapse (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.synapse.org/#!Synapse:syn5652278">https://www.synapse.org/#!Synapse:syn5652278</ext-link>) and transformed them into BESD file using SMR (version 1.02) for the integrative analyses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par11">A recent study provided the PsychENCODE eQTL summary data at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://resource.psychencode.org/">http://resource.psychencode.org/</ext-link><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Briefly, the authors calculated the eQTL association results after correcting for 100 hidden covariate (HCP) factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, and the data was generated based on 1387 individuals recruited by the research projects of CommonMind, CommonMind-HBCC, BrainGVEX, LIBD, and BipSeq etc.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Therefore, although duplicative individuals exist between PsychENCODE and CommonMind and BrainSeq datasets, the PsychENCODE is a larger eQTL dataset with a stronger detection power. The PsychENCODE eQTL summary data in BESD format was directly downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://resource.psychencode.org/">http://resource.psychencode.org/</ext-link><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par12">For SMR analysis, firstly, these eQTL summary statistics were transformed to the binary format files named BESD, as the key input files of SMR program. In addition, the other major input file was the genome-wide statistics of depression GWAS. SNPs and genes in the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) extended region were removed before SMR analyses due to the complexity of this genomic region (chr6:26M-34M, hg19). The threshold of eQTL <italic>p</italic>-value in the SMR analysis was set to be 1.00 × 10<sup>−5</sup> (--peqtl-smr 0.00001) and the default values of other parameters were used. The genes with <italic>p</italic>-value less than 5.00 × 10<sup>−4</sup> of multi-SNP-based SMR test and passed the HEIDI test (<italic>P</italic><sub>HEIDI</sub> &gt; 0.005) were considered as susceptibility genes, whose mRNA expression alterations associated with risk SNPs of depression.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec7">
<title>Integrative risk gene selector (iRIGS) analyses</title>
<p id="Par13">The growing knowledge of the importance of physical interactions between distal regulatory elements (DREs) and target promoters has promoted recent development of multiple technologies (e.g., Hi-C) capable of detecting such interactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Through integrating results of studies applying these approaches, Wang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> developed a Bayesian framework, named iRIGS, to probabilistically rank high-confidence risk genes at each GWAS locus of schizophrenia. Following their method, we herein focused on the 102 independent lead risk SNPs from previous European depression GWAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, and used the iRIGS analyses to estimate whether these index SNPs interacted with promoters of particular genes based on the omics data of short-range and long-range enhancer-promoter links. These omics data were derived from four sources in three independent published studies as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. The first study is the Hi-C analyses of the cortical/subcortical plate and the germinal zone of human cerebral cortex conducted by Won et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. This study reported 221,069 and 228,323 DRE-promoter links in the cortical/subcortical plate and the germinal zone, respectively. The second study is a capture Hi-C analysis of the cell line GM12878, a human Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)-transformed lymphoblastoid cell line<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and identified 1,618,000 DRE-promoter links. The third study is conducted by the FANTOM5 project to infer the enhancer-promoter links across multiple human tissues, and eventually obtained 66,899 enhancer-promoter links<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The data of these studies were placed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.vumc.org/cgg/irigs">https://www.vumc.org/cgg/irigs</ext-link> in a ready-to-use format for iRIGS analyses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. The R code of iRIGS were run using the default pipeline. The Bayesian posterior probability of observing the link between a SNP and a particular gene higher than 0.8 was considered to be strong, in which case the gene is a potential risk gene regulated by the SNP.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec8">
<title>Gene-wise MAGMA analyses</title>
<p id="Par14">The gene-wise <italic>p</italic>-values were respectively calculated using MAGMA (v1.07b)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> based on the depression GWAS statistics from Europeans and Han Chinese<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. MAGMA applies Brown’s method to combine SNP p-values which will consider LD, and the window size of each gene is defined as the region spanning 35-kb upstream and 10-kb downstream of this gene as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. The <italic>snp-wise</italic> = <italic>mean</italic> gene analysis model was used in the present study, which tests the mean SNP association for each gene. For the LD reference, we utilized European-ancestry and Han Chinese-ancestry individuals from the 1000 Genomes Project (Phase 3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec9">
<title>LD analyses</title>
<p id="Par15">The Haploview program (version 4.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> was utilized to estimate LD between paired SNPs using the <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> algorithm, and to determine the haplotype blocks based on the SNP data from the 1000 Genomes Project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The regional association results are plotted using LocusZoom (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://locuszoom.sph.umich.edu/locuszoom/">http://locuszoom.sph.umich.edu/locuszoom/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec10">
<title>GWAS of depressive symptoms, neuroticism, life satisfaction, positive affect, and well-being spectrum</title>
<p id="Par16">Phenotypes such as neuroticism, life satisfaction, and positive affect are generally believed to be associated with depression. Specifically, neuroticism refers to a personality trait characterized by significantly instable mood in response to stress-inducing events<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, and is presumed to be a risk factor for depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Phenotypes of the well-being spectrum, including depressive symptoms, neuroticism, life satisfaction, and positive affect, have all been found genetically correlated with depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. We therefore collected GWAS resources of these biological phenotypes from a recent study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, in which the authors measured the well-being spectrum using survey questions on depressive symptoms, neuroticism, life satisfaction, and positive affect, and applied multivariate genome-wide-association meta-analysis (GWAMA) on univariate GWAMAs of depressive symptoms (<italic>N</italic> = 1,295,946), neuroticism (<italic>N</italic> = 582,989), life satisfaction (<italic>N</italic> = 80,852), and positive affect (<italic>N</italic> = 410,603), as well as the combinatory well-being spectrum (<italic>N</italic> = 2,370,390).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec11">
<title>GWAS of cognitive performance and intelligence</title>
<p id="Par17">The data of cognitive performance were retrieved from a recent GWAS of 257,828 individuals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. In their study, the authors conducted a meta-analysis of the general cognitive ability GWAS by the COGENT consortium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> and additional results of the recent cognitive performance analyses in UK Biobank<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Meanwhile, the authors also conducted GWAS analysis of educational attainment (<italic>N</italic> = 766,345)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, a proxy phenotype of cognitive abilities that is believed to also reflect some personality traits. In addition, we also retrieved the results of intelligence from a GWAS of 269,867 individuals into the current study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. The authors calculated and applied a common latent <italic>g</italic> factor underlying multiple dimensions of cognitive functioning during statistical analyses given the distinct approaches of intelligence measurement in each sample.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec12">
<title>GWAS of brain imaging phenotypes</title>
<p id="Par18">Statistics of brain imaging analyses were extracted from a recent GWAS of 3144 functional and structural brain imaging phenotypes (e.g., hippocampal volume, putamen volume, task functional MRI median BOLD faces) in 8,428 subjects by the UK Biobank (accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://big.stats.ox.ac.uk/">http://big.stats.ox.ac.uk/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. In this website, GWAS results of other related phenotypes were also deposited (i.e., GWAS of a total of 3999 UK Biobank brain imaging phenotypes and other traits). We also collected the independent data from the ENIGMA Consortium GWAS of different subcortical brain volumes (accumbens, amygdala, caudate, hippocampus, pallidum, putamen, and thalamus)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. According to the previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, there was a strong correlation between the UK Biobank and ENIGMA imaging samples, suggesting that methodologies applied in the measurement and statistical analyses of these phenotypes were relatively consistent. In addition, a more recent GWAS has been conducted to meta-analyze imaging data from CHARGE, ENIGMA and UK Biobank, resulting in a total of 38,851 subjects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec13">
<title>RNA-seq, mRNA correlation, and pathway analyses in human brains</title>
<p id="Par19">We downloaded the aligned (hg19 as reference genome) RNA-seq data (bam files) of the DLPFC tissue from three independent sample pools (BrainGVEX, CommonMind, and LIBD)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, and only non-psychiatric controls were utilized to prevent effects of confounders relevant to medical treatment. Based on this criterion, 59 controls from BrainGVEX, 50 controls from CommonMind, and 70 controls from LIBD were included. We applied the same procedures and criteria for the quality control across the three RNA-seq datasets as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. The counts of aligned reads at the gene level were calculated using featureCounts according to the annotation file of GRCh37p13<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. We calculated the transcripts per million reads (TPM) of each gene using R program following a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, and only kept the protein-coding genes with their average TPM ≥ 1.0 for the following analyses. The TPM of each gene was log2 transformed followed by Pearson analyses to assess their correlations with <italic>DCC</italic>. We used clusterProfiler<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> to analyze whether the “<italic>DCC</italic>-correlated” genes were significantly enriched in specific molecular pathways and biological processes via Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) and Gene Ontology (GO) annotations based on the integrative database called org.Hs.eg.db, and FDR <italic>q</italic>-value less than 0.1 was set to be reliable. We then performed semantic similarity analyses with GOSemSim<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> to narrow down those GO terms based on their similarity between each other (<italic>r</italic> &gt; 0.5 was considered highly similar).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec14" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="Sec15">
<title>Integrative analyses of multi-omics data identified high-confidence risk genes for depression in Europeans</title>
<p id="Par20">We applied multi-SNP-based SMR method to test the associations between risk SNPs of depression identified in the GWAS study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> and mRNA expression based on two independent DLPFC eQTL datasets from BrainSeq Phase 2 (<italic>N</italic> = 397)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> and CommonMind (<italic>N</italic> = 467)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, respectively. Subsequently, we performed additional analyses to confirm these findings using a larger eQTL dataset from PsychENCODE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, which consisted of more individuals (<italic>N</italic> = 1387) that were also partly overlapped with those in CommonMind and BrainSeq. The number of genes included in the SMR analysis were 5502 (BrainSeq Phase 2), 6036 (CommonMind) and 13,567 (PsychENCODE), respectively. The remaining genes were 5,455, 5,981 and 13,372 after ignoring the genes failing to pass the HEIDI test and 3239 genes were overlapped in all datasets. Finally, 16, 18, and 30 susceptibility genes (<italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> ≤ 5.00 × 10<sup>−4</sup>) were identified in the three eQTL datasets, respectively. As expected, SMR analyses using this larger eQTL samples replicated most of the risk genes identified in the earlier datasets, and a total of 10 risk genes exhibited statistical significance throughout all the SMR analyses (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Multi-SNP-based SMR analyses through integrating different DLPFC eQTL datasets (BrainSeq Phase 2, CommonMind, and PsychENCODE), and iRIGS analyses of the risk SNPs form European depression GWAS.</title><p>Ten genes of <italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> less than 5.00 × 10<sup>−4</sup> in all three eQTL datasets and sixteen genes of posterior probability more than 0.8 in iRIGS were marked in red.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e993" xlink:href="41398_2020_777_Fig1_HTML"></graphic></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Detailed information about the significant genes in SMR analyses.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">CHR</th><th colspan="4">Gene</th><th colspan="3">Multi-SNP-based SMR</th><th colspan="5">iRIGS</th><th colspan="2">MAGMA</th></tr><tr><th>Name</th><th>Start</th><th>End</th><th>Type</th><th>BrainSeq</th><th>CommonMind</th><th>PsychENCODE</th><th>Index SNP</th><th>CHR</th><th>Position</th><th><italic>P</italic><sub>depression</sub></th><th>Post_Prob</th><th>European</th><th>Chinese</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2</td><td><italic>AC068057.2</italic></td><td>105363096</td><td>105374177</td><td>lincRNA</td><td>1.87E–05</td><td>3.27E–05</td><td>2.13E–05</td><td>NA</td><td>NA</td><td>NA</td><td>NA</td><td>NA</td><td>6.33E–06</td><td>0.364</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td><italic>ZKSCAN7</italic></td><td>44596685</td><td>44624975</td><td>protein_coding</td><td>2.45E–04</td><td>8.02E–05</td><td>1.59E–05</td><td>rs4346585</td><td>3</td><td>44736493</td><td>7.13E–10</td><td>0.061</td><td>6.80E–08</td><td>0.484</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td><italic>ZNF502</italic></td><td>44754135</td><td>44765323</td><td>protein_coding</td><td>7.02E–05</td><td>5.29E–06</td><td>3.85E–06</td><td>rs4346585</td><td>3</td><td>44736493</td><td>7.13E–10</td><td>0.031</td><td>4.38E–05</td><td>0.394</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td><italic>ZNF501</italic></td><td>44771088</td><td>44778575</td><td>protein_coding</td><td>3.29E–04</td><td>2.14E–05</td><td>6.84E–06</td><td>rs4346585</td><td>3</td><td>44736493</td><td>7.13E–10</td><td>0.024</td><td>1.78E–04</td><td>0.320</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td><italic>NEK4</italic></td><td>52744800</td><td>52804965</td><td>protein_coding</td><td>3.45E–04</td><td>3.91E–04</td><td>1.17E–05</td><td>rs7624336</td><td>3</td><td>53244151</td><td>3.96E–08</td><td>0.005</td><td>3.44E–05</td><td>0.436</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td><italic>B3GALTL</italic></td><td>31774073</td><td>31906413</td><td>protein_coding</td><td>4.68E–05</td><td>1.01E–06</td><td>1.11E–09</td><td>rs1409379</td><td>13</td><td>31907741</td><td>1.67E–09</td><td>0.026</td><td>7.21E–13</td><td>0.777</td></tr><tr><td><bold><underline>14</underline></bold></td><td><bold><italic><underline>LRFN5</underline></italic></bold></td><td><bold><underline>42076773</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>42373752</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>protein_coding</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>4.05E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>06</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>1.96E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>04</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>4.11E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>04</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>rs61990288</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>14</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>42074726</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>1.68E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>13</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>1.000</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>1.01E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>11</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>0.406</underline></bold></td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td><italic>AREL1</italic></td><td>75120140</td><td>75179818</td><td>protein_coding</td><td>1.10E–05</td><td>6.47E–05</td><td>2.18E–06</td><td>rs1045430</td><td>14</td><td>75130235</td><td>7.31E–13</td><td>0.019</td><td>1.32E–07</td><td>0.572</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td><italic>TRMT61A</italic></td><td>103995521</td><td>104003410</td><td>protein_coding</td><td>3.80E–05</td><td>2.42E–05</td><td>4.47E–08</td><td>rs10149470</td><td>14</td><td>104017953</td><td>3.72E–14</td><td>0.002</td><td>6.41E–10</td><td>0.624</td></tr><tr><td><bold><underline>18</underline></bold></td><td><bold><italic><underline>DCC</underline></italic></bold></td><td><bold><underline>49866542</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>51057784</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>protein_coding</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>6.58E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>05</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>1.27E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>04</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>2.78E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>05</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>rs7227069</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>18</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>50731802</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>1.50E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>11</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>0.828</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>2.85E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>12</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>3.21E</underline></bold>–<bold><underline>04</underline></bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Post_Prob</italic> posterior probability.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
<p id="Par21">We then conducted iRIGS analyses to identify potential risk genes through evaluating the physical interactions between enhancers and promoters. Briefly, whether the 102 independent lead risk SNPs from previous European depression GWAS were involved in such interactions were examined<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. SNPs and genes in the MHC extended region were removed before iRIGS analyses, and the enhancer-promoter links between 1229 genes and these depression risk SNPs were then captured. Our results revealed that the posterior probabilities of 16 genes were higher than 0.8, indicating that they are potentially high-confidence depression risk genes under the influences of the risk SNPs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par22">Through the SMR and iRIGS analyses, two genes were identified in both approaches (marked in bold and underlined in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>). The first gene, <italic>LRFN5</italic> at 14q23.1, showed significant associations in SMR (<italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> = 4.05 × 10<sup>−6</sup> in BrainSeq Phase 2, <italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> = 1.96 × 10<sup>−4</sup> in CommonMind, <italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> = 4.11 × 10<sup>−4</sup> in PsychENCODE) and iRIGS analyses (posterior probability = 1.000). This gene encodes a protein of leucine rich repeat and fibronectin type III domain containing 5, and previous studies implicated its crucial roles in synapse formation and differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par23">Another high-confidence risk gene is <italic>DCC</italic> at 18q21.3 which encodes a transmembrane receptor for the protein netrin-1. <italic>DCC</italic> exhibited significant association signals in both SMR (<italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> = 6.58 × 10<sup>−5</sup> in BrainSeq Phase 2, <italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> = 1.27 × 10<sup>−4</sup> in CommonMind, <italic>P</italic><sub>SMR-multi</sub> = 2.78 × 10<sup>−5</sup> in PsychENCODE) and iRIGS analyses (posterior probability = 0.828). <italic>DCC</italic> has been extensively described in a recent review regarding its potential roles in the central nervous systems and psychiatric disorders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, in brief, this gene is highly expressed in dendritic spines of pyramidal neurons, and exerts pivotal regulatory effects on synaptic function and plasticity in adult brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. The Dcc protein is known to be a cell adhesion molecule that mediates the effects of netrin-1 on axon outgrowth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>, and deficits of <italic>Dcc</italic> in the adult forebrain neurons results in aberrant long-term potentiation (LTP), long-term depression (LTD) and dendritic spine morphology, as well as impaired spatial and recognition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Intriguingly, recent studies have shown that <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA levels in the prefrontal cortex of antidepressant-free depression patients who committed suicide were significantly elevated comparing with control subjects (i.e.<italic>, DCC</italic> mRNA levels were 48% higher in cases compared to control subjects in the first cohort by Manitt et al. (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.026)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>, and were ~40% higher in cases in comparison with controls in the second independent cohort by Torres-Berrío et al. (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>). Moreover, in a blood transcriptome analysis, <italic>DCC</italic> was again significantly upregulated in depression patients compared to controls in two independent samples (GSK-HiTDIP cohort, fold change = 1.085, <italic>p</italic> = 0.0231; Janssen-BRC cohort, fold change = 1.137, <italic>p</italic> = 0.000655)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. In addition, in the mPFC of mice exhibiting chronic social defeat stress (CSDS) exposure-induced depressive-like symptoms, expression level of <italic>Dcc</italic> is also increased<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>; on the other hand, decreased <italic>Dcc</italic> expression in the mouse PFC pyramidal neurons produces resilience against stress-induced depression-like phenotypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec16">
<title>Independent replications across populations further confirmed the association of DCC with depression</title>
<p id="Par24">Our analyses so far suggest pivotal roles of the SNPs spanning <italic>LRFN5</italic> and <italic>DCC</italic> in the risk of depression in Europeans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. We then performed the gene-level analyses via MAGMA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, which primarily consider LD structures. Intriguingly, the significant associations between these two genes with the risk of depression were again observed in Europeans (<italic>P</italic><sub>MAGMA</sub> = 1.01 × 10<sup>−11</sup> for <italic>LRFN5</italic>, <italic>P</italic><sub>MAGMA</sub> = 2.85 × 10<sup>−12</sup> for <italic>DCC</italic>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>). Given the emerging evidence supporting the notion that vital genetic markers for psychiatric disorders are normally associated with the disease across different ethnic populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> (e.g., psychiatric risk loci in <italic>ZNF804A</italic>, <italic>FADS1</italic>, and <italic>VRK2</italic> show significant associations in both Europeans and East Asians<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>), we then examined whether <italic>LRFN5</italic> and <italic>DCC</italic> were also associated with depression in Han Chinese subjects through MAGMA gene-level analyses using a published Han Chinese GWAS dataset (5303 cases and 5337 controls)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Notably, <italic>DCC</italic> was associated with depression as well in Han Chinese despite the lower level of statistical significance compared with that in Europeans (<italic>P</italic><sub>MAGMA</sub> = 3.21 × 10<sup>−4</sup>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>), but <italic>LRFN5</italic> was not associated with depression in Han Chinese (<italic>P</italic><sub>MAGMA</sub> = 0.406, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>). A detailed examination found that none of the SNPs spanning <italic>LRFN5</italic> were significantly associated with depression Han Chinese (all <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.01, Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec17">
<title>Identification of SNPs in DCC showing significant associations with depression in both populations</title>
<p id="Par25">It is generally acknowledged that potential causal variants usually exhibit consistent associations with the illnesses across populations, whereas the associations for other linked variants may be significantly affected by the different LD structures between populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>. To further explore the genetic architecture of complex illnesses, cross-population replication analysis is usually necessary. In this study, our detailed examinations found that although multiple SNPs spanning <italic>DCC</italic> showed genome-wide significant associations with depression in Europeans, their associations with the illness in Han Chinese were distinct possibly due to variations in LD (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). For example, rs7227069 showed genome-wide significant association with depression in 170,756 European cases and 329,443 matching controls collected by UK Biobank and PGC2 (rs7227069, <italic>P</italic><sub>depression</sub> = 4.64 × 10<sup>−9</sup>, odds ratio (OR) = 1.026 for A-allele, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>), and when the 23andMe GWAS dataset was also added, the association between rs7227069 and depression was strengthened in the new sample pool of 246,363 cases and 561,190 controls (<italic>P</italic><sub>depression</sub> = 1.50 × 10<sup>−11</sup>, OR = 1.024 for A-allele)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The risk association was further confirmed in an independent cohort of 414,055 cases and 892,299 controls (<italic>P</italic><sub>depression</sub> = 8.89 × 10<sup>−19</sup>, OR = 1.025 for A-allele)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. While in Han Chinese subjects, rs7227069 was only marginally associated with depression (<italic>P</italic><sub>depression</sub> = 0.071, OR = 1.127 for A-allele in 5303 cases and 5337 controls, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. By comparing the allele distributions of rs7227069 in Europeans and Chinese, we found that the frequency of A-allele at rs7227069 was 0.425 in Europeans, but it is not a common SNP in Han Chinese (frequency of A-allele is 0.038), which likely contributed to the different levels of association significance of this SNP with depression between populations.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Genetic associations of SNPs spanning <italic>DCC</italic> region with depression in Europeans and Han Chinese populations.</title><p>A physical map of the region is given and depicts known genes within the region, and the LD is defined based on the SNP rs1367635. The LD between rs7227069 and rs1367635 in both populations are also shown.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e1987" xlink:href="41398_2020_777_Fig2_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par26">Notably, we found another SNP rs1367635 in <italic>DCC</italic>, which was genome-wide significantly associated with depression in Europeans (<italic>P</italic><sub>depression</sub> = 4.35 × 10<sup>−9</sup>, OR = 1.026 for C-allele in 170,756 cases and 329,443 controls, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>), was also highly associated with this illness in Han Chinese (<italic>P</italic><sub>depression</sub> = 1.21 × 10<sup>−5</sup>, OR = 1.173 for C-allele in 5303 cases and 5337 controls, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). Rs1367635 and rs7227069 lie more than 129.0-kb apart in different introns of the <italic>DCC</italic> gene. They are in moderate LD in Europeans (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.61), while low LD in Han Chinese (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.14), highlighting the genetic heterogeneity in this locus between populations. Rs1367635 is a common SNP in both Europeans and Han Chinese despite different allelic frequencies between populations (C-allele, 0.501 in Europeans versus 0.183 in Han Chinese), and rs1367635 exhibited a stronger association signal with depression in Han Chinese than rs7227069 probably due to its higher minor allele frequency (MAF) in this population. Although the relatively smaller sample size of the current depression GWAS of Han Chinese (5303 cases and 5337 controls)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> has limited the level of statistical significance of the association signal of rs1367635 with depression, the effect size of rs1367635 on the risk of depression is comparable to other risk loci identified in genome-wide analyses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. We also performed a power analysis of rs1367635 according to its effect size on the risk of depression in Han Chinese and its allelic frequency in this population. This analysis estimated that at least 39,628 cases and controls in total were needed to reach the 80% power of detecting genome-wide significant association. Further analyses of the association between rs1367635 and depression in a large enough cohort will likely reveal a genome-wide level significant association.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec18">
<title>The depression risk alleles indicated higher DCC mRNA level in DLPFC</title>
<p id="Par27">We examined whether the depression risk SNPs (e.g., rs7227069 and rs1367635) spanning <italic>DCC</italic> were also associated with <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA expression in DLPFC. Rs7227069 showed significant association with mRNA expression of <italic>DCC</italic> in BrainSeq Phase 2 eQTL dataset, which included the RiboZero RNA-seq results of DLPFC tissues from 397 individuals (<italic>P</italic><sub>eQTL</sub> = 5.36 × 10<sup>−5</sup>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>); in the CommonMind polyA<sup>+</sup> RNA-seq eQTL dataset of 467 individuals, rs7227069 again exhibited significant association with <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA levels (<italic>P</italic><sub>eQTL</sub> = 4.41 × 10<sup>−6</sup>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>); while rs7227069 was not covered in the PsychENCODE dataset of 1,387 subjects, its complete LD SNP rs8086812 (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 1.000 in Europeans) was significantly associated with <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA expression (<italic>P</italic><sub>eQTL</sub> = 7.05 × 10<sup>−15</sup>, eQTL plot in PsychENCODE dataset was not available since we do not have access to individual-level genotype and expression data).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) analyses of rs7227069 and rs1367635/rs4940252 with <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA expression in BrainSeq Phase 2 and CommonMind datasets.</title><p>In the CommonMind eQTL dataset, rs1367635 was not directly genotyped or imputed, and we therefore used its high LD SNP rs4940252 as a proxy readout (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.880 between rs1367635-T/C and rs4940252-A/G in Europeans).</p></caption><graphic id="d29e2117" xlink:href="41398_2020_777_Fig3_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par28">Rs1367635 also showed significant association with mRNA expression of <italic>DCC</italic> in BrainSeq Phase 2 and PsychENCODE eQTL datasets (<italic>P</italic><sub>eQTL</sub> = 5.86 × 10<sup>−6</sup> in BrainSeq Phase 2, <italic>P</italic><sub>eQTL</sub> = 1.76 × 10<sup>−8</sup> in PsychENCODE; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>). In the CommonMind eQTL dataset, rs1367635 was not genotyped or imputed, and we therefore used its high LD SNP rs4940252 as a proxy readout (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.880 in Europeans). Again, rs4940252 was significantly associated with <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA expression in the CommonMind dataset (<italic>P</italic><sub>eQTL</sub> = 6.82 × 10<sup>−3</sup>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>). Therefore, the depression risk alleles at rs7227069 and rs1367635 consistently indicated higher <italic>DCC</italic> expression in the three selected eQTL datasets. This result is consistent with the published diagnostic analyses of <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA level in humans and rodent models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>, suggesting that increased expression of <italic>DCC</italic> in the brain likely serves as a risk factor of depression.</p>
<p id="Par29">We also explored the expression pattern of <italic>DCC</italic> in diverse human tissues using GTEx (Genotype-Tissue Expression project; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gtexportal.org/">https://www.gtexportal.org/</ext-link>) dataset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>, and found that <italic>DCC</italic> was preferably expressed in frontal cortex, caudate, nucleus accumbens, putamen and hippocampus compared with most other peripheral tissues (only except testis) (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S2</xref>). Further spatio-temporal expression pattern analyses using data of the developing prefrontal cortex from the BrainCloud dataset (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://braincloud.jhmi.edu/">http://braincloud.jhmi.edu/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> showed that the mRNA expression levels of <italic>DCC</italic> were higher at early developmental stages (i.e., fetal stages) compared with the later childhood and adulthood stages (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S3</xref>). We then performed the same analyses in data of multiple human brain tissues (e.g., dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, hippocampus, cerebellar cortex) from the BrainSpan dataset (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.brainspan.org/static/home">http://www.brainspan.org/static/home</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. Again, we observed that the mRNA levels of <italic>DCC</italic> were higher in prenatal brain tissues than in postnatal brain tissues. Notably, the expression of <italic>DCC</italic> was the highest during early or mid prenatal stages (9–13 post-conceptional weeks (pcw)) (Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S4</xref>), at which the developing brain starts to undergo striking changes such as the formation of gyri and sulci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>. This result supports the putative molecular origins of psychiatric disorders arise from the early developmental events<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>. Given the high expression levels of <italic>DCC</italic> in prenatal brains, using eQTL datasets including samples from only postnatal donors (e.g., CMC samples &gt; 17 years old; BrainSeq2 samples &gt; 13 years old) may not fully reveal eQTL association signals involved in psychiatric disorders. We therefore also explored the eQTL associations of risk SNPs with <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA expression in fetal brains using recently published data in European populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>. Briefly, data of 120 prenatal human brain samples (second trimester of gestation) included in the Human Developmental Biology Resource (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hdbr.org">http://www.hdbr.org</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup> was retrieved and analyzed. The risk A-allele at rs7227069 again predicted higher <italic>DCC</italic> expression (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01) (Table <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S2</xref>). There were 427 additional SNPs significantly associated with the expression of <italic>DCC</italic> (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and many of these SNPs also showed genome-wide significant associations with depression (Table <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S2</xref>). However, rs1367635 was not associated with <italic>DCC</italic> expression in this dataset. In another 201 prenatal human brain samples (mid-gestational human brains) from the UCLA Gene and Cell Therapy core<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>, neither rs7227069 nor rs1367635 showed significant association with <italic>DCC</italic> expression, but there were other SNPs significantly associated with both <italic>DCC</italic> expression and risk of depression (Table <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S3</xref>). Overall, these results support the hypothesis that certain genetic variations influencing <italic>DCC</italic> expression in human brains also affect risk of depression.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec19">
<title>DCC was associated with well-being spectrum, cognitive function, and putamen structure</title>
<p id="Par30">Given that several biological and psychological phenotypes such as mood instability, depressive symptoms and aberrant cognitive functions have been common observed in depression patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>, we hypothesized that these phenotypes were also associated with the depression risk alleles at <italic>DCC</italic>. We utilized the published GWAS resources and found that <italic>DCC</italic> SNPs showed significant associations with depressive symptoms (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 6.18 × 10<sup>−16</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 8.57 × 10<sup>−15</sup>), and were also highly associated with neuroticism (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 4.73 × 10<sup>−16</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 8.23 × 10<sup>−15</sup>), well-being spectrum (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 2.12 × 10<sup>−16</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 8.58 × 10<sup>−15</sup>), life satisfaction (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 4.92 × 10<sup>−11</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 1.91 × 10<sup>−11</sup>) and positive affect (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 4.36 × 10<sup>−15</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 5.25 × 10<sup>−13</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, among which the depression risk allele carriers tended to show increased vulnerable personality traits compared with the protective allele carriers. We also found that rs7227069 and rs1367635 showed strong associations with cognitive performance (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 2.15 × 10<sup>−6</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 1.48 × 10<sup>−6</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, educational attainment (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 5.95 × 10<sup>−13</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 1.10 × 10<sup>−9</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, and intelligence (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 1.34 × 10<sup>−6</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 2.58 × 10<sup>−8</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>, while carriers of the depression risk alleles tended to exhibit worse cognitive abilities compared with the non-risk allele carriers.</p>
<p id="Par31">We then took one step further to delve into potential neural mechanisms underlying this risk gene. In a phewas analysis including GWAS of 3999 UK Biobank brain imaging phenotypes and other traits (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://big.stats.ox.ac.uk/">http://big.stats.ox.ac.uk/</ext-link>), rs7227069 and rs1367635 were again primarily associated with depression related traits (such as mood swings and frequency of depressed mood in last 2 weeks, Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S5</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, further highlighting the involvement of <italic>DCC</italic> in this illness. More intriguingly, in this explorative analysis, we found that <italic>DCC</italic> was suggestively genome-wide significantly associated with putamen volume in the UK Biobank dataset (<italic>N</italic> = 8428 individuals; rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 9.90 × 10<sup>−7</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 8.90 × 10<sup>−6</sup>; Fig. <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">S5</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. We then tried to replicate this observation in an independent GWAS of brain imaging phenotypes from ENIGMA consortium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, and again observed suggestive genome-wide association between <italic>DCC</italic> and putamen volume in the same direction of allelic effects (<italic>N</italic> = 13,145 subjects; rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 3.32 × 10<sup>−7</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 6.64 × 10<sup>−7</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. The imaging samples from UK Biobank and ENIGMA were totally independent. More intriguingly, in a latest meta-analysis of imaging data from CHARGE, ENIGMA and UK Biobank (<italic>N</italic> = 38,851), both SNPs showed genome-wide significant associations with putamen volume (rs7227069, <italic>p</italic> = 4.64 × 10<sup>−10</sup>; rs1367635, <italic>p</italic> = 8.72 × 10<sup>−10</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec20">
<title>DCC participated in the pathways and biological processes relevant to depression pathogenesis</title>
<p id="Par32">Previous neurological studies using cellular and molecular technologies have suggested that <italic>DCC</italic> might be involved in the regulation of synaptic plasticity and relevant brain functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup>. Given the importance of these biological processes in cognition and emotion, we sought to further explore the possibility that <italic>DCC</italic> participates in depression via affecting these processes using population-level expression data. We hypothesized that genes significantly correlated with the mRNA expression of <italic>DCC</italic> should belong to the molecular pathways and biological processes in which <italic>DCC</italic> was involved. To test this hypothesis, the global mRNA expression data in three independent human brain RNA-seq datasets (i.e., BrainGVEX, CommonMind, and LIBD)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> was retrieved and the Pearson analysis was conducted. We ranked the top 800 genes (~top 5% among all protein-coding genes) in each dataset according to the corresponding significance levels of correlations between their expression and <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA levels. These top 800 genes from all three datasets then underwent an overlapping analysis, which yielded 145 genes consistently showing high correlations with <italic>DCC</italic> expression. There genes were significantly enriched in the pathways and biological processes related to synaptic plasticity, axon guidance, circadian entrainment, learning, and long-term potentiation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>). Therefore, our analyses using population-level expression data also supports the putative roles of <italic>DCC</italic> in synapses and brain functions, providing hints for the molecular mechanisms explaining the participation of <italic>DCC</italic> in depression pathogenesis.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway and Gene Ontology (GO) biological processes enrichment analyses of <italic>DCC</italic> correlated genes in the human DLPFC brain tissues.</p></caption><graphic id="d29e2599" xlink:href="41398_2020_777_Fig4_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="Par33">Great efforts have been spent to elucidate genetic and biological basis of depression in the past few decades<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>, however, the high prevalence, great phenotypic heterogeneity, and limited penetrance of known genetic risk markers of this illness have together significantly hampered success in this field. Nevertheless, multiple breakthroughs have been made through genetic studies of depression since the application of recent large GWAS, and integration of the massive data to dissect mechanisms underlying depression pathogenesis has been widely called on. In the present study, we utilize data of depression GWAS, and conduct the genome-wide integrative analyses through combining multiple brain eQTL and Hi-C datasets, followed by independent replications across populations and explorative analyses of relevant biological phenotypes. Through this stepwise analysis, we find that the gene <italic>DCC</italic> confers risk of depression in both Europeans and Han Chinese. Besides, the risk alleles predict higher <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA expression in the DLPFC, which is also proven to affect depression-relevant personality traits, cognitive function and putamen volumes in independent samples. The current study reveals that the depression risk alleles indicate larger putamen volume. Putamen is a brain region known to influence motor behaviors and learning abilities, and has also been reported to involve in the “hate circuit”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref></sup> that was lately proven vital in depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup>. Although previous studies did not identify significant putamen volume differences between depression patients and healthy controls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>, its involvement in this illness is appealing for further analyses with larger samples of different ethnic backgrounds to gain insights into the sophisticated mechanisms of depression.</p>
<p id="Par34">Notably, a recent meta-analysis of 232,964 cases and 494,162 controls across eight psychiatric illnesses (anorexia nervosa, attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder, autism spectrum disorder, bipolar disorder, major depression, obsessive-compulsive disorder, schizophrenia, and Tourette syndrome) detected 109 loci associated with at least two of them. Intriguingly, the <italic>DCC</italic> genomic region featured the most pleiotropic association (<italic>P</italic><sub>meta</sub> = 4.26 × 10<sup>−12</sup>) in this meta-analysis, exhibited significant associations with all eight diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref></sup>. Additionally, previous studies have also highlighted <italic>DCC</italic> in mood instability and the risk of depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref></sup> as well as schizophrenia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref></sup>, and multiple in vitro and murine analyses have proven its potential impact on synaptic function. For example, the protein netrin-1 and its receptor (encoded by <italic>Dcc</italic>) are widely expressed in cortical neurons during synapse formation, with significant enrichment at synapses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup>. Another study showing enrichment of <italic>Dcc</italic> in dendritic spines of pyramidal neurons further supports its involvement in synaptic physiology, and selective deletion of <italic>Dcc</italic> leads to loss of LTP, intact LTD, reduced spine length, and impaired spatial and recognition memory in mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref></sup>. The <italic>Dcc</italic> deficient/haploinsufficient mice study found that alterations in dcc expression resulted in selective alternations in dopaminergic function (e.g., exaggerated mPFC dopamine concentrations), differences in dopaminergic related behaviors during adulthood, and blunted behavioral responses to amphetamine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref></sup>. From the neurodevelopmental perspective, <italic>Dcc</italic> likely controls the growth of dopamine axon targeting in adolescence, and thereby affects the development and function of prefrontal cortex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref></sup>, resulting in aberrant cognitive processes found in depression. In agreement with this hypothesis, a previous study found that the <italic>DCC</italic> haploinsufficient adult Quebecers showed similar phenotypic features with adult <italic>Dcc</italic> haploinsufficient mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par35">Earlier studies using postmortem brain tissues have revealed neuronal loss, reduced synapse density and abnormal expression of synaptic markers in the DLPFC of depression patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, and in vitro and in vivo studies also found that risk factors of depression (e.g., stress and genetic effects) usually result in disruption of synaptic morphology and function as well as brain circuits that are essential for mood regulation and cognition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref></sup>, and thereby eventually lead to the onset of depression. Moreover, both established antidepressants used in clinical settings (<italic>e.g</italic>., serotonin-reuptake inhibitors) and molecules recently found to alleviate depressive symptoms (e.g., ketamine) confer protective effects on synaptic deficits related to depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Therefore, it is widely accepted that synaptic dysfunctions play determinant roles in the pathogenesis of depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Recent depression GWAS have also supported this contention, as genes involved in synaptic structure and neurotransmission related pathways have been repeatedly highlighted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. <italic>DCC</italic> is also an example of such genes, and further functional studies are urgently needed to gain mechanistic insights into whether and how it affects synaptic functions, brain circuits and behaviors in a disease-specific manner. Whether this gene or its proximate signaling pathway might serve as potential therapeutic targets should also be analyzed.</p>
<p id="Par36">From the Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>, we can see that sequence variations spanning <italic>TCF4</italic> gene were also genome-wide significantly associated with depression in European populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, and the magnitude is even stronger than those spanning <italic>DCC</italic>. However, <italic>TCF4</italic> was not associated with depression in Han Chinese, and the current study therefore did not include this gene in the subsequent analyses. Nevertheless, the potential importance of this gene in depression or other relevant illnesses/phenotypes should not be denied. In fact, <italic>TCF4</italic> has gained considerable attention from researchers due to its significant associations with depression, schizophrenia, cognitive processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref></sup>, and Pitt-Hopkins Syndrome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref></sup>. In a recent schizophrenia GWAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref></sup>, numerous SNPs spanning <italic>TCF4</italic> showed genome-wide significance, and the involvement of this gene in synaptic plasticity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref></sup>, CNS development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref></sup> and neuronal activity regulatory network<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref></sup> has been defined by functional analyses. We also sought to identify whether the association of <italic>DCC</italic> with depression in Europeans were a reflection of its potential LD with <italic>TCF4</italic>, and examined the distance and LD among SNPs spanning the two genes. We found that <italic>DCC</italic> and <italic>TCF4</italic> were ~2.0 Mb away from each other on the genome, the risk signals of these two genes were independent in Europeans according to the LD structure (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). Therefore, SNPs in <italic>DCC</italic> are likely genetic risk markers of depression independent of those in <italic>TCF4</italic>.</p>
<p id="Par37">Despite the above implications brought by this study, there are limitations to be interpreted. First, our study mainly focuses on variants affecting expression of particular genes, but a number of the genome-wide risk alleles for depression were not associated with expression of any genes in our analyses. While the principal purpose of our study is to prioritize high-confidence risk genes through integrative stepwise analyses, the possibility that the variants not highlighted in eQTL analyses also contribute to the progression of depression should not be denied. In fact, the characteristics of the eQTL datasets utilized in the current study might have “twisted our perceptions” of these variants. For example, the eQTL data we utilized was obtained from DLPFC homogenates rather than from specific types of cells, in the event that some variants and genes exert function in particular types of cells, the current datasets would be inappropriate for detecting such signals. Besides, the individuals in the eQTL datasets were postnatal in a wide range of different ages, making it an ideal source for exploring genes functioning throughout the lifespan but not those participate in depression in a spatio-temporal specific manner. In fact, previous studies have shown that the some psychiatric risk eQTLs are detectable only in a specific stage of life<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref></sup>. Further comprehensive functional annotations of other depression risk alleles are necessary to gain a better knowledge of the genetic risk architecture of depression. In addition, despite we found that multiple risk SNPs were significantly associated with mRNA expression of <italic>DCC</italic>, all of them were in the intron regions. Although we attempted to make functional predictions of the risk SNPs using HaploReg v4.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref></sup> and GWAVA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref></sup> through assessing whether they reside in the binding regions of H3K4me1, H3K4me3, H3K9ac, H3K27ac, or transcription factors, we were unable to identify any SNPs showing potential regulatory functions. Therefore, a more complicated regulatory mechanism might underlie the association between the risk SNPs and <italic>DCC</italic> mRNA expression. One possibility might be that the risk SNPs reflect a causal structural variation beyond the detection scope of the current GWAS approach. While the importance of <italic>DCC</italic> in depression should be acknowledged, further studies revealing the causal variant in this genomic region are needed.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary information</title>
<sec id="Sec22">
<p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41398_2020_777_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Materials</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
</fn>
<fn>
<p>These authors contributed equally: Hui-Juan Li, Na Qu, Li Hui</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<sec>
<title>Supplementary information</title>
<p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at (10.1038/s41398-020-0777-y).</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81722019 to M.L., 81871067 to H.C., 81771439 to L.H.); Hubei Province health and family planning scientific research project (WJ2015Q033 to N.Q.); Population and Family Planning Commission of Wuhan (WX14B34 to N.Q.). X.X. was supported by the Chinese Academy of Sciences Western Light Program, and Youth Innovation Promotion Association, CAS. M.L. was supported by CAS Pioneer Hundred Talents Program and the 1000 Young Talents Program. Data were generated as part of the PsychENCODE Consortium, supported by: U01MH103392, U01MH103365, U01MH103346, U01MH103340, U01MH103339, R21MH109956, R21MH105881, R21MH105853, R21MH103877, R21MH102791, R01MH111721, R01MH110928, R01MH110927, R01MH110926, R01MH110921, R01MH110920, R01MH110905, R01MH109715, R01MH109677, R01MH105898, R01MH105898, R01MH094714, P50MH106934, U01MH116488, U01MH116487, U01MH116492, U01MH116489, U01MH116438, U01MH116441, U01MH116442, R01MH114911, R01MH114899, R01MH114901, R01MH117293, R01MH117291, and R01MH117292 awarded to: Schahram Akbarian (Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai), Gregory Crawford (Duke University), Stella Dracheva (Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai), Peggy Farnham (University of Southern California), Mark Gerstein (Yale University), Daniel Geschwind (University of California, Los Angeles), Fernando Goes (Johns Hopkins University), Thomas M. Hyde (Lieber Institute for Brain Development), Andrew Jaffe (Lieber Institute for Brain Development), James A. Knowles (University of Southern California), Chunyu Liu (SUNY Upstate Medical University), Dalila Pinto (Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai), Panos Roussos (Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai), Stephan Sanders (University of California, San Francisco), Nenad Sestan (Yale University), Pamela Sklar (Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai), Matthew State (University of California, San Francisco), Patrick Sullivan (University of North Carolina), Flora Vaccarino (Yale University), Daniel Weinberger (Lieber Institute for Brain Development), Sherman Weissman (Yale University), Kevin White (University of Chicago), Jeremy Willsey (University of California, San Francisco), and Peter Zandi (Johns Hopkins University). Data were generated as part of the CommonMind Consortium supported by funding from Takeda Pharmaceuticals Company Limited, F. Hoffman-La Roche Ltd and NIH grants R01MH085542, R01MH093725, P50MH066392, P50MH080405, R01MH097276, RO1-MH-075916, P50M096891, P50MH084053S1, R37MH057881 and R37MH057881S1, HHSN271201300031C, AG02219, AG05138, and MH06692. Brain tissue for the study was obtained from the following brain bank collections: the Mount Sinai NIH Brain and Tissue Repository, the University of Pennsylvania Alzheimer’s Disease Core Center, the University of Pittsburgh NeuroBioBank and Brain and Tissue Repositories and the NIMH Human Brain Collection Core. CMC Leadership: Pamela Sklar, Joseph Buxbaum (Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai), Bernie Devlin, David Lewis (University of Pittsburgh), Raquel Gur, Chang-Gyu Hahn (University of Pennsylvania), Keisuke Hirai, Hiroyoshi Toyoshiba (Takeda Pharmaceuticals Company Limited), Enrico Domenici, Laurent Essioux (F. Hoffman-La Roche Ltd), Lara Mangravite, Mette Peters (Sage Bionetworks), Thomas Lehner, Barbara Lipska (NIMH).</p>
</ack>
<notes notes-type="author-contribution">
<title>Author contributions</title>
<p>X.X., Y.L., and M.L. designed the study and interpreted the results. H.J.L., N.Q., and L.H. conducted the primary analysis. X.C., C.Y.Z., B.L.Z., S.F.Z., J.C., B.X., W.L., L.W., Q.F.J., and H.C. contributed to literature search and assistance in analysis. H.L., X.X., and M.L. drafted the manuscript, and all authors contributed to the final version of the paper.</p>
</notes>
<notes notes-type="COI-statement">
<title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p id="Par38">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
</notes>
<ref-list id="Bib1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CR1">
<label>1.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frank</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Major depressive disorder: new clinical, neurobiological, and treatment perspectives</article-title>
<source/>Lancet
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>379</volume>
<fpage>1045</fpage>
<lpage>1055</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60602-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22189047</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR2">
<label>2.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>PF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Neale</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kendler</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetic epidemiology of major depression: review and meta-analysis</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Psychiatry
          <year>2000</year>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>1552</fpage>
<lpage>1562</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.157.10.1552</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11007705</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR3">
<label>3.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wray</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association analyses identify 44 risk variants and refine the genetic architecture of major depression</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>668</fpage>
<lpage>681</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0090-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29700475</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR4">
<label>4.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide meta-analysis of depression identifies 102 independent variants and highlights the importance of the prefrontal brain regions</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>343</fpage>
<lpage>352</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-018-0326-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718901</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR5">
<label>5.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wendland</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ehlers</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Translating neurogenomics into new medicines</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>650</fpage>
<lpage>656</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.04.027</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26140822</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR6">
<label>6.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gandal</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leppa</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Won</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parikshak</surname>
<given-names>NN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Geschwind</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The road to precision psychiatry: translating genetics into disease mechanisms</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1397</fpage>
<lpage>1407</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4409</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27786179</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR7">
<label>7.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beesley</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>French</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dunning</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Beyond GWASs: illuminating the dark road from association to function</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>779</fpage>
<lpage>797</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2013.10.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24210251</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR8">
<label>8.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A human-specific AS3MT isoform and BORCS7 are molecular risk factors in the 10q24.32 schizophrenia-associated locus</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Med.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>649</fpage>
<lpage>656</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.4096</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27158905</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR9">
<label>9.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The depression GWAS risk allele predicts smaller cerebellar gray matter volume and reduced SIRT1 mRNA expression in Chinese population</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>333</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-019-0675-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31819045</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR10">
<label>10.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of a functional 339-bp Alu polymorphism in the schizophrenia-associated locus at 10q24.32</article-title>
<source/>Zool. Res.
          <year>2020</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>84</fpage>
<lpage>89</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24272/j.issn.2095-8137.2020.014</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31840948</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR11">
<label>11.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of the primate-specific gene BTN3A2 as an additional schizophrenia risk gene in the MHC loci</article-title>
<source/>EBioMedicine
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>530</fpage>
<lpage>541</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2019.05.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31133542</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR12">
<label>12.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Comprehensive integrative analyses identify GLT8D1 and CSNK2B as schizophrenia risk genes</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>838</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03247-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29483533</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR13">
<label>13.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The genome-wide risk alleles for psychiatric disorders at 3p21.1 show convergent effects on mRNA expression, cognitive function and mushroom dendritic spine</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2020</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>48</fpage>
<lpage>66</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-019-0592-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31723243</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR14">
<label>14.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Decreased expression of synapse-related genes and loss of synapses in major depressive disorder</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Med.
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>1413</fpage>
<lpage>1417</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2886</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22885997</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR15">
<label>15.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Penzes</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cahill</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>VanLeeuwen</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Woolfrey</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dendritic spine pathology in neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>285</fpage>
<lpage>293</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2741</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21346746</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR16">
<label>16.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Forrest</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parnell</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Penzes</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dendritic structural plasticity and neuropsychiatric disease</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>215</fpage>
<lpage>234</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn.2018.16</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29545546</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR17">
<label>17.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Russo</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nestler</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The brain reward circuitry in mood disorders</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>609</fpage>
<lpage>625</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3381</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23942470</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR18">
<label>18.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Duman</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aghajanian</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sanacora</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krystal</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic plasticity and depression: new insights from stress and rapid-acting antidepressants</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Med.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>238</fpage>
<lpage>249</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.4050</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26937618</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR19">
<label>19.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Duman</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aghajanian</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic dysfunction in depression: potential therapeutic targets</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>338</volume>
<fpage>68</fpage>
<lpage>72</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1222939</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23042884</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR20">
<label>20.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Niculescu</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Le-Niculescu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Convergent functional genomics: what we have learned and can learn about genes, pathways, and mechanisms</article-title>
<source/>Neuropsychopharmacology
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>355</fpage>
<lpage>356</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2009.107</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20010721</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR21">
<label>21.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Integration of summary data from GWAS and eQTL studies predicts complex trait gene targets</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>481</fpage>
<lpage>487</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3538</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27019110</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR22">
<label>22.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Integrative analysis of omics summary data reveals putative mechanisms underlying complex traits</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>918</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03371-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29500431</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR23">
<label>23.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Bayesian framework that integrates multi-omics data and gene networks predicts risk genes from schizophrenia GWAS data</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>691</fpage>
<lpage>699</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-019-0382-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30988527</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR24">
<label>24.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Converge consortium.</collab>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sparse whole-genome sequencing identifies two loci for major depressive disorder</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>523</volume>
<fpage>588</fpage>
<lpage>591</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14659</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26176920</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR25">
<label>25.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ebrahim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>‘Mendelian randomization’: can genetic epidemiology contribute to understanding environmental determinants of disease?</article-title>
<source/>Int. J. Epidemiol.
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>22</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyg070</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12689998</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR26">
<label>26.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Collado-Torres</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Regional heterogeneity in gene expression, regulation, and coherence in the frontal cortex and hippocampus across development and Schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>
<lpage>216</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2019.05.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31174959</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR27">
<label>27.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fromer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Gene expression elucidates functional impact of polygenic risk for schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1442</fpage>
<lpage>1453</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4399</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27668389</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR28">
<label>28.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gandal</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptome-wide isoform-level dysregulation in ASD, schizophrenia, and bipolar disorder</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>362</volume>
<fpage>6420</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aat8127</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR29">
<label>29.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>PsychEncode Consortium</surname>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The PsychENCODE project</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>1707</fpage>
<lpage>1712</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4156</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26605881</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR30">
<label>30.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mifsud</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mapping long-range promoter contacts in human cells with high-resolution capture Hi-C</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>598</fpage>
<lpage>606</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3286</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25938943</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR31">
<label>31.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Won</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Chromosome conformation elucidates regulatory relationships in developing human brain</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>538</volume>
<fpage>523</fpage>
<lpage>527</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature19847</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27760116</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR32">
<label>32.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Andersson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>An atlas of active enhancers across human cell types and tissues</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>507</volume>
<fpage>455</fpage>
<lpage>461</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12787</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24670763</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR33">
<label>33.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Leeuw</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mooij</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heskes</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Posthuma</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>MAGMA: generalized gene-set analysis of GWAS data</article-title>
<source/>PLoS Comput. Biol.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>e1004219</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004219</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25885710</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR34">
<label>34.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Genomes Project Consortium.</collab>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A global reference for human genetic variation</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>526</volume>
<fpage>68</fpage>
<lpage>74</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature15393</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26432245</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR35">
<label>35.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fry</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maller</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Haploview: analysis and visualization of LD and haplotype maps</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>263</fpage>
<lpage>265</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bth457</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15297300</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR36">
<label>36.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pruim</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>LocusZoom: regional visualization of genome-wide association scan results</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>2336</fpage>
<lpage>2337</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq419</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20634204</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR37">
<label>37.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lahey</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Public health significance of neuroticism</article-title>
<source/>Am. Psychol.
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>241</fpage>
<lpage>256</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0015309</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19449983</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR38">
<label>38.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kendler</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gatz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gardner</surname>
<given-names>CO</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pedersen</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Personality and major depression: a Swedish longitudinal, population-based twin study</article-title>
<source/>Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>1113</fpage>
<lpage>1120</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.63.10.1113</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17015813</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR39">
<label>39.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baselmans</surname>
<given-names>BML</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Multivariate genome-wide analyses of the well-being spectrum</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>445</fpage>
<lpage>451</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0320-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30643256</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR40">
<label>40.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Gene discovery and polygenic prediction from a genome-wide association study of educational attainment in 1.1 million individuals</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>1112</fpage>
<lpage>1121</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0147-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30038396</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR41">
<label>41.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trampush</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>GWAS meta-analysis reveals novel loci and genetic correlates for general cognitive function: a report from the COGENT consortium</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>336</fpage>
<lpage>345</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2016.244</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28093568</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR42">
<label>42.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Study of 300,486 individuals identifies 148 independent genetic loci influencing general cognitive function</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>2098</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04362-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29844566</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR43">
<label>43.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Savage</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association meta-analysis in 269,867 individuals identifies new genetic and functional links to intelligence</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>912</fpage>
<lpage>919</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0152-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29942086</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR44">
<label>44.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Elliott</surname>
<given-names>LT</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association studies of brain imaging phenotypes in UK Biobank</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>562</volume>
<fpage>210</fpage>
<lpage>216</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0571-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30305740</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR45">
<label>45.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hibar</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Common genetic variants influence human subcortical brain structures</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>520</volume>
<fpage>224</fpage>
<lpage>229</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14101</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25607358</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR46">
<label>46.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Satizabal</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetic architecture of subcortical brain structures in 38,851 individuals</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>1624</fpage>
<lpage>1636</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0511-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31636452</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR47">
<label>47.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Integrative analyses of major histocompatibility complex loci in the genome-wide association studies of major depressive disorder</article-title>
<source/>Neuropsychopharmacology
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>1552</fpage>
<lpage>1561</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-019-0346-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30771788</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR48">
<label>48.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Interactome analyses implicated CAMK2A in the genetic predisposition and pharmacological mechanism of bipolar disorder</article-title>
<source/>J. Psychiatr. Res.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>115</volume>
<fpage>165</fpage>
<lpage>175</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2019.05.024</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150948</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR49">
<label>49.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smyth</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>923</fpage>
<lpage>930</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt656</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227677</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR50">
<label>50.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>QY</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>clusterProfiler: an R package for comparing biological themes among gene clusters</article-title>
<source/>OMICS
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>284</fpage>
<lpage>287</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/omi.2011.0118</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455463</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR51">
<label>51.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>GOSemSim: an R package for measuring semantic similarity among GO terms and gene products</article-title>
<source/>Bioinformatics
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>976</fpage>
<lpage>978</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq064</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20179076</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR52">
<label>52.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis of SALM5-induced PTPdelta dimerization for synaptic differentiation</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>268</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02414-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29348579</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR53">
<label>53.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mah</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Selected SALM (synaptic adhesion-like molecule) family proteins regulate synapse formation</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>5559</fpage>
<lpage>5568</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4839-09.2010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20410109</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR54">
<label>54.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neuron-specific SALM5 limits inflammation in the CNS via its interaction with HVEM</article-title>
<source/>Sci. Adv.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>e1500637</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1500637</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27152329</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR55">
<label>55.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goto-Ito</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis of trans-synaptic interactions between PTPdelta and SALMs for inducing synapse formation</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>269</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02417-z</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29348429</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR56">
<label>56.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>SALM5 trans-synaptically interacts with LAR-RPTPs in a splicing-dependent manner to regulate synapse development</article-title>
<source/>Sci. Rep.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>26676</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep26676</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27225731</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR57">
<label>57.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vosberg</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leyton</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The Netrin-1/DCC guidance system: dopamine pathway maturation and psychiatric disorders emerging in adolescence</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2020</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>297</fpage>
<lpage>307</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-019-0561-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31659271</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR58">
<label>58.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Horn</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>DCC expression by neurons regulates synaptic plasticity in the adult brain</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>173</fpage>
<lpage>185</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2012.12.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23291093</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR59">
<label>59.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Keino-Masu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Deleted in colorectal cancer (DCC) encodes a netrin receptor</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>1996</year>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>175</fpage>
<lpage>185</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81336-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8861902</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR60">
<label>60.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brankatschk</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dickson</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Netrins guide Drosophila commissural axons at short range</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2006</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>188</fpage>
<lpage>194</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn1625</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16429137</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR61">
<label>61.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ly</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>DSCAM is a netrin receptor that collaborates with DCC in mediating turning responses to netrin-1</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>133</volume>
<fpage>1241</fpage>
<lpage>1254</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.05.030</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18585357</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR62">
<label>62.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manitt</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>dcc orchestrates the development of the prefrontal cortex during adolescence and is altered in psychiatric patients</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>e338</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2013.105</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24346136</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR63">
<label>63.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Torres-Berrio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>DCC confers susceptibility to d epression-like behaviors in humans and mice and is regulated by miR-218</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>306</fpage>
<lpage>315</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.08.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27773352</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR64">
<label>64.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leday</surname>
<given-names>GGR</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Replicable and coupled changes in innate and adaptive immune gene expression in two case-control studies of blood microarrays in major depressive disorder</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>70</fpage>
<lpage>80</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.01.021</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28688579</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR65">
<label>65.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association analysis identifies 30 new susceptibility loci for schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>1576</fpage>
<lpage>1583</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3973</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28991256</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR66">
<label>66.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The schizophrenia risk gene ZNF804A: clinical associations, biological mechanisms and neuronal functions</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>944</fpage>
<lpage>953</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2017.19</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28289284</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR67">
<label>67.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yue</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>VRK2, a candidate gene for psychiatric and neurological disorders</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Neuropsychiatry
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>119</fpage>
<lpage>133</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000493941</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30643786</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR68">
<label>68.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Further evidence of an association between NCAN rs1064395 and bipolar disorder</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Neuropsychiatry
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>30</fpage>
<lpage>34</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000488590</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29998116</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR69">
<label>69.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ikeda</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A genome-wide association study identifies two novel susceptibility loci and trans population polygenicity associated with bipolar disorder</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>639</fpage>
<lpage>647</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2016.259</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28115744</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR70">
<label>70.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Replicated associations of FADS1, MAD1L1, and a rare variant at 10q26.13 with bipolar disorder in Chinese population</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>270</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-018-0337-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30531795</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR71">
<label>71.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The Gene Encoding Protocadherin 9 (PCDH9), a novel risk factor for major depressive disorder</article-title>
<source/>Neuropsychopharmacology
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>1128</fpage>
<lpage>1137</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2017.241</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28990594</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR72">
<label>72.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kichaev</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pasaniuc</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Leveraging functional-annotation data in trans-ethnic fine-mapping studies</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Hum. Genet.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>260</fpage>
<lpage>271</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2015.06.007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26189819</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR73">
<label>73.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>YR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keating</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Trans-ethnic genome-wide association studies: advantages and challenges of mapping in diverse populations</article-title>
<source/>Genome Med.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>91</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13073-014-0091-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25473427</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR74">
<label>74.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>GTEx Consortium.</collab>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetic effects on gene expression across human tissues</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>550</volume>
<fpage>204</fpage>
<lpage>213</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature24277</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29022597</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR75">
<label>75.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Colantuoni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Temporal dynamics and genetic control of transcription in the human prefrontal cortex</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>478</volume>
<fpage>519</fpage>
<lpage>523</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10524</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22031444</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR76">
<label>76.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptional landscape of the prenatal human brain</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>508</volume>
<fpage>199</fpage>
<lpage>206</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13185</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695229</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR77">
<label>77.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stiles</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jernigan</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The basics of brain development</article-title>
<source/>Neuropsychol. Rev.
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>327</fpage>
<lpage>348</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11065-010-9148-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21042938</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR78">
<label>78.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Birnbaum</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Investigation of the prenatal expression patterns of 108 schizophrenia-associated genetic loci</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>77</volume>
<fpage>e43</fpage>
<lpage>e51</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.10.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25592863</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR79">
<label>79.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Birnbaum</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jaffe</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hyde</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kleinman</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weinberger</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prenatal expression patterns of genes associated with neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title>
<source/>Am. J. Psychiatry
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>171</volume>
<fpage>758</fpage>
<lpage>767</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2014.13111452</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24874100</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR80">
<label>80.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Brien</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Expression quantitative trait loci in the developing human brain and their enrichment in neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title>
<source/>Genome Biol.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>194</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-018-1567-1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30419947</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR81">
<label>81.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetic control of expression and splicing in developing human brain informs disease mechanisms</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>179</volume>
<fpage>750</fpage>
<lpage>771 e722</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.09.021</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31626773</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR82">
<label>82.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hinkelmann</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cognitive impairment in major depression: association with salivary cortisol</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2009</year>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>879</fpage>
<lpage>885</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.06.023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19709646</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR83">
<label>83.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Netrin-1 promotes excitatory synaptogenesis between cortical neurons by initiating synapse assembly</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>17278</fpage>
<lpage>17289</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1085-13.2013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24174661</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR84">
<label>84.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>DCC receptors drive prefrontal cortex maturation by determining dopamine axon targeting in adolescence</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>181</fpage>
<lpage>192</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.06.009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28720317</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR85">
<label>85.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular signatures of major depression</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Biol.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1146</fpage>
<lpage>1156</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.03.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25913401</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR86">
<label>86.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bigdeli</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genetic effects influencing risk for major depressive disorder in China and Europe</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>e1074</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2016.292</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28350396</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR87">
<label>87.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zeki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Romaya</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neural correlates of hate</article-title>
<source/>PLoS ONE
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>e3556</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003556</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18958169</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR88">
<label>88.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Depression uncouples brain hate circuit</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>
<lpage>111</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2011.127</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21968929</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR89">
<label>89.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schmaal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Subcortical brain alterations in major depressive disorder: findings from the ENIGMA Major Depressive Disorder working group</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>806</fpage>
<lpage>812</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2015.69</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26122586</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR90">
<label>90.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Cross-Disorder Group of the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium.</collab>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genomic relationships, novel loci, and pleiotropic mechanisms across eight psychiatric disorders</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>179</volume>
<fpage>1469</fpage>
<lpage>1482</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.11.020</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31835028</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR91">
<label>91.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A combined pathway and regional heritability analysis indicates NETRIN1 pathway is associated with major depressive disorder</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>336</fpage>
<lpage>346</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.04.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27422368</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR92">
<label>92.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arnau-Soler</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide by environment interaction studies of depressive symptoms and psychosocial stress in UK Biobank and Generation Scotland</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>14</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-018-0360-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718454</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR93">
<label>93.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide analysis in UK Biobank identifies four loci associated with mood instability and genetic correlation with major depressive disorder, anxiety disorder and schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>1264</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-017-0012-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29187730</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR94">
<label>94.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fathalli</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rouleau</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Joober</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Association between schizophrenia and genetic variation in DCC: a case-control study</article-title>
<source/>Schizophr. Res
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>26</fpage>
<lpage>31</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2012.02.023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22418395</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR95">
<label>95.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manitt</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The netrin receptor DCC is required in the pubertal organization of mesocortical dopamine circuitry</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>8381</fpage>
<lpage>8394</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0606-11.2011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653843</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR96">
<label>96.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Netrin receptor deficient mice exhibit functional reorganization of dopaminergic systems and do not sensitize to amphetamine</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>606</fpage>
<lpage>612</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001607</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15534618</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR97">
<label>97.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pokinko</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moquin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torres-Berrio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gratton</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Resilience to amphetamine in mouse models of netrin-1 haploinsufficiency: role of mesocortical dopamine</article-title>
<source/>Psychopharmacology
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>232</volume>
<fpage>3719</fpage>
<lpage>3729</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-015-4032-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26264903</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR98">
<label>98.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Netrin-1 receptor-deficient mice show age-specific impairment in drug-induced locomotor hyperactivity but still self-administer methamphetamine</article-title>
<source/>Psychopharmacology
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>230</volume>
<fpage>607</fpage>
<lpage>616</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-013-3187-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23820928</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR99">
<label>99.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gifuni</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCrea</surname>
<given-names>ET</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shizgal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>dcc Haploinsufficiency results in blunted sensitivity to cocaine enhancement of reward seeking</article-title>
<source/>Behav. Brain Res.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>298</volume>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>31</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2015.05.020</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26005129</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR100">
<label>100.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Netrin-1 receptor-deficient mice show enhanced mesocortical dopamine transmission and blunted behavioural responses to amphetamine</article-title>
<source/>Eur. J. Neurosci.
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>3215</fpage>
<lpage>3228</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2007.05888.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18005074</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR101">
<label>101.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Role of netrin-1 in the organization and function of the mesocorticolimbic dopamine system</article-title>
<source/>J. Psychiatry Neurosci.
          <year>2011</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>296</fpage>
<lpage>310</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/jpn.100171</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21481303</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR102">
<label>102.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoops</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Making dopamine connections in adolescence</article-title>
<source/>Trends Neurosci.
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>709</fpage>
<lpage>719</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2017.09.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29032842</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR103">
<label>103.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vosberg</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mesocorticolimbic connectivity and volumetric alterations in DCC mutation carriers</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>4655</fpage>
<lpage>4665</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3251-17.2018</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29712788</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR104">
<label>104.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ota</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>REDD1 is essential for stress-induced synaptic loss and depressive behavior</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Med.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>531</fpage>
<lpage>535</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.3513</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24728411</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR105">
<label>105.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Duric</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A negative regulator of MAP kinase causes depressive behavior</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Med.
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>1328</fpage>
<lpage>1332</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2219</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20953200</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR106">
<label>106.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Associations between TCF4 gene polymorphism and cognitive functions in schizophrenia patients and healthy controls</article-title>
<source/>Neuropsychopharmacology
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>683</fpage>
<lpage>689</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2012.234</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23249814</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR107">
<label>107.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blake</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>TCF4, schizophrenia, and Pitt-Hopkins Syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Schizophr. Bull.
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>
<lpage>447</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbq035</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20421335</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR108">
<label>108.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pardinas</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Common schizophrenia alleles are enriched in mutation-intolerant genes and in regions under strong background selection</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>381</fpage>
<lpage>389</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0059-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29483656</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR109">
<label>109.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tcf4 regulates synaptic plasticity, DNA methylation, and memory function</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>2666</fpage>
<lpage>2685</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2016.08.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568567</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR110">
<label>110.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rannals</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Psychiatric risk gene transcription factor 4 regulates intrinsic excitability of prefrontal neurons via repression of SCN10a and KCNQ1</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>43</fpage>
<lpage>55</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2016.02.021</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26971948</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR111">
<label>111.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Disruption of TCF4 regulatory networks leads to abnormal cortical development and mental disabilities</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1235</fpage>
<lpage>1246</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-019-0353-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30705426</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR112">
<label>112.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Forrest</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The psychiatric risk gene transcription factor 4 (TCF4) regulates neurodevelopmental pathways associated with schizophrenia, autism, and intellectual disability</article-title>
<source/>Schizophr. Bull.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>1100</fpage>
<lpage>1110</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbx164</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29228394</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR113">
<label>113.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wittmann</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haberle</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Linking the neuropsychiatric disease gene TCF4 to neuronal activity-dependent regulatory networks</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>2653</fpage>
<lpage>2655</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3475-17.2018</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29540544</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR114">
<label>114.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Expression of ZNF804A in human brain and alterations in schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, and major depressive disorder: a novel transcript fetally regulated by the psychosis risk variant rs1344706</article-title>
<source/>JAMA Psychiatry
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>1112</fpage>
<lpage>1120</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.1079</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25162540</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR115">
<label>115.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kellis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>HaploReg: a resource for exploring chromatin states, conservation, and regulatory motif alterations within sets of genetically linked variants</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res.
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>D930</fpage>
<lpage>D934</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr917</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22064851</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR116">
<label>116.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ritchie</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dunham</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zeggini</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flicek</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Functional annotation of noncoding sequence variants</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Methods
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>294</fpage>
<lpage>296</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2832</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487584</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>