<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="editorial" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Frontiers in Psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1664-0640</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32346372</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7171716</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00297</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Psychiatry</subject>
<subj-group>
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial: Secondary vs. Idiopathic Autism</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Casanova</surname>
<given-names>Manuel F.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/3604" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Casanova</surname>
<given-names>Emily L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/183744" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frye</surname>
<given-names>Richard Eugene</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/12818" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baeza-Velasco</surname>
<given-names>Carolina</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/527096" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>LaSalle</surname>
<given-names>Janine M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/99968" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hagerman</surname>
<given-names>Randi Jensen</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/415286" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scherer</surname>
<given-names>Stephen W.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/575182" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Natowicz</surname>
<given-names>Marvin R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
<uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/575292" xlink:type="simple"></uri>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Medicine Greenville, University of South Carolina</institution>, <addr-line>Greenville, SC</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Phoenix Children’s Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Phoenix, AZ</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Université Paris Descartes</institution>, <addr-line>Île-de-France</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>University of California, Davis</institution>, <addr-line>Davis, CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Pediatrics, UC Davis School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Sacramento, CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>University of Toronto</institution>, <addr-line>Toronto, ON</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff>
<aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup><institution>Cleveland Clinic</institution>, <addr-line>Cleveland, OH</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="edited-by">
<p>Edited and reviewed by: David Cohen, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, France</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Manuel F. Casanova, <email xlink:href="mailto:m0casa02@louisville.edu" xlink:type="simple">m0casa02@louisville.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn002">
<p>This article was submitted to Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychiatry</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<elocation-id>297</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>25</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2020 Casanova, Casanova, Frye, Baeza-Velasco, LaSalle, Hagerman, Scherer and Natowicz</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Casanova, Casanova, Frye, Baeza-Velasco, LaSalle, Hagerman, Scherer and Natowicz</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-article ext-link-type="uri" id="d35e241" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/8531/secondary-vs-idiopathic-autism">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>Secondary vs. Idiopathic Autism</article-title>
</related-article>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
<kwd>idiopathic autism</kwd>
<kwd>secondary autism</kwd>
<kwd>Fragile X syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>anxiety</kwd>
<kwd>seizures</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="0"></fig-count>
<table-count count="0"></table-count>
<equation-count count="0"></equation-count>
<ref-count count="16"></ref-count>
<page-count count="3"></page-count>
<word-count count="1330"></word-count>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This Research Topic consists of four articles, contributed by 30 authors, each focusing on various aspects of secondary autism spectrum disorder (ASD). The articles in this Research Topic discuss some of the controversies and progress made in how to assess a child with secondary ASD. They discuss the utility of using genetic and metabolic tests, as well as combinations of the same. They also grapple with the relationship of intellectual disability (ID) and other symptoms in patients with secondary ASD.</p>
<p>The diagnostic boundaries of the behavioral phenotype that define ASD are fairly broad due to the large variability that is observed in symptom types, onset, and severity. This variability serves as an index of etiological heterogeneity for a group of complex conditions where multiple genetic/environmental hits provide an additive burden to symptom expression. Within this spectrum of disorders our Research Topic examines a subpopulation of patients where the ASD phenotype occurs and a specific cause can be identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). These cases are often referred to as “secondary” ASD as a way of distinguishing them from “idiopathic” ASD. While there is some variation of the estimates, about 85% of individuals with ASD are termed as having idiopathic ASD with about 15% diagnosed with secondary ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Cases of secondary ASD display significant etiological diversity and, sometimes, more severe behavioral problems than individuals having idiopathic ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Well documented causes of secondary ASD include conditions such as tuberous sclerosis, down syndrome, Fragile X syndrome (FXS), and some congenital infections (e.g., cytomegalovirus) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>).</p>
<p>Differentiating between idiopathic and secondary ASD is essential when drawing conclusions regarding pharmacological and behavioral treatments among published studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Clinical study design benefits from the selection of homogeneous populations, those without prognostically distinct subgroups, as it makes it easier to assess treatment efficacy (<italic>vide infra</italic>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>)]. Indeed, a thorough understanding of the different clinical presentations, natural history and even life expectancies of persons with ASD should go beyond the influence of traditional variables and use relevant classifiers of biomedical and sociocultural differences that may have an impact on the health and wellbeing of the studied subject population.</p>
<p>Genomic scanning is beginning to elucidate the underlying genetic architecture that confers ASD susceptibility. Chromosomal and penetrant gene abnormalities are common, contributing to about 5%–15% of ASD cases in some estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). By way of contrast, <italic>de novo</italic> chromosomal copy number variants, important contributors to lower IQ, and diminished motor skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>), are seen in approximately 5% of persons diagnosed with idiopathic ASD (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00647">Glinton and Elsea</ext-link>). Many additional cases have DNA sequence variants in genes whose pathology and function provide an uncertain contribution to ASD. These genetic modifications are described as variants with unknown significance (VUS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>).</p>
<p>For disorders associated with secondary ASD, there is a substantial increase in the prevalence rate of ASD as compared to the general population. The underlying reason for this association is complex and may include a disruption of brain function caused by the superimposed pathology, the possible linkage between ASD risk genes and those of the secondary condition (e.g., ID), and, for some, the commonality in the expression of seizures and their effects on brain development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00526/full">Thurm et al.</ext-link>). Establishing a diagnosis of ASD in this patient population is complicated by the fact that traits of ASD often exhibit a phenotypic and genetic overlap with symptoms of other disorders. It is therefore unsurprising that affected individuals often live with challenges that may confound behavioral observations (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00526/full">Thurm et al.</ext-link>). Indeed, these patients may commonly present with ID, seizures and/or anxiety in addition to comorbid ASD symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Identification in these cases often depends on clinical suspicion, especially in severe phenotypes, and both metabolic and genome-wide screening (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00647">Glinton and Elsea</ext-link>).</p>
<p>We suggest a concerted effort at developing integrated surveys of clinical, metabolic, and genomic data as a background tool for patient stratification. By establishing a proper diagnosis these tools would aid in understanding underlying pathogenetic mechanisms, in customizing medical/treatment decisions, in offering explanations towards some of the patients’ behaviors and, possibly, in providing knowledge helpful in guiding parents and professionals regarding needed school and community services. This integrated approach complements, when necessary, the recommended general developmental screening proposed by the American Academy of Pediatrics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), keeping in mind that early intervention can and does influence outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>).</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00810">Potter et al.</ext-link> reported a clinical trial of sertraline, a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor, in nonsyndromic ASD. A previous controlled trial of low dose sertraline in children 2 to 6 years old with FXS had demonstrated significant benefit of sertraline compared to placebo in developmental measures on the Mullen Scales of Early Development, especially in the 60% who has ASD in addition to FXS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). However, Potter et al. performed a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study (n=32 sertraline, n=26 controls) in children with ASD without FXS aged 24-72 months that showed no benefit in primary or secondary outcome measures of language development.</p>
<p>In ASD, the heterogeneity observed along a spectrum of clinical presentations and natural histories is a sobering reminder of the difficulty ingrained in making comparisons among different patient populations. It is not surprising that results of studies using populations of syndromic [FXS, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>)] and idiopathic ASD (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00810">Potter et al.</ext-link>) may not reproduce each other. In these cases, large and well characterized study populations are needed in order to perform secondary analyses that could help elucidate differences in severity among the studied populations and better capture individual differences within and between subgroups of autistic individuals. This study concurs with the majority of clinical trials on selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors which show very mixed results and overall suggest that these medications may not be appropriate for children with ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>).</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00647">Glinton and Elsea</ext-link> offer a comprehensive review of metabolomics and the use of targeted/untargeted assays and their possible role in the early screening and diagnosis of secondary ASD caused by inborn errors of metabolism. The review also introduces the reader to the emerging field of nonspecific metabolic disturbances and how they can lead to clues on mechanisms and treatment. Considering the large variety of metabolic disturbances identified in ASD, the authors question the extent to which any biomarker would accurately assess risk or guide individual treatment. The answer to the question may lie in the use of untargeted assays in order to broadly survey the multiple aspects of the metabolism of each individual patient. The use of biomarkers as metabolic measurements to improve ASD diagnosis and identification of underlying causes is a promising research tool in the hands of physicians but requires specialized skills for proper interpretation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>).</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00526">Thurm et al.</ext-link> consider the impact of ID on the diagnosis of ASD. The authors provide a review of the conceptual evolution of autism diagnosis and the different tools used for this purpose. They propose the use of operationalized criteria for making the clinical distinction between ID with and without ASD and provide specific recommendation for testing depending on the degree of ID. The authors consider that the presence of ID in ASD is one of the strongest indicators that an associated condition may be present.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00409">Lovato et al.</ext-link> clarifies the relevance of genetic variants of purported unknown significance (VUS). Some of these variants are genes associated with ASD, but the altered region lacks functional data linking it to pathogenicity. Other VUS are located in genes having few associations with ASD, but may seem relevant to the clinical phenotype. This review summarizes a strategy for obtaining information about VUS by focusing on both clinical phenotyping and a genetic curation process. It is hoped that advanced understanding of these genetic variants may help clarify risk and guide individual treatment options.</p>
<sec id="s1">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p>All authors listed have made a substantial, direct, and intellectual contribution to the work, and approved it for publication.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Conflict of Interest</title>
<p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>To the always helpful Frontiers team whose organizational skills and understanding made this Research Topic possible.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="B1">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faras</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Ateeqi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tidman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source/>Ann Saudi Med (<year>2010</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0256-4947.65261</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20622347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Institute of Health</collab></person-group>
<article-title>About autism</article-title>. National Human Genome Research Institute. Updated <date-in-citation>May, 2019</date-in-citation>
<uri xlink:href="https://www.genome.gov/Genetic-Disorders/Autism" xlink:type="simple">https://www.genome.gov/Genetic-Disorders/Autism</uri>.
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tammimies</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiruvahindrapuram</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lionel</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular diagnostic yield of chromosomal microarray analysis and whole-exome sequencing in children with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source/>JAMA (<year>2015</year>) <volume>314</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>903</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.10078</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26325558</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiznitzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Autism and tuberous sclerosis</article-title>. <source/>J Child Neurol (<year>2004</year>) <volume>19</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>675–9</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/08830738040190090701</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of autism spectrum disorder symptomatology and related behavioural characteristics in individuals with Down syndrome</article-title>. <source/>Autism (<year>2013</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1362361312442790</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22589453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mussey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Villagomez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Raspa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>DSM-5 changes and the prevalence of parent-reported autism spectrum symptoms in Fragile X syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J Autism Dev Disord (<year>2015</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>816–29</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-014-2246-z</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Aripiprazole for the treatment of irritability and aggression in children and adolescents affected by autism spectrum isorders</article-title>. <source/>Expert Rev Neurother (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<page-range>867–74</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14737175.2016.1211007</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genetic architecture in autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source/>Curr Opin Gent Dev (<year>2012</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<page-range>229–37</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2012.03.002</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buja</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Volfovsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Damaging de novo mutations diminish motor skills in children on the autism spectrum</article-title>. <source/>Proc Natl Acad Sci (<year>2018</year>) <volume>115</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>E1859–66</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1715427115</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaaf</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Huda</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Solving the autism puzzle a few pieces at a time</article-title>. <source/>Neuron. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<page-range>806–8</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.05.025</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dy</surname><given-names>ABC</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Autism symptoms in Fragile X syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J Child Neurol (<year>2017</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>903–9</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0883073817712875</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><collab>Council on Children with Disabilities, Section on Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Identification, evaluation, and management of children with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source/>Pediatrics (<year>2019</year>) <volume>145</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <elocation-id>e20193447</elocation-id>.  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2019-3447</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31843864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwaigenbaum</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Choueiri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Granpeesheh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>Early intervention for children with autism spectrum disorder under 3 years of age: recommendations for practice and research</article-title>. <source/>Pediatrics (<year>2015</year>) <volume>136</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<page-range>S60–81</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2014-3667E</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greiss Hess</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaul</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group>
<article-title>A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of low-dose sertraline in young children with Fragile X syndrome</article-title>. <source/>J Dev Behav Pediatr (<year>2016</year>) <volume>37</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>619–28</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DBP.0000000000000334</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brignell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Silove</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) for autism spectrum disorders (ASD)</article-title>. <source/>Cochrane Database Syst Rev (<year>2013</year>) (<issue>8</issue>), <elocation-id>CD004677</elocation-id>.  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD004677.pub3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23959778</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossignol</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Emerging biomarkersin autism spectrum disorder: a systematic review</article-title>. <source/>Ann Transl Med (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>792</fpage>.  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm.2019.11.53</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32042808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>