<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">iScience</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">iScience</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>iScience</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2589-0042</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32450518</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7251951</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2589-0042(20)30339-4</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2020.101154</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101154</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Optic Atrophy 1 Controls Human Neuronal Development by Preventing Aberrant Nuclear DNA Methylation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
<name>
<surname>Caglayan</surname>
<given-names>Safak</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
<name>
<surname>Hashim</surname>
<given-names>Adnan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
<name>
<surname>Cieslar-Pobuda</surname>
<given-names>Artur</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
<name>
<surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>Vidar</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
<name>
<surname>Behringer</surname>
<given-names>Sidney</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
<name>
<surname>Talug</surname>
<given-names>Burcu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
<name>
<surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>Dinh Toi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
<name>
<surname>Pecquet</surname>
<given-names>Christian</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9">
<name>
<surname>Rogne</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10">
<name>
<surname>Brech</surname>
<given-names>Andreas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au11">
<name>
<surname>Brorson</surname>
<given-names>Sverre Henning</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au12">
<name>
<surname>Nagelhus</surname>
<given-names>Erlend Arnulf</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au13">
<name>
<surname>Hannibal</surname>
<given-names>Luciana</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au14">
<name>
<surname>Boschi</surname>
<given-names>Antonella</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au15">
<name>
<surname>Taskén</surname>
<given-names>Kjetil</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au16">
<name>
<surname>Staerk</surname>
<given-names>Judith</given-names>
</name>
<email>judith.staerk@ncmm.uio.no</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">11</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">12</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">∗</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Centre for Molecular Medicine Norway, Nordic EMBL Partnership, University of Oslo and Oslo University Hospital, 0318 Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>GliaLab and Letten Centre, Division of Physiology, Department of Molecular Medicine, Institute of Basic Medical Sciences, University of Oslo, 0317 Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Laboratory of Clinical Biochemistry and Metabolism, Department of General Pediatrics, Adolescent Medicine and Neonatology, Faculty of Medicine, Medical Center, University of Freiburg, Mathildenstraße 1, 79106 Freiburg, Germany</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research Brussels, 1200 Brussels, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Université Catholique de Louvain and de Duve Institute, 1200 Brussels, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Molecular Cell Biology, Institute for Cancer Research, Oslo University Hospital, 0424 Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Pathology, Oslo University Hospital, 0424 Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Cliniques Universitaires Saint-Luc, UCL, 1200 Brussels, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>Department for Cancer Immunology, Institute for Cancer Research, Oslo University Hospital, 0424 Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff10"><label>10</label>Institute of Clinical Medicine, University of Oslo, 0318 Oslo, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff11"><label>11</label>Department of Haematology, Oslo University Hospital, 0424 Oslo, Norway</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author <email>judith.staerk@ncmm.uio.no</email></corresp>
<fn id="fn1">
<label>12</label>
<p id="ntpara0010">Lead Contact</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>11</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<day>26</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>101154</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>29</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>3</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>6</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
<license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="abs0010">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>Optic atrophy 1 (OPA1), a GTPase at the inner mitochondrial membrane involved in regulating mitochondrial fusion, stability, and energy output, is known to be crucial for neural development: <italic>Opa1</italic> heterozygous mice show abnormal brain development, and inactivating mutations in OPA1 are linked to human neurological disorders. Here, we used genetically modified human embryonic and patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells and reveal that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency leads to aberrant nuclear DNA methylation and significantly alters the transcriptional circuitry in neural progenitor cells (NPCs). For instance, expression of the forkhead box G1 transcription factor, which is needed for GABAergic neuronal development, is repressed in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs. Supporting this finding, <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs cannot give rise to GABAergic interneurons, whereas formation of glutamatergic neurons is not affected. Taken together, our data reveal that OPA1 controls nuclear DNA methylation and expression of key transcription factors needed for proper neural cell specification.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015">
<title>Graphical Abstract</title>
<fig id="undfig1" position="anchor">
<graphic xlink:href="fx1"></graphic>
</fig>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020">
<title>Highlights</title>
<p>
<list id="ulist0010" list-type="simple">
<list-item id="u0010">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0010"><italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency impairs formation of DLX1/2-positive GABAergic neurons</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0015">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0015">Reduced OPA1 levels significantly alter the transcriptional circuitry in neural cells</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0020">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0020">Expression of the pioneer factor <italic>FOXG1</italic> is decreased in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> neural progenitor cells</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0025">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0025">Impaired <italic>FOXG1</italic> expression correlates with increased CpG methylation at its promoter</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025">
<p>Neurogenetics; Developmental Neuroscience</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
<title>Subject Areas</title>
<kwd>Neurogenetics</kwd>
<kwd>Developmental Neuroscience</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<p id="misc0010">Published: June 26, 2020</p>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="p0030">Mitochondria are double-membrane-bound subcellular organelles required for numerous cellular functions. In response to metabolic and physiological signals, mitochondria undergo fusion and fission, processes that are catalyzed by conserved GTP-hydrolyzing enzymes and their associated proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Chan, 2012</xref>). Fission of mitochondria is needed for their fragmentation. This is triggered by dynamin 1-like protein (DNM1L), a cytoplasmic protein that is recruited to the mitochondrial surface where it constricts mitochondrial tubules. Fusion of the outer membranes is catalyzed by mitofusin 1 and 2 (MFN1, MFN2), whereas fusion of the mitochondrial inner membranes is catalyzed by the mitochondrial dynamin-like GTPase optic atrophy 1 (OPA1). Due to RNA splicing and protein processing, different isoforms of OPA1 exist. The long isoforms localize to the mitochondrial inner membrane through their transmembrane domains, whereas the short isoforms are expressed as soluble proteins in the mitochondrial intermembrane space. A balance of long and short OPA1 isoforms is required to maintain a healthy mitochondrial network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Del Dotto et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">MacVicar and Langer, 2016</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0035">OPA1 is crucial for tissue development. <italic>Opa1</italic> heterozygous animals are viable, but experience a progressive loss of retinal ganglion cells (RGCs), optic nerve degeneration, and abnormal brain development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Davies et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alavi et al., 2007</xref>), whereas <italic>Opa1</italic>-null mice die early during embryonic development due to growth retardation and morphological abnormalities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Davies et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alavi et al., 2007</xref>). In humans, heterozygous mutations in <italic>OPA1</italic> cause the most common form of autosomal dominant optic atrophy (ADOA), a neuropathy wherein the majority of patients experience impaired vision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Delettre et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Alexander et al., 2000</xref>). Homozygous mutations in <italic>OPA1</italic> result in severe and fatal infantile disorders with neurodevelopmental deficits, multi-organ complications, encephalopathy, cardiomyopathy, and optic atrophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Spiegel et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nasca et al., 2017</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0040">To elucidate the molecular mechanisms by which OPA1 contributes to human neural development, we used <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficient pluripotent stem cell lines and differentiated them into neural progenitor cells (NPCs) and forebrain neurons. Although we were able to generate NPCs and glutamatergic neurons, <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency interfered with GABAergic interneuron formation. We then explored the molecular changes associated with the observed altered neural cell specification and identified a novel function for OPA1.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec2.1">
<title><italic>OPA1</italic> Haploinsufficiency Induces Oxidative Stress in hESCs</title>
<p id="p0045">To study the role of OPA1 during neural development, we used human embryonic stem cells (hESCs) and the CRISPR-Cas9 gene editing technology and deleted a stretch of nucleotides, which induces a frameshift and a premature stop codon in the second exon of the <italic>OPA1</italic> transcript (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S1</xref>A). Because the majority of human disorders linked to <italic>OPA1</italic> are caused by heterozygous mutations, we targeted one allele only. We found a 50% reduction in <italic>OPA1</italic> mRNA transcript levels in heterozygous <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> hESCs, confirming that only one <italic>OPA1</italic> allele was transcribed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>A). The reduction in mRNA expression levels correlated with a 50% reduction in OPA1 protein levels in hESCs, indicating a non-sense-mediated RNA decay in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>B and 1C). Expression levels of OCT4 and NANOG were comparable between <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− and parental hESCs, as shown by immunostaining and immunoblotting (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref>B and S1C). Moreover, hESC proliferation rates, assessed by automated live-cell analysis system, were similar between the two genotypes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S1</xref>D). To further analyze cell cycle dynamics in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs, we performed flow cytometry (fluorescence-activated cell sorting [FACS]) analysis of hESCs labeled with the fluorescent DNA-intercalating dye propidium iodide (PI) and Ki-67 antibody. The ratio of cells in G0/G1, S, and G2/M phases (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref>E and S1F), as well as Ki-67 labeling (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S1</xref>G), were similar between <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESC, indicating that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency does not affect pluripotency or proliferation rates in hESCs. Using transmission electron microscopy (TEM), we then assessed mitochondrial morphology and distribution in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> hESCs. The TEM images showed no obvious differences in mitochondrial morphology between <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> hESCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>A). Next, we measured mitochondrial length in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> hESCs and binned the data into categories of intervals. Although this analysis revealed no significant change, we found a trend of more fragmented mitochondria in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> hESCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>B). We therefore determined the circumference of mitochondria, and found a small, but significant decrease in circumference in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> hESCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>C). In addition, we found a significant increase in the intercristae distance in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> hESCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S2</xref>D and S2E). Mitochondria-targeted GFP (mito-GFP)-transduced hESCs also demonstrated that there was no obvious difference in mitochondrial shape or size among the two genotypes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>F). The mitochondrial DNA content, as analyzed by copy number of the mitochondrial genes NADH-ubiquinone oxidoreductase chain 1 (<italic>MT-ND1</italic>) and <italic>MT-ND4,</italic> was similar between <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>G). Using mitochondrial respiration assays, we found similar ATP production and basal respiration rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>D and 1E) and an increase in maximal respiration in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ hESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>D and 1E). Next, we analyzed whether reactive oxygen species (ROS) were altered in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs. Flow cytometry analysis using the hydrogen peroxide-sensitive ROS indicator CM-H2DCFDA revealed significantly increased ROS levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ hESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>F and 1G). Taken together, our results reveal subtle changes in the mitochondrial morphology and increased levels of ROS in <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficient hESCs.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>OPA1</italic> Haploinsufficiency Induces Oxidative Stress in hESCs</p><p>(A) <italic>OPA1</italic> mRNA expression levels in hESCs determined by qRT-PCR analysis.</p><p>(B) Representative immunoblotting images showing OPA1 protein levels in hESCs, week 3 NPCs, and neurons. Beta-actin was used as loading control.</p><p>(C) Densitometric analysis of immunoblots in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− cells. Mean ± SEM, N = 4 independent experiments.</p><p>(D) Oxygen consumption rate changes under mitochondrial stress in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs. Oligomycin, FCCP, antimycin, and rotenone were sequentially applied. Mean ± SEM, N = 2 independent experiments.</p><p>(E) Basal respiration rates, maximum respiration rates, and ATP production calculated in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs. Mean ± SEM, N = 2 independent experiments were performed and N ≥ 9 technical replicates were analyzed for each genotype. Student's t test was used to analyze the difference between two groups. n.s. not significant. ∗p &lt; 0.05.</p><p>(F) Representative flow cytometry analysis of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs labeled with the hydrogen peroxide-sensitive oxidative stress indicator CM-H2DCFDA. Unlabeled hESCs (−) were used as negative control. hESCs that were incubated with 0.5 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> were used as positive control.</p><p>(G) Quantification of flow cytometry measurements in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs. Arithmetic mean values were normalized to the values of labeled <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> hESCs.</p><p>Mean ± SEM, N ≥ 3 independent experiments and N = 2 technical replicates. Student's t test was used to analyze difference between two groups. n.s. not significant. ∗∗p &lt; 0.01, ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.2">
<title><italic>OPA1</italic> Expression Is Upregulated during Neural Differentiation</title>
<p id="p0050">Next, we investigated how <italic>OPA1</italic> heterozygosity affects neural differentiation. Using the dual SMAD inhibition protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chambers et al., 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Shi et al., 2012</xref>), hESCs were differentiated into neuroepithelial progenitors and NPCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>A). On day 11 of the differentiation protocol, neural commitment was evident by morphological transformation and expression of the neural stem cell marker PAX6 (day 11 NPCs, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>B). After passaging and further differentiation, PAX6-positive NPCs reorganized themselves into neural rosette structures (week 3 NPCs, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>C) before being differentiated into beta-tubulin III-positive neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>D). To assess the neurogenic ability of hESCs, we first compared rosette formation of NPCs. Immunostainings showed that <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs formed tight junction protein Zonula-occludens-1 (ZO-1)-positive rosette structures with comparable efficiency as <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>E). As the self-organization of neural rosettes is reminiscent of neural tube formation from neuroepithelium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Deglincerti et al., 2016</xref>), these results reveal that early neural development is not affected by <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency.</p>
<p id="p0055">Quantification of <italic>OPA1</italic> transcript levels by qRT-PCR showed a 25% increase of total <italic>OPA1</italic> mRNA levels during neuronal differentiation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>A). <italic>OPA1</italic> is alternatively spliced in different tissues. Of these splice variants, <italic>OPA1</italic> transcript variant 1 (NM_015560), which lacks exons 4b and 5b (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S1</xref>A), is the most abundantly expressed isoform in the mouse brain and retina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Delettre et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Akepati et al., 2008</xref>). In line with this, we found that <italic>OPA1</italic> isoform 1 levels markedly increased in our neuronal cultures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>B). Moreover, we found that isoform 1 became the predominant splice form during neural differentiation. In hESCs, the ratio of transcript variant 1 to total <italic>OPA1</italic> mRNA levels was approximately 1:1, whereas in neurons the majority of <italic>OPA1</italic> transcripts were isoform 1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>C). Immunoblotting experiments showed a 25% and 2-fold increase of OPA1 protein in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs and neurons when compared with hESCs, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>B, 1C, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S4</xref>D).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.3">
<title><italic>OPA1</italic> Heterozygous NPCs Fail to Generate DLX1/2+ Neurons</title>
<p id="p0060">To investigate the role of OPA1 during differentiation and neuronal function further, we analyzed neurons derived from <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Immunostaining experiments showed that pan-neuronal marker beta-tubulin III-positive neurons could be efficiently generated from both genotypes, indicating that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency is not affecting overall neuronal development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>A). Patch-clamp experiments demonstrated that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency did not interfere with the ability of neurons to fire action potentials in response to current stimuli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>B). To determine neuronal lineage specification, we selected T-box brain 1 (<italic>TBR1</italic>) as a marker for glutamatergic neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hevner et al., 2001</xref>), and <italic>DLX1</italic> and <italic>DLX2</italic> as they are important for specification of RGCs and GABAergic neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Anderson et al., 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Letinic et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">de Melo et al., 2005</xref>). As expected, <italic>TBR1</italic>, <italic>DLX1,</italic> and <italic>DLX2</italic> mRNA expression levels increased during the neuronal differentiation of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ hESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>C–2E), demonstrating that our neuronal cultures included cell types representing forebrain development. During neuronal differentiation of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs, we found that <italic>TBR1</italic> was expressed at similar levels as in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>C). However, <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− cells notably failed to induce mRNA expression of <italic>DLX1</italic> and <italic>DLX2</italic> during neuronal maturation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>D and 2E). Using immunostaining, we showed that there were significantly less DLX2 immunoreactive cells in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neuronal cultures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>F and 2G). The absence of DLX2 protein in lysates of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− but not <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ neurons was further confirmed using immunoblotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>H). Neurons derived from both genotypes expressed comparable levels of beta-tubulin III protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>H).<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><italic>OPA1</italic> Heterozygous NPCs Fail to Generate DLX1/2+ Neurons</p><p>(A) Beta-tubulin III (TUJ1) staining of neurons. Scale bar, 100 μm.</p><p>(B) Representative traces of patch-clamped neurons. Action potentials were elicited in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> neurons upon depolarizing current injection. Black bar indicates time of depolarizing current injection.</p><p>(C–E) (C) <italic>TBR1</italic>, (D) <italic>DLX1</italic>, and (E) <italic>DLX2</italic> mRNA levels determined by qRT-PCR analyses in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs, NPCs, and neurons. Mean ± SEM, N ≥ 3 independent experiments for each genotype and cell type.</p><p>(F) Immunostaining images of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. DAPI was used to stain nuclei. Scale bar, 100 μm.</p><p>(G) Quantification of DLX2+ neurons. Mean ± SEM, N = 3 independent experiments.</p><p>(H) Immunoblotting showing OPA1, DNM1L, GAD1/GAD67, DLX2, and beta-tubulin III protein expression in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs and neurons. Beta-actin was used as loading control.</p><p>Student's t test was used to analyze difference between two groups. n.s. not significant. ∗p &lt; 0.05, ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.4">
<title><italic>OPA1</italic> Haploinsufficient NPCs Do Not Give Rise to GABAergic Interneurons</title>
<p id="p0065">DLX1 and DLX2 are transcription factors (TFs) important for GABAergic interneuron and RGC development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Letinic et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Anderson et al., 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">de Melo et al., 2005</xref>). As their downregulation indicated an altered neuronal function and differentiation potential when <italic>OPA1</italic> was reduced, we performed RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) in 7-week-old neurons. We found several genes encoding for TFs with known function in neurogenesis differentially regulated in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Table S1</xref>). For instance, <italic>FOXG1</italic>, <italic>DLX1</italic>, <italic>DLX2</italic>, <italic>DLX5</italic>, and <italic>DLX6</italic> were genes highly downregulated in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>A; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Table S1</xref>). Moreover, expression of <italic>SFRP1</italic> and <italic>SEMA5A</italic>, which are known to control RGC development and axonal growth, as well as <italic>CTIP2/BCL11B</italic> and <italic>NEUROD6,</italic> which are TFs that are highly expressed in the developing brain and retinal cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cherry et al., 2011</xref>), were also significantly downregulated. Other genes downregulated included <italic>SLITRK2, SLITRK4,</italic> and <italic>SLITRK6</italic>, which are plasma membrane proteins expressed in the retina, and several GABA receptor subunits (<italic>GABRA2</italic>, <italic>GABRA4</italic>, <italic>GABRB1</italic>, and <italic>GABRG1</italic>). Among the upregulated genes in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons we found <italic>NR2F1</italic>, <italic>NR2F2,</italic> and <italic>NEUROD4,</italic> which are TFs known to regulate cell fate specification in the retina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>A).<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><italic>OPA1</italic> Haploinsufficient NPCs Do Not Give Rise to GABAergic Interneurons</p><p>(A) Log<sub>2</sub> fold-change and expression heatmaps of selected down- (green) and up- (red) regulated genes in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neurons. FC = fold-change. Expression intensities are displayed from blue (low expression) to yellow (high expression).</p><p>(B) Immunoblotting showing OPA1, DNM1L, TBR1, and GAD1/GAD67 protein expression in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs and neurons. OCT4 was used as pluripotency marker; beta-actin was used as loading control.</p><p>(C) Densitometric analysis of GAD1 protein levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. Mean ± SEM, N = 2 independent experiments.</p><p>(D) Immunoblotting showing GAD2/GAD65 and beta-tubulin III protein expression in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs and neurons.</p><p>(E) Densitometric analysis of GAD2 protein levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. Mean ± SEM, N = 2 independent experiments.</p><p>Student's t test was used to analyze difference between two groups. ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S4</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Table S1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0070">The absence of DLX1/2 expression in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons prompted us to further investigate GABAergic neuronal markers. Glutamate decarboxylase 1 (GAD1/GAD67) and 2 (GAD2/GAD65), which catalyze the production of GABA from L-glutamic acid, were expressed in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neurons, whereas they were absent or markedly reduced in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref>B–3E and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S4</xref>E). TBR1 and beta-tubulin III were expressed at comparable levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref>B and 3D). Overall, our transcriptional analysis demonstrates that reduced OPA1 protein levels alter the expression of genes that are important for GABAergic interneuron formation and retinal development.</p>
<p id="p0075">We imaged mito-GFP-transduced neurons to assess mitochondrial morphology. Confocal microscopy analysis demonstrated that mitochondrial morphology and distribution were similar in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>A). Quantification of mitochondrial length and binning of measurements into categories of intervals showed no evident differences in mitochondrial distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>B and 4C). Next, we analyzed energy metabolism in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ neuronal cultures using mitochondrial respiration assays. Our data revealed that neurons exhibited an increased mitochondrial respiration compared with hESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>D). However, basal respiration, maximal respiration, and ATP production rates were similar in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> and <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>E), suggesting that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency does not affect mitochondrial respiration in neurons. We then investigated oxidative stress levels in neuronal cultures. Flow cytometry analysis showed significantly increased ROS levels in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>F and 4G). FACS analysis of neurons labeled with the early apoptosis indicator Annexin V and late apoptosis indicator PI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>H) demonstrated no differences in apoptosis in neuronal culture conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>I and 4J). Importantly, when neurons were exposed to stress by pre-treatment with hydrogen peroxide we observed significantly more Annexin V+ cells in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>I and 4J).<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><italic>OPA1</italic> Haploinsufficiency Induces Oxidative Stress and Apoptosis in Neurons</p><p>(A) Confocal microscopic images of mito-GFP-transduced <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. ∗ denotes nucleus. Scale bar, 10 μm.</p><p>(B) Quantification of mitochondria length in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. N = 680 mitochondria for <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and N = 645 mitochondria for <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− were measured.</p><p>(C) Mitochondrial length was measured and binned into categories of length intervals.</p><p>(D) Oxygen consumption rate changes under mitochondrial stress in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. Oligomycin, FCCP, antimycin, and rotenone were sequentially applied. Mean ± SEM, N = 2 independent experiments.</p><p>(E) Basal respiration rates, maximum respiration rates, and ATP production calculated in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. Mean ± SEM, N = 2 independent experiments were performed and N ≥ 40 technical replicates were analyzed for each genotype.</p><p>(F) Representative flow cytometry analysis of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons labeled with the hydrogen peroxide-sensitive oxidative stress indicator CM-H2DCFDA. Unlabeled neurons (−) were used as negative control. Neurons that were incubated with 0.5 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> were used as positive control.</p><p>(G) Quantification of flow cytometry measurements in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons. Arithmetic mean values were normalized to the values of labeled <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> neurons. Mean ± SEM, N ≥ 3 independent experiments and N = 2 technical replicates.</p><p>(H) Representative flow cytometry analysis of live <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− neurons labeled with the early apoptosis indicator annexin V and late-apoptosis indicator propidium iodide (PI). Neurons were incubated with 50 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> to assess sensitivity to apoptotic stimuli.</p><p>(I) Quantification of early apoptotic annexin V+/PI<italic>−</italic> neurons. Percentage of labeled cells in total gated cells is shown.</p><p>(J) Quantification of late-apoptotic Annexin V+/PI+ neurons. Percentage of labeled cells in total gated cells is shown.</p><p>Mean ± SEM, N = 4 independent experiments and N = 2 technical replicates. Student's t test was used to analyze difference between two groups. n.s. not significant. ∗p &lt; 0.05, ∗∗∗ p &lt; 0.001. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.5">
<title><italic>OPA1</italic> Heterozygous NPCs Exhibit a Significantly Altered Transcriptional Signature</title>
<p id="p0080">Next, we addressed whether the impaired formation of DLX1/2+ neurons in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− cultures could be explained by an altered transcriptional circuitry at the NPC level. Successful formation of day 11 NPCs was verified by the loss of the pluripotency markers OCT4 and NANOG, and the gain of the neural stem cell marker PAX6 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>A). We then performed RNA-seq analysis in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs after 11 days and 3 weeks of differentiation to elucidate potential transcriptional changes associated with <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency. Principal-component analysis was used to assess and visualize the neural differentiation trajectory (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>A). When we analyzed differentially expressed genes (DEGs) at day 11 <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> versus <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs, we found <italic>FOXG1</italic> already highly downregulated at this early NPC stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S2</xref>). Another gene we found highly downregulated encodes for TAF9B (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S2</xref>), a protein that is part of the neuronal core promoter complex and known to regulate the induction of specific neuronal genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Herrera et al., 2014</xref>). Moreover, we found <italic>SLITRK2</italic>, a transmembrane protein expressed in proliferative neuroblastic layer of the retina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Beaubien and Cloutier, 2009</xref>), to be significantly downregulated in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S2</xref>). In addition, <italic>GABRA2</italic>, the gene coding for GABRA receptor alpha 2; <italic>ATP10D</italic>, a putative phospholipid transporting ATPase; and several neural cell adhesion genes, including <italic>NCAM2</italic>, <italic>PCDHGA3</italic>, and <italic>PCDHGA6,</italic> were also downregulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S2</xref>). Significantly upregulated genes in day 11 <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− versus <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs included genes coding for neural guidance proteins, such as <italic>SEMA3E</italic>, <italic>SLIT3</italic>, Ephrin type-A receptor 1 (<italic>EPHA1</italic>), and its ligand ephrin A1 (<italic>EFNA1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S2</xref>).<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><italic>OPA1</italic> Haploinsufficiency Significantly Alters the Transcriptional Circuitry in NPCs</p><p>(A) Principal-component analysis of hESCs, day 11 and week 3 NPCs, and neurons.</p><p>(B) Log<sub>2</sub> fold-change and expression heatmaps of selected down- (green) and up- (red) regulated genes in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> day 11 NPCs. FC = fold-change. Expression intensities are displayed from blue (low expression) to yellow (high expression).</p><p>(C and D) (C) <italic>PAX6</italic> and (D) <italic>FOXG1</italic> mRNA levels in day 11 and week 3 NPCs, normalized to transcript levels in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> hESCs.</p><p>(E) Immunoblotting showing OPA1, FOXG1, and PAX6 protein expression in NPCs. Beta-actin was used as loading control. N = 3 independent experiments.</p><p>(F) <italic>ATP10D</italic>, <italic>GABRA2</italic>, <italic>SLITRK2</italic>, <italic>TAF9B,</italic> and <italic>ZNF280D</italic> mRNA expression levels in day 11 NPCs. mRNA expression levels were normalized to transcript levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ NPCs.</p><p>(G) <italic>GRHL2</italic>, <italic>GRHL3</italic>, <italic>SIX6</italic>, <italic>VAX1,</italic> and <italic>VSX2</italic> mRNA expression levels in day 11 NPCs. mRNA expression levels were normalized to transcript levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ NPCs.</p><p>Mean ± SEM, N ≥ 4 independent samples for each genotype and cell type. Student's t test was used to analyze the differences between two groups. n.s. not significant. ∗p &lt; 0.05, ∗∗p &lt; 0.01, ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S5</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S6</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Tables S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">S3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0085">DEG analysis of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs in week 3 revealed that <italic>FOXG1</italic>, <italic>ATP10D</italic>, <italic>GABRA2</italic>, <italic>SLITRK2, ZNF280D,</italic> and <italic>TAF9B</italic> also remained highly downregulated at this later stage of differentiation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">Table S3</xref>). In addition, several genes encoding for TFs involved in primary neurulation, forebrain development, and retinal development were upregulated in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs. These included <italic>SIX6</italic>, <italic>GRHL2</italic>, <italic>GRHL3</italic>, <italic>VAX1,</italic> and <italic>VSX</italic><italic>2</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">Table S3</xref>). Overall, our RNA-seq analyses identified significant alterations in the transcriptional circuitry of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figures 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S5</xref>B, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Tables S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">S3</xref>), which can explain the observed altered neuronal cell fate specification.</p>
<p id="p0090">We then assessed the expression levels of selected genes in more detail. qRT-PCR analysis at three different time points showed continuous increase of <italic>PAX6</italic> mRNA expression levels during NPC derivation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>C). <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs also showed significant upregulation of <italic>FOXG1,</italic> starting 11 days after differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>D), a finding in line with its previously described critical role in early brain development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Xuan et al., 1995</xref>). <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs expressed similar <italic>PAX6</italic> mRNA levels as <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>C), whereas <italic>FOXG1</italic> transcription was absent in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− cells during all stages of NPC differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>D). This was also true at the protein level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>E). In addition, we used qRT-PCR analyses to confirm the downregulation of <italic>ATP10</italic>, <italic>GABRA2</italic>, <italic>SLITRK2</italic>, <italic>TAF9B,</italic> and <italic>ZNF280D</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>F) and upregulation of <italic>GRHL2</italic>, <italic>GRHL3</italic>, <italic>SIX6</italic>, <italic>VAX1,</italic> and <italic>VSX2</italic> mRNA expression in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>G). Using a second, independently derived <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESC clone #63, we confirmed reduced OPA1 protein (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S6</xref>A) and <italic>OPA1</italic> mRNA expression levels in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> hESC and NPCs, respectively. Moreover, <italic>PAX6</italic> mRNA expression was comparable between genotypes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S6</xref>B), whereas <italic>FOXG1</italic> and <italic>TAF9B</italic> mRNA expression levels were also markedly reduced in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> #63 NPCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S6</xref>B).</p>
<p id="p0095">To investigate whether altered transcriptional regulation affects proliferation or cell survival of <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs, we performed FACS analysis of NPCs labeled with PI. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S5</xref>C and S5D showed no differences in cell cycle dynamics in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Similarly, Ki-67 expression was also comparable between the two genotypes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>E). Next, we analyzed the levels of apoptosis in NPCs under normal conditions and upon stimulation with hydrogen peroxide (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>F). We found no significant difference in apoptosis between <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>G), whereas pre-treatment of NPCs with hydrogen peroxide increased Annexin V+/PI+ late apoptotic cells in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>H), supporting our results that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency increases the sensitivity of cells to apoptotic stimuli. Collectively, our data demonstrate that OPA1 is essential for proper transcriptional regulation in NPCs, and that <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs exhibit a developmental defect that causes impaired neural subtype specification.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.6">
<title>OPA1 Protects against Aberrant DNA Methylation</title>
<p id="p0100">Recently, it has been shown that metabolic stress and accumulation of mitochondria affect hematopoietic stem cell fate decisions through altered nuclear DNA methylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ho et al., 2017</xref>). Our transcriptome analyses showed that several genes important for NPC differentiation, GABAergic interneuron formation, and retinal development such as the pioneer transcription factor <italic>FOXG1</italic> were strongly downregulated in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs. To address whether this downregulation was caused by epigenetic alterations, we analyzed the CpG content in annotated sequences and found CpG-enriched promoters in genes encoding <italic>FOXG1</italic>, <italic>ATP10D</italic>, <italic>TAF9B</italic>, <italic>SLITRK2</italic>, <italic>GABRA2</italic>, and <italic>ZNF280D</italic>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>A depicts the location and CpG-enriched regions in the promoter and 5′ UTR of <italic>FOXG1</italic>. Genomic DNA was isolated from NPCs, bisulfite treated, and the <italic>FOXG1</italic> 5′UTR region was sequenced. We found that all CpG bases within this region were methylated in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− cells, whereas this was not the case in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>B). This result demonstrates that DNA hypermethylation was the reason for the observed repression of <italic>FOXG1</italic> transcription. The amplification of the <italic>FOXG1</italic> promoter CpG island was not possible due to the long CpG stretches, which prevented optimal primer design (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>A). Bisulfite sequencing of the <italic>ATP10D</italic> locus also revealed a high content of methylated promoter CpG in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− but not in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref>C and 6D), further confirming that DNA methylation patterns were altered in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Taken together, our results suggest that OPA1 is necessary for NPC transcriptional regulation by preventing aberrant methylation.<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>OPA1 Protects against Aberrant DNA Methylation</p><p>(A) Location and sequence of CpG-enriched regions in the <italic>FOXG1</italic> gene promoter and 5′ UTR. ATG is indicated as translation start codon. Numbers denote sequences upstream (−) or downstream (+) of the start codon. The yellow box indicates the 5′ UTR, and blue lines represent CpG enriched regions. CpGs are marked in red.</p><p>(B) Bisulfite sequencing of the <italic>FOXG1</italic> 5′UTR in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Empty circles represent unmodified cytosines, and filled circles represent methylated cytosines.</p><p>(C) Location and sequence of CpG-enriched regions in the <italic>ATP10D</italic> gene promoter and 5′ UTR. ATG is indicated as translation start codon, and numbers denote sequences upstream (−) or downstream (+) of the start codon. Yellow box indicates the 5′ UTR flanked by a 20-kb intron, and blue lines represent CpG-enriched regions. CpGs are marked in red.</p><p>(D) Bisulfite sequencing of the <italic>ATP10D</italic> gene promoter in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Empty circles represent unmodified CpG bases, and filled circles represent methylated cytosines.</p><p>(E) <italic>FOXG1</italic> mRNA levels in day 11 <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs treated with different concentrations of DNMT inhibitor RG108. Mean ± SEM, N = 4 independent experiments with N = 2 technical replicates for each condition. mRNA expression levels were normalized to transcript levels in untreated <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ NPCs.</p><p>(F) Succinate and alpha-ketoglutarate levels measured in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs and day 11 NPCs measured by mass spectrometry analysis. Mean ± SEM, N ≥ 3 independent samples for each genotype and cell type.</p><p>(G) Oxygen consumption rate changes under mitochondrial stress in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Oligomycin, FCCP, antimycin, and rotenone were sequentially applied. Mean ± SEM, N = 3 independent experiments.</p><p>(H) Basal respiration rates, maximum respiration rates, and ATP production in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Mean ± SEM, N = 3 independent experiments were performed and N ≥ 40 technical replicates were analyzed for each genotype.</p><p>(I) Representative flow cytometry analysis of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs labeled with the hydrogen peroxide-sensitive oxidative stress indicator CM-H2DCFDA. Unlabeled NPCs (−) were used as negative control. NPCs that were incubated with 0.5 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> were used as positive control.</p><p>(J) Quantification of flow cytometry measurements in <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Arithmetic mean values were normalized to the values of labeled <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs. Mean ± SEM, N ≥ 4 independent experiments and N = 2 technical replicates.</p><p>(K) <italic>CAT</italic> mRNA expression levels in day 11 <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. mRNA expression levels were normalized to transcript levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ NPCs.</p><p>Mean ± SEM, N ≥ 3 independent samples were assessed for each genotype. Student's t test was used to analyze the difference between two groups. n.s. not significant. ∗p &lt; 0.05, ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S6</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S7</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0105">Next, we tested whether inhibition of DNA methylation can restore the transcriptional silencing in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs. Strikingly, incubation of cells with the DNA methyltransferase (DNMT) inhibitor RG108 during neural differentiation resulted in a partial rescue of <italic>FOXG1</italic> expression in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs, demonstrating that the transcriptional silencing caused by <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency could be rescued by inhibiting DNMTs and preventing DNA methylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>E). To determine whether DNA methylation and hydroxymethylation levels were affected on a global level in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs, we used mass spectrometry-based quantification and found similar total methylation (5me(dC)) and hydroxymethylation (5hm(dC)) levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S7</xref>A). Moreover, immunoblotting for DNMT3A and DNMT3B proteins showed similar expression levels between different genotypes, suggesting that reduced OPA1 levels lead to loci-specific rather than global DNA methylation changes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S7</xref>B).</p>
<p id="p0110">To further explore the potential cause for the observed loci-specific changes in DNA methylation, we analyzed the concentration of the small metabolites S-adenosylmethionine (SAM) and S-adenosylhomocysteine (SAH), which serve as substrates for DNMTs. Using mass spectrometry analysis we demonstrate that the overall SAM/SAH ratio in NPCs of both <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− and <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ genotypes was significantly higher than in hESCs, indicating an overall higher methylation capacity in NPCs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S7</xref>C). However, the overall SAM/SAH ratio was not altered when OPA1 was reduced (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S7</xref>C). Next, we quantified succinate and alpha-ketoglutarate levels in hESCs and NPCs. Again, there were no significant changes in succinate and alpha-ketoglutarate levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− versus <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>F), indicating that altered availability of these small metabolites is likely not the reason for the observed changes in DNA methylation.</p>
<p id="p0115">When analyzing the mitochondrial energy metabolism in NPCs, we found a small but significant increase in basal respiration and ATP production levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− compared with <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref>G and 6H). In addition, flow cytometry analysis showed significantly increased ROS levels in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref>I and 6J), further confirming our results in hESC and neurons. In line with the observed increased oxidative stress level in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs, we found catalase (<italic>CAT</italic>) and <italic>FOXC1</italic> mRNA expression levels significantly upregulated in day 11 <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Table S2</xref>). Catalase is a peroxisomal enzyme protecting cells against oxidative stress, and FOXC1 is a stress-responsive TF that provides resistance to oxidative stress in the eye (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Mirzayans et al., 2007</xref>). The upregulation of <italic>CAT</italic> expression was confirmed by qRT-PCR in NPCs derived from two independent <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref>K and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">S6</xref>B).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.7">
<title>Patient-Derived iPSC Harboring a Pathogenic <italic>OPA1</italic> Mutation Exhibit Increased ROS Levels and Downregulation of <italic>FOXG1</italic></title>
<p id="p0120">Heterozygous mutations in OPA1 are a common cause of ADOA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Delettre et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Alexander et al., 2000</xref>). To ensure that the changes detected in our genetically engineered hESCs were not caused by off-target effects by CRISPR-Cas9, we generated induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) derived from two male donors who carry the inactivating <italic>OPA1</italic> c.2873_2876delTTAG mutation. First, we assessed <italic>OPA1</italic> mRNA expression and found that mRNA expression levels were reduced by 35%–40% compared with <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>A). Next, we found that <italic>PAX6</italic> mRNA expression levels were similar between patient iPSC- and hESC-derived NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>B). Moreover, <italic>FOXG1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>C) and <italic>CAT</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>D) mRNA expression levels were down- and upregulated in patient iPSC-derived NPCs, respectively. Next, we used the ROS indicator CM-H2DCFDA and further demonstrated that ROS levels were markedly increased in patient-derived iPSCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figures 7</xref>E and 7F). Taken together, these results indicate that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency is accompanied by aberrant nuclear DNA methylation and changed transcriptional circuitry.<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Patient-Derived iPSCs Harboring a Pathogenic <italic>OPA1</italic> Mutation Exhibit Increased ROS Levels and Downregulation of <italic>FOXG1</italic></p><p>(A–D) (A) <italic>OPA1</italic> mRNA, (B) <italic>PAX6</italic>, (C) <italic>FOXG1,</italic> and (D) <italic>CAT</italic> mRNA expression levels in day 11 NPCs differentiated from iPSC lines derived from two donors diagnosed with ADOA.</p><p>(E) Representative flow cytometry analysis of <italic>OPA1</italic>+/+ hESCs, iPSC #1, and iPSC #2 labeled with the oxidative stress indicator CM-H2DCFDA. Unlabeled hESCs (−) were used as negative control. hESCs and iPSCs that were incubated with 0.5 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> were used as positive control.</p><p>(F) Quantification of flow cytometry measurements in iPSC #1 and iPSC #2. Arithmetic mean values were normalized to the values of labeled <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> hESCs.</p><p>Mean ± SEM, N = 3 independent experiments and N = 2 technical replicates. Student's t test was used to analyze difference between two groups. n.s. not significant. ∗p &lt; 0.05, ∗∗p &lt; 0.01, ∗∗∗p &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="p0125">Our study shows for the first time that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency correlates with aberrant nuclear DNA methylation patterns as well as a significantly altered transcriptional circuitry and differentiation potential of NPCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>).<fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Schematics Illustrating the Metabolic and Epigenetic Changes in <italic>OPA1</italic> Haploinsufficient Cells, Which May Contribute to Altered Neuronal Differentiation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr8"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0130">The role of OPA1 during physiologic and pathologic neural development remains incompletely understood. We observed a severe loss of DLX1/DLX2-positive neurons when OPA1 protein levels were reduced by 50%. Studies using mouse models have previously shown that Dlx1 and Dlx2 are expressed in the developing retinal neuroepithelium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Eisenstat et al., 1999</xref>) and are needed for the terminal differentiation of late-born RGCs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">de Melo et al., 2005</xref>). Moreover, <italic>Dlx1</italic>/<italic>Dlx2</italic> double-null mice exhibit up to 30% reduced numbers of RGCs, whereas formation of other retinal neuronal cell types is not affected. In addition to Dlx1/2, loss of <italic>Sfrp1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Esteve et al., 2003</xref>) and forced expression of NeuroD factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cherry et al., 2011</xref>) are known to dysregulate retinal cell diversity in mice and chicken. Strikingly, we find impaired expression of DLX1/2 and SFRP1 as well as an upregulation of NEUROD4 when OPA1 levels are reduced, which may explain the loss of RGCs observed in patients with ADOA.</p>
<p id="p0135">Our transcriptome analysis in NPCs substantiates the relevance of balanced OPA1 levels for proper neural cell homeostasis. One TF that we find consistently repressed in our study is the pioneer factor <italic>FOXG1,</italic> which is predominantly expressed in the developing neuroepithelium, retina, and optic chiasm. A previous study found that FOXG1 is crucial for GABAergic neuronal formation and retinal development because <italic>Foxg1</italic>−/− mice exhibit eye abnormalities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Xuan et al., 1995</xref>). Importantly, <italic>Foxg1−/−</italic> telencephalic progenitors fail to generate Dlx1-and Dlx2-positive neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Xuan et al., 1995</xref>). Other evidence that links FOXG1 to the generation of DLX1/2+ neurons stems from a recent report demonstrating that <italic>FOXG1</italic> upregulation is responsible for the overproduction of GABAergic neurons in brain organoids derived from iPSCs obtained from patients with autism spectrum disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Mariani et al., 2015</xref>). In addition, studies in mice and chicken showed that loss of <italic>Foxg1</italic> expression results in RGC axonal misprojection and pathfinding defects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Yuasa et al., 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Pratt et al., 2004</xref>). Our gene expression analyses in hESC-derived NPCs and neurons also suggest that FOXG1 is a direct regulator of human GABAergic neuronal formation and retinal development.</p>
<p id="p0140">Recently, iPSCs derived from patients carrying heterozygous mutations in <italic>OPA1</italic> and having an inherited form of Parkinson disease (PD) were generated and used to investigate dopaminergic neuronal development. The authors found fragmented mitochondria, a decrease in respiration, and a decrease in neuronal viability, as well as an increase in ROS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Iannielli et al., 2018</xref>). Although we also observe an increase in ROS and sensitivity to apoptotic stimuli, we only find subtle changes in mitochondrial morphology including increased intercristae distance, reduced circumference, and a trend to more fragmented mitochondria in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> hESCs. Overall, the phenotype in PD patient-derived iPSCs seems more severe than the one observed in <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficient hESCs and ADOA patient-derived iPSCs. It is possible that this is because PD is a more complex disease with potential additional epigenetic and genetic changes in contrast to familial optic atrophy with a single-gene mutation. Other studies also show significant mitochondrial fragmentation in mouse cerebellar granule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jahani-Asl et al., 2011</xref>) and HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Arnoult et al., 2005</xref>). In these studies OPA1 expression was almost completely abolished, whereas in our cells 50% OPA1 proteins remain, which might explain the mild changes in mitochondrial morphology in our cells. In line with this, a recent study using <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficient iPSCs derived from patients with syndromic parkinsonism also shows only subtle changes in the mitochondrial ultrastructure in iPSC-derived dopaminergic neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jonikas et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0145">A fascinating question is how <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency impacts on nuclear DNA methylation at specific sites, such as the <italic>FOXG1</italic> and <italic>ATP10D</italic> promoters. Epigenetic pathways and transcriptional regulation are influenced by non-protein-coding RNA molecules. For instance, the murine long non-coding RNA Kcnq1ot1 recruits the DNA methyltransferase Dnmt1 to CpG islands of imprinted genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Mohammad et al., 2010</xref>), and the natural antisense transcript AS1DHRS4 controls localization of DNMTs to the promoter regions of transcripts DHRS4L1 and DHRS4L2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Li et al., 2012</xref>). Given that the DNA methylation changes we observe in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs are loci specific, it is possible that expression and availability of non-coding RNAs that regulate DNA methylation is affected in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> NPCs.</p>
<p id="p0150">Enzymes catalyzing epigenetic changes require specific metabolites as sources of acetyl or methyl groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Katada et al., 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lu and Thompson, 2012</xref>). Small metabolites such as SAM, SAH, and alpha-ketoglutarate establish a link between mitochondrial metabolism and epigenetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Matilainen et al., 2017</xref>). We find similar SAM/SAH and succinate/alpha-ketoglutarate levels in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> and <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> cells, suggesting that the observed changes in DNA methylation are not caused by alterations of these small metabolites. Previously, it has been shown that oxidative stress causes aberrant DNA methylation and transcriptional silencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">O'Hagan et al., 2011</xref>). The authors reveal that DNMT1 is targeted to damaged chromatin, forming a complex with DNMT3B and polycomb repressive complex 4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">O'Hagan et al., 2011</xref>), and show that hydrogen peroxide treatment causes a relocalization of these proteins to promoter CpG islands. Importantly, we find that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency results in increased oxidative stress and ROS accumulation in <italic>OPA1</italic>+/− hESCs and ADOA patient-derived iPSCs. It is well possible that altered ROS levels play a role in the DNA methylation changes we described. Supporting this notion, mitochondrial dysfunction and increased ROS levels have recently been described to cause specific promoter hypermethylation and decreased expression of microRNA-663 in cancer cell lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Carden et al., 2017</xref>). Exogenous and endogenous ROS are also known to affect neural stem cell renewal and proliferation. For instance, Le Belle et al. show that brain-derived neural progenitors maintain a high ROS status and are responsive to ROS stimulation leading to posttranslational oxidative inactivation of PTEN, and activation of PI3K/Akt signaling pathway, which is required for NPC self-renewal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Le Belle et al., 2011</xref>). Another study by Chui et al. demonstrated that selective removal of histone-lysine N-methyltransferase <italic>PRDM16</italic> in NPCs leads to abnormal neuronal composition and organization in the mouse brain by inducing excessive ROS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Chui et al., 2020</xref>). Our results together with these studies suggest that activation of specific pathways by ROS signaling is context dependent and may influence various pathways during cell fate specification.</p>
<p id="p0155">In conclusion, we provide evidence that <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficient cells exhibit increased oxidative stress, aberrant nuclear DNA methylation, and a significantly altered transcriptional circuitry.</p>
<sec id="sec3.1">
<title>Limitations of the Study</title>
<p id="p0160">Although we addressed DNA methylation changes in the promoter regions of selected down-regulated genes, we did not explore this for up-regulated genes or in a global context. Moreover, we did not assess cell death under stress conditions in iPSC-derived neurons, and performed the mitochondrial respiration assay in two not three independent experiments, although each with 10–40 replicates. In addition, although we observed an increase in ROS that might contribute to the aberrant DNA methylation, we were not able to identify the exact mechanism by which <italic>OPA1</italic> haploinsufficiency contributes to these changes in nuclear DNA methylation. Defining primary versus secondary changes related to OPA1 will be exciting to explore in the future.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3.2">
<title>Resource Availability</title>
<sec id="sec3.2.1">
<title>Lead Contact</title>
<p id="p0165">Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Judith Staerk (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0010" xlink:href="mailto:judith.staerk@ncmm.uio.no">judith.staerk@ncmm.uio.no</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3.2.2">
<title>Materials Availability</title>
<p id="p0170">There may be restrictions or delays to the availability of hESC and iPSC lines due to our need to maintain the stock and patient consent. Availability of iPSC lines will require a Materials Transfer Agreement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3.2.3" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data and Code Availability</title>
<p id="p0175">Access to data that support the findings of this study are available from the authors on reasonable request. RNA-seq information including all raw data has been deposited at Gene Expression Omnibus under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0015" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE117976">GSE117976</ext-link>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0020" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE117976">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE117976</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4">
<title>Methods</title>
<p id="p0180">All methods can be found in the accompanying <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Transparent Methods supplemental file</xref>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list id="cebib0010">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bib1">
<element-citation id="sref1" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Akepati</surname>
<given-names>V.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muller</surname>
<given-names>E.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Otto</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strauss</surname>
<given-names>H.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Portwich</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alexander</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of OPA1 isoforms isolated from mouse tissues</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurochem.
          <volume>106</volume>
<year>2008</year>
<fpage>372</fpage>
<lpage>383</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18419770</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<element-citation id="sref2" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alavi</surname>
<given-names>M.V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bette</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schimpf</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schuettauf</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schraermeyer</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wehrl</surname>
<given-names>H.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ruttiger</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>S.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tonagel</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pichler</surname>
<given-names>B.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A splice site mutation in the murine Opa1 gene features pathology of autosomal dominant optic atrophy</article-title>
<source/>Brain
          <volume>130</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>1029</fpage>
<lpage>1042</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314202</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<element-citation id="sref3" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alexander</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Votruba</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pesch</surname>
<given-names>U.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thiselton</surname>
<given-names>D.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kellner</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leo-Kottler</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Auburger</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>OPA1, encoding a dynamin-related GTPase, is mutated in autosomal dominant optic atrophy linked to chromosome 3q28</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <volume>26</volume>
<year>2000</year>
<fpage>211</fpage>
<lpage>215</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11017080</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<element-citation id="sref4" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eisenstat</surname>
<given-names>D.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubenstein</surname>
<given-names>J.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Interneuron migration from basal forebrain to neocortex: dependence on Dlx genes</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>278</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>474</fpage>
<lpage>476</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9334308</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<element-citation id="sref5" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arnoult</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grodet</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Y.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Estaquier</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blackstone</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Release of OPA1 during apoptosis participates in the rapid and complete release of cytochrome c and subsequent mitochondrial fragmentation</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>280</volume>
<year>2005</year>
<fpage>35742</fpage>
<lpage>35750</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16115883</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<element-citation id="sref6" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beaubien</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cloutier</surname>
<given-names>J.-F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Differential expression of slitrk family members in the mouse nervous system</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Dyn.
          <volume>238</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>3285</fpage>
<lpage>3296</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19924824</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<element-citation id="sref7" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carden</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mooga</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bajpai</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>K.K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Epigenetic modification of miR-663 controls mitochondria-to-nucleus retrograde signaling and tumor progression</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>292</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>20694</fpage>
<lpage>20706</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29066618</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<element-citation id="sref8" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chambers</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fasano</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Papapetrou</surname>
<given-names>E.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tomishima</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sadelain</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Studer</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Highly efficient neural conversion of human ES and iPS cells by dual inhibition of SMAD signaling</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Biotechnol.
          <volume>27</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>275</fpage>
<lpage>280</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19252484</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<element-citation id="sref9" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>D.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fusion and fission: interlinked processes critical for mitochondrial health</article-title>
<source/>Annu. Rev. Genet.
          <volume>46</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>265</fpage>
<lpage>287</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22934639</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<element-citation id="sref10" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cherry</surname>
<given-names>T.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bormuth</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwab</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cepko</surname>
<given-names>C.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>NeuroD factors regulate cell fate and neurite stratification in the developing retina</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>31</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>7365</fpage>
<lpage>7379</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593321</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<element-citation id="sref11" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chui</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>S.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oxidative stress regulates progenitor behavior and cortical neurogenesis</article-title>
<source/>Development
          <volume>147</volume>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>dev184150</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32041791</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<element-citation id="sref12" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>V.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hollins</surname>
<given-names>A.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Piechota</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yip</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>J.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>White</surname>
<given-names>K.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nicols</surname>
<given-names>P.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boulton</surname>
<given-names>M.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Votruba</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Opa1 deficiency in a mouse model of autosomal dominant optic atrophy impairs mitochondrial morphology, optic nerve structure and visual function</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
          <volume>16</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>1307</fpage>
<lpage>1318</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17428816</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<element-citation id="sref13" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Melo</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fonseca</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gillespie</surname>
<given-names>L.-A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Turk</surname>
<given-names>W.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubenstein</surname>
<given-names>J.L.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eisenstat</surname>
<given-names>D.D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dlx1 and Dlx2 function is necessary for terminal differentiation and survival of late-born retinal ganglion cells in the developing mouse retina</article-title>
<source/>Development
          <volume>132</volume>
<year>2005</year>
<fpage>311</fpage>
<lpage>322</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604100</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<element-citation id="sref14" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deglincerti</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Etoc</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ozair</surname>
<given-names>M.Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brivanlou</surname>
<given-names>A.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Chapter six - self-organization of spatial patterning in human embryonic stem cells</chapter-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Wassarman</surname>
<given-names>P.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source/>Current Topics in Developmental Biology
          <volume>116</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
<fpage>99</fpage>
<lpage>113</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib15">
<element-citation id="sref15" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Del Dotto</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mishra</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vidoni</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fogazza</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maresca</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caporali</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCaffery</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cappelletti</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baruffini</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lenaers</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>OPA1 isoforms in the hierarchical organization of mitochondrial functions</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>19</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>2557</fpage>
<lpage>2571</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28636943</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib16">
<element-citation id="sref16" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Delettre</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Griffoin</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dollfus</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lorenz</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Faivre</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lenaers</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Belenguer</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hamel</surname>
<given-names>C.P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mutation spectrum and splicing variants in the OPA1 gene</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Genet.
          <volume>109</volume>
<year>2001</year>
<fpage>584</fpage>
<lpage>591</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11810270</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib17">
<element-citation id="sref17" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Delettre</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lenaers</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Griffoin</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gigarel</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lorenzo</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Belenguer</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pelloquin</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grosgeorge</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Turc-Carel</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Perret</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Nuclear gene OPA1, encoding a mitochondrial dynamin-related protein, is mutated in dominant optic atrophy</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <volume>26</volume>
<year>2000</year>
<fpage>207</fpage>
<lpage>210</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11017079</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib18">
<element-citation id="sref18" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eisenstat</surname>
<given-names>D.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mione</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ghattas</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Puelles</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubenstein</surname>
<given-names>J.L.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DLX-1, DLX-2, and DLX-5 expression define distinct stages of basal forebrain differentiation</article-title>
<source/>J. Comp. Neurol.
          <volume>414</volume>
<year>1999</year>
<fpage>217</fpage>
<lpage>237</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10516593</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib19">
<element-citation id="sref19" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Esteve</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trousse</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodríguez</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bovolenta</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SFRP1 modulates retina cell differentiation through aβ -catenin-independent mechanism</article-title>
<source/>J. Cell Sci.
          <volume>116</volume>
<year>2003</year>
<fpage>2471</fpage>
<lpage>2481</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724355</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib20">
<element-citation id="sref20" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Herrera</surname>
<given-names>F.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roelink</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tjian</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Core promoter factor TAF9B regulates neuronal gene expression</article-title>
<source/>Elife
          <volume>3</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>e02559</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25006164</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib21">
<element-citation id="sref21" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hevner</surname>
<given-names>R.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Justice</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hsueh</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sheng</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smiga</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bulfone</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goffinet</surname>
<given-names>A.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campagnoni</surname>
<given-names>A.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubenstein</surname>
<given-names>J.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tbr1 regulates differentiation of the preplate and layer 6</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>29</volume>
<year>2001</year>
<fpage>353</fpage>
<lpage>366</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239428</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib22">
<element-citation id="sref22" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>T.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Warr</surname>
<given-names>M.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adelman</surname>
<given-names>E.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lansinger</surname>
<given-names>O.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flach</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Verovskaya</surname>
<given-names>E.V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Figueroa</surname>
<given-names>M.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Passegue</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autophagy maintains the metabolism and function of young and old stem cells</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>543</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>205</fpage>
<lpage>210</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28241143</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib23">
<element-citation id="sref23" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Iannielli</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bido</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Folladori</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Segnali</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cancellieri</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maresca</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Massimino</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubio</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morabito</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caporali</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pharmacological inhibition of necroptosis protects from dopaminergic neuronal cell death in Parkinson's disease models</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>22</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>2066</fpage>
<lpage>2079</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29466734</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib24">
<element-citation id="sref24" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jahani-Asl</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pilon-Larose</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maclaurin</surname>
<given-names>J.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>D.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mcbride</surname>
<given-names>H.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Slack</surname>
<given-names>R.S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The mitochondrial inner membrane GTPase, optic atrophy 1 (Opa1), restores mitochondrial morphology and promotes neuronal survival following excitotoxicity</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>286</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>4772</fpage>
<lpage>4782</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21041314</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib25">
<element-citation id="sref25" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jonikas</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Madill</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mathy</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zekoll</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zois</surname>
<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wigfield</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kurzawa-Akanbi</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Browne</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sims</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chinnery</surname>
<given-names>P.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Stem cell modeling of mitochondrial parkinsonism reveals key functions of OPA1</article-title>
<source/>Ann. Neurol.
          <volume>83</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>915</fpage>
<lpage>925</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29604226</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib26">
<element-citation id="sref26" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Katada</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Imhof</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Connecting threads: epigenetics and metabolism</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>148</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>24</fpage>
<lpage>28</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265398</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib27">
<element-citation id="sref27" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Le Belle</surname>
<given-names>J.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Orozco</surname>
<given-names>N.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paucar</surname>
<given-names>A.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saxe</surname>
<given-names>J.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mottahedeh</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pyle</surname>
<given-names>A.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kornblum</surname>
<given-names>H.I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Proliferative neural stem cells have high endogenous ROS levels that regulate self-renewal and neurogenesis in a PI3K/Akt-dependant manner</article-title>
<source/>Cell Stem Cell
          <volume>8</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>59</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21211782</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib28">
<element-citation id="sref28" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Letinic</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zoncu</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rakic</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Origin of GABAergic neurons in the human neocortex</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>417</volume>
<year>2002</year>
<fpage>645</fpage>
<lpage>649</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050665</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib29">
<element-citation id="sref29" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sui</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>AS1DHRS4, a head-to-head natural antisense transcript, silences the DHRS4 gene cluster in cis and trans</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A
          <volume>109</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>14110</fpage>
<lpage>14115</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22891334</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib30">
<element-citation id="sref30" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>C.B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Metabolic regulation of epigenetics</article-title>
<source/>Cell Metab.
          <volume>16</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<lpage>17</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22768835</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib31">
<element-citation id="sref31" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>MacVicar</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Langer</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>OPA1 processing in cell death and disease - the long and short of it</article-title>
<source/>J. Cell Sci.
          <volume>129</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>2297</fpage>
<lpage>2306</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27189080</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib32">
<element-citation id="sref32" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mariani</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coppola</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abyzov</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Provini</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tomasini</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Amenduni</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Szekely</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Palejev</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>FOXG1-Dependent dysregulation of GABA/glutamate neuron differentiation in autism spectrum disorders</article-title>
<source/>Cell
          <volume>162</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>375</fpage>
<lpage>390</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26186191</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib33">
<element-citation id="sref33" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Matilainen</surname>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Quiros</surname>
<given-names>P.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Auwerx</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mitochondria and epigenetics - crosstalk in homeostasis and stress</article-title>
<source/>Trends Cell Biol.
          <volume>27</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>453</fpage>
<lpage>463</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28274652</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib34">
<element-citation id="sref34" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mirzayans</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walter</surname>
<given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>F.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Link</surname>
<given-names>B.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Skarie</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hudson</surname>
<given-names>T.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fortin</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raymond</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>FOXC1 is required for cell viability and resistance to oxidative stress in the eye through the transcriptional regulation of FOXO1A</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
          <volume>17</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>490</fpage>
<lpage>505</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17993506</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib35">
<element-citation id="sref35" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mohammad</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mondal</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guseva</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pandey</surname>
<given-names>G.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kanduri</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Kcnq1ot1 noncoding RNA mediates transcriptional gene silencing by interacting with Dnmt1</article-title>
<source/>Development
          <volume>137</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>2493</fpage>
<lpage>2499</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20573698</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib36">
<element-citation id="sref36" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nasca</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rizza</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Doimo</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Legati</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ciolfi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Diodato</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calderan</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Carrara</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lamantea</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aiello</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Not only dominant, not only optic atrophy: expanding the clinical spectrum associated with OPA1 mutations</article-title>
<source/>Orphanet J. Rare Dis.
          <volume>12</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>89</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28494813</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib37">
<element-citation id="sref37" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O'Hagan</surname>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heather</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Destefano Shields</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clements</surname>
<given-names>E.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Neste</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Oxidative damage targets complexes containing DNA methyltransferases, SIRT1, and polycomb members to promoter CpG islands</article-title>
<source/>Cancer Cell
          <volume>20</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>606</fpage>
<lpage>619</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22094255</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib38">
<element-citation id="sref38" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pratt</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>N.M.M.-L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>T.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mason</surname>
<given-names>J.O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Price</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The winged helix transcription factor Foxg1 facilitates retinal ganglion cell axon crossing of the ventral midline in the mouse</article-title>
<source/>Development
          <volume>131</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>3773</fpage>
<lpage>3784</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240555</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib39">
<element-citation id="sref39" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kirwan</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Livesey</surname>
<given-names>F.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Directed differentiation of human pluripotent stem cells to cerebral cortex neurons and neural networks</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Protoc.
          <volume>7</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>1836</fpage>
<lpage>1846</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22976355</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib40">
<element-citation id="sref40" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spiegel</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saada</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flannery</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burte</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soiferman</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Khayat</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eisner</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vladovski</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>R.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bindoff</surname>
<given-names>L.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fatal infantile mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and optic atrophy associated with a homozygous OPA1 mutation</article-title>
<source/>J. Med. Genet.
          <volume>53</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>131</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26561570</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib41">
<element-citation id="sref41" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xuan</surname>
<given-names>S.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baptista</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balas</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>W.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soares</surname>
<given-names>V.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Winged helix transcription factor Bf-1 is essential for the development of the cerebral hemispheres</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>14</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>1141</fpage>
<lpage>1152</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7605629</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib42">
<element-citation id="sref42" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yuasa</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hirano</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yamagata</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Noda</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Visual projection map specified by topographic expression of transcription factors in the retina</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>382</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>632</fpage>
<lpage>635</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8757134</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="appsec2" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplemental Information</title>
<p id="p0205">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
<caption>
<title>Document S1. Transparent Methods, Figures S1–S7, and Tables S4 and S5</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2">
<caption>
<title>Table S1. Deseq2 Output of Differentially Expressed Genes in hESC-Derived <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> Compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> Neurons, Related to Figure 3</title>
<p>Number of normalized reads, fold-change, p value, and adjusted p values are shown. Genes in bold were selected for the heatmaps shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>A.</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3">
<caption>
<title>Table S2. Deseq2 Output of Differentially Expressed Genes in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> Compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs at Day 11 (D11), Related to Figure 5</title>
<p>Number of normalized reads, fold-change, p value, and adjusted p values are shown. Genes in bold were selected for the heatmaps shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B.</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc3.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4">
<caption>
<title>Table S3. Deseq2 Output of Differentially Expressed Genes in <italic>OPA1+/−</italic> Compared with <italic>OPA1+/+</italic> NPCs at Week 3 (W3), Related to Figures 5 and S5</title>
<p>Number of normalized reads, fold-change, p value, and adjusted p values are shown. Genes in bold were selected for the heatmaps shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>B.</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc4.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
<ack id="ack0010">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100005416</institution-id><institution>Research Council of Norway</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, The <funding-source id="gs2">Regional Health Authority for South-Eastern Norway</funding-source>, <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100009708</institution-id><institution>Novo Nordisk Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, Denmark, the <funding-source id="gs4"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100005366</institution-id><institution>University of Oslo, Norway</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> and the <funding-source id="gs5"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100011102</institution-id><institution>European Union Seventh Framework Programme</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (FP7-PEOPLE-2013-COFUND) under grant agreement n° 609020 - Scientia Fellows. We thank the patients for agreeing to participate in this study. We thank Marianne Smestad and Ulrikke Brinch Dahl at the core facility for Advanced EM at OUS, which is funded by the <funding-source id="gs6">South East Regional Health Authority</funding-source>, Norway, for technical assistance. The HPLC-MS/MS analyses of DNA modifications were performed by the Proteomics and Modomics Experimental Core Facility (PROMEC), <funding-source id="gs7"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100009123</institution-id><institution>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (NTNU), Trondheim, Norway. PROMEC is funded by the Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences at <funding-source id="gs8"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100009123</institution-id><institution>NTNU</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> and the <funding-source id="gs9"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004590</institution-id><institution>Central Norway Regional Health Authority, Norway</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. We thank the Medical Bioinformatics Centre of Turku Centre for Biotechnology for the copy number data analysis. The Centre is supported by the <funding-source id="gs10"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100005609</institution-id><institution>University of Turku</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, <funding-source id="gs11"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100007360</institution-id><institution>Åbo Akademi University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, and <funding-source id="gs12"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100013840</institution-id><institution>Biocenter Finland</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, Finland.</p>
<sec id="sec5">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p id="p0190">S.C. and J.S. designed the study. J.S. generated genetically modified hESC and patient iPSC lines. S.C., A.C.-P., V.J., C.P., S.B., B.T., D.T.C., M.R., A. Brech, and S.H.B. performed experiments, A.H. performed bioinformatics analysis. A. Boschi provided primary patient material. S.C., A.H., V.J., A. Brech, S.H.B., E.A.N., L.H., K.T., and J.S. interpreted results. S.C. and J.S. wrote the manuscript. All authors commented and approved the final version.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6" sec-type="COI-statement">
<title>Declaration of Interests</title>
<p id="p0195">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supplementary-material" id="appsec1">
<p id="p0200">Supplemental Information can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0025" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2020.101154">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2020.101154</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>