<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="article-commentary" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Epilepsy Curr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Epilepsy Curr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spepi</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Epilepsy Currents</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1535-7597</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1535-7511</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32550838</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7281900</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1535759720919467</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1535759720919467</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Current Literature in Basic Science</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>RAP-ALO(N)G and Make Me Smart</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5491-5746</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>Alica</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>30</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<season>May-Jun</season>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>162</fpage>
<lpage>164</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits
non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work as published without
adaptation or alteration, without further permission provided the original work is
attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="d36e78" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="10.1186/s13229-019-0311-3"></related-article>
<abstract>
<p>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-1535759720919467" orientation="portrait" position="float"><p>
<bold>TSC Patient-Derived Isogenic Neural Progenitor Cells Reveal Altered Early
Neurodevelopmental Phenotypes and Rapamycin-Induced MNK-eIF4E Signaling</bold>
</p><p>Martin P, Wagh V, Reis SA, et al. <italic>Mol Autism.</italic> 2020;11:2.
doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13229-019-0311-3">10.1186/s13229-019-0311-3</ext-link>. eCollection 2020.</p><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Tuberous sclerosis complex (TSC) is a neurodevelopmental disorder with frequent
occurrence of epilepsy, autism spectrum disorder (ASD), intellectual disability
(ID), and tumors in multiple organs. The aberrant activation of mTORC1 in TSC has
led to treatment with mTORC1 inhibitor rapamycin as a lifelong therapy for tumors,
but TSC-associated neurocognitive manifestations remain unaffected by rapamycin.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Here, we generated patient-specific, induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) from a
patient with TSC with a heterozygous, germline, nonsense mutation in exon 15 of TSC1
and established an isogenic set of heterozygous (Het), null, and corrected wild-type
(Corr-WT) iPSCs using CRISPR/Cas9-mediated gene editing. We differentiated these
iPSCs into neural progenitor cells (NPCs) and examined neurodevelopmental
phenotypes, signaling, and changes in gene expression by RNA-seq.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Differentiated NPCs revealed enlarged cell size in TSC1-Het and Null NPCs,
consistent with mTORC1 activation. TSC1-Het and Null NPCs also revealed enhanced
proliferation and altered neurite outgrowth in a genotype-dependent manner, which
was not reversed by rapamycin. Transcriptome analyses of TSC1-NPCs revealed
differentially expressed genes that display a genotype-dependent linear response,
that is, genes upregulated/downregulated in Het were further increased/decreased in
Null. In particular, genes linked to ASD, epilepsy, and ID were significantly
upregulated or downregulated, warranting further investigation. In TSC1-Het and Null
NPCs, we also observed basal activation of ERK1/2, which was further activated upon
rapamycin treatment. Rapamycin also increased MNK1/2-eIF4E signaling in
TSC1-deficient NPCs.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>MEK-ERK and MNK-eIF4E pathways regulate protein translation, and our results
suggest that aberrant translation distinct in TSC1/2-deficient NPCs could play a
role in neurodevelopmental defects. Our data showing upregulation of these signaling
pathways by rapamycin support a strategy to combine an MEK or an MNK inhibitor with
rapamycin that may be superior for TSC-associated central nervous system defects.
Importantly, our generation of isogenic sets of NPCs from patients with TSC provides
a valuable platform for translatome and large-scale drug screening studies. Overall,
our studies further support the notion that early developmental events such as NPC
proliferation and initial process formation, such as neurite number and length that
occur prior to neuronal differentiation, represent primary events in neurogenesis
critical to disease pathogenesis of neurodevelopmental disorders such as ASD.</p></sec></boxed-text>
</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>May–June 2020</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>typesetter</meta-name>
<meta-value>ts3</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1535759720919467">
<title>Commentary</title>
<p>Tuberous sclerosis complex (TSC) is an autosomal dominant neurocutaneous disease with an
estimated incidence of 1:6000 to 1:10 000 live birth caused by pathogenic variants in
<italic>TSC1</italic> (hamartin) or <italic>TSC2</italic> (tuberin) genes that together
with <italic>TBC1D7</italic> act as the main negative regulator of the mechanistic target of
rapamycin (mTOR) signaling pathway. Mechanistic target of rapamycin further associates in 2
protein complexes, mTORC1 and mTORC2, that manifest distinct roles.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1535759720919467">1</xref></sup> In the brain, mTORC1 regulates protein and lipid synthesis, cell growth, metabolism,
and autophagy and has established functions in neuronal excitability, memory formation, and
learning. mTORC2 is primarily involved in the maintenance of cytoskeletal integrity and cell migration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1535759720919467">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1535759720919467">2</xref></sup> Hyperactivation of the mTOR signaling pathway subsequent to loss-of-function variants
in either <italic>TSC1</italic> or <italic>TSC2</italic> results in abnormal cellular
morphology, proliferation, and multi-organ hamartomatosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1535759720919467">1</xref></sup> Sirolimus (rapamycin) and everolimus (Afinitor) are macrolide derivatives that were
identified as potent mTORC1 inhibitors, and their clinical use demonstrated efficacy for the
treatment of renal angiomyolipoma, subependymal giant cell astrocytoma (SEGA), and lymphangioleiomyomatosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1535759720919467">1</xref></sup> A mouse model of TSC with conditional inactivation of the <italic>Tsc1</italic> gene
in glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP)-positive cells (Tsc1<sup>GFAP</sup>CKO mice)
manifested time-dependent control of epilepsy when treated with sirolimus. Early treatment
prior to the development of clinical seizures at postnatal day 14 suppressed the onset of
experimental epilepsy for the duration of treatment, while treatment after spontaneous
seizures were well established and resulted in an improvement but not a full control of seizures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1535759720919467">3</xref></sup> Clinical trials paralleled the preclinical experience, and treatment of patients with
TSC-related medically refractory epilepsy with everolimus resulted in a significant
reduction in seizure frequency, although most patients with TSC did not become seizure-free.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1535759720919467">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1535759720919467"></xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1535759720919467">6</xref></sup> Furthermore, epilepsy-related burden is only one of several challenging consequences
of TSC, as patients typically also manifest autism spectrum disorder and a variable degree
of intellectual disability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1535759720919467">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1535759720919467">2</xref></sup> While modulating hyperactive mTOR pathway with everolimus may lead to a meaningful
improvement in epilepsy, its effect on cognition and behavior remains less well defined.
Although preclinical data suggested improvement, a 6-month long administration of everolimus
to children with TSC in a randomized, placebo-controlled trial showed a possible trend but
not a statistically significant improvement in neurocognitive functioning or in behavior,
and similar results were noted in EXIST-3 substudy in Japan.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1535759720919467">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1535759720919467">7</xref></sup> Considering the logistical challenges of these trials (patient heterogeneity,
confounding effects of medications, comorbid conditions, and others), results of these
clinical studies hardly mean absolute lack of efficacy but rather highlight the biological
complexity that underlies neurocognitive dysfunction in TSC. As illustrated in the
Tsc1<sup>GFAP</sup>CKO model, sirolimus administration before the clinical onset of
seizures ameliorated progressive astrogliosis and abnormal neuronal organization, and it
suppressed the development of interictal and ictal abnormalities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1535759720919467">3</xref></sup> Treatment timing may similarly be critical when aiming to salvage cognition.
Furthermore, individual genetic background may influence the neurological phenotype and
treatment response, and this variable is difficult to model in a mouse. The application of
patient-specific induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) is transcending some limits inherent
to genetic mouse models since iPSCs preserve patients’ genetic background and are amenable
to molecular research and drug testing.</p>
<p>Martin et al took advantage of the unique attributes of the iPSC model system as they aimed
to contribute toward a deeper understanding of neurocognitive consequences observed in TSC.
They explored molecular effects of a private <italic>TSC1</italic> gene pathogenic variant
and the effects and limitations of sirolimus (rapamycin) in patient-specific skin
fibroblast-derived iPSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1535759720919467">8</xref></sup> The patient affected by TSC carried a truncating nonsense variant in
<italic>TSC1</italic> exon 15 (1746C&gt;T, Arg509X). Using CRISPR/Cas9 technique, the
investigators generated a null <italic>TSC1</italic>-iPSCs as well as “corrected” wild-type
(Corr-WT) of the heterozygous <italic>TSC1</italic>-Het iPSCs with <italic>TSC1</italic>
(1746C&gt;T, Arg509X) variant. The isogenic iPSCs (Het, Null, and Corr-WT) were then
differentiated into neural progenitor cells (NPCs). As would be expected, compared to
Corr-WT, the TSC1-Het and Null NPCs were larger in size and they proliferated faster in a
dose-dependent manner, a finding consistent with the activation of mTORC1 complex reflected
in downstream increase in expression levels of the phosphoribosomal protein S6. The TSC-Het
and Null also showed increased number and length of neurites. Signaling through mTORC1 and
mTORC2 complexes was shown to be important for the development and morphology of dendrites
and axonal outgrowth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1535759720919467">2</xref></sup> Administration of rapamycin reduced cell size but not the proliferation rate, and it
did not affect neurite length or number. This finding is supported by prior experimental
studies in a <italic>Tsc1</italic> knockout mice, which has shown that dendritic patterning
is modulated in an mTOR-independent manner through mitogen-activated protein kinases (MEK)
that regulate phosphorylation of extracellular signal-regulated kinases (ERK).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1535759720919467">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1535759720919467">9</xref></sup> The MEK-ERK was shown to be aberrantly activated in SEGAs,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1535759720919467">8</xref></sup> and a similar activation and elevation of phosphorylated ERK (pERK) was noticed in
the current study. Interestingly, pretreatment with rapamycin, while blocking mTORC1
activation, led to a significant increase in pERK1/2 in TSC-Het and Null and it was
abolished by an application of MEK inhibitor trametinib. An MEK-related pathway and
interaction important for the dynamic process of neuronal synaptic plasticity is
mitogen-activated protein kinase–interacting kinase (MNK). The MNK phosphorylates and thus
regulates the binding of eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4E (eIF4E) to its target
proteins, such as fragile X mental retardation protein (FMRP) and cytoplasmic fragile X
protein-interacting protein 1 (CYFIP1). The FMRP/CYFIP1 complex then regulates FMRP targets
and messenger RNAs involved in cytoskeletal regulation and growth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1535759720919467">10</xref></sup> In the study by Martin et al, the baseline phosphorylation status of eIE4A was
comparable among Corr-WT, TSC-Het, and Null, but rapamycin application led to PI3K-dependent
activation of MNK-eIE4A signaling. These findings, at least in part, may explain the
sustained cellular proliferation and neurite length and number despite rapamycin treatment.
Transcriptome comparative profiling of the TSC-Het and Null versus Corr-WT uncovered 107
differentially expressed genes shared between TSC-Het and Null, and 29 of 107 genes showed
gene dose-dependent up- or downregulation. Among the dysregulated genes were the zinc-finger
family of DNA-binding transcription factors, transcriptional regulators, and notably
<italic>PCDH19</italic>, <italic>PCDH10</italic>, <italic>ANXA1</italic>,
<italic>CNTN6</italic>, and <italic>HLA-B</italic> with a known association with epilepsy,
ASD, and ID.</p>
<p>To date, most human neuronal models have evaluated molecular consequences of
<italic>TSC2</italic> defects,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1535759720919467">11</xref></sup> while the study by Martin et al assessed dose-dependent effects and consequences of a
mutant <italic>TSC1</italic> gene, an important complement to the research on cellular
phenotypic impact of pathogenic variants in the 2 main <italic>TSC</italic> genes. Results
contribute to an emerging body of literature, indicating that early abnormalities in the
proliferation of NPCs, neurite outgrowth, and migration likely contribute to a subsequent
development of neurocognitive dysfunction later in life. This work also shows that
<italic>TSC1</italic> loss-related early neurodevelopmental phenotypes do not exclusively
depend on mTORC1 activation. This suggests that activation of an alternative signaling
pathway mediated by MEK-ERK and MNK-eIF4A mechanisms may be contributory to the cognitive
and neuropsychiatric consequences of TSC. While the authors demonstrate effective selective
inhibition of MEK-ERK and MNK-eIF4A pathways in NPCs on protein levels, it remains unclear
whether this translates into a normalized cellular phenotype. Similarly, the study stops
short of testing the effect of a combined inhibition of mTORC1 and MEK-ERK and MNK-eIF4A
pathways on the NPC phenotype. Furthermore, there is an absence of cellular
electrophysiology to relate the findings of perturbed transcriptome and molecular and
cellular phenotypes to epilepsy. Aside from some of these immediate questions, this study
makes one wonder about processes and adaptive changes that occur either as early sequelae of
<italic>TSC1</italic> gene deficiency or following treatment with rapamycin analogs at
different stages of neural and disease development. It also highlights candidate therapeutic
targets that will need further exploration in search for treatment and prevention of
epilepsy and cognitive consequences of TCS.</p>
</sec>
<sig-block>
<sig>
<italic>By Alica Goldman</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1535759720919467">
<p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Alica Goldman <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1535759720919467-img1.jpg"></inline-graphic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5491-5746">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5491-5746</ext-link>
</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1535759720919467">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Au</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Northrup</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genetics, genomics, and genotype-phenotype correlations of TSC: insights
for clinical practice</article-title>. <source/>Am J Med Genet C Semin Med
Genet.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>178</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30255984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1535759720919467">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crino</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The mTOR signalling cascade: paving new roads to cure
neurological disease</article-title>. <source/>Nat Rev Neurol.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27340022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1535759720919467">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutmann</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rapamycin prevents epilepsy in a mouse model of tuberous
sclerosis complex</article-title>. <source/>Ann neurol.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18389497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1535759720919467">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilfong</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mays</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Long-term treatment of epilepsy with everolimus in tuberous
sclerosis</article-title>. <source/>Neurology.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>2408</fpage>–<lpage>2415</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27815402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1535759720919467">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagitani-Shimono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Everolimus for epilepsy and autism spectrum disorder in tuberous sclerosis
complex: EXIST-3 substudy in Japan</article-title>. <source/>Brain Dev.
<year>2019</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30060984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1535759720919467">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yapici</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Adjunctive everolimus therapy for treatment-resistant focal-onset seizures
associated with tuberous sclerosis (EXIST-3): a phase 3, randomised, double-blind,
placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source/>Lancet.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>388</volume>(<issue>10056</issue>):<fpage>2153</fpage>–<lpage>2163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27613521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1535759720919467">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadhwani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Byars</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Everolimus for treatment of tuberous sclerosis complex-associated
neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source/>Ann Clin Transl Neurol.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>887</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29296616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1535759720919467">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>TSC patient-derived isogenic neural progenitor cells reveal altered early
neurodevelopmental phenotypes and rapamycin-induced MNK-eIF4E signaling</article-title>.
<source/>Mol Autism. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>
<comment>doi:10.1186/s13229-019-0311-3</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31921404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1535759720919467">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asati</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahapatra</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>PI3K/Akt/mTOR and Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK signaling pathways
inhibitors as anticancer agents: structural and pharmacological
perspectives</article-title>. <source/>Eur J Med Chem.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26807863</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1535759720919467">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bramham</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Proud</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tuning specific translation in cancer metastasis and
synaptic memory: control at the MNK-eIF4E axis</article-title>. <source/>Trends Biochem
Sci.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>847</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27527252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1535759720919467">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afshar Saber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Recent advances in human stem cell-based modeling of
tuberous sclerosis complex</article-title>. <source/>Mole Autism.
<year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>