<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101235742</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32212</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Med. Genet. B Neuropsychiatr. Genet.</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>American journal of medical genetics. Part B, Neuropsychiatric genetics : the official publication of the International Society of Psychiatric Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4841</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-485X</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29399949</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7294771</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.32619</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1594835</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Adaptive behavior in infants and toddlers with Down syndrome and fragile X syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Will</surname>
<given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names>
</name>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4152-1166</contrib-id>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Caravella</surname>
<given-names>Kelly E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hahn</surname>
<given-names>Laura J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fidler</surname>
<given-names>Deborah J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>Jane E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Psychology, University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Speech and Hearing Science, University of Illinois Urbana Champaign, Champaign, Illinois</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Human Development and Family Studies, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, Colorado</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence</bold>: Elizabeth Will, PhD, BCBA, Department of Psychology, The University of South Carolina, Columbia 29203, SC. <email>willea@mailbox.sc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>22</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>05</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>15</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>177</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>358</fpage>
<lpage>368</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/ajmg.b.32619-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">Individuals with Down syndrome (DS) experience deficits across all domains of adaptive functioning, however little is known about the emergence and age-related changes of these impairments compared to other neurogenetic disorders with similar intellectual disability impairments, such as fragile X syndrome (FXS). Adaptive behavior is key for optimal functioning in these populations. Participants aged 5–45 months comprised three age-matched groups, DS (<italic>n</italic> = 64), FXS (<italic>n</italic> = 69), and typically developing controls (TD; <italic>n</italic> = 69). Adaptive behavior was measured on the Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales-II. Regressions were used to examine adaptive behavior in a cross-sectional design across age. DS infants and toddlers evidenced deficits across all areas of adaptive behaviors compared to the age-matched TD group, with clear impairments present in the first year of life. Motor skills were the area of greatest weakness in children with DS with significant impairment evident at 12 months of age that remained low through 3 years. Compared to age-matched children with FXS, children with DS showed initially lower standard scores at 12 months of age, but slower declines in standard scores across age, resulting in less impaired functioning at 36 months. This is the first study to compare adaptive behavior in infants and toddlers with DS to FXS, and demonstrate the phenotypic specificity of adaptive profiles in this diagnostic group. These findings provide evidence that adaptive behavior should be a major target of intervention in children with FXS and DS, and that these differences are potentially driven by unique etiologies attributable to each disorder.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>adaptive behavior</kwd>
<kwd>cross-sectional developmental trajectories</kwd>
<kwd>Down syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>neurogenetic disorders</kwd>
<kwd>fragile X syndrome</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>