<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
<?properties manuscript?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101235741</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32200</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Med Genet A</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Med. Genet. A</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>American journal of medical genetics. Part A</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4825</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-4833</issn>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31639285</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7346528</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.a.61368</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS1596987</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mutations in the sonic hedgehog pathway cause macrocephaly-associated conditions due to crosstalk to the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>Steven D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>Dzung C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bhakta</surname>
<given-names>Viraj</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>Derek</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>Vivian Y.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davidson</surname>
<given-names>Tom B.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martinez-Agosto</surname>
<given-names>Julian A.</given-names>
</name>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6776-6949</contrib-id>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Human Genetics, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California</aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Division of Medical Genetics, Department of Pediatrics, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California</aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Division of Hematology-Oncology, Department of Pediatrics, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California</aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Julian A. Martinez-Agosto, 695 Charles E. Young Drive South, Gonda Research Center Room 4558, Los Angeles, CA 90095. <email>julianmartinez@mednet.ucla.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN1">
<p id="P32">CONFLICT OF INTEREST</p>
<p id="P33">The authors have no potential conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>5</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>22</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>09</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>179</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>2517</fpage>
<lpage>2531</lpage>
<!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1002/ajmg.a.61368-->
<abstract id="ABS1">
<p id="P1">The hedgehog (Hh) pathway is highly conserved and required for embryonic patterning and determination. Mutations in the Hh pathway are observed in sporadic tumors as well as under syndromic conditions. Common to these syndromes are the findings of polydactyly/syndactyly and brain overgrowth. The latter is also a finding most commonly observed in the cases of mutations in the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway. We have identified novel Hh pathway mutations and structural copy number variations in individuals with somatic overgrowth, macrocephaly, dysmorphic facial features, and developmental delay, which phenotypically closely resemble patients with phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN) mutations. We hypothesized that brain overgrowth and phenotypic overlap with syndromic overgrowth syndromes in these cases may be due to crosstalk between the Hh and PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathways. To test this, we modeled disease-associated variants by generating PTCH1 and Suppressor of Fused (SUFU) heterozygote cell lines using the CRISPR/Cas9 system. These cells demonstrate activation of PI3K signaling and increased phosphorylation of its downstream target p4EBP1 as well as a distinct cellular phenotype. To further investigate the mechanism underlying this crosstalk, we treated human neural stem cells with sonic hedgehog (SHH) ligand and performed transcriptional analysis of components of the mTOR pathway. These studies identified decreased expression of a set of mTOR negative regulators, leading to its activation. We conclude that there is a significant crosstalk between the SHH and PI3K/AKT/mTOR. We propose that this crosstalk is responsible for why mutations in PTCH1 and SUFU lead to macrocephaly phenotypes similar to those observed in PTEN hamartoma and other overgrowth syndromes associated with mutations in PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway genes.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>