<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Translational Psychiatry</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2158-3188</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32661233</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7359319</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">904</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-020-00904-4</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Tauopathy in the young autistic brain: novel biomarker and therapeutic target</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grigg</surname>
<given-names>Iris</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Ivashko-Pachima</surname>
<given-names>Yanina</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0661-8202</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Hait</surname>
<given-names>Tom Aharon</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Korenková</surname>
<given-names>Vlasta</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Touloumi</surname>
<given-names>Olga</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lagoudaki</surname>
<given-names>Roza</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6713-2943</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Van Dijck</surname>
<given-names>Anke</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marusic</surname>
<given-names>Zlatko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6789-617X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Anicic</surname>
<given-names>Mirna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8675-9170</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Vukovic</surname>
<given-names>Jurica</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2024-0485</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Kooy</surname>
<given-names>R. Frank</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grigoriadis</surname>
<given-names>Nikolaos</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9796-2430</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>Illana</given-names>
</name>
<address>
<email>igozes@tauex.tau.ac.il</email>
</address>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12136.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0546</institution-id><institution>Elton Laboratory for Neuroendocrinology, Department of Human Molecular Genetics and Biochemistry, Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Sagol School of Neuroscience and Adams Super Center for Brain Studies, </institution><institution>Tel Aviv University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tel Aviv, Israel </aff>
<aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12136.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0546</institution-id><institution>The Blavatnik School of Computer Science, </institution><institution>Tel Aviv University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tel Aviv, Israel </aff>
<aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>BIOCEV, Institute of Biotechnology CAS, Průmyslová 595, 252 50 Vestec, Czech Republic </aff>
<aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Neurology, Laboratory of Experimental Neurology, AHEPA University Hospital, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Greece </aff>
<aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5284.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0790 3681</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Genetics, </institution><institution>University of Antwerp, </institution></institution-wrap>Antwerp, Belgium </aff>
<aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412688.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0397 9648</institution-id><institution>Clinical Department of Pathology and Cytology, </institution><institution>University Hospital Centre Zagreb, </institution></institution-wrap>Zagreb, Croatia </aff>
<aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412688.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0397 9648</institution-id><institution>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition, </institution><institution>University Hospital Centre Zagreb, School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Zagreb, Croatia </aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<elocation-id>228</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>5</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>11</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>18</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement>
<license license-type="OpenAccess">
<license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="Abs1">
<p id="Par1">Given our recent discovery of somatic mutations in autism spectrum disorder (ASD)/intellectual disability (ID) genes in postmortem aged Alzheimer’s disease brains correlating with increasing tauopathy, it is important to decipher if tauopathy is underlying brain imaging results of atrophy in ASD/ID children. We concentrated on activity-dependent neuroprotective protein (ADNP), a prevalent autism gene. The unique availability of multiple postmortem brain sections of a 7-year-old male, heterozygous for ADNP de novo mutation c.2244Adup/p.His559Glnfs*3 allowed exploration of tauopathy, reflecting on a general unexplored mechanism. The tested subject exhibited autism, fine motor delays, severe intellectual disability and seizures. The patient died after multiple organ failure following liver transplantation. To compare to other ADNP syndrome mutations, immortalized lymphoblastoid cell lines from three different patients (including ADNP p.Arg216*, p.Lys408Valfs*31, and p.Tyr719* heterozygous dominant mutations) and a control were subjected to RNA-seq. Immunohistochemistry, high-throughput gene expression profiles in numerous postmortem tissues followed. Comparisons to a control brain and to extensive datasets were used. Live cell imaging investigated Tau-microtubule interaction, protecting against tauopathy. Extensive child brain tauopathy paralleled by multiple gene expression changes was discovered. Tauopathy was explained by direct mutation effects on Tau-microtubule interaction and correction by the ADNP active snippet NAP. Significant pathway changes (empirical <italic>P</italic> value &lt; 0.05) included over 100 genes encompassing neuroactive ligand–receptor and cytokine–cytokine receptor interaction, MAPK and calcium signaling, axon guidance and Wnt signaling pathways. Changes were also seen in steroid biosynthesis genes, suggesting sex differences. Selecting the most affected genes by the ADNP mutations for gene expression analysis, in multiple postmortem tissues, identified Tau (MAPT)-gene-related expression changes compared with extensive normal gene expression (RNA-seq) databases. <italic>ADNP</italic> showed relatively reduced expression in the ADNP syndrome cerebellum, which was also observed for 25 additional genes (representing &gt;50% of the tested genes), including <italic>NLGN1, NLGN2, PAX6, SMARCA4</italic>, and <italic>SNAP25</italic>, converging on nervous system development and tauopathy. NAP provided protection against mutated ADNP disrupted Tau-microtubule association. In conclusion, tauopathy may explain brain-imaging findings in ADNP syndrome children and may provide a new direction for the development of tauopathy protecting drug candidates like NAP in ASD/ID.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject">
<title>Subject terms</title>
<kwd>Diagnostic markers</kwd>
<kwd>Diagnostic markers</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
<meta-value>© The Author(s) 2020</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="Par2">Recent whole-exome sequencing studies in autism spectrum disorder (ASD)/intellectual disability (ID) cohorts, found ADNP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> as one of the most frequently de novo mutated genes, responsible for about 0.2% of ASD cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. ADNP syndrome, also known as Helsmoortel–Van der Aa syndrome (OMIM identification 615873, Orphanet—<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.orpha.net/consor/cgi-bin/OC_Exp.php?lng=EN&amp;Expert=404448">https://www.orpha.net/consor/cgi-bin/OC_Exp.php?lng=EN&amp;Expert=404448</ext-link>), is a complex developmental disorder with robust neurological consequences and effects on multiple organ functions. ADNP syndrome patients share multiple clinical features<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par3">ADNP is imperative for brain development and normal function by regulating multiple key genes associated with synaptic transmission including tubulin/microtubules, ion channel, and autophagy-controlling genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. In addition to its suggested role as a transcription factor and chromatin remodeling protein, in the neuronal cytoplasm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, ADNP interacts directly with cytoplasmic proteins regulating basic cellular processes. Thus, it was identified as a vital gene for the microtubule network essential for synapse formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> and maintaining normal axonal transport rates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par4">Importantly and highly pertinent to the current investigation, ADNP contains a neuroprotective motif, a drug candidate NAP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> (davunetide, CP201). This neuroprotective motif contains eight amino acids, NAPVSIPQ, with SIP (SxIP) being the signature structure for interaction with microtubule end binding proteins, enhancing dendritic spine formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, enlisting Tau to the microtubule shaft<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, thus protecting microtubule-dependent axonal transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> and inhibiting Tau pathology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. As such, <italic>Adnp</italic> haploinsufficiency in mice results in tauopathy, which is rescued by NAP treatment and is exacerbated with aging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par5">Here, having postmortem tissues from 7-year-old male, heterozygous for an ADNP de novo mutation c.2244Adup/p.His559Glnfs*3, we concentrated on a potential tauopathy outcome in this young ADNP subject. Furthermore, using RNA-seq on EBV-transformed human lymphoblastoid cell lines from a healthy control and from three ADNP syndrome patients, carrying three different mutations, we discovered ADNP-dependent altered gene regulation that was also mimicked by our <italic>Adnp</italic>-deficient mouse model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> and was correlated with the finding of this very early onset tauopathy. Our previous data, in cell cultures showed that ADNP mutations (p.Tyr719*, p.Arg730*) reduced microtubule–Tau interaction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> (leading to tauopathy)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, which was rescued by NAP treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. We now extended this finding to shorter ADNP mutated proteins (p.Ser404*) discovering a significant reduction in microtubule–Tau interaction (reflected in increases in immobile Tau) and complete reversal by NAP treatment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec2">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="Sec3">
<title>ADNP postmortem case</title>
<p id="Par6">Clinical information of a deceased 7-year-old ADNP syndrome boy was received from the mother (caregiver) and tending clinicians, under informed consent. Under informed consent from the mother (caregiver of the deceased child), postmortem tissues were collected during autopsy and documented with half undergoing immediate freezing (−180 °C) and half fixation for further histochemical analyses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Specifically, for RNA extractions, tissue samples were surgically removed and frozen in vials (brain stem, cerebellum, hippocampus, pituitary (hypophysis), striatum, visual cortex, blood, colon, muscle (gastrocnemius, tibialis, and tongue), heart, kidney, pancreas, skin, spinal cord, stomach, testis, and thyroid. Each tissue was homogenized using Bullet Blender<sup>®</sup> and the appropriate beads.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec4">
<title>Control brain</title>
<p id="Par7">Control hippocampus tissue was obtained by a surgical removal from a 31-year-old subject, fixed and submitted to further histological procedures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec5">
<title>Histology</title>
<p id="Par8">Human paraffin sections (6 μm) were deparaffinized and hydrated in xylene and alcohol solutions, rinsed with distilled water. The sections were then stained with Gallyas technique in order to identify Tau pathology.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec6">
<title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p id="Par9">Standard methods and antibodies are described in the <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">Supplementary methods</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec7">
<title>Neuronal-like cell models, differentiation, co-transfection of overexpressing plasmid, and fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup></title>
<p id="Par10">All methodology was published before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and is further detailed in the <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">Supplementary methods</xref>.</p>
<p id="Par11">Protein expressing plasmids were prepared based on a pEGFP-C1 backbone and inclusion of the full-length <italic>ADNP</italic> or of the truncated form expressiong the mutated p.Ser404* ADNP (<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">Supplementary materials</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec8">
<title>Cell RNA extraction and RNA sequencing</title>
<p id="Par12">RNA was extracted from EBV-transformed human lymphoblastoid cell lines using TRI Reagent<sup>®</sup>, as instructed (Sigma-Aldrich, MO, USA). At the time of extraction, cell confluence was about 70–80%. Cell lines included one healthy control and three ADNP syndrome patients, carrying three different mutations (Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">1</xref>). Technical details of cell line library preparation, sequencing, and data analysis are described in the <xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">Supplementary methods</xref> and published articles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec9">
<title>Organ DNA/RNA extraction</title>
<p id="Par13">After homogenization, DNA and RNA were extracted using ZR-Duet<sup>TM</sup> DNA/RNA MiniPrep Plus (Zymo Research. CA, USA). A DNA sample from the kidney was Sanger sequenced to validate the mutation (<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">Supplementary Results</xref>, Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">1</xref>. Note, all supplementary figures are labeled S and the respective Fig. number).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec10">
<title>qPCR gene expression analysis</title>
<p id="Par14">Analysis was performed in BIOCEV institute (Prague, Czech Republic) with BioMark HD system (Fluidigm, San Francisco, CA) (<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">Supplementary methods</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec11">
<title>RNA expression data</title>
<p id="Par15">Normal gene expression data from two extensive databases were used: HPA RNA-seq normal tissues (NCBI) and GTEx portal (accession number phs000424.vN.pN)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec12">
<title>Bioinformatics</title>
<sec id="Sec13">
<title>Analysis of lymphoblastoid RNA-seq data</title>
<p id="Par16">We downloaded our preprocessed lymphoblastoid (Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">1</xref>) RNA-seq data from gene expression omnibus (GEO) (GSE81268)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> and computed the log fold change (LFC) as follows: First, for each gene, we computed the median expression value of the three mutated samples (expression-Ig1, expression-SSC4121, and expression-SSC8311). Second, we divided the median expression value with expression-Lympho_cont column and applied log2 (we added a prior value of 1 to the nominator and denominator to prevent dividing by zero or logarithm of zero). Results are available at Supplementary Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">1</xref>.</p>
<p id="Par17">We ranked the LFCs from highest to lowest, and applied the gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> implemented in Expander<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. We chose to apply 1000 permutation tests. Gene sets selected for the analysis are: Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes (KEGG) pathways gene-sets from EXPANDER and MSigDB (C2 collection) databases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, Reactome pathways and gene ontology gene-sets from MSigDB (C2 and C5 collections)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Results are available in Supplementary Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM3">2</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec14">
<title>Comparison between healthy controls and ADNP syndrome</title>
<p id="Par18">We applied log<sub>2</sub>(<italic>x</italic> + 1) transformation on the HPA, GTEx, and ADNP syndrome expression values (Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM4">3</xref>) in order to reduce the effect of outliers in the data. Next, for each gene, we created a heatmap using pheatmap R package with standardization (scale = “row” in the “pheatmap” function), per dataset (HPA, GTEx, and ADNP syndrome), of each gene across the tissues (Kolde R. pheatmap: Pretty Heatmaps [Internet]. 2019. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=pheatmap">https://cran.r-project.org/package=pheatmap</ext-link>) (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>). The standardization helped us to compare the expression values between the datasets, per tissue and per gene, since the distributions between the datasets were not the same (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">3</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec15" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="Sec16">
<title>Clinical disease manifestation</title>
<p id="Par19">Seven-year-old male was diagnosed as a toddler with ASD, confirmed by cDNA sequencing as ADNP syndrome (heterozygous for a de novo mutation c.2244Adup/p.His559Glnfs*3, RefSeq isoform NM_015339.4) (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">1</xref>). Medical records showed that besides autistic traits, the patient presented gross and fine motor delays, severe ID and seizures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Specifically, after a first liver transplantation at the age of about 3.5 years, the patient developed generalized symptomatic epilepsy. As epilepsy was refractory, several antiepileptic drugs were used to control it. He was first on carbamazepine, then oxcarbazepine was added. Later carbamazepine was stopped, and he continued on oxcarbazepine and levetiracetam. Following that, he was switched to clobazam and topiramate, and for the last 18 months before death, he had been prescribed a combination of three antiepileptic drugs including: levetiracetram + topiramate + clonazepam. The patient also suffered from low muscle tone, convergence insufficiency (impaired 3D vision), as well as parent-reported feeding/eating and sleep problems. He also manifested a potential ADNP marker, early eruption and loss of deciduous teeth (full set of teeth by the age of one)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The patient died after multiple organ failures following a second liver transplantation. An autopsy was performed and different tissue samples were taken for analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec17">
<title>ADNP syndrome postmortem tauopathy is potentially rescued by NAP treatment</title>
<p id="Par20">The combination of histochemical methods (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1a</xref>, Gallyas staining, frontal cortex, cerebellum hippocampal hilus, and dentate gyrus, and Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">4</xref>, hypothalamus and olfactory bulb) and immunohistochemistry (hippocampal hilus and dentate gyrus, with antibodies recognizing Alzheimer’s disease-related hyperphosphorylated Tau AT8 and AT180, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1a</xref>, dashed blue box)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> identified extensive tauopathy. However, the corpus callosum and the trigeminal nerve were negative (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">4</xref>). No apparent staining was observed in the control brain hippocampus (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1a</xref> red box, “GALLYAS” staining).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Discovery of ADNP syndrome juvenitle postmortem tauopathy and potential rescue by NAP treatment.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The ADNP syndrome juvenile brain exhibits intensive tauopathy. Gallyas staining (Tau pathology) is indicated by green arrows. Frontal cortex (Pr cortex), cerebellum, hippocampal hilus, and dentate gyrus showed positive staining. In the hippocampus the positive cells were in the hillus and in the molecular area, in the granular area of dentate gyrus, CA1, CA2, CA3, there were no positive cells. While no apparent Gallyas staining was observed in the control hippocampus (red box), the ADNP case study tauopathy was verified by hippocampal hyperphosphorylated Tau immunohistochemistry (AT180 and AT8 antibodies). Bars represent 100 μm. The ADNP snippet, drug candidate. <bold>b</bold> NAP enlists Tau to microtubules in the face of ADNP mutations: protection against Tauopathy. Representative images of photo-bleaching (0′) and fluorescence recovery (60′) of mCherry-tagged Tau in differentiated N1E-115 cells co-transfected with GFP-tagged full-length ADNP or truncated p.Ser404* ADNP form with or without NAP treatment (10<sup>−12</sup>M, 4h). Transfection with backbone plasmid (pEGFP-C1) expressing non-conjugated GFP, was performed as a control. <bold>c</bold> Fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP) recovery curves of normalized data (see “Online Resources 1”). <bold>d</bold> The graph represents averages (±SEM) of the fitted data (from three independent experiments) of immobile fractions. Normalized FRAP data were fitted with one-exponential functions (GraphPad Prism 6) and statistical analyses was done by Two Way ANOVA (SigmaPlot 11, with all pairwise multiple comparison procedures—Tukey Test). Statistical significance is presented by **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001. Control <italic>n</italic> = 64; control+NAP <italic>n</italic> = 14; full-length ADNP <italic>n</italic> = 55; full-length ADNP+NAP <italic>n</italic> = 46; p.Ser404* <italic>n</italic> = 33; p.Ser404* + NAP <italic>n</italic> = 62.</p></caption><graphic id="d30e784" xlink:href="41398_2020_904_Fig1_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par21">Our previous data, in cell cultures showed that ADNP mutations (p.Tyr719*, p.Arg730*) reduced microtubule–Tau interaction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> (leading to tauopathy)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, which was rescued by NAP treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Here, we extended this finding to shorter ADNP mutated proteins (p.Ser404*, Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">5A,B</xref>) discovering significant reduction in microtubule–Tau interaction (reflected in increases in immobile Tau content) and complete reversal by NAP treatment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1b, c</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par22">At the immunohistochemical level, two additional findings were observed. (1) A dramatic hippocampal staining of postsynaptic density protein 95 (PSD95). (2) A similar increased stain of the N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor 1 (NMDAR1) in the hippocampus (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">6A</xref>), which was much lower in the control hippocampal stain (albeit in a different hippocampal region—a control seizure-free region, Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">6B</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec18">
<title>ADNP mutant lymphoblasotoid RNA-Seq supporting Tau pathology</title>
<p id="Par23">To evaluate human mutated ADNP (different mutations including p.Arg216*, p.Lys408Valfs*31, and p.Tyr719*) signature RNA expression patterns, we first looked at our lymphoblatoids RNA-seq datasets (“Methods” and Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">1</xref>). Three ADNP mutated samples were sufficient for our analysis as most of the genes had similar expression values in two out of the three samples. Therefore, we chose for each gene, the median expression value in the three samples as the representative gene expression for the mutated ADNP samples (“Methods”). We applied a GSEA on the LFCs between the ADNP mutated and control gene expressions (GSEA results are available in Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM3">2</xref>). We discovered effects on multiple pathways. Significant KEGG pathway changes (empirical <italic>P</italic> value &lt; 0.05) encompassing over hundred genes included the following, neuroactive ligand–receptor and cytokine–cytokine receptor interaction (implicated for ADNP signaling)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, MAPK signaling, calcium signaling (implicated in ADNP brain activity)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, axon guidance and Wnt signaling pathway (previously associated with ADNP regulation of teeth/bone and brain)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Highly significant changes were also seen in steroid biosynthesis genes, suggesting sex differences, as noted in mice and linked with microtubule regulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Interestingly, Alzheimer’s disease and Parkinson’s disease were among the discovered KEGG pathways (with over a 100 genes of interest, however with empirical <italic>P</italic> value 0.093/0.12, respectively). We also observed neuron-related GO biological processes enrichments such as negative regulation of neurological system process, forebrain generation of neurons, and neuroepithelial cell differentiation (empirical <italic>P</italic> value &lt; 0.001).</p>
<p id="Par24">Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>, prepared based on our RNA-seq data (GEO, GSE81268)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> lists the genes that showed the highest change when comparing ADNP mutated lymphoblastoid cells to a control lymphoblastoid cell line. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab2">2</xref> lists additional genes of interest that changed either as consequence of <italic>Adnp</italic> deficiency or as a results of NAP treatment or of both. These genes/proteins differentiate ADNP syndrome and healthy control lymphoblastoids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. As expected, String analysis for protein–protein interactions showed that most of the genes regulated by ADNP (i.e., genes changing in expression presumably because of ADNP mutation as explained in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab2">2</xref>) exhibited a connection to Tau (MAPT) and the expected nervous system development pathway enrichment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>RNA SEQ data (GEO, GSE81268)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene*</th><th>Fold change (Ig1 vs. Lympho)</th><th>Fold change (SSC4121 vs. Lympho)</th><th>Fold change (SSC8311 vs. Lympho)</th><th>Expression-Lympho_cont</th><th>Expression-Ig1</th><th>Expression-SSC4121</th><th>Expression-SSC8311</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>ROBO1</td><td>745.647</td><td>91.2253</td><td>812.44</td><td>0.0128824</td><td>9.60575</td><td>1.1752</td><td>10.4662</td></tr><tr><td>NLRP2</td><td>112.939</td><td>124.576</td><td>905.512</td><td>0.0184944</td><td>2.08874</td><td>2.30397</td><td>16.7469</td></tr><tr><td>HOXB2</td><td>107.756</td><td>94.6583</td><td>91.1358</td><td>0.0847141</td><td>9.12846</td><td>8.0189</td><td>7.72049</td></tr><tr><td>IPCEF1</td><td>73.9769</td><td>49.2174</td><td>89.7259</td><td>0.219583</td><td>16.2441</td><td>10.8073</td><td>19.7023</td></tr><tr><td>PTK7</td><td>72.7466</td><td>22.561</td><td>122.293</td><td>0.0228934</td><td>1.66542</td><td>0.516499</td><td>2.79971</td></tr><tr><td>TLR4</td><td>72.0192</td><td>91.7155</td><td>63.094</td><td>0.0117378</td><td>0.845345</td><td>1.07654</td><td>0.740583</td></tr><tr><td>TBX15</td><td>63.2896</td><td>212.859</td><td>167.082</td><td>0.0388303</td><td>2.45756</td><td>8.26537</td><td>6.48786</td></tr><tr><td>ALOX12P2</td><td>52.9232</td><td>58.8549</td><td>52.5783</td><td>0.0490289</td><td>2.59477</td><td>2.88559</td><td>2.57786</td></tr><tr><td>TLR2</td><td>49.104</td><td>83.3778</td><td>275.744</td><td>0.00997296</td><td>0.489712</td><td>0.831523</td><td>2.74999</td></tr><tr><td>IGFBP2</td><td>44.1936</td><td>12.5067</td><td>5.84204</td><td>0.0949699</td><td>4.19706</td><td>1.18776</td><td>0.554818</td></tr><tr><td>LPAR6</td><td>34.7975</td><td>42.8991</td><td>35.26</td><td>0.441516</td><td>15.3636</td><td>18.9406</td><td>15.5678</td></tr><tr><td>AIF1</td><td>12.5361</td><td>8.50887</td><td>16.9555</td><td>0.156669</td><td>1.96403</td><td>1.33308</td><td>2.65641</td></tr><tr><td>FGFR1</td><td>6.50824</td><td>6.67026</td><td>6.91029</td><td>0.753597</td><td>4.90459</td><td>5.02669</td><td>5.20757</td></tr><tr><td>VSTM2L</td><td>−6.46587</td><td>−7.61594</td><td>−27.1737</td><td>2.19728</td><td>0.339827</td><td>0.28851</td><td>0.0808603</td></tr><tr><td>GRM3</td><td>−17.1065</td><td>−5.70896</td><td>−11.9821</td><td>0.446002</td><td>0.026072</td><td>0.0781232</td><td>0.0372223</td></tr><tr><td>LOC151174</td><td>−29.3255</td><td>2.94275</td><td>−4.56462</td><td>0.554209</td><td>0.0188985</td><td>1.6309</td><td>0.121414</td></tr><tr><td>GPR98</td><td>−31.1584</td><td>−4.95165</td><td>−21.8246</td><td>0.179003</td><td>0.00574493</td><td>0.0361501</td><td>0.00820188</td></tr><tr><td>HOMER3</td><td>−36.3133</td><td>−19.0099</td><td>−135.655</td><td>4.0601</td><td>0.111807</td><td>0.213578</td><td>0.0299296</td></tr><tr><td>MYL9</td><td>−64.4865</td><td>−42.5937</td><td>−19.0713</td><td>37.8958</td><td>0.587655</td><td>0.889704</td><td>1.98705</td></tr><tr><td>HMX3</td><td>−75.6048</td><td>−7.00876</td><td>−2.882</td><td>10.4248</td><td>0.137885</td><td>1.4874</td><td>3.61722</td></tr><tr><td>CDH17</td><td>No change</td><td>−95.1494</td><td>No change</td><td>2.49733</td><td>0</td><td>0.0262464</td><td>0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(*) Here, unlike the fold changes computed for GSEA analysis (“Methods”), we ranked genes by the highest fold change among the three mutated samples versus the control “Lympho” sample.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Gene selection rationale.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene and reason for choice</th><th>Fold change (Ig1 vs. Lympho)</th><th>Fold change (SSC4121 vs. Lympho)</th><th>Fold change (SSC8311 vs. Lympho)</th><th>Expression-Lympho_cont</th><th>Expression-Ig1</th><th>Expression-SSC4121</th><th>Expression-SSC8311</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>HIST1H3B</td><td>2.728</td><td>4.90457</td><td>4.67363</td><td>0.143763</td><td>0.392185</td><td>0.705095</td><td>0.671894</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Decreased in the cortex of Adnp<sup>+/−</sup> female mice and increased (normalized) with NAP CP201 treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>SLC12A2</td><td>1.48183</td><td>1.64404</td><td>1.67656</td><td>3.31149</td><td>4.90706</td><td>5.44423</td><td>5.55191</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">(Slc12a2, Slc9a3) showed ADNP-age-dependent regulation in the hippocampus, cortex and spleen in mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>ADNP</td><td>1.34291</td><td>1.29374</td><td>1.31103</td><td>28.3059</td><td>38.0124</td><td>36.6205</td><td>37.1097</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Studied gene</td></tr><tr><td>NR4A2</td><td>1.27615</td><td>1.1638</td><td>1.109</td><td>0.566908</td><td>0.723459</td><td>0.659766</td><td>0.628699</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Nuclear receptor subfamily 4 group A member 2—pathogenic NR4A2 variants cause developmental delays/intellectual disabilities DD/ID and/or autism spectrum disorder (ASD) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://panelapp.genomicsengland.co.uk/panels/285/gene/NR4A2/">https://panelapp.genomicsengland.co.uk/panels/285/gene/NR4A2/</ext-link>), regulated by ADNP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>SNAP25</td><td>1.2276</td><td>1.10353</td><td>−3.42346</td><td>0.124965</td><td>0.153407</td><td>0.137903</td><td>0.0365025</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">SNAP-25 regulates dendritic spine formation through postsynaptic binding to p140Cap<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> that in turn interacts with ADNP/NAP (CP201)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>MBP</td><td>1.08443</td><td>−1.10046</td><td>1.3582</td><td>17.4361</td><td>18.9082</td><td>15.8444</td><td>23.6817</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Myelin basic protein – ADNP is associated with myelin – white matter – health<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>SMARCA4</td><td>1.04815</td><td>−1.15125</td><td>−1.0588</td><td>26.9341</td><td>28.2311</td><td>23.3955</td><td>25.4384</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">SMARC4, also known as BRG1 is an ADNP, SWI/SNF-interacting protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>TBP</td><td>1.02512</td><td>1.01825</td><td>1.13606</td><td>10.2996</td><td>10.5583</td><td>10.4876</td><td>11.7009</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Used sometimes for calibration as house-keeping gene</td></tr><tr><td>NLGN2</td><td>−1.11457</td><td>−1.43361</td><td>1.35016</td><td>0.328901</td><td>0.295093</td><td>0.229422</td><td>0.44407</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Linked with synaptic regulation, shows age-dependent hippocampal reduction in Adnp<sup>+/−</sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>NLGN1</td><td>not found</td><td>not found</td><td>not found</td><td>not found</td><td>not found</td><td>not found</td><td>not found</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Linked with synaptic regulation, shows hippocampal sex-dependent regulation in Adnp<sup>+/+</sup> as well as Adnp<sup>+/−</sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>MTOR</td><td>−1.18542</td><td>−1.03791</td><td>−1.05758</td><td>10.8397</td><td>9.14418</td><td>10.4438</td><td>10.2495</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Autophagy-related, regulated by Adnp<sup>+/−</sup> and corrected by NAP (CP201) in the mouse spleen<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>BECN1</td><td>−1.28996</td><td>−1.1749</td><td>−1.14578</td><td>32.6192</td><td>25.287</td><td>27.7633</td><td>28.4691</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Regulated by Adnp/NAP (CP201)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>IL1B</td><td>−1.62136</td><td>−3.90792</td><td>1.32081</td><td>0.520924</td><td>0.321288</td><td>0.1333</td><td>0.688041</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Regulated by the Adnp<sup>+/−</sup> genotype<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>MDGA1</td><td>−1.62457</td><td>−238.553</td><td>−1.43052</td><td>1.78268</td><td>1.09732</td><td>0.00747288</td><td>1.24618</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">MAM domain containing glycosylphosphatidylinositol anchor 1, associated with nervous system development and psychiatric disorders <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/266727">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/266727</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>PAX6</td><td>−2.11482</td><td>−1.09227</td><td>1.2463</td><td>0.138463</td><td>0.0654726</td><td>0.126766</td><td>0.172566</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Important for nervous system development, regulated by ADNP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>KDM5D</td><td>Not determined change</td><td>Not determined change</td><td>Not determined change</td><td>0</td><td>15.1514</td><td>0</td><td>13.5382</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Increased in the Adnp<sup>+/−</sup> mouse spleen, decreased (normalized) by NAP (CP201) treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>NTS</td><td>Not determined change</td><td>Not determined change</td><td>Not determined change</td><td>0</td><td>0.0298807</td><td>0</td><td>2.43162</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">This gene encodes a common precursor for two peptides, neuromedin N and neurotensin and may function as a neurotransmitter or a neuromodulator—was discovered as regulated by ADNP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>FOXP2</td><td>No change</td><td>−4.58755</td><td>−3.8514</td><td>0.0431349</td><td>0</td><td>0.0094026</td><td>0.0111998</td></tr><tr><td>Reason</td><td colspan="7">Important for language regulated by ADNP and NAP (CP201)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Significant ADNP influence on protein expression associated with signature transcript changes because of ADNP mutation.</title><p>Gene transcripts (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab2">2</xref>) were subjected to String protein interaction analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://string-db.org/cgi/network.pl?taskId=J365DTd906k7">https://string-db.org/cgi/network.pl?taskId=J365DTd906k7</ext-link>) including MAPT – Tau, which was found to be hyperphosphorylated, forming neurofibrillary tangles in Adnp-haploinsufficient mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and above (<bold>a</bold>). Expected enrichment/involvement in the biological process of nervous system development (<bold>b</bold>). <bold>c</bold> Heatmaps of selected genes in a subset of tissues for examination. We examined 27 genes in cerebellum, hypophysis, blood, kidney, stomach, testis, and thyroid. The heatmaps were extracted from Online Resource 5. Each triplet of rows represents a single gene in three datasets (see the ADNP gene example on the top-left plot): ADNP syndrome (qPCR), Healthy (HPA RNA-seq), and Healthy (GTEx RNA-seq). Expression values (z-scores) are indicated within the cells. Gene transcripts showing significant reduction in the cerebellum include: Beclin1 (<italic>BECN1</italic>), fibroblast growth factor receptor 1 (<italic>FGFR1</italic>), forkhead box protein P2 (<italic>FOXP2</italic>), G-protein coupled receptor 98 (<italic>GPR98</italic>), glutamate metabotropic receptor 3 (<italic>GRM3</italic>), homeobox 3 (<italic>HMX3</italic>), homer scaffold protein 3 (<italic>HOMER3</italic>), interleukin 1 beta (<italic>IL1beta</italic>), interactor protein for cytohesin exchange factors 1 (<italic>IPCEF1</italic>), Lysine-specific demethylase 5A (<italic>KDM5D</italic>), myelin basic protein (<italic>MBP</italic>), MAM domain-containing glycosylphosphatidylinositol anchor protein 1 (<italic>MDGA1</italic>), mammalian target of rapamycin (<italic>MTOR</italic>), neuroligin1/2 (<italic>NLGN1, NLGN2</italic>), nuclear receptor family pyrin domain containing (<italic>NLRP2</italic>), nuclear receptor subfamily 4 group A member 2 (<italic>NR4A2</italic>), paired box 6 (<italic>PAX6</italic>), inactive tyrosine-protein kinase 7 (<italic>PTK7</italic>), roundboat guidance receptor (<italic>ROBO1</italic>), solute carrier family 12 member 2 (<italic>SLC12A2</italic>, electrically silent transporter system, mediates sodium and chloride reabsorption), SWI/SNF related, matrix associated, actin dependent regulator of chromatin, subfamily A, member 4 (<italic>SMARCA4</italic>) also known as Brahma protein-like 1 (<italic>BRG1</italic>), synaptosomal nerve-associated protein 25 (<italic>SNAP25</italic>), TATA-box-binding protein (<italic>TBP</italic>) and V-set and transmembrane domain-containing protein 2-like protein (<italic>VSTM2L</italic>).</p></caption><graphic id="d30e2300" xlink:href="41398_2020_904_Fig2_HTML"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="Par25">In search for signature transcriptome associated with the ADNP syndrome in the postmortem samples, RNA extracted from multiple tissues was submitted to high throughput qPCR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> focusing on the chosen transcripts (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab2">2</xref>, primer sets, Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM5">4</xref>) and compared with normal expression (obtained from two databases, “Methods”). Since each of the public databases and our qPCR results were obtained and calculated with different methods, we applied a log<sub>2</sub> transformation and a standardization scheme, per gene and per dataset (Methods). Below, we examined genes mostly showing high and significant Spearman correlation between the GTEx and HPA datasets (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">7</xref>; Spearman <italic>P</italic> value &lt; 0.1). We also considered genes with limited expression values in one of the control datasets (HPA or GTEx) and expressed in at least 15 out of 24 examined tissues in the other control and ADNP syndrome datasets. This way, we were confident that the standardization of the gene expression across tissues per dataset represents the relative gene expression between the tissues per dataset.</p>
<p id="Par26">ADNP showed relatively reduced expression in the child’s postmortem cerebellum (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>). This relatively reduced expression was also observed for <italic>BECN1, FGFR1, FOXP2, GPR98, GRM3, HMX3, HOMER3, IL1beta, IPCEF1, KDM5D, MBP, MDGA1, MTOR, NLGN1, NLGN2, NLRP2, NR4A2, PAX6, PTK7, ROBO1, SLC12A2, SMARCA4, SNAP25, TBP</italic>, and <italic>VSTM2L</italic> (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref> legend for complete gene names). All these genes converge on nervous system development and represent a majority of the tested genes. Interestingly, while expression in testis, pituitary (hypophysis) and thyroid was occasionally similar in trend with the cerebellum, the stomach, kidney and blood exhibited occasionally opposite (increased) trends in gene expression associated with the ADNP mutation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>, Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>).</p>
<p id="Par27">In contrast to the listed gene transcripts above, histone cluster 1 H3 family member B (<italic>HIST1H3B</italic>) that encodes a nucleosome core protein, showed a relatively high expression in the ADNP syndrome cerebellum and pituitary (hypophysis), and a decreased expression in the hippocampus, indicating gene specificity.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Sec19" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="Par28">The novel tauopathy findings in ASD/ID are directly related to ADNP function that by binding to microtubule end binding proteins, which in turn bind to Tau, enhances Tau association with microtubules<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and protects against tauopathy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. However, in the <italic>Adnp</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup> mice tauopathy appeared with aging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, similar to Alzheimer’s disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and unlike the childhood discovery here. Interestingly, ADNP/NAP preferentially interact with the alternatively spliced three microtubule binding repeat dynamic Tau (associated with development) compared with four microtubule binding repeat Tau<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> implicating potential early onset tauopathy in association with the ADNP syndrome. In this respect, early Tau hyperphosphorylation was observed in the <italic>Adnp</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup> mice, which was reversed by NAP treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par29">The ADNP-mutation associated PSD95 and NMDAR1 increased expression might be related to aberrant synaptic plasticity as observed in the <italic>Adnp</italic><sup>+/−</sup> mice also at the dendritic spine level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> and to increased excitotoxicity linked with seizures, which have been observed in the case study, with intact ADNP/NAP, protecting against excitotoxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par30"><italic>ADNP</italic> expression was reduced in the case study cerebellum, hypophysis, testis, thyroid, and skin because of ADNP mutation (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>), with some other tissues such as stomach, kidney and blood showing an apparent increase (as partly noted above; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>). In this respect, ADNP, regulating its own expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, has been implicated in brain function (ID) affecting all known ADNP syndrome cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> with motor impediments correlated in severity to ID, endocrine problems (24.5% of the children/thyroid hormone problem, 15%), early puberty (30%), skin problems, gastrointestinal problems (83% of the children), and urogenital problems (28%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par31"><italic>PAX6</italic>, a major regulatory gene for brain development, originally discovered by us as a major ADNP-regulated gene during embryonic and postnatal development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> showed here a dramatically decreased expression in the cerebellum in the ADNP case compared with controls (as noted above; Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>). This finding is in-line with known functions of PAX6 and the ADNP phenotype, with PAX6 playing a seminal role in the development of glutamatergic neurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> and ADNP regulating the glutamatergic synapse<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The seemingly robust control of brain-development associated gene expression (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>) is now further exemplified in the human brain PAX6 regulation. PAX6 has a key role in neural tissue development, particularly the eye. Mutations in this gene are associated with ocular disorders, cerebral malformations auditory deficiency, pancreatic and pituitary development and function, development of the CNS, and beyond<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par32">SMARCA4 (BRG1), an ADNP-interacting protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> showed here to be regulated by the ADNP mutation (transcript down regulated also in the hypophysis and thyroid as in the ADNP reduced expression) (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>). SMARCA4 is also implicated in autism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Similarly, BECN1, a major regulator of autophagy, which has been previously shown to be downregulated by <italic>Adnp</italic> deficiency, and corrected by the ADNP snippet drug candidate NAP, microtubule end protein binding motif (SxIP) SKIP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, was downregulated here as well.</p>
<p id="Par33">A closer inspection of brain gene expression showed an overall downregulation of <italic>ADNP</italic> (mimicking <italic>Adnp</italic> haploinsufficiency, except in the hippocampus) and a dramatic downregulation <italic>FOXP2</italic> in the cerebellum. FOXP2, a major transcription factor involved in language acquisition was increased in the hippocampus (Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>), as was seen before also in the haploinsufficient Adnp male mouse hippocampus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, with direct association to language acquisition impediments in the ADNP children<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par34">Looking at genes that might be associated with peripheral phenotypes of the ADNP syndrome, <italic>FGFR1</italic> showed reduced expression in the cerebellum and hypophysis. This gene influences mitogenesis as well as differentiation and is important for normal bone development. This particular family member is involved in limb induction and is related to several syndromes in which symptoms include: high forehead, wide-set eyes, wide feet and dental aberrations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, well matched with the ADNP syndrome phenotype<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. FGFR1 has a role in neural crest formation as well<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. <italic>HIST1H3B</italic> that encodes a nucleosome core protein, showed a relatively high expression in the cerebellum and hypophysis, and a decreased expression in the hippocampus. Interestingly, in our RNA-seq results (Table S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM2">1</xref>), most of the <italic>HIST</italic> transcripts were up regulated suggestive of aberrations in nucleosomes and DNA regulation possibly by ADNP mutations. Furthermore, <italic>Hist1h3b</italic> was downregulated in the <italic>Adnp</italic>-deficient mouse cerebral cortex and this was corrected by treatment with the ADNP snippet, drug candidate NAP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par35">Further assessing RNA expression, <italic>GRM3, MBP SNAP25</italic> and <italic>NGLN1</italic> were all decreased in the cerebellum because of the ADNP mutation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>, Fig. S<xref ref-type="media" rid="MOESM1">2</xref>). These genes, directly associated with synapse plasticity and myelin function, have been implicated before with ADNP regulation in the <italic>Adnp</italic><sup>+/−</sup> mouse, with an increase in <italic>Ngln2</italic> in the male hippocampus and correction by NAP treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> with ADNP interacting with key regulatory proteins at the synapse<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> and regulating the excitatory glutamategic synapse<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. ADNP regulation of <italic>MBP</italic> is further directly linked to white matter lesions in the ADNP syndrome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par36">Further leading from brain to peripheral tissues, we have previously shown a direct binding of ADNP to the <italic>Myl2</italic> promoter, the most downregulated gene in <italic>Adnp</italic> knockout mouse embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> and strongly affected by <italic>Adnp</italic> haploinsufficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. In normal tissues this gene is expressed mainly in the cardiac muscle and in smooth muscles and may be directly linked to the digestive problems, hypotonia and occasional cardiac problems noted in ADNP children<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par37">Taken together also in comparison to the in depth phenotypic analysis of 78 ADNP children<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, our gene expression results correlate with the developmental delays measured in the ADNP children (100%), the cognitive, motor and gastrointestinal problems observed in the majority of the children, as well as the potential hormonal imbalance and urogenital abnormalities. Furthermore, our recent findings also associated somatic brain mutations in ADNP (among other genes) as possible risk factors/driving pathologies of Alzheimer’s disease (the most prevalent tauopathy). Importantly, a substantial overlap between autism/ID and Alzheimer’s brain mutations was discovered as well as a relatively high proportion of mutations in cytoskeletal genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="Par38">Finally, we have now extended our previous finding with truncating ADNP mutations (p.Tyr719* and p.Arg730*) reducing microtubule Tau interaction and microtubule dynamics rescued by NAP treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> to a shorter truncating mutation (p.Ser404*), still showing a significant protection by NAP treatment. Together these results corroborate ADNP/NAP microtubule-Tau protective mechanism, while offering potential clinical relief against tauopathy.</p>
<p id="Par39">In terms of strength and limitations, our current study reports for the first time tauopathy in an ADNP syndrome child. We have utilized the only available postmortem tissue of the ADNP syndrome to-date and compared it to a young adult control brain. Gene expression analysis identified Tau (MAPT) as a central deregulated protein in the ADNP syndrome brain. NAP enhanced Tau—microtubule binding in the face of ADNP mutation, which is potentially protective against juvenile tauopathy. Study limitations reside in the constraints of a case report, comparison to a young adult and the focus on the ADNP syndrome. It should also be taken into consideration that previous brain MRI (unavailable) showed diffuse cortical atrophy of the brain parenchyma, marked reduction in volume of white matter as well as gliosis in both frontal and temporoparietal lobes that could indicate the sequelae of acute hepatic encephalopathy including a 3.3 cm large arachnoid cyst in middle cranial fossa. This pathology may have affected gene expression and tauopathy. Regardless, similar brain pathologies are shared by other ADNP patients with none (except for the current case) undergoing liver transplantations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the ADNP syndrome shares similarities with other ASD/ID syndromes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.orpha.net/consor/cgi-bin/OC_Exp.php?lng=EN&amp;Expert=404448">https://www.orpha.net/consor/cgi-bin/OC_Exp.php?lng=EN&amp;Expert=404448</ext-link>) broadening result impact. Lastly, a recent study in different ASD mouse models showing a strong Tau involvement may generalize our findings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Specifically, Tau reduction by transgenic mouse mating (<italic>Mapt</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup> or <italic>Mapt</italic><sup><italic>−/−</italic></sup> compared with <italic>Mapt</italic><sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>controls) ameliorated autistic features (e.g., repetitive self-grooming and social disinterest) in two different mouse lines, <italic>Scn1a</italic><sup><italic>RX/+</italic></sup> (sodium voltage-gated channel alpha subunit 1A-R1407* modeling Dravet syndrome) and <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup><italic>–/–</italic></sup> mice (contactin associated protein 2 representing a relatively prevalent autism-causing protein deficiency). Lowering tau also reduced megalencephaly toward normalization of brain size in these mice. In contrast, in a mouse line of <italic>Shank3B</italic><sup><italic>–/–</italic></sup> (SH3 and multiple ankyrin repeat domains 3 deficiency, modeling the Phelan McDermid Syndrome), Tau reduction was not beneficial. The authors suggested that the PI3K/Akt/mTOR (protease inhibitor 13/AKT Serine/Threonine kinase/mTOR) pathway, activated by interactions of Tau and PTEN (phosphatase and tensin homolog) plays a key role in the ASD development in the <italic>Scn1a</italic><sup><italic>RX/+</italic></sup> and the <italic>Cntnap2</italic><sup><italic>–/–</italic></sup> cases, but not in the <italic>Shank3B</italic><sup><italic>–/–</italic></sup> mouse<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Notably, MTOR was found to be regulated by ADNP in human postmortem tissues (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>) and in the <italic>Adnp</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup> mouse model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Regardless of the precise mechanism/pathway that may vary among different autistic syndromes (e.g., the ADNP syndrome is not characterized by megalencephaly), Tau pathology emerges as a key player in versatile ASD syndromes.</p>
<p id="Par40">In conclusion, the robust changes in gene expression linked to nervous tissue and organ development coupled to early onset brain tauopathy and exhibiting strong similarities to the <italic>Adnp</italic>-deficient inbred<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and outbred mouse<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, places ADNP as a highly conserved master gene regulator of human development. The identification of taoupathy, which might be associated with the observed MRI pathology in the ADNP patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> and potentially detected by advanced tau tangle imaging technologies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> coupled to the corrective effects of NAP (drug name CP201)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, paves the path for precision disease modifying therapeutics.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary information</title>
<sec id="Sec20">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
<media xlink:href="41398_2020_904_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">
<caption>
<p>Supplementary Information</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2">
<media xlink:href="41398_2020_904_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx">
<caption>
<p>Supplementary Table S1</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3">
<media xlink:href="41398_2020_904_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx">
<caption>
<p>Supplementary Table S2</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4">
<media xlink:href="41398_2020_904_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx">
<caption>
<p>Supplementary Table S3</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5">
<media xlink:href="41398_2020_904_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx">
<caption>
<p>Supplementary Table S4</p>
</caption>
</media>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
</fn>
<fn>
<p>These author contributed equally: Yanina Ivashko-Pachima, Tom Aharon Hait</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<sec>
<title>Supplementary information</title>
<p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at (10.1038/s41398-020-00904-4).</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>We thank the deceased child family for their contribution and cooperation. Dr. Ran Elkon for the help with statistical analyses. We further thank Dr. Metsada Pasmanik-Chor for her initial help with the bioinformatics analysis. This study is in partial fulfillment of the Ph.D. requirements for I. Grigg. Control brain tissue for this study was provided by Professor Iris Barshack, Associate Dean and Head of the Medical School, Tel Aviv University. We thank the ADNP Kids Research Foundation for continuous collaboration.</p>
<sec id="FPar1">
<title>Funding</title>
<p id="Par41">V.K. was supported by the CAS (RVO: 86652036) and LQ1604 NPU II, project BIOCEV (CZ.1.05/1.1.00/02.0109) from the ERDF, and MEYS CR. Professor I. Gozes held the first Lily and Avraham Gildor Chair for the Investigation of Growth Factors. Professor Gozes is supported by the following grants, ERA-NET neuron ADNPinMED (Professors Gozes and Kooy), AMN Foundation as well as Drs. Ronith and Armand Stemmer (French Friends of Tel Aviv University). T.A.H. (Ph.D. Mentors, Dr. Ran Elkon and Professor Ron Shamir) is supported in part by a fellowship from the Edmond J. Safra Center for Bioinformatics at Tel-Aviv University. Y.I-P. is supported in part by the Aufzien Family Center for the Prevention and Treatment of Parkinson’s Disease (APPD) postdoctoral fellowship and by a scholarship donated by Sandra Fischer, in the field of Alzheimer’s research, in memory of Nettie and Manuel Fisher.</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<notes notes-type="author-contribution">
<title>Author contributions</title>
<p>I. Grigg and V.K. conducted gene expression analysis. O.T., R.L., and N.G. performed the histological tissue staining experiments. Y.I-P. conducted cell culture imaging experiments. T.A.H. provided the bioinformatics datamining. Z.M. provided the postmortem tissues, M.A., J.V., A.V.D., and R.F.K. provided clinical data. I. Gozes designed the studies and wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p>
</notes>
<notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement">
<title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p id="Par42">Professor I. Gozes serves as the Chief Scientific Officer of Coronis Neurosciences developing CP201 for the ADNP syndrome.</p>
</notes>
<ref-list id="Bib1">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="CR1">
<label>1.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bassan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Complete sequence of a novel protein containing a femtomolar-activity-dependent neuroprotective peptide</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurochem.
          <year>1999</year>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>1283</fpage>
<lpage>1293</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.1999.0721283.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10037502</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR2">
<label>2.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zamostiano</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cloning and characterization of the human activity-dependent neuroprotective protein</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <year>2001</year>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>708</fpage>
<lpage>714</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M007416200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11013255</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR3">
<label>3.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Helsmoortel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A SWI/SNF-related autism syndrome caused by de novo mutations in ADNP</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>380</fpage>
<lpage>384</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2899</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24531329</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR4">
<label>4.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Deciphering Developmental Disorders S.</collab>
</person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence and architecture of de novo mutations in developmental disorders</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>542</volume>
<fpage>433</fpage>
<lpage>438</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature21062</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28135719</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR5">
<label>5.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stessman</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Targeted sequencing identifies 91 neurodevelopmental-disorder risk genes with autism and developmental-disability biases</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>515</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3792</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28191889</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR6">
<label>6.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Van Dijck</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Clinical presentation of a complex neurodevelopmental disorder caused by mutations in ADNP</article-title>
<source/>Biol. Psychiatry
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>287</fpage>
<lpage>297</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2018.02.1173</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29724491</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR7">
<label>7.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Amram N. et al. Sexual divergence in microtubule function: the novel intranasal microtubule targeting SKIP normalizes axonal transport and enhances memory. <italic>Mol. Psychiatry</italic><bold>21</bold>, 1467–1476 (2016).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR8">
<label>8.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Merenlender-Wagner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Autophagy has a key role in the pathophysiology of schizophrenia</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>126</fpage>
<lpage>132</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2013.174</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24365867</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR9">
<label>9.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mandel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spivak-Pohis</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ADNP differential nucleus/cytoplasm localization in neurons suggests multiple roles in neuronal differentiation and maintenance</article-title>
<source/>J. Mol. Neurosci.
          <year>2008</year>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>141</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12031-007-9013-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18286385</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR10">
<label>10.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hacohen-Kleiman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent neuroprotective protein deficiency models synaptic and developmental phenotypes of autism-like syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J. Clin. Investig.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>128</volume>
<fpage>4956</fpage>
<lpage>4969</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI98199</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30106381</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR11">
<label>11.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The NAP motif of activity-dependent neuroprotective protein (ADNP) regulates dendritic spines through microtubule end binding proteins</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2014</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1115</fpage>
<lpage>1124</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2014.97</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25178163</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR12">
<label>12.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ivashko-Pachima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sayas</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Malishkevich</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ADNP/NAP dramatically increase microtubule end-binding protein-Tau interaction: a novel avenue for protection against tauopathy</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>1335</fpage>
<lpage>1344</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2016.255</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28115743</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR13">
<label>13.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ivashko-Pachima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The ADNP derived peptide, NAP modulates the tubulin pool: implication for neurotrophic and neuroprotective activities</article-title>
<source/>PLoS ONE
          <year>2012</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>e51458</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051458</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23272107</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR14">
<label>14.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jouroukhin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>NAP (davunetide) modifies disease progression in a mouse model of severe neurodegeneration: protection against impairments in axonal transport</article-title>
<source/>Neurobiol. Dis.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>79</fpage>
<lpage>94</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2013.04.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23631872</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR15">
<label>15.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vulih-Shultzman</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent neuroprotective protein snippet NAP reduces tau hyperphosphorylation and enhances learning in a novel transgenic mouse model</article-title>
<source/>J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther.
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>323</volume>
<fpage>438</fpage>
<lpage>449</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.107.129551</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720885</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR16">
<label>16.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Quraishe</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cowan</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mudher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>NAP (davunetide) rescues neuronal dysfunction in a Drosophila model of tauopathy</article-title>
<source/>Mol. Psychiatry
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>834</fpage>
<lpage>842</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2013.32</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587881</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR17">
<label>17.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ivashko-Pachima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maor-Nof</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>NAP (davunetide) preferential interaction with dynamic 3-repeat Tau explains differential protection in selected tauopathies</article-title>
<source/>PLoS ONE
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>e0213666</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0213666</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30865715</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR18">
<label>18.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Premature primary tooth eruption in cognitive/motor-delayed ADNP-mutated children</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2017</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>e1166</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2017.128</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28675391</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR19">
<label>19.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ivashko-Pachima Y. et al. Discovery of autism/intellectual disability somatic mutations in Alzheimer’s brains: mutated ADNP cytoskeletal impairments and repair as a case study. <italic>Mol. Psychiatry</italic> (2019). (EPUB)</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR20">
<label>20.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carithers</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A novel approach to high-quality postmortem tissue procurement: the GTEx project</article-title>
<source/>Biopreserv. Biobank.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>311</fpage>
<lpage>319</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/bio.2015.0032</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484571</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR21">
<label>21.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Subramanian</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA
          <year>2005</year>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>15545</fpage>
<lpage>15550</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0506580102</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199517</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR22">
<label>22.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hait</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The EXPANDER integrated platform for transcriptome analysis</article-title>
<source/>J. Mol. Biol.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>431</volume>
<fpage>2398</fpage>
<lpage>2406</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2019.05.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31100387</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR23">
<label>23.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</article-title>
<source/>Nucleic Acids Res.
          <year>2000</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>30</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.27</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592173</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR24">
<label>24.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liberzon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) hallmark gene set collection</article-title>
<source/>Cell Syst.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>417</fpage>
<lpage>425</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cels.2015.12.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26771021</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR25">
<label>25.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Escher</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Anti-inflammatory effects of the octapeptide NAP in human microbiota-associated mice suffering from Subacute Ileitis</article-title>
<source/>Eur. J. Microbiol. Immunol.
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>34</fpage>
<lpage>40</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/1886.2018.00006</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR26">
<label>26.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heimesaat</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giladi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuhl</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bereswill</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The octapetide NAP alleviates intestinal and extra-intestinal anti-inflammatory sequelae of acute experimental colitis</article-title>
<source/>Peptides
          <year>2018</year>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.peptides.2017.12.023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29288684</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR27">
<label>27.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mandel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rechavi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent neuroprotective protein (ADNP) differentially interacts with chromatin to regulate genes essential for embryogenesis</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Biol.
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>303</volume>
<fpage>814</fpage>
<lpage>824</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.11.039</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17222401</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR28">
<label>28.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ha</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Swanson</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldowitz</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A novel and multivalent role of Pax6 in cerebellar development.</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <year>2016</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>9057</fpage>
<lpage>9069</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4385-15.2016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27581449</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR29">
<label>29.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sragovich</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>The autism/neuroprotection-linked ADNP/NAP regulate the excitatory glutamatergic synapse</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>2</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-018-0357-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30664622</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR30">
<label>30.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Glaser</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>PAX6 gene dosage effect in a family with congenital cataracts, aniridia, anophthalmia and central nervous system defects</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>1994</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>463</fpage>
<lpage>471</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0894-463</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7951315</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR31">
<label>31.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heins</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Glial cells generate neurons: the role of the transcription factor Pax6</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <year>2002</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>308</fpage>
<lpage>315</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn828</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896398</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR32">
<label>32.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mandel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent neuroprotective protein constitutes a novel element in the SWI/SNF chromatin remodeling complex</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <year>2007</year>
<volume>282</volume>
<fpage>34448</fpage>
<lpage>34456</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M704756200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878164</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR33">
<label>33.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hacohen-Kleiman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Atypical auditory brainstem response and protein expression aberrations related to ASD and hearing loss in the adnp haploinsufficient mouse brain</article-title>
<source/>Neurochem. Res.
          <year>2019</year>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>1494</fpage>
<lpage>1507</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11064-019-02723-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659505</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR34">
<label>34.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Muenke</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>A common mutation in the fibroblast growth factor receptor 1 gene in Pfeiffer syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Genet.
          <year>1994</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>269</fpage>
<lpage>274</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1194-269</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7874169</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR35">
<label>35.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Villanueva</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Roux</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>FGFR1 mutations in Kallmann syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Front. Horm. Res.
          <year>2010</year>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>61</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000312693</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20389085</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR36">
<label>36.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trokovic</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trokovic</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mai</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Partanen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fgfr1 regulates patterning of the pharyngeal region</article-title>
<source/>Genes Dev.
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>141</fpage>
<lpage>153</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.250703</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12514106</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR37">
<label>37.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tai</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Tau reduction prevents key features of autism in mouse models</article-title>
<source/>Neuorn
          <year>2020</year>
<volume>106</volume>
<fpage>421</fpage>
<lpage>437</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2020.01.038</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR38">
<label>38.</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other">La Joie R. et al. Prospective longitudinal atrophy in Alzheimer’s disease correlates with the intensity and topography of baseline tau-PET. <italic>Sci. Transl. Med.</italic><bold>12</bold>, eaau5732 (2020).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR39">
<label>39.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tomasoni</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>SNAP-25 regulates spine formation through postsynaptic binding to p140Cap</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <year>2013</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>2136</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms3136</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23868368</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR40">
<label>40.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Malishkevich</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leyk</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldbaum</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Richter-Landsberg</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ADNP/ADNP2 expression in oligodendrocytes: implication for myelin-related neurodevelopment</article-title>
<source/>J. Mol. Neurosci.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>304</fpage>
<lpage>313</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12031-015-0640-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26315608</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR41">
<label>41.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Malishkevich</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent neuroprotective protein (ADNP) exhibits striking sexual dichotomy impacting on autistic and Alzheimer’s pathologies</article-title>
<source/>Transl. Psychiatry
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>e501</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2014.138</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25646590</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR42">
<label>42.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pinhasov</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal></etal>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent neuroprotective protein: a novel gene essential for brain formation</article-title>
<source/>Dev. Brain Res.
          <year>2003</year>
<volume>144</volume>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<lpage>90</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-3806(03)00162-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12888219</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="CR43">
<label>43.</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vaisburd</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shemer</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeheskel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giladi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gozes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Risperidone and NAP protect cognition and normalize gene expression in a schizophrenia mouse model</article-title>
<source/>Sci. Rep.
          <year>2015</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>16300</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep16300</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26553741</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>