<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">

<pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Rep</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell Rep</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Cell Reports</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">2211-1247</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Cell Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32783927</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7435362</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2211-1247(20)30973-6</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2020.107988</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">107988</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Input-Output Relationship of CA1 Pyramidal Neurons Reveals Intact Homeostatic Mechanisms in a Mouse Model of Fragile X Syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
<name>
<surname>Booker</surname>
<given-names>Sam A.</given-names>
</name>
<email>sbooker@ed.ac.uk</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">∗</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
<name>
<surname>Simões de Oliveira</surname>
<given-names>Laura</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
<name>
<surname>Anstey</surname>
<given-names>Natasha J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
<name>
<surname>Kozic</surname>
<given-names>Zrinko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
<name>
<surname>Dando</surname>
<given-names>Owen R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>Adam D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
<name>
<surname>Baxter</surname>
<given-names>Paul S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
<name>
<surname>Isom</surname>
<given-names>Lori L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9">
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>Diane L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10">
<name>
<surname>Hardingham</surname>
<given-names>Giles E.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au11">
<name>
<surname>Brophy</surname>
<given-names>Peter J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au12">
<name>
<surname>Wyllie</surname>
<given-names>David J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="au13">
<name>
<surname>Kind</surname>
<given-names>Peter C.</given-names>
</name>
<email>pkind@ed.ac.uk</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">8</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2">∗∗</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Centre for Discovery Brain Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Simons Initiative for the Developing Brain, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Patrick Wild Centre for Autism Research, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Dementia Research Institute, University of Edinburgh, Hugh Robson Building, George Square, Edinburgh EH8 9XD, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Centre for Brain Development and Repair, InStem, GKVK Campus, Bangalore 560065, India</aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Pharmacology, University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, MI 48109-5632, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author <email>sbooker@ed.ac.uk</email></corresp>
<corresp id="cor2"><label>∗∗</label>Corresponding author <email>pkind@ed.ac.uk</email></corresp>
<fn id="fn1">
<label>7</label>
<p id="ntpara0010">These authors contributed equally</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn2">
<label>8</label>
<p id="ntpara0015">Lead Contact</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>107988</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>28</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>1</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>14</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
<license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract id="abs0010">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>Cellular hyperexcitability is a salient feature of fragile X syndrome animal models. The cellular basis of hyperexcitability and how it responds to changing activity states is not fully understood. Here, we show increased axon initial segment length in CA1 of the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mouse hippocampus, with increased cellular excitability. This change in length does not result from reduced AIS plasticity, as prolonged depolarization induces changes in AIS length independent of genotype. However, depolarization does reduce cellular excitability, the magnitude of which is greater in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons. Finally, we observe reduced functional inputs from the entorhinal cortex, with no genotypic difference in the firing rates of CA1 pyramidal neurons. This suggests that AIS-dependent hyperexcitability in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice may result from adaptive or homeostatic regulation induced by reduced functional synaptic connectivity. Thus, while AIS length and intrinsic excitability contribute to cellular hyperexcitability, they may reflect a homeostatic mechanism for reduced synaptic input onto CA1 neurons.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015">
<title>Graphical Abstract</title>
<fig id="undfig1" position="anchor">
<graphic xlink:href="fx1"></graphic>
</fig>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020">
<title>Highlights</title>
<p>
<list id="ulist0010" list-type="simple">
<list-item id="u0010">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0010"><italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons in CA1 are hyperexcitable, with longer axon initial segments</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0015">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0015">Pyramidal cells respond more strongly to prolonged depolarization in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0020">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0020">Temporoammonic input to CA1 is reduced in the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mouse</p>
</list-item>
<list-item id="u0025">
<label>•</label>
<p id="p0025">Cellular hyperexcitability equalizes neuron firing to reduced temporoammonic input</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025">
<p>Neuronal hyperexcitability may underlie many features of fragile X syndrome. Booker et al. show that in hippocampal area CA1, pyramidal neurons are hyperexcitable, with longer axon initial segments. This hyperexcitability helps neurons to overcome a strong reduction in synaptic input from the entorhinal cortex, thus homeostatically regulating local network outputs.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>fragile X syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>ASD/ID</kwd>
<kwd>axon initial segment</kwd>
<kwd>hyperexcitability</kwd>
<kwd>homeostasis</kwd>
<kwd>structural plasticity</kwd>
<kwd>intrinsic excitability</kwd>
<kwd>whole-cell patch clamp</kwd>
<kwd>2-photon microscopy</kwd>
<kwd>hippocampus</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<p id="misc0010">Published: August 11, 2020</p>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="p0030">Fragile X syndrome (FXS) is the leading single gene cause of intellectual disability, with co-occurring autism, hyperactivity, and epilepsy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hagerman et al., 1996</xref>). FXS results from hypermethylation of the <italic>FMR1</italic> gene and loss of the protein FMRP. Rodent models of FXS have revealed a role for FMRP in directly and indirectly regulating cellular and local circuit excitability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Contractor et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gibson et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). They also display behavioral phenotypes, such as increased susceptibility to audiogenic seizures that have been linked to cellular/circuit hyperexcitability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Dölen et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Musumeci et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Osterweil et al., 2010</xref>). Furthermore, it has been suggested that impairments in learning and memory may result, in part, from these alterations in cellular excitability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Contractor et al., 2015</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0035">Cellular excitability is tightly regulated by, for example, intrinsic mechanisms such as ion channel density and function, synaptic mechanisms that regulate the balance of excitation to inhibition (E:I balance), and the regulation of action potential (AP) initiation at the axon initial segment (AIS). FMRP has been shown to directly regulate excitability through direct FMRP-ion channel interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Deng and Klyachko, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Deng et al., 2013</xref>). The loss of FMRP also potentially alters the translational regulation, and hence the density and/or activity-dependent expression of ion channels and synaptic proteins critical for regulating excitability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Antoine et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Booker et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brager et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Bülow et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Bureau et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gibson et al., 2008</xref>). However, changes in cellular excitability may not be a direct consequence of the loss of FMRP; rather, excitability phenotypes may arise as a compensatory or homeostatic change to try to normalize neuronal excitability following altered FMRP-dependent events. Recent findings indicate that the altered E:I balance observed in the mouse model of FXS serves to normalize neuronal excitability in the primary somatosensory cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Antoine et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Domanski et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0040">The AIS plays a key role in regulating neuronal excitability. The AIS originates from the soma or proximal dendrite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Thome et al., 2014</xref>), where it is required for the correct integration and dynamic control of AP generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Leterrier (2016)</xref>). Although axonal APs can still be evoked when the AIS is dissolved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Zonta et al., 2011</xref>), spontaneously generated APs are abolished, and the waveform of the AP is altered. The AIS is composed of specific cytoskeletal elements (i.e., ankyrin G and β4-spectrin) and a high density of voltage-gated sodium channels (VSGCs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Leterrier, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Ogawa and Rasband, 2008</xref>). The AIS is not static, but can regulate its length and position in response to changing neuronal activity states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Grubb and Burrone, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Grubb et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Gutzmann et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Kuba et al., 2010</xref>). Hence, it can act as a means of homeostatic regulation the neuron AP discharge in response to changing activity levels. For example, in cultured dentate granule cells, the AIS shortens in length following prolonged depolarization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Grubb et al., 2011</xref>), while <italic>in vivo</italic>, the AIS has been suggested to increase in length following prolonged sensory deprivation, and modulate VGSC density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Gutzmann et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Kuba, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Kuba et al., 2010</xref>). However, these homeostatic alterations to AIS length and function require long-term alteration in neuronal activity, which at present have not been observed in CA1 of the hippocampus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Klemmer et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0045">Despite playing a key role in regulating cellular excitability, the AIS has received little attention in FXS, or in developmental disorders more generally. A notable exception is an increase in AIS length observed in the Angelman syndrome model of intellectual disability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Kaphzan et al., 2011</xref>), which shares some excitability features with FXS, as well as a variety of epilepsy mouse models also displaying AIS-dependent phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Wimmer et al., 2010</xref>). Here, we directly examine whether the AIS is altered in a mouse model of FXS. We focus on pyramidal cells of the hippocampal area CA1, due to emerging evidence for enhanced cellular excitability of these neurons in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−<italic>/y</italic></sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Luque et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Talbot et al., 2018</xref>). The present study combines immunohistological labeling, whole-cell patch-clamp recordings, and live 2-photon imaging to test the hypothesis that AIS pathology contributes to the excitability phenotypes of <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−<italic>/y</italic></sup> mice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec2.1">
<title>CA1 PCs Are Hyperexcitable in the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−/y</italic></sup> Mouse, Resulting from Increased AIS Lengths</title>
<p id="p0050">To assess the excitability of CA1 pyramidal cells (PCs) we performed whole-cell patch-clamp recordings from acute hippocampal slices of postnatal (P) days 28–35 wild-type (WT) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> littermate mice. We measured the active properties of CA1 PCs in response to small depolarizing steps (25 pA, 500 ms), all from a holding potential of −70 mV to induce well-controlled AP discharge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>A). Analysis of AP discharge revealed a leftward shift in the current-frequency response in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−</italic>/y</sup> mice compared to that in WT mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>B). WT CA1 PCs (33 cells from 15 mice) reliably produced APs with a rheobase current of 156.8 ± 11.6 pA, with a voltage threshold of −42.6 ± 0.6 mV, and peak AP discharge of 36.2 ± 1.1 Hz. In <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−</italic>/y</sup> littermates (29 cells from 14 mice), we observed a significantly lower rheobase current of 111.7 ± 10.8 pA (χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(df60)</sub> = 16.6, p = 4.6 × 10<sup>−5</sup>, generalized form of the linear mixed-effects model [GLMM]), resulting from a more hyperpolarized voltage threshold of −45.9 ± 1.1 mV (χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(df60)</sub> = 13.5, p = 0.0002, GLMM). The maximum firing of <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons was 38.9 ± 1.0 Hz, not significantly higher than WT (t<sub>(11,8)</sub> = 1.53, p = 0.50, Holm-Sidak test). To confirm that this hyperexcitability was due to an altered voltage threshold, we measured passive membrane properties in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> and WT mice. CA1 PCs from WT mice had a resting membrane potential of −60.2 ± 1.4 mV and, in response to small, hyperpolarizing steps (−10 pA, 500 ms), an input resistance of 162.1 ± 14.2 MΩ. In <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−</italic>/y</sup> mice, the input resistance was not different from that of WT mice (169.4 ± 10.6 MΩ, χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(df60)</sub> = 0.81, p = 0.37, GLMM); however, the resting membrane potential was substantially more hyperpolarized (−64.2 ± 1.9 mV, χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(df60)</sub> = 8.9, p = 0.003, GLMM). We observed no difference in AP kinetic properties, such as amplitude, half-height duration, or maximum rates of rise or decay, which are detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Table S1</xref>. Furthermore, a full summary of all of the statistical tests performed in the present study is provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">Table S2</xref>. These data show that CA1 PCs in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice appear hyperexcitable due to a reduced threshold for AP discharge.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Increased CA1 PC Excitability and AIS Length in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> Mice</p><p>(A) Representative voltage responses from WT (black) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−<italic>/y</italic></sup> mice (red), in response to depolarizing current steps (0–400 pA, 25 pA steps, 500 ms duration).</p><p>(B) Current frequency plot for WT mice (33 cells from 15 mice) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−<italic>/y</italic></sup> mice (29 cells from 14 mice), indicating increased AP discharge.</p><p>(C–F) Quantification of (C) rheobase, (D) voltage threshold, (E) resting membrane potential, and (F) input resistance from both genotypes.</p><p>(G) Top: overview flattened confocal stacks of CA1 labeled for ankyrinG (green pseudocolor) and NeuN (blue pseudocolor). Bottom: high-power magnification of a single AIS. The AIS total extent is indicated (dashed line). Scale bars (top): 20 μm, (bottom): 5 μm.</p><p>(H) Average cumulative distributions (thick lines) of AIS lengths across all mice examined for each genotype. Cumulative distributions for individual mice shown below (thin lines).</p><p>(I) Quantification of AIS length for each genotype (750 AIS from 8 WT mice, 896 AIS from 9 <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice). All bar chart data are overlain by the averages of individual mice, with the total mice analyzed in parentheses.</p><p>ns, p &gt; 0.05, <sup>∗</sup>p &lt; 0.05 from 2-way RM ANOVA (B) and GLMM (C–I). All of the data are shown as means ± SEMs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0055">The presence of a high density of sodium channels at the AIS, and its role in controlling the voltage threshold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Kole et al., 2008</xref>) led us to ask whether the AIS was structurally altered in the FXS mouse model, as in the Angelman syndrome mouse model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Kaphzan et al., 2011</xref>). Immunohistochemical labeling was performed on hippocampal sections from perfusion-fixed mice using ankyrinG, a specific AIS marker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>G). AnkyrinG reliably labeled AISs emerging from the soma (∼80% of AISs) or a proximal dendrite (∼20% of AISs), which entered the <italic>Stratum oriens</italic> (<italic>str. oriens)</italic> of CA1. The average AIS length in WT mice was 25.9 ± 0.3 μm (750 AISs from 8 mice); meanwhile, <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice had AISs that on average were 20% longer, with an average length of 31.0 ± 0.3 μm (896 AISs from 9 mice; t-ratio<sub>(df10)</sub> = −3.67, p = 0.0046, GLMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>H and 1I). We confirmed that the number of AISs measured per mouse was sufficient to define the difference we observed using bootstrapping analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref>A and S1B). We observed similar distances from the soma for AISs measured in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> CA1 PCs (2.7 ± 0.2 μm from soma) as compared to WT (3.2 ± 0.2 μm, p = 0.30, LMM; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S1</xref>C). To determine whether these effects on AIS length were specific to the CA1 or were more widespread across the brain, we next assessed the AIS length in the medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC) and hippocampal subfield CA3 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref>E–S1H). In both areas tested, the AIS length was longer in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice, with 12% and 11% longer AISs from layer 5 (L5) mPFC and CA3, respectively. Analysis of the intrinsic excitability of L5 mPFC PCs revealed that while these neurons showed increased excitability, this was not associated with any change in voltage threshold or rheobase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S1</xref>I–S1K). These data suggest that while AIS length may be longer in these other brain areas, it is does not contribute to large physiological changes.</p>
<p id="p0060">As many factors contribute to the overall excitability of a given neuron, we next asked whether this change in AIS length was sufficient to account for the altered voltage threshold. To address this, we produced a single-cell computational model of a CA1 PC based on realistic constraints (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Migliore, 2003</xref>) and altered AIS length, assuming no change in sodium-channel density (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>). Under these conditions, only changing the AIS length results in near-identical changes in voltage threshold and rheobase, without affecting the maximum discharge rate. These data reveal an increase in CA1 PC excitability, primarily due to a voltage threshold change. Furthermore, the region-specific increase in AIS length observed in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice is sufficient to account for the altered excitability.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.2">
<title>CA1 PCs in Acute Hippocampal Slices Display Activity-Dependent Excitability Changes, Which Is Enhanced in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−/y</italic></sup> Mice</title>
<p id="p0065">A key feature of neuronal excitability is its ability to self-modulate in the face of sustained alterations to ongoing activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Marder and Prinz, 2002</xref>). The ability of neurons to undergo such homeostatic regulation has been shown to be enhanced in the mouse model of FXS, albeit in cultured neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Bülow et al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, we next asked whether the enhanced excitability we observe in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice results from underlying changes in cell homeostasis, leading to the inappropriate regulation of cell function, using a paradigm previously reported to depolarize neurons over short (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Evans et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Grubb et al., 2011</xref>) and long (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Grubb and Burrone, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">O’Leary et al., 2010</xref>) timescales <italic>in vitro</italic>. To directly assess the effect of depolarization in a cell-wise manner, we performed whole-cell patch-clamp recordings from the same CA1 PCs before and after 3-h application of 15 mM KCl, using 15 mM NaCl as an osmotic control. Cells were targeted by the inclusion of Alexa Fluor 488 (100 μM) in the patch pipette to allow recording from the same neuron and to examine intrinsic physiology at both time points (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>A and 2B). From recordings of WT CA1 PCs, 3-h treatment with 15 mM NaCl did not alter the current-frequency relationship (t<sub>1, 11</sub> = 0.51, p = 0.49, repeated-measures [RM] 2-way ANOVA; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>C, left) or any other measure physiological property measured. By comparison, 3-h treatment with 15 mM KCl resulted in a small but significant decrease in AP discharge in WT CA1 PCs (t<sub>1, 18</sub> = 6.37, p = 0.02, RM 2-way ANOVA; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>C, right), consistent with previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Evans et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">O’Leary et al., 2010</xref>). This change in AP discharge was paired with a 39% increase in the rheobase current from 159 ± 13 pA under control to 221 ± 24 pA after KCl (p = 0.002, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>E) and a 23% reduction in input resistance (p = 0.05, LMM), as well as altered K<sup>+</sup> channel function, as the AP decay rate was slowed by 14% (p = 0.05, LMM). However, we observed no change in voltage threshold (2% depolarized, p = 0.91, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>F). These findings suggest that AIS structure may be unrelated to the observed physiological changes following such treatment in <italic>ex vivo</italic> brain tissue, which are likely due to multiple, complementary K<sup>+</sup>-channel mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Kole et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Kuba et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">O’Leary et al., 2010</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Intrinsic Physiological Plasticity and Homeostatic Responses in WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> Mice</p><p>(A and B) Representative voltage responses from (A) WT (black) and (B) <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> (red) CA1 PCs to current injections, from −70 mV (0–400 pA, 25 pA steps, 500 ms duration).</p><p>(C) Current frequency plots for the same CA1 PCs from WT mice, when recorded before (top) and after (bottom) 3-h NaCl (12 cells from 5 mice) or KCl (19 cells from 8 mice) applications.</p><p>(D) According to the same format as (C), but for <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (NaCl: 7 cells from 4 mice; KCl: 18 cells from 8 mice).</p><p>(E and F) Pairwise analysis of rheobase current (E) and voltage threshold (F) from the same WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> CA1 PCs.</p><p>(G) Subtracted AP discharge across the range of injected currents given to CA1 PCs.</p><p>ns, p &gt; 0.05, <sup>∗</sup>p &lt; 0.05 from GLMM (E–G) and 2-way RM ANOVA (C, D, and H). All of the data are shown as means ± SEMs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0070">We next assessed the effect of sustained depolarization on the function of <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> CA1 PCs in acute brain slices. 15 mM of KCl also appeared to very strongly attenuate the current-frequency relationship in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (t<sub>1, 17</sub> = 21.95, p = 0.0002, RM 2-way ANOVA; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>B and 2D); 15 mM NaCl treatment for 3 h had no effect on AP discharge (t<sub>1, 6</sub> = 0.14, p = 0.72, RM 2-way ANOVA; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>D, left). Similar to observations from WT mice, we observed a 66% increase in rheobase from 113 ± 11 pA to 188 ± 18 pA; (p = 0.004, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>E) and a tendency to decreased input resistance (−14%, 197 ± 22 MΩ to 167 ± 20 MΩ; p = 0.17, LMM). As for WT mice, we saw no change in voltage threshold following KCl treatment (p = 0.95, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>F). We observed an 18% slowing of the AP decay rate (p = 0.008, GLMM), indicative of a potentially similar role of K<sup>+</sup> channels in this physiological plasticity as in WT neurons. To allow us to compare the change in AP discharge between WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice, we subtracted the number of APs produced following KCl application from the control measurement, as each current step tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>G). We observed a much larger decrease in the number of APs elicited by <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> CA1 PCs, compared to WT (F<sub>1, 35</sub> = 23.84, p &lt; 0.0001, 2-way ANOVA), which was most apparent over the range of 175–300 pA (interaction: F <sub>1, 35</sub> = 2.225, p = 0.0052; Bonferroni post-tests T<sub>17,20</sub> = 3.0, 3.0, 3.2, 3.3, 3.3, 3.2; p = 0.05, 0.04, 0.03, 0.02, 0.02, 0.03) In no tested intrinsic parameter did we observe a change following the 3-h treatment with NaCl treatment. These data clearly show that responses to prolonged depolarization are present in both WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice; however, the latter respond more strongly to depolarizing stimuli, leading to reduced AP generation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.3">
<title>Short-Term Depolarization Results in AIS Shortening in WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−/y</italic></sup> Cultured Neurons but Lengthening in Intact Tissue</title>
<p id="p0075">We show above that prolonged depolarization of neurons in <italic>ex vivo</italic> tissue leads to a reduction in cellular excitability. Previously, it was shown that the application of 15 mM KCl reduces AIS length, over short timescales in cultured dentate gyrus neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Evans et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Grubb et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, we asked whether this form of plasticity was present in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> CA1 neurons, perhaps accounting for the differences in AIS length, baseline excitability, and enhanced cellular responses observed.</p>
<p id="p0080">To address this, we used the same 15 mM KCl or NaCl treatment as we used for the physiological manipulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>), but in a subset of acute hippocampal slices. Following slicing and recovery, slices were transferred to chambers containing artificial cerebrospinal fluid (ACSF), treated for 3 h with 15 mM KCl or NaCl (as osmotic control) then fixed and immunolabeled for ankyrinG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>A). Following 15 mM KCl treatment of slices, we observed AIS lengths in WT mice of 28.7 ± 1.7 μm, which were 11% longer than that of 15 mM NaCl osmotic controls (25.8 ± 1.4 μm, p &lt; 0.001, GLMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>B). In <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−</italic>/y</sup> slices, we also observed a similar increase in AIS length, with AIS lengths following 15 mM KCl treatment of 29.4 ± 1.9 μm, 11% longer than NaCl controls (26.6 ± 1.6 μm; p &lt; 0.001, GLMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>I). We observed no change in AIS distance from the soma following the 3-h 15 mM KCl treatment, as compared to NaCl controls (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S2</xref>B). These data clearly indicate that short-term structural AIS shortening in CA1 neurons, over the timescales as described previously in cultured dentate gyrus neurons, is absent from the intact tissue from WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice. In 10-day-old mice, we observed a very small shortening of the AIS in WT mice after 3 h KCl, which was not present in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S3</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Short-Term AIS Shortening Is Absent in Acute Slices after Sustained Depolarization</p><p>(A) Representative flattened confocal stack of AIS labeled in acute hippocampal slices from WT (top) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (bottom), following 3-h incubation with 15 mM KCl (right) or NaCl osmotic controls (left). AISs were visualized with ankyrinG (green pseudocolor) and measured in neurons labeled with NeuN (blue pseudocolor). Scale bars: 20 μm.</p><p>(B) Quantification of AIS length following 3-h application of 15 mM KCl, compared to NaCl osmotic controls in WT mice. Average AIS length of each mouse tested is shown overlaid.</p><p>(C) The same analysis as in (B), but in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice.</p><p>(D) AIS measured in primary dissociated hippocampal cell cultures produced from WT (left) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> (right) mice following 3 h of 15 mM NaCl or KCl and labeled with ankyrinG (green) and NeuN (blue). Scale bars: 20 μm (top), 10 μm (bottom).</p><p>(E) Quantification of AIS length under control conditions from WT (black) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> (red) single-mouse cultures. The average AIS length per mouse (from 2 coverslips) is shown overlain; the number of mice is indicated in parentheses.</p><p>(F) AIS lengths plotted for WT mouse cultured neurons following 3 h of 15 mM KCl and NaCl.</p><p>(G) AIS lengths of <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons following 15 mM KCl and NaCl application.</p><p>(H) Comparative difference in AIS length (KCl length − NaCl length), plotted for each mouse.</p><p>ns, p &gt; 0.05, <sup>∗</sup>p &lt; 0.05, from LMM (B–G) and Student’s 2-tailed unpaired t test (H). All of the data are shown as means ± SEMs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"></graphic></fig></p>
<p id="p0085">As this form of plasticity has only been previously reported in cell culture, we finally asked whether we could confirm that this form of plasticity was present in our hands and test whether <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons are capable of shortening. To examine the AIS structure in dissociated hippocampal cultures of WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>D), we fixed coverslips at day <italic>in vitro</italic> 10 (DIV10), before and after 15 mM KCl or NaCl treatment and then measured the AIS from ankyrinG labeling. In WT primary hippocampal neurons, the AIS had an average length of 29.9 ± 1.0 μm. Similar to observations in fixed brains, <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons had AISs that on average were 7% longer than those of WT mice (32.1 ± 0.7 μm, p &lt; 0.001, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>E), confirming that hippocampal cultures obey the same relationship as observed in <italic>ex vivo</italic> tissue. Following the 15 mM KCl addition to the culture medium for 3 h, the WT AIS length in 15 mM KCl was 28.1 ± 1.2 μm, which is 10% shorter than NaCl controls (31.1 ± 1.2 μm, p &lt; 0.001, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>F). In <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> cultures, we observed similar AIS shortening, with 15 mM KCl (30.3 ± 0.8 μm) being 7% shorter than NaCl controls (32.7 ± 1.1 μm, p &lt; 0.001, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>G). The degree of AIS shortening between KCl and NaCl was modest but similar for both WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (p = 0.41, T<sub>(df29)</sub> = 0.82, 2-tailed Student’s t test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>H). These data indicate that short-term structural AIS plasticity is present in cultured WT and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons, but that different or additional factors may regulate structural plasticity following sustained depolarization in hippocampal neurons, such as the presence of an intact extracellular matrix. Furthermore, these findings suggest a functional disconnect between AP discharge properties and AIS length following prolonged depolarization.</p>
<p id="p0090">One limitation of the above data is that AIS lengths before and after plasticity induction are measured in fixed tissue from different slices, thus precluding the direct measurement of potential within-cell shortening of AIS. As such, we next asked whether the AIS length of individual CA1 PCs were plastic during the application of 15 mM KCl. To address this, we performed 2-photon live imaging of acute hippocampal slices from a new transgenic mouse expressing GFP fused to the sodium channel β1 subunit (β1-NaV-GFP) that reliably labelled the AIS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>A and 4B) and which faithfully reflected ankyrinG immunolabeling (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S4</xref>). This transgenic mouse was crossed with the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mouse line and 2-photon z stacks of images containing <italic>str. pyramidale</italic>, and proximal <italic>str. oriens</italic> of CA1 were collected before and after a 3-h treatment with either 15 mM KCl or 15 mM NaCl; AIS lengths were then measured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>C). A comparison of the starting AIS length to the final length showed no difference between either 15 mM NaCl or 15 mM KCl in WT (F<sub>1, 158</sub> = 0.62, p = 0.43, sum-of-least-squares F-test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>D) or <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (F<sub>1, 85</sub> = 1.63, p = 0.21, sum-of-least-squares F-test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>E). Comparing the AIS length change between treatments from live imaging in WT mice, we observed that 3-h 15 mM NaCl treatment produced an average of 1.6 ± 1.0 μm increases in length, which are not different from the 1.1 ± 1.0 μm increases in length produced by 15 mM KCl treatment (p = 0.67, LMM). NaCl application to brain slices from <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice produced a 1.6 ± 1.3 μm shortening of the AIS, which is not different from the 2.1 ± 2.0 μm shortening observed in KCl (p = 1.0, LMM). Finally, modeling AIS lengths over the ranges we measured from CA1 PCs reveals that AIS length has the ability to change both AP discharge threshold and rheobase in a non-linear manner. However, small changes in membrane resistance, such as those we observed following KCl treatment, may best describe the homeostatic changes in rheobase that we observed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figures S2</xref>H and S2I). These data further confirm that short-term, depolarization-induced AIS shortening is absent in the <italic>ex vivo</italic> tissue of CA1, even when measured at the single-cell level in real time.<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Live Imaging of the AIS Fails to Reveal Short-Term Structural Plasticity</p><p>(A) Low-power flattened confocal stack of CA1 of the hippocampus showing β1-NaV-GFP (β1-GFP, green pseudocolor) expression compared to ankyrinG (red pseudocolor), showing an overlapping distribution. Scale bar: 100 μm.</p><p>(B) High magnification of a β1-NaV-GFP labeled PC and AIS, demonstrating faithful overlap of GFP with ankyrinG labeling. Scale bar: 20 μm.</p><p>(C) Representative 2-photon images of CA1 showing β1-NaV-GFP labeling under control conditions (0 h) compared to 3 h of treatment with 15 mM NaCl (top) or KCl (bottom). Scale bar: 10 μm.</p><p>(D) Comparison of AIS length before (x axis) to the AIS length 3 h later for 15 mM NaCl (filled circles) and 15 mM KCl (open circles) in WT CA1 PCs. Data are shown for 99 AISs treated with NaCl and 65 AISs treated with KCl from 7 WT mice and fitted with linear regression (solid line, NaCl; dashed line, KCl).</p><p>(E) The same data as in (D), but plotted for 44 AISs treated with NaCl and 45 AISs treated with KCl from 5 <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice.</p><p>All of the data are shown as individual cell replicates with, where appropriate, fitted linear relationships.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2.4">
<title>Reduced Temporoammonic (TA) Input to CA1 Accounts for Homeostatic Changes to PCs</title>
<p id="p0095">The data we have presented so far show that CA1 PCs in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice are hyperexcitable due to increased AP discharge related to increased AIS length and greater short-term adaptation of membrane excitability. These observations could reflect homeostatic remodeling of CA1 PCs in the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mouse, in response to reduced excitatory tone. To determine whether extrinsic TA input to CA1 is reduced in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice, we performed correlated extracellular field and whole-cell patch-clamp recordings from CA1, combined with electrical stimulation of the TA afferents. Brief trains of electrical stimuli (5 stimuli at 20 Hz, 200 μs stimulus duration) were delivered via a bipolar, twisted NiChrome wire placed in distal <italic>str. lacunosum-moleculare</italic> ∼1 mm distal to CA1. Input-output relationships were recorded as both somatic whole-cell excitatory postsynaptic potentials (EPSP) or field EPSPs (fEPSPs; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>A) from <italic>str. lacunosum-moleculare</italic> of CA1. To first assess the degree of TA afferent recruitment, we measured the afferent fiber volley from fEPSP recordings. We observed that increasing constant voltage stimuli resulted in a linearly increasing fiber volley. The relative recruitment of the fiber volley was similar in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> slices, when compared to WT (F<sub>1, 348</sub> = 2.12, p = 0.15, sum-of-least-squares F-test), suggesting the equivalent recruitment of entorhinal afferents, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Wahlstrom-Helgren and Klyachko, 2015</xref>). To determine whether synaptic responses from the TA pathway were altered, we measured both the dendritic field and somatic whole-cell responses, measured as a function of fiber volley amplitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>B). Despite unchanged fiber volley amplitudes, the input-output response for fEPSPs in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> brain slices was significantly reduced compared to WT in both peak amplitude (F<sub>1, 348</sub> = 33.7, p &lt; 0.0001, sum-of-least-squares F-test) and area under the curve (F<sub>1, 303</sub> = 32.1, p &lt; 0.0001, sum-of-least-squares F-test). Consistent with this observation, whole-cell EPSPs also showed lower input-output relationships (F<sub>1, 346</sub> = 5.55, p = 0.019, sum-of-least-squares F-test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>G), indicating that dendritic filtering is insufficient to overcome reduced synaptic inputs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brager et al., 2012</xref>). As synaptic inhibition and excitation is known to be altered at TA inputs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Wahlstrom-Helgren and Klyachko, 2015</xref>), we next asked whether altered inhibition was the cause of the reduced input. Blocking GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor-mediated inhibition with picrotoxin was also insufficient to overcome reduced dendritic inputs in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice both in fEPSP recordings (F<sub>1, 370</sub> = 23.6, p &lt; 0.0001, sum-of-least-squares F-test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>F) and whole-cell EPSPs (F<sub>1, 324</sub> = 21.8, p &lt; 0.0001, sum-of-least-squares F-test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>H). Comparing the slopes of individual CA1 PC input-output plots, <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> cells had lower EPSP recruitment under both control (t<sub>30</sub> = 3.21, p = 0.039, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>I) and in the presence of picrotoxin (t<sub>30</sub> = 3.21, p = 0.039, LMM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>I). These data show that TA inputs to the CA1 region of the hippocampus are reduced in strength, providing a plausible explanation for the homeostatic compensation of CA1 PC intrinsic physiology and AIS structure during postnatal development. To test whether the changes in excitability may represent a homeostatic compensation for the decrease in synaptic input, we examined the probability of spiking of CA1 neurons to a range of stimulation voltages using cell-attached recording in the presence of picrotoxin. Despite the decrease in synaptic input to CA1 neurons, no genotypic differences were observed in the output of neurons to electrical stimulation of <italic>str. lacunosum-moleculare</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figures 5</xref>K and 5L). Furthermore, the spike output of CA1 PCs was not affected when biologically relevant 20-Hz trains of stimuli were delivered to <italic>str. lacunosum-moleculare</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Figure S5</xref>). These data show that homeostatic alterations of CA1 PC intrinsic excitability are sufficient to regulate their spiking output.<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Reduced Temporoammonic (TA) Inputs to the CA1 Region</p><p>(A) Slice recording configuration showing the stimulus electron (Stim) placed in the perforant path, extracellular field electrode (Field) placed in <italic>str. lacunosum-moleculare</italic> (SLM), and the whole-cell patch-clamp electrode (Patch) in <italic>str. pyramidale</italic> (Pyr). Scale bar: 100 μm.</p><p>(B) Representative extracellular field EPSP (fEPSP, top) and whole-cell EPSP (bottom), recorded in response to increasing voltage stimulation (0–100 V DC), from WT (black) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> (red) mice.</p><p>(C) Input-output relationship for the afferent fiber volley amplitude in WT (black, 14 slices from 6 mice) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> (red 18 slices from 7 mice) mouse slices. Number of slices indicated.</p><p>(D and E) fEPSP amplitude (D) and integral (E) recorded in SLM, plotted as a function of afferent fiber volley amplitude from the same slices as above.</p><p>(F) fEPSP plotted against fiber volley following 50 μM picrotoxin bath application (WT: 12 slices from 5 mice; <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup>: 18 slices from 7 mice).</p><p>(G) Whole-cell patch-clamp recorded EPSP against fiber volley amplitude (WT: 14 cells from 6 mice; <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup>: 18 cells from 7 mice).</p><p>(H) Whole-cell EPSP amplitude in the presence of picrotoxin (WT: 10 cells from 5 mice; <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup>: 20 cells from 7 mice).</p><p>(I) Quantification of the slope of input-output relationships for all EPSPs measured from whole-cell recordings.</p><p>(J) Representative cell attached recordings from CA1 PCs following stimulation of SLM, overlaid and showing cell spiking for WT (black) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> (red) neurons.</p><p>(K) Quantification of the percentage of CA1 PCs that responded to TA stimulation with a spike, in cell attached mode, at any stimulation voltage (light shading), compared to those that did not spike (dark shading).</p><p>(L) Measured spike probability of CA1 PCs at each stimulus strength for WT (black, 26 cells from 7 mice) and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> CA1 PCs (red, 30 cells from 9 mice). The number of cells tested is shown in parentheses.</p><p><sup>∗</sup>p &lt; 0.05, from 2-way RM ANOVA (C), sum-of-least-squares F-test (D–H), and GLMM (I). All of the data in (D)–(H) are plotted with linear regression (straight lines). All of the data in the figure are shown as means ± SEMs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"></graphic></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="p0100">Here, we show that hippocampal CA1 PCs are intrinsically hyperexcitable in a mouse model of FXS, likely due to an underlying increase in AIS length. We show that this genotype-specific length change is not due to a lack of plasticity at the AIS, as short-term structural plasticity is present in cultured <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons. Furthermore, in <italic>ex vivo</italic> tissue, we do not observe a depolarization-induced decrease in AIS length in agreement with previous findings in CA1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Evans et al., 2015</xref>), suggesting the restriction of AIS length changes in intact tissue in the timescales described. Despite the lack of decrease in AIS length (we observe a small but significant increase in AIS length), we do observe a decrease in intrinsic excitability following prolonged depolarization, the magnitude of which is significantly greater in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice. We also observe reduced entorhinal input to CA1 PCs and in the absence of altered inhibition, suggesting a homeostatic regulation of intrinsic excitability. In support of this activity-dependent homeostatic change in excitability, cell-attached recordings showed no genotypic differences in spike output to entorhinal axon stimulation. In agreement with previous studies, our findings reveal a range of cellular alterations in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−</italic>/y</sup> mice, some of which are likely compensatory or homeostatic, that result in altered circuit function.</p>
<sec id="sec3.1">
<title>Hyperexcitability in the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−/y</italic></sup> Mouse Model and AIS Length</title>
<p id="p0105">In the mouse model of FXS, local microcircuits are hyperexcitable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Contractor et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gibson et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). Increased intrinsic neuronal excitability has been observed in hippocampal neurons from CA1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Luque et al., 2017</xref>), CA3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Deng et al., 2013</xref>), and the entorhinal cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Deng and Klyachko, 2016</xref>), as well as from the neocortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Routh et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). The loss of FMRP has been shown to alter cellular excitability through a range of mechanisms. For example, FMRP directly binds to K<sup>+</sup> channels, and the loss of this interaction alters AP kinetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Brown et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Deng and Klyachko, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Deng et al., 2013</xref>). Other studies have suggested altered ion channel expression, resulting from homeostatic regulation or altered mRNA translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brager et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Routh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). In this context, we have also observed a decrease in resting membrane potential in CA1 neurons in the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−/y</italic></sup> rats. Although difficult to directly relate changes in resting membrane potential in acute slice to neurons <italic>in vivo</italic>, any alteration in resting membrane potential, possibly from an altered K<sup>+</sup> leak current, would likely contribute to the altered excitability of these neurons. Changes in cellular excitability through subsequent effects on circuit dynamics could explain a range of phenotypes, from altered cognition to increased sensory reactivity and motor dysfunction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Biane et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Breton and Stuart, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Marder and Goaillard, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Ransdell et al., 2012</xref>). The change in AIS length shown here in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice constitutes a further potential mechanism contributing to cellular hyperexcitability in hippocampal CA1 pyramidal neurons. The AIS length changes are unlikely related to dendritic complexity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Hamada et al., 2016</xref>), as AIS location relative to soma was consistent between genotypes. AIS length modulation and increased intrinsic excitability has also been observed in CA1 of the Angelman syndrome mouse model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Kaphzan et al., 2011</xref>). This commonality of AIS regulation in another monogenic model of local circuit hyperexcitability suggests a potential convergent mechanism of hyperexcitability between models of autism spectrum disorders and intellectual disability (ASD-ID).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3.2">
<title>Absence of Short-Term AIS Shortening in <italic>Ex Vivo</italic> Neurons</title>
<p id="p0110">In the present study, we confirm that AISs undergo short-term structural plasticity in primary dissociated cell culture following the application of a depolarizing stimuli, as has been shown previously for dentate granule neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Evans et al., 2015</xref>). This form of plasticity is intact in CA1 <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−<italic>/y</italic></sup> neurons, indicating that FMRP is unlikely to play a role in the mechanism by which AIS length is regulated by activity. Furthermore, given that we observed longer AISs in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−<italic>/y</italic></sup> CA1 neurons, <italic>in vivo</italic> and in a more simplified neuronal circuit present <italic>in vitro</italic>, our data suggest that altered AIS length may be a compensatory or homeostatic mechanism used to regulate neuronal excitability in the mouse model of FXS. We did not observe a shortening of the AIS in acute CA1 hippocampal slices from 4- to 5-week-old mice in contrast to cell cultures from other hippocampal cell types. Instead, we observed a small but consistent increase in AIS length in CA1 following KCl treatment. Given that we observed the length changes in cultured neurons from the same mouse colony, we believe that our data cast doubt on the ability of neurons to undergo shortening on the timescales described in cell culture in <italic>ex vivo</italic> tissue. However, it should be noted that we have only tested one time point (i.e., 3 h post-stimulation). It is possible that transient changes in AIS length could be taking place over a shorter time frame, may take longer to manifest, or may be age dependent. Nonetheless, it is clear that the changes in excitability to KCl treatment observed in the present study cannot be explained by changes in AIS length.</p>
<p id="p0115">Despite an absence of AIS shortening, we did observe a dampening of neuron excitability following 3 h of 15 mM KCl, as shown in the cell culture experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Evans et al., 2015</xref>) or following longer incubation of KCl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">O’Leary et al., 2010</xref>), which also oppose the length changes we observe if the rule of longer AIS equates to increased excitability. Since changes in AIS length cannot explain the changes in excitability, other mechanisms must be involved. One possibility could be altered potassium channel expression or function. Numerous K<sup>+</sup> channels have been linked to pathophysiology in FXS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Contractor et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Deng et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). The observed slowing of AP decay kinetics is consistent with altered Kv1.1 function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Kole et al., 2007</xref>), and the reduction in input resistance we observe could result from increased leak potassium currents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">O’Leary et al., 2010</xref>), altered M-channel activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Wu et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Yue and Yaari, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>), or altered tonic GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Curia et al., 2009</xref>). The homeostatic changes in cellular excitability were stronger in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice, which could result from altered proteostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Louros and Osterweil, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Richter et al., 2015</xref>) or that neuronal spiking in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice responds more strongly to stimuli on short timescales, thus recruiting ion channels that are typically surplus to the required activity state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">O’Leary et al., 2013</xref>). However, it is beyond the scope of the present article to identify the precise mechanism underlying the observed changes in cellular excitability.</p>
<p id="p0120">It has recently been shown that intrinsic homeostasis is altered in cultured <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> cortical neurons following reduced activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Bülow et al., 2019</xref>), based on neuronal discharge properties not regularly observed in intact brain tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Connors and Gutnick, 1990</xref>). Here, we show that increasing activity results in an exaggerated decrease in neuronal activity in neurons from <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice in <italic>ex vivo</italic> slices. However, consistent with recent findings from the somatosensory cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Antoine et al., 2019</xref>), our finding that CA1 neuronal output is normal despite the decrease in synaptic input from entorhinal cortex suggests that homeostatic mechanisms are able to reset neuronal firing in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−/y</italic></sup> neurons.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3.3">
<title>Network-Level Homeostatic Activity in the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−/y</italic></sup> Mouse</title>
<p id="p0125">Altered long-range connectivity has been proposed as a mechanism for cognitive impairment in FXS and <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Haberl et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">van der Molen et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Wang et al., 2017</xref>) and <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Bureau et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Harlow et al., 2010</xref>). Hippocampal function, particularly spatial and episodic memory, has been shown to be deficient in the mouse and rat models of FXS, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Asiminas et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">D’Hooge et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Talbot et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Till et al., 2015</xref>); however, most studies have only examined synaptic function and plasticity at specific synapses (i.e., Schaffer collaterals) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Huber et al., 2002</xref>). The entorhinal cortex is known to drive spatial inputs to CA1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Fyhn et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Miller and Best, 1980</xref>) and forms the TA pathway into the CA1 region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Amaral and Witter, 1989</xref>). Therefore, the reduced synaptic input we observe in the <italic>str. lacunosum-moleculare</italic> (co-aligning with TA inputs) may serve as a synaptic correlate of reduced spatial performance in FXS mice. The source of this reduced input could originate in the presynaptic domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Klemmer et al., 2011</xref>), as entorhinal input to the dentate gyrus is also reduced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Yun and Trommer, 2011</xref>). However, presynaptic release properties are not altered at this synapse in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Wahlstrom-Helgren and Klyachko, 2015</xref>). An alternative explanation for the altered homeostatic plasticity is altered hyperpolarization-activated cyclic nucleotide-gated ion (HCN) channel density or function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Shah, 2014</xref>), since HCN channels are strongly upregulated in the distal dendrites of CA1 PCs in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brager et al., 2012</xref>). Given the role of HCN channels in reducing dendritic gain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Magee, 1998</xref>) and enhancing dendritic supralinearity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Branco and Häusser, 2011</xref>), it is plausible that increased HCN channel expression is regulated by reduced TA input. HCN channels may be an additional homeostatic element in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>−</italic>/y</sup> mice, given that their expression is also bidirectional in different cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Booker et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Kalmbach et al., 2015</xref>).</p>
<p id="p0130">In summary, we postulate that the increased AIS length and intrinsic excitability in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>−/y</sup> neurons result from decreased excitation from extrinsic synaptic inputs through altered synaptic strength during development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Booker et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Domanski et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Harlow et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4">
<title>STAR★Methods</title>
<sec id="sec4.1">
<title>Key Resources Table</title>
<p id="p0135">
<table-wrap id="undtbl1" position="float">
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th>REAGENT or RESOURCE</th>
<th>SOURCE</th>
<th>IDENTIFIER</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Antibodies</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti-AnkyrinG</td>
<td>NeuroMAB</td>
<td>N106/36; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref65" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_10673030">AB_10673030</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit polyclonal anti-AnkyrinG</td>
<td>Santa Cruz</td>
<td>sc-28561; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref70" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_633909">AB_633909</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rabbit polyclonal anti-NeuN</td>
<td>Millipore EMD</td>
<td>ABN78; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref75" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_10807945">AB_10807945</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mouse monoclonal anti-NeuN</td>
<td>Millipore EMD</td>
<td>MAB377; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref80" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2298772">AB_2298772</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alexa 488 goat anti-mouse</td>
<td>Thermo Fisher Scientific</td>
<td>A-11001; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref85" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2534069">AB_2534069</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alexa 568 goat anti-mouse</td>
<td>Thermo Fisher Scientific</td>
<td>A-11004; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref90" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2534072">AB_2534072</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alexa 568 goat anti-rabbit</td>
<td>Thermo Fisher Scientific</td>
<td>A-11011; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref95" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_143157">AB_143157</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alexa 633 goat anti-rabbit</td>
<td>Thermo Fisher Scientific</td>
<td>A-21071; RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref100" xlink:href="nif-antibody:AB_2535732">AB_2535732</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>To-Pro 3 Iodide</td>
<td>Thermo Fisher Scientific</td>
<td>T3605</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Picrotoxin</td>
<td>Hellobio</td>
<td>HB0506</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alexafluor 594 Hydrazide</td>
<td>Thermo Fisher Scientific</td>
<td>A10438</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Vectashield mounting medium</td>
<td>Vector Labs</td>
<td>H-1400</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Experimental Models: Organisms/Strains</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Mouse: C57/Bl6J, B6.129P2-Fmr1tm1Cgr/J</italic> (Dutch Belgian Consortium)</td>
<td>Jackson Labs</td>
<td>003025</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>β1-NaV-GFP</td>
<td>Newly generated</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<bold>Software and Algorithms</bold>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<hr/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Graphpad Prism 7</td>
<td>GraphPad Software</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0010" xlink:href="https://www.graphpad.com">https://www.graphpad.com</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R/ R studio</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">R Core Team (2013)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">R Studio Team (2015)</xref></td>
<td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0015" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org">https://www.r-project.org</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0020" xlink:href="https://rstudio.com">https://rstudio.com</ext-link></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>pClamp</td>
<td>Molecular devices</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0025" xlink:href="https://www.moleculardevices.com/products/axon-patch-clamp-system/acquisition-and-analysis-software/pclamp-software-suite#gref">https://www.moleculardevices.com/products/axon-patch-clamp-system/acquisition-and-analysis-software/pclamp-software-suite#gref</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stimfit</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Guzman et al., 2014</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0030" xlink:href="https://github.com/neurodroid/stimfit">https://github.com/neurodroid/stimfit</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ImageJ</td>
<td>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>
</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0035" xlink:href="https://imagej.net/Fiji/Downloads">https://imagej.net/Fiji/Downloads</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NEURON 7.6</td>
<td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Carnevale and Hines, 2006</xref>)</td>
<td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0040" xlink:href="https://neuron.yale.edu/neuron/">https://neuron.yale.edu/neuron/</ext-link>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.2">
<title>Resource Availability</title>
<p id="p0140">Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Peter C Kind (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0045" xlink:href="mailto:pkind@ed.ac.uk">pkind@ed.ac.uk</ext-link>).</p>
<sec id="sec4.2.1">
<title>Lead Contact</title>
<p id="p0145">Peter C Kind (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0050" xlink:href="mailto:pkind@ed.ac.uk">pkind@ed.ac.uk</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.2.2">
<title>Materials Availability</title>
<p id="p0150">All materials will be made available upon reasonable request.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.2.3" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data and Code Availability</title>
<p id="p0155">All data generated in this study will be made available upon reasonable request.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.3">
<title>Experimental Model and Subject Details</title>
<sec id="sec4.3.1">
<title>Mouse models</title>
<p id="p0160">All procedures were performed according to Home Office (ASPA, 2013) and The University of Edinburgh Ethical Board. Mice were maintained on a C57/Bl6J background and housed on a 12hr light/dark cycle with <italic>ad libitum</italic> access to food and water. For cell-cultures full litters of male mice were taken at embryonic day 17.5 (E17.5). For 2P imaging experiments, double transgenic mice were bred with β1-NaV-GFP male mice (see below) crossed with <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup><italic>+/−</italic></sup> mice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.3.2">
<title>Dissociated hippocampal culture preparation</title>
<p id="p0165">Hippocampal neuronal cell culture were prepared as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Baxter et al., 2015</xref>). Briefly, hippocampi from embryonic day 17.5 mice were dissected, neurons dissociated in 36000 USP units/ml papain, and then plated on glass-coverslips coated with poly-L-lysine at a density of 1315 cells/mm<sup>2</sup>. Only male mice were selected and a sample of cells from each mouse was kept for later genotyping. Cells were grown in Neurobasal A culture medium supplemented with B-27 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad), 1 mM glutamine, 1% rat serum (Harlan Laboratories) and antibiotic/antimycotic (Life Technologies Ltd). Neurons were treated with mitotic inhibitor Cytosine β-D-arabino-furanoside hydrochloride (4.8 μM) at Div 4 to limit astrocyte proliferation and grown in Neurobasal A media until 10 days <italic>in vitro</italic> (DIV10).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4">
<title>Method Details</title>
<sec id="sec4.4.1">
<title>Generation of β1-NaV-GFP mice:</title>
<p id="p0170">Transgenic mice expressing the beta1 subunit of the sodium channel (b1-Nav) fused to GFP at the C terminus under the control of the Thy1.2 promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Caroni, 1997</xref>) were generated by pronuclear injection. The β1-Na<sub>V</sub>-GFP cDNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">McEwen et al., 2009</xref>) was cloned into the blunted XhoI site of the pTSC21k vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Lüthi et al., 1997</xref>), released using Not I as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Zonta et al., 2011</xref>) and used for pronuclear injection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Sherman and Brophy, 2000</xref>). Transgenic mice were backcrossed to the C57BL6J/Ola strain. Male b1-Nav-GFP were then backcrossed with female <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>+/−</sup> C57BL6J/Crl mice for at least six generations before data collection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.2">
<title>Acute slice preparation</title>
<p id="p0175">Acute brain slices were prepared similarly to previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Booker et al., 2017</xref>). Briefly, mice were anesthetised with isofluorane, decapitated and their brain rapidly dissected into ice-cold carbogenated (95 % O2/5 % CO2) sucrose-modified artificial cerebrospinal fluid (ACSF; in mM: 87 NaCl, 2.5 KCl, 25 NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 1.25 NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 25 glucose, 75 sucrose, 7 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5 CaCl<sub>2</sub>). 400 μm brain slices were cut on an oscillating blade vibratome (VT1200S, Leica, Germany). Slices were cut in both the coronal and horizontal planes; in which prelimbic prefrontal cortex (PL-mPFC) or dorsal hippocampus (coronal) and ventro-medial hippocampus (horizontal) were present. Slices were transferred to a submerged chamber in sucrose-ACSF at 35°C for 30 min and then stored at room temperature until needed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.3">
<title>Whole-cell patch-clamp recordings</title>
<p id="p0180">For electrophysiological recordings, slices were transferred to a submerged recording chamber perfused with pre-warmed carbogenated ACSF (in mM: 125 NaCl, 2.5 KCl, 25 NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 1.25 NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 25 glucose, 1 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 CaCl<sub>2</sub>) at a flow rate of 4-6 mL.min<sup>-1</sup> at 31 ± 1°C).Slices were visualized under infrared differential inference contrast microscopy with a digital camera (Orca 2, Hamamatsu, Japan) mounted on an upright microscope (BX61-WI, Olympus, Japan) and a 20x water-immersion objective lens (1.0 N.A., Olympus, Japan). Whole-cell patch-clamp recordings were performed with a Multiclamp 700B (Molecular Devices, CA, USA) amplifier. Recording pipettes were pulled from borosilicate glass capillaries (1.7 mm outer/1mm inner diameter, Harvard Apparatus, UK) on a horizontal electrode puller (P-97, Sutter Instruments, CA, USA). For recordings, pipettes were filled with a K-gluconate based internal solution (in mM 142 K-gluconate, 4 KCl, 0.5 EGTA, 10 HEPES, 2 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 Na<sub>2</sub>ATP, 0.3 Na<sub>2</sub>GTP, 1 Na<sub>2</sub>Phosphocreatine, 2.7 Biocytin, pH = 7.4, 290-310 mOsm), resulting in 3-5 MΩ tip resistance. Cells were rejected if: they were more depolarised than −50 mV, series resistance &gt; 30 MΩ, or series resistance changed by more than 20% over the course of the recording. For recordings, coronal slices were used to assess baseline intrinsic excitability to match histological findings, while horizontal slices were used for 2-photon imaging, acute plasticity, and temporoammonic stimulation.</p>
<p id="p0185">Stimulation of the temporoammonic pathway was made with a bipolar twisted Ni:Chrome wire electrode placed in <italic>str. lacunosum-moleculare</italic> at the border of CA1 and subiculum (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>A) in slices which CA3 was severed to prevent recurrent activation. Field EPSPs were recorded with a second electrode (patch pipette filled with ACSF) placed in <italic>str. L-M</italic> and a CA1 PC recorded in first cell-attached or whole-cell configurations. Increasing stimuli of 200 μs duration were given to <italic>str. L-M</italic> at 5 or 10 s intervals from constant-voltage stimulation box (Digitimer, Cambridge, UK).</p>
<p id="p0190">All intrinsic membrane properties were measured in I-clamp. Passive membrane properties, including membrane time constant, input resistance, were measured small hyperpolarising steps (10 pA, 500 ms duration), from resting membrane potential. Active properties were determined from a series of depolarising current steps (0 to +400 pA, 500 ms) from a holding potential of −70mV. All AP properties were determined from the first AP elicited at rheobase. For recordings before 15 mM NaCl or KCl treatment, the intracellular solution included 100 μM AlexaFluor 594 hydrazide (Invitrogen, Dunfermline, UK), which allowed later visual identification of the cell. All recordings were filtered online at 10 kHz with the built-in 4-pole Bessel Filter and digitized at 20 kHz (Digidata1440, Molecular Devices, CA, USA). Traces were recorded in pCLAMP 9 (Molecular Devices, CA, USA) and stored on a personal computer. Analysis of electrophysiological data was performed offline using the open source software package Stimfit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Guzman et al., 2014</xref>), blind to both genotype and treatment condition.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.4">
<title>2-photon imaging</title>
<p id="p0195">To measure the AIS length in real time, we performed live imaging of β1-NaV-GFP mice. Live imaging was performed on 400 μm thick horizontal, hippocampal slices, as described above. For imaging we used a custom built galvanometric scanning 2-photon microscope (Femto2D-Galvo, Femtonics, Budapest, Hungary) fitted with a tuneable wavelength Ti:Sapphire laser (Chameleon, Coherent, CA, USA), with laser power controlled by a Pockels cell (Conoptics, CT, USA). Signals were detected with photomultiplier tubes through the MES microscope software (Femtonics, Hungary). Following a whole-cell patch-clamp recording being obtained, neurons were dye filled and baseline intrinsic physiology recordings collected. Then a small region of interest (ROI), which comprised the dye filled cell and proximal <italic>str. oriens</italic> of CA1, thus covering the full extent of CA1 PC AIS. Following baseline recordings, a Z stack (1 μm steps) was taken in the top 50 μm of the slice. Then slices were transferred to back to a holding chamber containing recording ACSF with either 15 mM NaCl or 15 mM KCl added 3 h. At the end of the 3 h treatment, slices were then transferred back to the recording chamber and the same ROI (using the filled cell as a landmark) was imaged, under the initial conditions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.5">
<title>Dissociated hippocampal culture preparation</title>
<p id="p0200">Hippocampal neuronal cell culture were prepared as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Baxter et al., 2015</xref>). Briefly, hippocampi from embryonic day 17.5 mice were dissected, neurons dissociated in 36000 USP units/ml papain, and then plated on glass-coverslips coated with poly-L-lysine at a density of 1315 cells/mm<sup>2</sup>. Only male mice were selected and a sample of cells from each mouse was kept for later genotyping. Cells were grown in Neurobasal A culture medium supplemented with B-27 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad), 1 mM glutamine, 1% rat serum (Harlan Laboratories) and antibiotic/antimycotic (Life Technologies Ltd). Neurons were treated with mitotic inhibitor Cytosine β-D-arabino-furanoside hydrochloride (4.8 μM) at Div 4 to limit astrocyte proliferation and grown in Neurobasal A media until 10 days <italic>in vitro</italic> (DIV10).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.6">
<title>Short term plasticity</title>
<p id="p0205">Induction of short term AIS plasticity was performed according to previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Evans et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Grubb and Burrone, 2010</xref>). In dissociated cell-culture, Neurobasal A media was supplemented with 15 mM KCl or NaCl, from 1 M stocks and coverslips returned to the incubator for 3 hours at 37°C. For acute slice plasticity, following recovery at 35°C (as above) slices were transferred to a holding chamber containing recording-ACSF, with 15 mM KCl or NaCl added on top of baseline ionic concentrations. Slices were then incubated for 3h at 35°C, and carbogenated throughout. Following incubation with KCl or NaCl, coverslips or slices were immediately immersion fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in 0.1 M phosphate buffer (PB), pH 7.35 for 20 minutes (coverslips) or 1 hour (slices) at room temperature. For intrinsic physiology plasticity and 2-photon imaging, slices were transferred from the recording chamber into 15 mM KCl or NaCl (as above). After 3 hour incubation, slices were returned to the recording chamber circulating with fresh ACSF and further recordings performed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.7">
<title>Histological processing and imaging</title>
<p id="p0210">For immunohistochemistry, mice were perfusion fixed. Briefly, mice were sedated with isofluorane, followed by terminal anesthesia with sodium pentobarbital (27.5 mg/kg body weight) via intraperitoneal injection. Mice were then transcardially perfused with 20 mL PB with 0.9% saline (PBS), followed by 20 mL of 4% PFA in PB (pH 7.4). The brain was removed and post-fixed in 4% PFA for 1h. 50 μm coronal sections were cut using either an oscillating blade vibratome (VT1000S, Leica, Germany) or a freezing microtome (HM430, Thermo Scientific, UK). Immunocytochemistry was then performed on free floating sections. Sections were washed in PBS, and then blocked for 1 hour at room temperature in 10% normal goat serum (NGS), 0.3% Triton X-100, 0.05% NaN<sub>3</sub> in PBS. Slices were then incubated in primary antibodies raised against Ankyrin G (mouse, 1:500, clone-N106/36 NeuroMab, UNC Davis, CA, USA) and NeuN (rabbit, 1:500, ABN78, Millipore) diluted in PBS containing 5% NGS, 0.3% Triton X-100 and 0.05% NaN<sub>3</sub>, for 24 to 72 hours at 4°C. Slices were thoroughly washed in PBS, then secondary antibodies (anti-mouse and anti-rabbit AlexaFluor488 and AlexaFluor 568, Invitrogen, UK) applied diluted in PBS containing 3% NGS, 0.1% Triton X-100 and 0.05% NaN3, for 3 hr at room temperature or 24 hr at 4°C. Slices were rinsed in PBS, then PB and mounted on glass slides with Vectashield hard-set mounting medium (H1400, Vector Labs, UK). For cell-culture blocking time was reduced to 10 minutes; primary antibodies incubated over-night at 4°C and secondary antibody incubation for 1 hour at room temperature. Both primary and secondary antibody solutions were identical to those used in slices, but lacking Triton-X.</p>
<p id="p0215">Confocal image stacks were collected with an AxiovertLSM 510 (Zeiss, Germany) invert scanning-confocal microscope equipped with a 63x (N.A. 1.4, Zeiss, Germany) oil-immersion objective lens. Z stacks (1 μm steps, 1024x1024 pixels) containing ROIs were collected either through the entire 50 μm section (perfusion fixed tissue) or the top 20-30 μm of acute slices. Two stacks of each brain region were collected per experimental condition for each animal. For cell culture experiments, z stacks (1 μm steps, 1024 × 1024 pixels) were taken from the top to bottom of the monolayer of cells and 2 images per coverslip were collected with a 40x (N.A. 1.3, Zeiss, Germany) oil-immersion objective lens.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.8">
<title>Image analysis</title>
<p id="p0220">All image analysis was performed with the FIJI package of ImageJ. Based on AnkyrinG or β1-NaV-GFP labeling, AIS were manually traced from their distal tip to either the base of AnkyrinG labeling or the soma (β1-NaV-GFP images) through the 3D image stack using the segmented line tool in FIJI. For fixed tissue, up to 50 AIS were measured for each image, giving a total of up to 100 AIS for each mouse per brain region. For coverslips, 10 to 15 AIS were measured per coverslip. When measuring distance from soma, each AIS was measured, then the distance from the base, to the soma surface measured. For the β1-NaV-GFP labeling validation, 25 AISs per mouse were measured. Independent confirmation of the methodology for AIS measurement was performed by three experimenters, all blind to genotype, and demonstrated a high degree of consistency.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.4.9">
<title>Computational modeling</title>
<p id="p0225">Simulations were performed in NEURON 7.6 software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Carnevale and Hines, 2006</xref>) using a realistic CA1 pyramidal neuron morphology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Migliore, 2003</xref>). Four additional voltage-dependent currents were added: fast Na<sup>+</sup> (I<sub>Na</sub>), fast K<sup>+</sup> (I<sub>Kv</sub>), slow non-inactivating K<sup>+</sup> (I<sub>Km</sub>) and high voltage activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> (I<sub>Ca</sub>) and a Ca<sup>2+</sup> -dependent K<sup>+</sup> current (I<sub>KCa</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Mainen and Sejnowski, 1996</xref>). Cytoplasmic resistance (R<sub>i</sub>) was set to 150 Ω.cm, membrane capacitance (C<sub>M</sub>) was set to 1 μF/cm<sup>2</sup> and membrane resistance (R<sub>M</sub>) was set to 30 MΩ.cm<sup>2</sup>. The electrical impact of dendritic spines in realistic neuron morphologies was simulated by doubling dendritic C<sub>M</sub> and halving dendritic R<sub>M</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Holmes, 1989</xref>). The axon consisted of a variable length axon initial segment (AIS) followed by twenty 100 μm long segments with low membrane capacitance (C<sub>M</sub> = 0.1 μF/cm<sup>2</sup>) and high resistance (R<sub>M</sub> = 150 kΩ.cm<sup>2</sup>) representing myelinated regions, interspersed with 1 μm long Nodes of Ranvier (R<sub>M</sub> = 50 Ω.cm<sup>2</sup>). Conductance densities (in pS.μm<sup>-2</sup>) were as follows. Dendrites: g<sub>Na</sub> = 20, g<sub>Ca</sub> = 0.3, g<sub>KCa</sub> = 3, and g<sub>Kv</sub> = 0.1. Soma: as dendrites but g<sub>Kv</sub> = 200. Axon initial segment: g<sub>Kv</sub> = 2000, g<sub>Na</sub> = 30,000. Nodes of Ranvier: g<sub>Na</sub> = 30,000. Reversal potential for different ionic currents were E<sub>Leak</sub> = −70 mV, E<sub>K</sub> = −90 mV, E<sub>Na</sub> = 60 mV, E<sub>Ca</sub> = 140 mV). For input resistance changes, R<sub>M</sub> was scaled uniformly throughout all compartments. Simulations were performed at 40 kHz. 500 ms somatic current steps were applied and the rheobase determined to the nearest 1 pA. AP threshold was classified as the voltage at which the speed of membrane depolarisation first exceeded 20 mV/ms. Simulations were performed at 31°C.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4.5">
<title>Quantification and Statistical Analysis</title>
<p id="p0230">All experiments were performed blind to genotype, age and treatment (where applicable. Throughout, all data is shown as mean ± SEM. Where applicable, data was analyzed with either a linear mixed-effects model (LMM), or its generalized form (GLMM), whereby the variability due to random effects (animal, slice) was taken into account, allowing for direct measurement of genotype and/or treatment effects. Mixed-effects models were fitted using the Lme4 R package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bates et al., 2015</xref>), where the tested variable is a fixed-effect parameter (i.e., genotype, age or treatment) and random effects (animal, slice) are modeled vectors. All data was tested for normality, with <italic>p-value</italic>s reported as the output of ANOVA tests. Additionally, repeated-measures 2-way ANOVA, with Holm-Sidak post-tests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>C, 3D, and 3H) and Sum-of-least-squares F-tests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>D–4H) were employed. For boot-strapping analysis, the proportions of AIS (% of 100 AIS) from the dataset, in an animal dependent manner, were randomly sampled 1000 times and LMM ran on the subsampled data. <italic>P value</italic>s were calculated from these repeated LMM tests and plotted for each percentage of the data sampled and plotted as the x axis. As some animals had &gt; 95 AIS measured, but not 100, a percentage was used instead of absolute AIS number. Where reported, statistical significance was assumed if p &lt; 0.05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list id="cebib0010">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bib1">
<element-citation id="sref1" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Amaral</surname>
<given-names>D.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Witter</surname>
<given-names>M.P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The three-dimensional organization of the hippocampal formation: a review of anatomical data</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience
          <volume>31</volume>
<year>1989</year>
<fpage>571</fpage>
<lpage>591</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2687721</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib2">
<element-citation id="sref2" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Antoine</surname>
<given-names>M.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Langberg</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schnepel</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feldman</surname>
<given-names>D.E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Increased excitation-inhibition ratio stabilizes synapse and circuit excitability in four autism mouse models</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>101</volume>
<year>2019</year>
<fpage>648</fpage>
<lpage>661.e4</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30679017</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib3">
<element-citation id="sref3" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asiminas</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>A.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Louros</surname>
<given-names>S.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Till</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spano</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dando</surname>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bear</surname>
<given-names>M.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chattarji</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hardingham</surname>
<given-names>G.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osterweil</surname>
<given-names>E.K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sustained correction of associative learning deficits after brief, early treatment in a rat model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Sci. Transl. Med.
          <volume>11</volume>
<year>2019</year>
<fpage>eaao0498</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31142675</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib4">
<element-citation id="sref4" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bates</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mächler</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bolker</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fitting linear mixed-effects models using lme4</article-title>
<source/>J. Stat. Softw.
          <year>2015</year>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v067.i01</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib5">
<element-citation id="sref5" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baxter</surname>
<given-names>P.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>K.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hasel</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaindl</surname>
<given-names>A.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fricker</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thomson</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cregan</surname>
<given-names>S.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gillingwater</surname>
<given-names>T.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hardingham</surname>
<given-names>G.E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic NMDA receptor activity is coupled to the transcriptional control of the glutathione system</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>6761</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25854456</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib6">
<element-citation id="sref6" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Biane</surname>
<given-names>J.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scanziani</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuszynski</surname>
<given-names>M.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Conner</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Motor cortex maturation is associated with reductions in recurrent connectivity among functional subpopulations and increases in intrinsic excitability</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>35</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>4719</fpage>
<lpage>4728</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25788688</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib7">
<element-citation id="sref7" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Booker</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>G.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mysiak</surname>
<given-names>K.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brophy</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kind</surname>
<given-names>P.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mahad</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wyllie</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Loss of protohaem IX farnesyltransferase in mature dentate granule cells impairs short-term facilitation at mossy fibre to CA3 pyramidal cell synapses</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>595</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>2147</fpage>
<lpage>2160</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28083896</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib8">
<element-citation id="sref8" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Booker</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Domanski</surname>
<given-names>A.P.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dando</surname>
<given-names>O.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>A.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isaac</surname>
<given-names>J.T.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hardingham</surname>
<given-names>G.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wyllie</surname>
<given-names>D.J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kind</surname>
<given-names>P.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered dendritic spine function and integration in a mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>10</volume>
<year>2019</year>
<fpage>4813</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31645626</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib9">
<element-citation id="sref9" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brager</surname>
<given-names>D.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Akhavan</surname>
<given-names>A.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Impaired dendritic expression and plasticity of h-channels in the <italic>fmr1</italic><sup><italic>-/y</italic></sup> mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>1</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>225</fpage>
<lpage>233</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22662315</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib10">
<element-citation id="sref10" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Branco</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Häusser</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Synaptic integration gradients in single cortical pyramidal cell dendrites</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>69</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>885</fpage>
<lpage>892</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21382549</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib11">
<element-citation id="sref11" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Breton</surname>
<given-names>J.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stuart</surname>
<given-names>G.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Loss of sensory input increases the intrinsic excitability of layer 5 pyramidal neurons in rat barrel cortex</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>587</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>5107</fpage>
<lpage>5119</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19736297</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib12">
<element-citation id="sref12" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>M.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kronengold</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gazula</surname>
<given-names>V.-R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strumbos</surname>
<given-names>J.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sigworth</surname>
<given-names>F.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Navaratnam</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaczmarek</surname>
<given-names>L.K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fragile X mental retardation protein controls gating of the sodium-activated potassium channel Slack</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <volume>13</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>819</fpage>
<lpage>821</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20512134</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib13">
<element-citation id="sref13" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bülow</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bassell</surname>
<given-names>G.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wenner</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Homeostatic Intrinsic Plasticity Is Functionally Altered in Fmr1 KO Cortical Neurons</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>26</volume>
<year>2019</year>
<fpage>1378</fpage>
<lpage>1388.e3</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30726724</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib14">
<element-citation id="sref14" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bureau</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shepherd</surname>
<given-names>G.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Svoboda</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Circuit and plasticity defects in the developing somatosensory cortex of FMR1 knock-out mice</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>28</volume>
<year>2008</year>
<fpage>5178</fpage>
<lpage>5188</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18480274</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib15">
<element-citation id="sref15" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carnevale</surname>
<given-names>N.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hines</surname>
<given-names>M.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>The NEURON Book</chapter-title>
<year>2006</year>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib16">
<element-citation id="sref16" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Caroni</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Overexpression of growth-associated proteins in the neurons of adult transgenic mice</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci. Methods
          <volume>71</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9125370</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib17">
<element-citation id="sref17" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Connors</surname>
<given-names>B.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gutnick</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Intrinsic firing patterns of diverse neocortical neurons</article-title>
<source/>Trends Neurosci.
          <volume>13</volume>
<year>1990</year>
<fpage>99</fpage>
<lpage>104</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1691879</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib18">
<element-citation id="sref18" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Contractor</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klyachko</surname>
<given-names>V.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Portera-Cailliau</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered neuronal and circuit excitability in fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>87</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>699</fpage>
<lpage>715</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26291156</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib19">
<element-citation id="sref19" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Curia</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Papouin</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Séguéla</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Avoli</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Downregulation of tonic GABAergic inhibition in a mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Cereb. Cortex
          <volume>19</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>1515</fpage>
<lpage>1520</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18787232</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib21">
<element-citation id="sref21" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>P.-Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klyachko</surname>
<given-names>V.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Increased persistent sodium current causes neuronal hyperexcitability in the entorhinal cortex of <italic>Fmr1</italic> knockout mice</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>16</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>3157</fpage>
<lpage>3166</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27653682</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib22">
<element-citation id="sref22" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>P.-Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rotman</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blundon</surname>
<given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cavalli</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zakharenko</surname>
<given-names>S.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klyachko</surname>
<given-names>V.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>FMRP regulates neurotransmitter release and synaptic information transmission by modulating action potential duration via BK channels</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>77</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>696</fpage>
<lpage>711</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23439122</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib20">
<element-citation id="sref20" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>D’Hooge</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nagels</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Franck</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reyniers</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Storm</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kooy</surname>
<given-names>R.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oostra</surname>
<given-names>B.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Willems</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De Deyn</surname>
<given-names>P.P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mildly impaired water maze performance in male <italic>Fmr1</italic> knockout mice</article-title>
<source/>Neuroscience
          <volume>76</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>367</fpage>
<lpage>376</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9015322</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib23">
<element-citation id="sref23" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dölen</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osterweil</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>B.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>G.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Auerbach</surname>
<given-names>B.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chattarji</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bear</surname>
<given-names>M.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Correction of fragile X syndrome in mice</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>56</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>955</fpage>
<lpage>962</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18093519</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib24">
<element-citation id="sref24" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Domanski</surname>
<given-names>A.P.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Booker</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wyllie</surname>
<given-names>D.J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isaac</surname>
<given-names>J.T.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kind</surname>
<given-names>P.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cellular and synaptic phenotypes lead to disrupted information processing in <italic>Fmr1</italic>-KO mouse layer 4 barrel cortex</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>10</volume>
<year>2019</year>
<fpage>4814</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31645553</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib25">
<element-citation id="sref25" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>M.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dumitrescu</surname>
<given-names>A.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kruijssen</surname>
<given-names>D.L.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>S.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grubb</surname>
<given-names>M.S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Rapid modulation of axon initial segment length influences repetitive spike firing</article-title>
<source/>Cell Rep.
          <volume>13</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>1233</fpage>
<lpage>1245</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26526995</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib26">
<element-citation id="sref26" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fyhn</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Molden</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Witter</surname>
<given-names>M.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moser</surname>
<given-names>E.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moser</surname>
<given-names>M.-B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Spatial representation in the entorhinal cortex</article-title>
<source/>Science
          <volume>305</volume>
<year>2004</year>
<fpage>1258</fpage>
<lpage>1264</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15333832</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib27">
<element-citation id="sref27" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gibson</surname>
<given-names>J.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bartley</surname>
<given-names>A.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hays</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huber</surname>
<given-names>K.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Imbalance of neocortical excitation and inhibition and altered UP states reflect network hyperexcitability in the mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurophysiol.
          <volume>100</volume>
<year>2008</year>
<fpage>2615</fpage>
<lpage>2626</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18784272</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib28">
<element-citation id="sref28" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grubb</surname>
<given-names>M.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burrone</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activity-dependent relocation of the axon initial segment fine-tunes neuronal excitability</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>465</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>1070</fpage>
<lpage>1074</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20543823</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib29">
<element-citation id="sref29" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grubb</surname>
<given-names>M.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shu</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuba</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rasband</surname>
<given-names>M.N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wimmer</surname>
<given-names>V.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bender</surname>
<given-names>K.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Short- and long-term plasticity at the axon initial segment</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>31</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>16049</fpage>
<lpage>16055</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22072655</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib30">
<element-citation id="sref30" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gutzmann</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ergül</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grossmann</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wahle</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engelhardt</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A period of structural plasticity at the axon initial segment in developing visual cortex</article-title>
<source/>Front. Neuroanat.
          <volume>8</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>11</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24653680</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib31">
<element-citation id="sref31" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guzman</surname>
<given-names>S.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schlögl</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schmidt-Hieber</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Stimfit: quantifying electrophysiological data with Python</article-title>
<source/>Front. Neuroinform.
          <volume>8</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>16</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24600389</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib32">
<element-citation id="sref32" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Haberl</surname>
<given-names>M.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zerbi</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Veltien</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ginger</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heerschap</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frick</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural-functional connectivity deficits of neocortical circuits in the <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>-/y</sup> mouse model of autism</article-title>
<source/>Sci. Adv.
          <volume>1</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>e1500775</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26702437</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib33">
<element-citation id="sref33" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hagerman</surname>
<given-names>R.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Staley</surname>
<given-names>L.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Conner</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lugenbeel</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McLean</surname>
<given-names>S.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Learning-disabled males with a fragile X CGG expansion in the upper premutation size range</article-title>
<source/>Pediatrics
          <volume>97</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>122</fpage>
<lpage>126</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8545206</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib34">
<element-citation id="sref34" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hamada</surname>
<given-names>M.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goethals</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Vries</surname>
<given-names>S.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brette</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kole</surname>
<given-names>M.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Covariation of axon initial segment location and dendritic tree normalizes the somatic action potential</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
          <volume>113</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>14841</fpage>
<lpage>14846</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27930291</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib35">
<element-citation id="sref35" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harlow</surname>
<given-names>E.G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Till</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Russell</surname>
<given-names>T.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wijetunge</surname>
<given-names>L.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kind</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Contractor</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Critical period plasticity is disrupted in the barrel cortex of FMR1 knockout mice</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>65</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>385</fpage>
<lpage>398</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20159451</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib36">
<element-citation id="sref36" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>W.R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The role of dendritic diameters in maximizing the effectiveness of synaptic inputs</article-title>
<source/>Brain Res.
          <volume>478</volume>
<year>1989</year>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>137</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2538199</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib37">
<element-citation id="sref37" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huber</surname>
<given-names>K.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gallagher</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Warren</surname>
<given-names>S.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bear</surname>
<given-names>M.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Altered synaptic plasticity in a mouse model of fragile X mental retardation</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
          <volume>99</volume>
<year>2002</year>
<fpage>7746</fpage>
<lpage>7750</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12032354</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib38">
<element-citation id="sref38" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kalmbach</surname>
<given-names>B.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brager</surname>
<given-names>D.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cell-type specific channelopathies in the prefrontal cortex of the <italic>fmr1</italic><sup><italic>-/y</italic></sup> mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>eNeuro
          <volume>2</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<comment>ENEURO. 0114-0115.2015</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib39">
<element-citation id="sref39" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kaphzan</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buffington</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>J.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rasband</surname>
<given-names>M.N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klann</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Alterations in intrinsic membrane properties and the axon initial segment in a mouse model of Angelman syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>31</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>17637</fpage>
<lpage>17648</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22131424</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib40">
<element-citation id="sref40" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klemmer</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meredith</surname>
<given-names>R.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holmgren</surname>
<given-names>C.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klychnikov</surname>
<given-names>O.I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stahl-Zeng</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Loos</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van der Schors</surname>
<given-names>R.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wortel</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Wit</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spijker</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Proteomics, ultrastructure, and physiology of hippocampal synapses in a fragile X syndrome mouse model reveal presynaptic phenotype</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>286</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>25495</fpage>
<lpage>25504</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21596744</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib41">
<element-citation id="sref41" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kole</surname>
<given-names>M.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Letzkus</surname>
<given-names>J.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stuart</surname>
<given-names>G.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Axon initial segment Kv1 channels control axonal action potential waveform and synaptic efficacy</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>55</volume>
<year>2007</year>
<fpage>633</fpage>
<lpage>647</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17698015</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib42">
<element-citation id="sref42" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kole</surname>
<given-names>M.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ilschner</surname>
<given-names>S.U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kampa</surname>
<given-names>B.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>S.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ruben</surname>
<given-names>P.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stuart</surname>
<given-names>G.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Action potential generation requires a high sodium channel density in the axon initial segment</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <volume>11</volume>
<year>2008</year>
<fpage>178</fpage>
<lpage>186</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18204443</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib43">
<element-citation id="sref43" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuba</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural tuning and plasticity of the axon initial segment in auditory neurons</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>590</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>5571</fpage>
<lpage>5579</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23027822</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib44">
<element-citation id="sref44" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuba</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oichi</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ohmori</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Presynaptic activity regulates Na(+) channel distribution at the axon initial segment</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>465</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>1075</fpage>
<lpage>1078</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20543825</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib45">
<element-citation id="sref45" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuba</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yamada</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ishiguro</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adachi</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Redistribution of Kv1 and Kv7 enhances neuronal excitability during structural axon initial segment plasticity</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Commun.
          <volume>6</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>8815</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26581625</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib46">
<element-citation id="sref46" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leterrier</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The axon initial segment, 50 years later: a nexus for neuronal organization and function</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Top. Membr.
          <volume>77</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>233</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26781833</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib47">
<element-citation id="sref47" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Louros</surname>
<given-names>S.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osterweil</surname>
<given-names>E.K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Perturbed proteostasis in autism spectrum disorders</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurochem.
          <volume>139</volume>
<year>2016</year>
<fpage>1081</fpage>
<lpage>1092</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27365114</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib48">
<element-citation id="sref48" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luque</surname>
<given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beltran-Matas</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marin</surname>
<given-names>M.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torres</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Herrero</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Excitability is increased in hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells of Fmr1 knockout mice</article-title>
<source/>PLOS ONE
          <volume>12</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>e0185067</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28931075</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib49">
<element-citation id="sref49" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lüthi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van der Putten</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Botteri</surname>
<given-names>F.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mansuy</surname>
<given-names>I.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meins</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frey</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sansig</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Portet</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schmutz</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schröder</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Endogenous serine protease inhibitor modulates epileptic activity and hippocampal long-term potentiation</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>17</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>4688</fpage>
<lpage>4699</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9169529</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib50">
<element-citation id="sref50" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Magee</surname>
<given-names>J.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dendritic hyperpolarization-activated currents modify the integrative properties of hippocampal CA1 pyramidal neurons</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>18</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>7613</fpage>
<lpage>7624</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9742133</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib51">
<element-citation id="sref51" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mainen</surname>
<given-names>Z.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sejnowski</surname>
<given-names>T.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Influence of dendritic structure on firing pattern in model neocortical neurons</article-title>
<source/>Nature
          <volume>382</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>363</fpage>
<lpage>366</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8684467</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib52">
<element-citation id="sref52" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marder</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goaillard</surname>
<given-names>J.-M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Variability, compensation and homeostasis in neuron and network function</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
          <volume>7</volume>
<year>2006</year>
<fpage>563</fpage>
<lpage>574</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16791145</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib53">
<element-citation id="sref53" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marder</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prinz</surname>
<given-names>A.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Modeling stability in neuron and network function: the role of activity in homeostasis</article-title>
<source/>BioEssays
          <volume>24</volume>
<year>2002</year>
<fpage>1145</fpage>
<lpage>1154</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12447979</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib54">
<element-citation id="sref54" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McEwen</surname>
<given-names>D.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Meadows</surname>
<given-names>L.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lopez-Santiago</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isom</surname>
<given-names>L.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The voltage-gated Na+ channel β3 subunit does not mediate trans homophilic cell adhesion or associate with the cell adhesion molecule contactin</article-title>
<source/>Neurosci. Lett.
          <volume>462</volume>
<year>2009</year>
<fpage>272</fpage>
<lpage>275</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19596049</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib55">
<element-citation id="sref55" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Migliore</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>On the integration of subthreshold inputs from Perforant Path and Schaffer Collaterals in hippocampal CA1 pyramidal neurons</article-title>
<source/>J. Comput. Neurosci.
          <volume>14</volume>
<year>2003</year>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>192</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12567016</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib56">
<element-citation id="sref56" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>V.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Best</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Spatial correlates of hippocampal unit activity are altered by lesions of the fornix and endorhinal cortex</article-title>
<source/>Brain Res.
          <volume>194</volume>
<year>1980</year>
<fpage>311</fpage>
<lpage>323</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7388617</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib57">
<element-citation id="sref57" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Musumeci</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bosco</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calabrese</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>De Sarro</surname>
<given-names>G.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Elia</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oostra</surname>
<given-names>B.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Audiogenic seizures susceptibility in transgenic mice with fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Epilepsia
          <volume>41</volume>
<year>2000</year>
<fpage>19</fpage>
<lpage>23</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10643918</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib58">
<element-citation id="sref58" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Leary</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Rossum</surname>
<given-names>M.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wyllie</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Homeostasis of intrinsic excitability in hippocampal neurones: dynamics and mechanism of the response to chronic depolarization</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>588</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>157</fpage>
<lpage>170</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19917565</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib59">
<element-citation id="sref59" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Leary</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>A.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caplan</surname>
<given-names>J.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marder</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Correlations in ion channel expression emerge from homeostatic tuning rules</article-title>
<source/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
          <volume>110</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>E2645</fpage>
<lpage>E2654</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23798391</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib60">
<element-citation id="sref60" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ogawa</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rasband</surname>
<given-names>M.N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The functional organization and assembly of the axon initial segment</article-title>
<source/>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.
          <volume>18</volume>
<year>2008</year>
<fpage>307</fpage>
<lpage>313</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18801432</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib61">
<element-citation id="sref61" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Osterweil</surname>
<given-names>E.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krueger</surname>
<given-names>D.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reinhold</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bear</surname>
<given-names>M.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Hypersensitivity to mGluR5 and ERK1/2 leads to excessive protein synthesis in the hippocampus of a mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>30</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>15616</fpage>
<lpage>15627</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21084617</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib62">
<element-citation id="sref62" publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>R Core Team</collab>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</chapter-title>
<year>2013</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib63">
<element-citation id="sref63" publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>R Studio Team</collab>
</person-group>
<article-title>RStudio: integrated development for R</article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0060" xlink:href="http://www.rstudio.com">http://www.rstudio.com</ext-link>
<year>2015</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib64">
<element-citation id="sref64" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ransdell</surname>
<given-names>J.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nair</surname>
<given-names>S.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schulz</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Rapid homeostatic plasticity of intrinsic excitability in a central pattern generator network stabilizes functional neural network output</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>32</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>9649</fpage>
<lpage>9658</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22787050</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib65">
<element-citation id="sref65" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Richter</surname>
<given-names>J.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bassell</surname>
<given-names>G.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klann</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dysregulation and restoration of translational homeostasis in fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
          <volume>16</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>595</fpage>
<lpage>605</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26350240</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib66">
<element-citation id="sref66" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Routh</surname>
<given-names>B.N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brager</surname>
<given-names>D.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Loss of functional A-type potassium channels in the dendrites of CA1 pyramidal neurons from a mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci.
          <volume>33</volume>
<year>2013</year>
<fpage>19442</fpage>
<lpage>19450</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336711</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib67">
<element-citation id="sref67" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Routh</surname>
<given-names>B.N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rathour</surname>
<given-names>R.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baumgardner</surname>
<given-names>M.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kalmbach</surname>
<given-names>B.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brager</surname>
<given-names>D.H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Increased transient Na<sup>+</sup> conductance and action potential output in layer 2/3 prefrontal cortex neurons of the <italic>fmr1</italic><sup><italic>-/y</italic></sup> mouse</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>595</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>4431</fpage>
<lpage>4448</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28370141</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib68">
<element-citation id="sref68" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rasband</surname>
<given-names>W.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eliceiri</surname>
<given-names>K.W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Methods
          <volume>9</volume>
<year>2012</year>
<fpage>671</fpage>
<lpage>675</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib69">
<element-citation id="sref69" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>M.M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cortical HCN channels: function, trafficking and plasticity</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>592</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>2711</fpage>
<lpage>2719</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24756635</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib70">
<element-citation id="sref70" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>D.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brophy</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A tripartite nuclear localization signal in the PDZ-domain protein L-periaxin</article-title>
<source/>J. Biol. Chem.
          <volume>275</volume>
<year>2000</year>
<fpage>4537</fpage>
<lpage>4540</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10671475</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib71">
<element-citation id="sref71" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Talbot</surname>
<given-names>Z.N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sparks</surname>
<given-names>F.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dvorak</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Curran</surname>
<given-names>B.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alarcon</surname>
<given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fenton</surname>
<given-names>A.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Normal CA1 place fields but discoordinated network discharge in a <italic>Fmr1</italic>-null mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>97</volume>
<year>2018</year>
<fpage>684</fpage>
<lpage>697.e4</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29358017</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib72">
<element-citation id="sref72" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thome</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yanez</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engelhardt</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cambridge</surname>
<given-names>S.B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Both</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Draguhn</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Egorov</surname>
<given-names>A.V.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Axon-carrying dendrites convey privileged synaptic input in hippocampal neurons</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>83</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>1418</fpage>
<lpage>1430</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25199704</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib73">
<element-citation id="sref73" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Till</surname>
<given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Asiminas</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>A.D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katsanevaki</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>S.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osterweil</surname>
<given-names>E.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bear</surname>
<given-names>M.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chattarji</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>E.R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wyllie</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kind</surname>
<given-names>P.C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Conserved hippocampal cellular pathophysiology but distinct behavioural deficits in a new rat model of FXS</article-title>
<source/>Hum. Mol. Genet.
          <volume>24</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>5977</fpage>
<lpage>5984</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26243794</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib74">
<element-citation id="sref74" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van der Molen</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stam</surname>
<given-names>C.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van der Molen</surname>
<given-names>M.W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Resting-state EEG oscillatory dynamics in fragile X syndrome: abnormal functional connectivity and brain network organization</article-title>
<source/>PLOS ONE
          <volume>9</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>e88451</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24523898</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib75">
<element-citation id="sref75" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wahlstrom-Helgren</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klyachko</surname>
<given-names>V.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>GABAB receptor-mediated feed-forward circuit dysfunction in the mouse model of fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>593</volume>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>5009</fpage>
<lpage>5024</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26282581</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib76">
<element-citation id="sref76" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ethridge</surname>
<given-names>L.E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mosconi</surname>
<given-names>M.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>White</surname>
<given-names>S.P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Binder</surname>
<given-names>D.K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pedapati</surname>
<given-names>E.V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erickson</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Byerly</surname>
<given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A resting EEG study of neocortical hyperexcitability and altered functional connectivity in fragile X syndrome</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurodev. Disord.
          <volume>9</volume>
<year>2017</year>
<fpage>11</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28316753</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib77">
<element-citation id="sref77" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wimmer</surname>
<given-names>V.C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>So</surname>
<given-names>E.Y.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berkovic</surname>
<given-names>S.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petrou</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Axon initial segment dysfunction in epilepsy</article-title>
<source/>J. Physiol.
          <volume>588</volume>
<year>2010</year>
<fpage>1829</fpage>
<lpage>1840</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20375142</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib78">
<element-citation id="sref78" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>W.W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>C.S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Surmeier</surname>
<given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Disterhoft</surname>
<given-names>J.F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Coupling of L-type Ca2+ channels to KV7/KCNQ channels creates a novel, activity-dependent, homeostatic intrinsic plasticity</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurophysiol.
          <volume>100</volume>
<year>2008</year>
<fpage>1897</fpage>
<lpage>1908</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18715900</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib79">
<element-citation id="sref79" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yue</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yaari</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Axo-somatic and apical dendritic Kv7/M channels differentially regulate the intrinsic excitability of adult rat CA1 pyramidal cells</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurophysiol.
          <volume>95</volume>
<year>2006</year>
<fpage>3480</fpage>
<lpage>3495</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16495357</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib80">
<element-citation id="sref80" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yun</surname>
<given-names>S.H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trommer</surname>
<given-names>B.L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fragile X mice: reduced long-term potentiation and N-Methyl-D-Aspartate receptor-mediated neurotransmission in dentate gyrus</article-title>
<source/>J. Neurosci. Res.
          <volume>89</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>176</fpage>
<lpage>182</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21162125</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib81">
<element-citation id="sref81" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bonnan</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bony</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferezou</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pietropaolo</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ginger</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sans</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rossier</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oostra</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LeMasson</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frick</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dendritic channelopathies contribute to neocortical and sensory hyperexcitability in <italic>Fmr1</italic><sup>-/y</sup> mice</article-title>
<source/>Nat. Neurosci.
          <volume>17</volume>
<year>2014</year>
<fpage>1701</fpage>
<lpage>1709</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25383903</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bib82">
<element-citation id="sref82" publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zonta</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Desmazieres</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rinaldi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tait</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>D.L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nolan</surname>
<given-names>M.F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brophy</surname>
<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A critical role for Neurofascin in regulating action potential initiation through maintenance of the axon initial segment</article-title>
<source/>Neuron
          <volume>69</volume>
<year>2011</year>
<fpage>945</fpage>
<lpage>956</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21382554</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="app2" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplemental Information</title>
<p id="p0255">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
<caption>
<title>Document S1. Table S1 and Figures S1–S5</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2">
<caption>
<title>Table S2. Details of Statistical Tests Performed in the Study, Related to Figures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, S1, S3, S4, and S5</title>
<p>Details of all statistical tests with reference to specific location in article body, mean ± SEM, number of replicates, replicate tested, test performed, data model, and test outputs; for both main article and supplementary materials.</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx"></media>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3">
<caption>
<title>Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="mmc3.pdf"></media>
</supplementary-material>
</p>
</sec>
<ack id="ack0010">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors would like to thank Olivia Bailey and Naima Eloisgui-Borras for assistance with imaging, Dr. Elizabeth Davenport for E17.5 mouse sexing, and all of the members of the Kind and Wyllie laboratories for their helpful discussions. We thank our funders: the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100014370</institution-id><institution>Simons Foundation Autism Research Initiative</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (529085), the Patrick Wild Centre, <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000265</institution-id><institution>Medical Research Council UK</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (MR/P006213/1), the <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100014280</institution-id><institution>Shirley Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, and the <funding-source id="gs4">R S Macdonald Charitable Trust</funding-source>.</p>
<sec id="sec5">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p id="p0240">P.C.K., D.J.A.W., S.A.B., and L.S.O. conceptualized and designed the experimental plan. S.A.B., L.S.O., and N.J.A. performed and analyzed the electrophysiology and imaging experiments. Z.K. and O.R.D. performed the statistical modeling. A.D.J. performed the computational neuron modeling. L.L.I., D.L.S., and P.J.B. generated and validated the β1-NaV-GFP mice. P.S.B. and G.E.H. developed the cell culture assays. S.A.B., L.S.O., G.E.H., D.L.S., P.J.B., D.J.A.W., and P.C.K. devised the experiments. All of the authors contributed to writing the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6" sec-type="COI-statement">
<title>Declaration of Interests</title>
<p id="p0245">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supplementary-material" id="app1">
<p id="p0250">Supplemental Information can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="intref0055" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2020.107988">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2020.107988</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>